Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Disha Sarawgi
and Mohammed Kabir. Disha and
Kabir both work at Corvus
Robotics. Disha is the head of
Special Projects and an early
employee at Corvus, while Kabir
is a co founder and the CTO at
Corvus. Corvus robotics is a
Boston based startup that makes
a drone to fly around warehouses
and help with inventory
management. Their drone, the
Corvus one seems to promise to
reduce inventory loss in
warehouses, which currently
happens to a staggering rate. As
you'll find out in the
interview, they speak about
flying their drone in warehouses
working with customers, safety,
fleet management, how Corvus is
funded, and they give advice to
aspiring entrepreneurs. This is
the Sense Think Act Podcast. I'm
Audrow Nash. Thank you to our
founding sponsor Open Robotics.
And here is my conversation with
Disha and Kabir.
Kabir, would you introduce
yourself?
Mohammed Kabir: Yeah, sure. So
I'm Kabir. I'm the I'm the co
founder and CTO of Corvis
robotics.
Audrow Nash: Hi, Disha.
Disha Sarawgi: Hi, I'm Disha. I
work as head of Special Projects
and General Projects.
I lead basically all the product
lines here at Corvus.
Mohammed Kabir: And she's also
one of our early employees, one
of the very first
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. How large
are you guys now?
Disha Sarawgi: We do have about
15 people across engineering and
on engineering goes
Audrow Nash: to the shot when
what number employee were you?
Disha Sarawgi: I read? Second,
probably.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. She's the
second employee. Right after you
come here.
Mohammed Kabir: The co founder,
the founders,
Audrow Nash: I see. So tell me
about Corvus. Yeah, about what
is the mission and everything.
Mohammed Kabir: Yeah, sure. So
when we started out, sometime in
2017, or so we saw this a whole
bunch of robotics companies,
newly formed robotics companies,
really kind of doing great
things in the warehouse and
industrial automation space. And
generally, my background is that
I come from a real robots. So I
really love flying things and
making drones. So when we
started the company, we kind of
were like looking for use cases,
which we could automate kind of
putting together this industrial
automation space, and aerial
robotics. And I think we found a
pretty good niche and decided to
pursue it, which is warehouse
inventory management. That's
kind of our singular, large
focus throughout the company. So
all our product lines are kind
of trying to solve for that one
specific thing, which is
warehouse inventory. And that's
where the idea for purpose one
was born. What purpose one is,
it's a drone, which which does,
which helps warehouses do
inventory. This is a huge
market, warehouses lose millions
and billions of dollars worth of
goods from inside their own
facilities every year. And this
is the problem we set out to
solve.
Audrow Nash: Why is that? Why
are they losing millions and
billions of dollars? Right,
good, right.
Mohammed Kabir: So the way
warehouses do inventory
management today is whenever
they send a person out with like
a handheld barcode scanner, and
then this person goes up and
down the racks. So these are
huge facilities that can be
millions of square feet. So this
person goes up and down the
racks with this handheld barcode
scanner, and basically scans
barcodes on the on whatever
stuff they have on the shelves.
And then they basically write
down or somehow tie back into
their warehouse management
system where this thing was. Now
in variably, because there's a
human involved in the loop. This
introduces a lot of errors. And
typically, I think the
nationwide average for kind of
the inventory accuracy across
warehouses in the US, it's
something about 40 to 60%, which
is actually quite bad. So they
lose half of their stuff just
because they don't know where
they put it. How could
Audrow Nash: that be that they
lose 42 They only retain 46 to
60%. Yeah. So so what happens is
like, why why are these red? Why
such a large number of loss?
Mohammed Kabir: Right? So um,
basically, the way inventory
comes into warehouses, you
basically unload from trucks and
Then there is a person who is
taking it from these truck bays
and then putting it in their
shelf somewhere. And this person
is responsible for kind of doing
an incremental scan. So they
can. So basically, we can input
into their warehouse management
system, where this particular
thing was booked. So it's
basically all deltas. So it's,
it's as things coming.
Audrow Nash: What do you mean,
deltas? It's, it's every, it's
the change effectively?
Mohammed Kabir: Yes, yes, it is
the change. So every time
there's a change, they update
their warehouse management
system, but invariably, because
there isn't like a global view
of the warehouse, per se. Errors
build up over time.
Audrow Nash: Why? Why are
they're building up, though? I
mean, if I just put something
there and leave it there, it
should stay there. And it
shouldn't matter that I only
have Delta's what's going on?
Are people stealing some of the
packages that people move?
Knowing or like, what's creating
60% of the law?
Mohammed Kabir: So I think it's
a bunch of human factors at the
end of the day, I wouldn't say
that stealing is a big one. But
I'm sure it is an actual
problem. One of the main things
we've seen is people just put it
in the wrong place in the first
place. So basically, you say
that you're putting it in
whatever aisle a slot B, but
then you put it in aisle a slot,
see the one next to it? And they
just don't care about where they
put it at the end of the
Audrow Nash: day? Because you
mean the person who puts it
there? Like, yeah, doesn't
matter.
Mohammed Kabir: Yeah, they're
processing like 1000s of orders
a day. So it's really hard at
even at the human level to kind
of keep up that 100% accuracy.
Audrow Nash: I mean, it seems
like getting one and two wrong
if you're getting that level of
like loss, which is kind of
nuts. Yeah. Yeah.
Mohammed Kabir: It's a huge
problem. It sounds ridiculous,
but it is what it is. And that's
that's what we set out to solve.
Audrow Nash: So then, what your
so tell me a bit about how
you're solving it with your
Corvus one, drone.
Mohammed Kabir: Sure. So what
premise one is, it's basically a
full cycle autonomous solution.
It's a drone, and this charging
dock, which we go and install in
facilities. So it sits at the
end of warehouse racks. And it
does scheduled flights on its
own, and then goes out into the
aisles, scans inventory as it's
flying, it finds barcode scans
them comes back home lands, and
then we process this data and
then send it to the customer,
usually through some sort of
digital data dump. And what this
does is we're basically taking
that person who was doing this
with a barcode scanner, and we
put the barcode scanner on the
ground. And then we can do this
repeatedly because well, it's a
drone day don't get tired.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, so you're
thinking of this. So if you were
thinking of the diff, so it's
kind of like in edge detection,
and image or something like
this. So you only get like, I
don't know, you're only getting
the difference, it's not a very
clear way to see the whole state
of the warehouse, right. And so
now what you're saying is your
drone flies around periodically.
And so you can kind of get
updates over time of where all
the packages are. Exactly.
Mohammed Kabir: And if you do
this frequently enough, we can
basically get that global view
of the warehouse basically every
day, depending on the size of
the facility. Okay.
Disha Sarawgi: Yeah, generally,
like do I do that? Generally,
inventory counts are taken by
houses maybe once a year. But
with the drawing, we're able to
get the entire inventory counts
multiple times. So God gives you
a great idea of like
historically, timestamps data,
which you can go back to and
refer to when like locate every
item at the warehouse at any
instant.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Very
interesting. Now, how I'm
thinking about this crazy loss.
that puzzles me honestly, that
it's so large, and I imagine
like goods are twice as
expensive as they would be if
they didn't have this loss. Is
that true? Would you think?
Like, that's probably included
in the cost of things? Yeah.
Mohammed Kabir: So the way the
business model for warehouses
work is they just write this
loss off. So they account for
that loss as they're moving
stuff around.
Audrow Nash: Write it off in
what way
Mohammed Kabir: as just lost.
Audrow Nash: Okay, but yeah, but
it's
Mohammed Kabir: still in their
facility somewhere. It's they
just don't know where.
Audrow Nash: Hmm. Interesting.
So that with the perspective of
fraud, flying The drone around,
often, you can kind of get a
better sense doesn't require the
human to place the package as
accurately or in the specific
section so you can manage it, or
at least in the one that they
say it's placed in, because I
would imagine, it would be the
reason for the error. So then
from that, you can kind of see
if things are missing, or like
if it was here, and now it's not
you at least have a small window
of time to investigate where it
has gone to, or where, or
something like that. Yeah,
Disha Sarawgi: it's not always
just miss loading of items, but
sometimes, because the humans in
the loop, people also forget to
just scan because they're taking
care of 1000s of orders a day.
And it's, it's easy if you're
also on the ground level, but
warehouse racks go up to like 20
feet, or 20 to 30 feet. And
getting up a forklift scanning,
and then coming down going to
the next track at the same
height is not an easy feat. So
human error does play a big part
of this as well.
Audrow Nash: I see. Yeah, that's
a good point that they're so
high that these packages are
just stored with layer on layer
on layer of packages. Is that
the motivation for the drone?
Disha Sarawgi: Oh, badly. Yes.
It's like humans can do
inventory tracking at ground
level, probably at the same
rate. But as the height
increases, the complexity
increases. And that's where the
drone comes in. And we get a
Audrow Nash: diversity increase,
because you have to have some
sort of ID or something to lift
the person and you need a person
Manning, or thing that tries and
holds the basket. I'm picturing
one of those like, things that
they put up power lines, or go
and work on the power lines
with, I don't know how,
Mohammed Kabir: yeah, it's
actually quite close. So they
have forklifts or bucket trucks.
And basically, there's a person
in a harness clip to that. And
then they go up in that, and
they're running the barcode
scanner. And it's, it's actually
quite dangerous. Yeah, it is
quite terrifying. Like, we've
we've been in them just to get a
feel for what it's like, do this
annually. And it's more or less
and were
Audrow Nash: lifted by Yes, yes.
That's awesome. I like that. You
guys do that? Yeah. How was it
terrifying? It's it's, I'm just
imagining, like dangling trying
to scan packages. That sounds
incredibly difficult. Yeah.
Okay. So, being a drone really
helps you get to those high
packages very easy, it's almost
free, because you just have to
pilot it. Is there other other
advantages to having a drone,
rather than like a robot with
like a real big telescoping
pole, or something like this?
Right. So
Mohammed Kabir: we've, when we
started, we've actually looked
into all of the options.
Starting from like a lower
complexity, like ground robot is
obviously easier to build,
right? Because it's not flying.
But it turns out that when you
get your poll 20 feet high, it
becomes really hard to make the
robot not tip over, just from
the weight of the ball. And then
if you want to kind of conquer
that you need to make your robot
like the you need the size of
the base, you need to put in
more batteries more weight. And
it's like it's a pretty bad
trade off at the end of the day,
if you want to do anything of
that kind.
Audrow Nash: Okay, yeah. And
then so you basically with the
drone, the Corvis. One, you have
the drone flying and it has
effectively a barcode scanner
attached to it. And it's just
pointing that at the packages.
Is that right? Yes, exactly. And
so now it's flying around from
package to package just scanning
all the different visible
barcodes? Exactly. Hmm. Okay. So
that's very interesting. How,
how far into how many systems
are deployed? And like, where
are you guys at in terms of
deploying yours to different
warehouses your system to
different warehouses?
Mohammed Kabir: Right. So we
have a bunch of customers, we
don't publish the exact number
on systems deployed. But it is
significant enough that we're
getting very interesting fleet
insights from them.
Audrow Nash: So order of
magnitude is like 10 100. It's
on the order of 100. Yes, that's
really exciting. 100 robots out
there. 100. Warehouses,
Mohammed Kabir: 100 vehicles.
Yeah.
Audrow Nash: And when you say
fleet, insights into fleet
management, you're meaning
multiple Have your drone systems
in a single warehouse? And how
to like urgently go about
scanning them? Yep. Yeah.
Gotcha. That's tell me a bit
about that. The different things
you're realizing at a fleet
level of controlling your
drones? Sure.
Mohammed Kabir: Let's see. So in
general, the way we design our
system, it's quite scalable. So
if you want to scale to a larger
facility, we can just add
systems basically. And they talk
to each other, the charging
docks can talk to each other and
kind of coordinate. And one of
the things we're just starting
to roll out is basically this
orchestration engine, which has
a global view of the entire
warehouse, and then it can
basically automatically tasked
groans to go and scan certain
parks either. Maybe it's a high
traffic area, which we are kind
of inferring from previous
flights, that if there's a lot
of change, and we can see that
in the data, we can, we can cast
more drones to kind of focus on
that one area, and things like
that.
Audrow Nash: That's really cool.
Yeah, you should do anything to
add
Disha Sarawgi: a bottle. Now, we
also give kind of a high level
control to the people at the
warehouse as well. We have
scheduling online, where,
whereas managers can schedule,
what time they want to draw to
go and scan what location, so
and then the charging of
orchestration figures out which
John was done there, and
autonomically does all the
missions and comes back and
charges again.
Audrow Nash: So that scheduling
that you mentioned, Keisha, it's
like you try to avoid when
people are in the area, or what
kind of why would I want to
schedule the flights of these
drones.
Disha Sarawgi: So there are
times in the warehouse where
there's too much traffic in an
area, and you'd rather dedicate
the drawing to less traffic
area, the friendships during the
day, were like, probably night
shifts have X number of people
around, and you want to get a
scan of whatever was moved
during the day. And that works
out better for people. So we
give customers that level of
control to decide what and how
they want to use this product as
well.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And could
be are that what you mentioned
for it, recognizing high traffic
areas that have a lot of change
and trying to do them? Or I was
imagining? Just I didn't
understand what about the fleet
management was extremely
interesting before because it
was like, Oh, you just patrol
certain regions. But then if a
certain region has a lot more
change, you want to make more
passes of it, because you want
to hire more temporal data.
That's very interesting. Yeah.
Gotcha. How so now that you have
100 robots out there or so like,
order of magnitude? How is this
affecting? Package loss?
Mohammed Kabir: Right, right.
Right. So one of the things
we've begun seeing is that we've
actually been able to increase
the inventory accuracy for
warehouses significantly. It
really depends on a per facility
level, how much we can help just
because facility dynamics, the
workers, their, their existing
practices. We don't have any
specific numbers, which we want
to share this point, just
because it's extremely facility
specific. And even like any
vague ballpark number idea will
be wrong. So
Audrow Nash: you can have a
specific instance of the thing.
Yeah, but I mean, maybe you have
like an average, or something or
like a median level of
improvement. Right. So
Mohammed Kabir: like, I'd be
interested in,
Audrow Nash: like, double it,
because the huge, like 60% loss
is crazy to me. And if you keep
an additional 30%, that would be
amazing. I just walk
Mohammed Kabir: across, right,
yeah, that is actually quite
close to what we almost
guarantee that if your facility
is using Corvis drones 95% Just
kind of the baseline you can
expect to achieve within months.
Yeah, and this involves working
really closely with every
customer because again, as I
said, every facility is
different. Everyone uses
different barcodes. There's
there's a lot of moving pieces
there.
Audrow Nash: See? So let's see,
can you tell me a bit about
working with these customers?
Mohammed Kabir: Um,
Audrow Nash: and maybe the chef
you have a perspective On this,
I want to try to get us all
talking about the same amount.
Disha Sarawgi: Sure, so, okay,
since the team is pretty small
right now, like, we are the ones
who actually go to the
deployment as well. And it's
good to have engineers on site
as well. Because if we build
products that people cannot use
in production, that it makes no
sense. So going on site
interacting with customers, we
get a sense of what they want,
and we build accordingly. So
like onside, Devon been
instances where customers have
told us stories, like they spent
hours on a Sunday night trying
to locate one package, which was
lost. And that's why like, and
if there was something on
Sunday, that sets them back for
the rest of the week, because
their week starts on Sunday. And
that's where our drones have
been able to get them a good
amount of improvement like that
is we have all the data stored.
And we can tell them exactly
where, what, where what package
was seen. And it has them
significantly improved their
buffers and dedicated with
others still actually getting
packages to avoid. So
Audrow Nash: that's cool. So
does this mean that you have to
tie the data that you guys
collect into their existing
package, localization
infrastructure, so like figuring
out where all the packages are,
and the map of that I imagine
it's like a grid or something
like a two 3d grid where they
say it's in here, or at this
location on this shelf, and you
have to like, locate the
package, and then map it to how
they actually represent the
location of the package. Is that
true?
Disha Sarawgi: Oh, yes. So every
facility has their own warehouse
management system, which is,
like, where every location is
tagged as, depending on the
rack. And it's not.
Audrow Nash: So it's like a
sticker is on the so say, we
have three shelves or something
high, that each shelf of those
will have a sticker or something
that says this is shelf one,
this is shelf two, this is shelf
three. Yeah. And so that's how
you localize them.
Disha Sarawgi: Yeah. So it also
is like, maybe a number as to
their eyes than their faces,
like the two faces on each eye.
So then, the next level is the
face. And then they go by the
level of the rag. And then each
level also has number of slots.
So the a hierarchical naming of
each pallet position in the
warehouse, which to keep track
of and the warehouse management
system. And we use the same
mapping, and we work with
customers to integrate the data
we collect into their management
systems as well.
Audrow Nash: So it's a big key
value problem effectively with
the key being the label of the
shelf, and then the value being
whatever packages are on it kind
of thing. That's when I guess so
if that's the case, it might not
be I basically, was it
challenging to kind of work with
all of the different warehouse
management setups that all of
the different warehouses have?
Or was there a challenge there?
Disha Sarawgi: Oh, okay. Kobe,
do you want it?
Mohammed Kabir: Sure, yeah. This
is just a huge pain generally
integrating with the consuming,
but the number of different
systems out in the wild. We have
a couple of ways of integrating
life from the very simplest
version, which we can basically
support for everyone is we just
give them a digital data dump.
It's something like a CSV or
something of that kind, which
they can. And everyone says,
yes, yes, yes, men is in
commerce,
Audrow Nash: it can be processed
like an Excel sheet. Exactly.
It's like it's essentially an
Excel sheet. Yeah. And then.
Mohammed Kabir: And then we can
also kind of go into slightly
more advanced integrations where
we have some API which they can
pull for data, or we can go the
other way, and we can push data
to their API's. This is again,
very facility specific, very
customer specific, and it's
essentially a custom integration
for every new facility.
Disha Sarawgi: We want to give
as much value to the customers
as we can, so we try to
integrate with whatever their
existing processes are and make
them make it as easy as we can.
Audrow Nash: See, so now,
getting into your drone a little
bit more. How I like just how
large is it? It has the
autonomous charging dock just
telling you bit about a bit more
about it. What sensors it has,
what it how large what it looks
like, everything should start.
Disha Sarawgi: Sure. Yeah, I'm
good tone is about.
Audrow Nash: And this is a
cordless one we're talking
about. Correct? Great. Yeah.
Yeah.
Disha Sarawgi: So it's basically
two components. We have the
landing pad, which is the
charging dock for us. And the
drone. The charging station is
about like, one meter or 2.7
meters, maybe. And the drawn is
probably, like 3.4. Yeah, five
Mohammed Kabir: meters in
diameter.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so for now,
just kind of, yes, landing
station is four feet or five
feet, like a square kind of
thing. And I saw it in a video.
And I don't know if it's
changed, but it's like a
fiducial marker, like a QR tag.
And then you have the charging
dock in the middle of it. So I'm
assuming that you're counting
that in the five foot width of
the station? Yes, yeah. Okay.
Yeah, go ahead.
Disha Sarawgi: So these are the
mountains at a height where
forklift can go through
underneath it, and we're not
causing any obstruction to
general warehouse traffic.
Audrow Nash: How did you What
was the lesson learned for why
you are mounting on the Bub
forklifts? I assume that was
like, there's some story there.
Disha Sarawgi: So yeah, like, we
genuinely love the landing pad
and the drawn to like at the end
of a warehouse racks. And there
is also a high traffic area for
anybody who wants to go into the
aisle or come out of the aisle.
And we do not want to cause any
obstruction for them to take
like a large radius around the
racks. Because some of them are
also narrow passages, which is
difficult to get through. So we
generally mount them at a height
where the drone can also operate
without obstructing the traffic
underneath it.
Audrow Nash: Did like a get run
over or where people just
frustrated that it was like a
long path around or
Mohammed Kabir: so we've had
some close calls before before
we kind of realized that we
should move it up even higher.
So one of the things about
forklifts is that they kind of
have two modes of operation. So
one is when they're just
traveling along the ground, and
therefore service fully at
ground level. And there's
another thing where if you have
to take packages off from a
higher act, they basically
extend up and then the whole
thing goes up in the forks also
go up with it. Now what happens
is, even though forklift drivers
instructed to not move around at
full extension,
Audrow Nash: sometimes even
meaning the fork all the way up
the exact right.
Mohammed Kabir: Yes, that is
correct. So they're never
supposed to actually be moving
around about the whole thing
extended in the forks all the
way up, because as you can
imagine, that's pretty
dangerous. stuff. Exactly. And
but it's actually it does happen
sometimes. And then well, as you
can imagine, they could hit our
landing pad or they could hit
other stuff. Um, that is why we
tried to position it at such a
place which minimizes any
Audrow Nash: of this kind. So
it's kind of you have like a
shelf side and then a few feet
up, you'll have your actual
landing pad, which is five foot
by five foot, approximately one
point So would you say seven
meter
Disha Sarawgi: square? Oh,
Mohammed Kabir: point 1.2 by
point seven. It's yeah,
Audrow Nash: yeah. Okay, so some
square that suspended up there,
like a little bird's nest. Yeah.
And that that has the charging
station there. You're Corvus one
drone. Does it have like guards
around the propellers? Or like
how is it set up? So it's a
quadrotor. It has four rotors.
And each of those rotors has a
propeller spinning. That's how
it lifts up. Do the propellers
have guards around them? So that
they don't like hit anything? Or
is it not a problem?
Mohammed Kabir: That actually,
there's a story behind that too.
So probably the story around
Yes, indeed. Indeed. So when we
started we actually did used to
have propeller guards around the
propellers. But after like doing
1000s of flights, one of the
things we realized was that If
there is any kind of collision
with anything, the propeller
guards don't really help in the
first place, they actually end
up. So the reason they don't
help is whatever material you
build your propeller guards out
of, they typically have some
amount of flex to them. And what
can happen is your propeller
guard can kind of bend and hit
your propellers instead. And
that's kind of a no win
situation for everyone. Because
then the drone, there's like a
catastrophic failure.
Audrow Nash: Just falls down.
Yeah, pretty much smashes on the
warehouse floor. Okay, pretty
much.
Mohammed Kabir: So the way we
started looking at the problem
was how can we prevent any kind
of a situation where there could
be a collision in the first
place. And kind of what we've
converged through is our economy
stack maintains this safety
envelope around the vehicle. And
we basically got rid of the the
hardware prop guards, and the
software makes sure that the
drone is just never close enough
to get into any situation of
that kind.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Okay, so
you found basically, you could
just stay far enough away from
everything so that you don't
need pretty much any sort of
propeller guards and the
propeller guards weren't even
that good, because they flex and
they would just go into the
propeller, and then it would
crash. So they'd be like, for
protecting fingers or something
where I would stop it. And I
would hit the propeller guard,
but then the propeller would hit
the propeller guard, and then it
would fall. So my fingers would
be okay, but the drone would
still suffer the same color. I
don't know falling from air. Why
not just use really rigid? I
guess. So you've eliminated the
need for it. I just wonder about
like, really rigid propeller.
But maybe they're heavier, they
reduce your flight time or
exactly. Yeah,
Mohammed Kabir: that's, that's
pretty much it. If you're going
to design with propeller guards
in mind, you need to kind of add
a lot of extra weight to the
vehicle, which might be
acceptable for for certain
companies, or certain people
working on drones. But for us,
as since we kind of designed
around the problem, it just was
never a thing.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. And then the
shot. Can you speak a little bit
to the are you doing something
with the cable?
Disha Sarawgi: No, I was
blogging?
Audrow Nash: Ah, yes. Yeah,
these lame to have the computer
turn off. Can you speak a little
bit to like safety concerns of
customers? Because I guess I'm
getting at what I'm getting at
with the propeller guards. Is I
wonder if people in the factory
would want something like that.
But just general safety things,
safety concerns of the customer?
This kind of thing?
Disha Sarawgi: Oh, yeah,
definitely. So safety is
something we take very seriously
because it's drawn with models
running at like 20,000 rpm, and
we do not want to collide into
anything or hurt anyone or not.
So we have a bunch of software
and hardware fail safes for
ensuring safety. We have bunch
of audio visual cues that we be
provide while taking off by
landing wire in case of
Audrow Nash: me that the drone
has a speaker and it will go
like I'm taking off now. Or like
landing now or something like
this. So people have some idea
of its intention. Yeah,
Disha Sarawgi: we actually do.
So we have Bibles on the drawn
on the landing pad, which make
it known that it's going to take
off now. Now we have a bunch of
spotlights to, like, tell people
where it's going to go, or it's
flying above you, you've taken
out or something like that, and
a bunch of flight to tell you
what it's doing now, like it's
on a flight or it's charging,
it's not charging stuff like
that, like anything that you can
as much as you can gather by
just looking at the system.
There will be a visual
Audrow Nash: indicators of its
status. Or audible as well. Yes.
Do you do any? So I was thinking
for hardware failsafe, like if
the drum does happen to
malfunction. Is there any like
because So you mentioned flying
above people? Is there any sort
of like I don't know failsafe
for something if the drone does
say for some reason, there's
just like a segfault on the
drone like worst case and it
just starts to fall. Any any
recourse from there?
Disha Sarawgi: Yeah, definitely.
That does happen sometimes. But
we have tried to resolve it by
software and our low level
thesis. So in case have an
emergency, which can be like a
mission computer, losing contact
with the landing pad or
something like that, or just
even a segfault. We try to find
a safe spot underneath the drawn
like the case, we have visual
information of everything around
the drone making figurative
Potter land, and the drone
navigates itself and land safely
around without external
intervention.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. What
sensors do you have on the
drone?
Disha Sarawgi: So for a sensor
stack, we nearly have an array
of like 12 cameras onboard?
Audrow Nash: Or do they have
like infrared? Or are there any?
Like, like low light conditions
or something? Maybe I think you
have depth cameras as well,
probably.
Disha Sarawgi: Yeah. So they're
all arranged in like, do
fashion. So we have infrared
cameras, and then we also get
information out of them. We have
a bunch of time use and modifier
to give you a no show
information. And it's basically
a visual inertial system.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So you have
a bunch of cameras are all of
the cameras, infrared depth
cameras?
Yeah. Yes.
Audrow Nash: Okay. And there's
no like, this is gonna sound
kind of silly, but there's no
like parachute on board or
something. If the book, I guess
the drone doesn't like hit
anything ever, or it hasn't. And
so that's you don't have to
worry about it, falling out
people's heads, or anything.
Like my track record. So it
isn't very
Mohammed Kabir: much. And also
another way we try to kind of
deal with this problem at the
root is we tell the customers to
schedule it in specific off
hours, when there is no traffic
in the aisles. And then we also
do us a lot of customer
training. And we train the
workers there that if you see
the drone, and it's about banter
and aisles, don't go in there,
wait for it to come back. It's
like probably going to spend
like five minutes there. So
there's a lot of like, kind of
human interaction between us and
the customer and the worker
stair which
Audrow Nash: you get exactly the
aisle, the drone is using. Okay,
because Disha you mentioned that
flying overhead in this kind of
thing. So I was imagining, like
drones, scanning people, but
need, and that seems risky to
me. Like I imagined my propeller
flies off or something that's
really hard to control for.
Disha Sarawgi: I mean, we have
safety systems in place, but
obviously the same sense to not
be that.
Audrow Nash: Yep. Gotcha. So it
can't, like you can't fly over
someone, but it's not desirable,
because it's a little bit more
risky. Yeah, exactly.
Mohammed Kabir: And variably. In
the wild, we see that someone
wanders in or someone just
didn't pay attention to what we
said. So we still design for
that kind of extreme case where
there's someone underneath it
all the time. But in reality,
that's probably like, 1% of our
international flights.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, I would
imagine far, far less. Yeah,
gotcha. Okay, so you have this
drone, it flies around. It uses
depth cameras. To get a sense of
the distance it is from
everything it probably. So do
you have to do? Like, do you
have to map the warehouse first?
Or how do you say you bring this
new drone to a new warehouse for
a new customer? How do you set
up the environment other than
putting this nest at? And by
nest? I mean, the launchpad
elevated for the drone? How else
do you do the setup? Do you do
some sort of mapping? Do you fly
the drone around? What kind of
things?
Disha Sarawgi: So yes, you are
exactly right about this. Apart
from setting the nest, we also
pre map the warehouse, which
means we get like geometric and
semantic information from the
warehouse and give the drone a
pre map environment. Based on
that we can define reasons or
slots that we want to fly in and
schedule missions accordingly
and fly exactly that.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And so for
mapping it, you just fly the
drone around and have it What
was it? So I understand? Right,
Mohammed Kabir: right, right. So
the exact process we cannot talk
about because it's something
we've developed internally. And
it's actually one of the hardest
parts of doing this even though
it may not Yeah, actually seem
so. But at the end of the day,
we're taking measurements, some
by hand Some using the vehicle
and then we're kind of putting
these together and generating
kind of a unified map for the
vehicles views.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so you will
custom generate a specific a map
for the warehouse. For that you
go off of that. Exactly. Do you
have problems? I guess the
shelves if they're really tall,
you don't have a problem where
they're like, move a few inches
or a few feet on one end, as
much.
Mohammed Kabir: Yeah,
Audrow Nash: we've actually
Mohammed Kabir: seen that. Yeah,
that does occur. It's ridiculous
again, but it does happen. Like
we have to map it again.
Whatever. So no, so we actually
designed into the system. Yeah.
So we have a map update method,
which basically deals with minor
change in the environment
automatically. So every time a
vehicle goes out, we can kind of
update the map and then share it
across the fleet. So all of the
vehicles know that. Okay, this
part changed a little bit. So
next time I go there, I know
what to do.
Audrow Nash: I see. So you're
updating a little bit with your
map. So you're doing some sort
of simultaneous localization and
mapping? Flight? And how does
the so when your drone I saw I
saw on the website, that you
only need internet connected to
the launch pad. And so when your
drone goes away, it needs to
probably stay within range of
the launch pad? Like why like
some sort of maybe it has a
router or something on the
launch pad? Or does it just does
it just go back to where the
launch pad is, and it doesn't
need that internet connection
for that period of time that it
is in flight?
Mohammed Kabir: Right? So the
way we design the system,
actually, we don't need any sort
of connection back to the launch
pad while in flight. So
everything all computation
happens on board. There is a
wireless link, but we don't
actually need it while flying.
It's just there for there's a
bunch of reasons why it's there.
But we don't actually require it
while flying. Also,
Audrow Nash: things like logging
data or something or what
Mohammed Kabir: pretty much
pretty much basically
information about flight
progress, stuff like that.
Audrow Nash: Oh, okay. That's
cool. Yeah. And then, but you
don't need that actual the
controller and the getting the
data and save saving the data
and everything that happens on
board on
Mohammed Kabir: exactly, it
happens all on the ground. And
that's another design decision,
which was actually driven by
stuff we saw. So warehouse is
like, typically it's a bunch of
metal racks, right? It's it's a
Faraday cage. And they're
terrible, terrible RF
propagation environments. Yeah,
so any sort of wireless is
destined to fail.
Audrow Nash: So that was that
was why you decided to put all
the computation on the drone.
Exactly. That's amazing. I
started in research in my
undergrad doing this kind of
thing where it was trying to put
a drone and all the computation
on the drone and having it
localize and maintain a swarm
formation. And it was really,
really difficult. This was like
10 years ago, or something. And
it's impressive now to have
everything and you're like
unbelievable suite of cameras on
your drone to it's amazing how
far things have come in the last
nine years.
Disha Sarawgi: We have extremely
long eyes in the warehouse as
was so that showboating that
kind of vibe firing is almost
impossible. I like like you have
made a backup pointer on it. So
we just had to compress
everything to onboard
combination.
Audrow Nash: Let's see. So now
talking a bit more about Corvus
as a company. So you got you
mentioned you started in 2017.
Will you tell me a little just
how did you decide to start a
company and then dish I'd love
to hear how did you decide to be
employee number two after the co
founders?
Mohammed Kabir: Yeah, sure, I
can start. Um, so basically. So
the company was, myself, Jackie,
our CEO, and then our two other
co founders, Jonathan and Brian.
And all of us, kind of happened
to come together. It was like a
matter of luck or chance almost.
So as the story goes, I knew
Brian and then Jackie knew
Jonathan. And then Jackie found
me on the internet in some
random IRC chat room and I was
helping people with drone
problems or something of that
sort. And what kind of got
connected there and decided to
kind of start looking into the
kinds of use cases which we
could all automate. Because
personally, I'm really into
automating anything that is
automatable. Just because people
should be spending their time
doing more high impact things.
So automation is really a big
part of my life. And kind of I
think this is true. Also for the
other co founders, all of them
really care about kind of this
problem space. And we sort of
came together. And it was a
really great, great team. That,
that we started with, basically,
to Brian was our hardware guy,
he's our lead of hardware today.
He does all of this. So anything
you see on the ground, it's it's
Brian, basically, all the
hardware, all of the basically
every piece, then Jonathan is
our chief of software, he does a
ton of work, both on the
autonomy stack, and also kind of
the almost, it's almost harder,
I would say, kind of the
customer integration side, which
is integrating with all these
custom systems, some of which
are from the 90s, stuff like
that. And then Jackie is our
CEO. And basically, well, yeah,
he does, he does everything. And
then all of us came together in
2017. It was like things, some,
some some point in the middle of
2017. And I told Jackie that,
okay, I know this great, good
hardware guy, my friend, we
could probably think of doing
something. And all of us came
together and decided to start
purpose.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. And how
did you pick the opportunity?
Like, how did you pick this
specific problem to work on?
Right?
Mohammed Kabir: So Jackie's
family back in China. They were
one of the very first generation
entrepreneurs in China. And he
had actually kind of firsthand
seen the problems that
warehouses go through. And kind
of this, like this huge thing.
Like as an outsider, like, I
personally had no idea about
what problems warehouses and
generally like industrial stuff,
people there go through. And
Jagga kind of introduced us to
this whole new problem space
where these sort of non sexy use
cases, which could still benefit
hugely from automation, like
it's not self driving cars, but
there's still a huge
opportunity.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, gotcha. Yeah,
that's awesome, that Jackie knew
so much. And then the shot you
joining as number two, how was
that for you? Like, how did you
decide to join this company?
Yeah. How did you like your
interest in startups at this
stage and this kind of thing.
Disha Sarawgi: So it was a bit
of both like, I personally
always wanted to work in an
early stage startup, because it
gives you the opportunity to
work on the entire stack, get a
sense of how everything's
interacting with each other,
have a good amount of ownership
on the code as well. And the
minute you get to learn is much
more than you would if you were
working just in a subsystem as
part of a big team. So it kind
of worked out that Jackie
reached out to me on LinkedIn, I
think. And I was in Austin at
the time, and I flew down to
Boston to meet the team. And I
was really intrigued by the work
we were doing, and just like
being a small team, like they
had come far, I guess, with the
hardware and the software at the
time, but I saw an opportunity
to contribute as well and get
the system to where it is now
today.
Audrow Nash: Where are you guys
located?
Disha Sarawgi: So we are in
Boston, Massachusetts, at the
moment.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Let's see.
And then just a more general
question about Corvis. How are
you guys funded? So are you
receiving investment or have you
received like a Series A or
like, where are you guys at?
Mohammed Kabir: Right? We're
Priya company. We went through Y
Combinator in 2018. We were like
the YC. Summer summer 2018.
Batch. Yeah. Cool.
Audrow Nash: And so you've
received what are they? They
they give it's like seed funding
kind of thing from a seed
funding. Yes. Gotcha. And then
you've just been running on that
and maybe pretty much are you
getting revenue from your
customers yet? Yeah. Proper
course.
Mohammed Kabir: But Yeah,
exactly, yeah. So we've been,
we've actually been deploying
for about one and a half years
now, we've been doing pilots
before that. But we've had, we
were doing production
deployments for quite a while
now. And all of these are active
revenue streams for the company.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And so are
you guys bootstrapping,
effectively where you're
reinvesting your profits back in
and you're not getting much?
Gotcha. Nice. I like that model.
Do you think that you'll be
seeking investment as a way to
kind of grow faster, or just
kind of stay off that keep
bootstrapping and keep your
equity really large? Or
Mohammed Kabir: when
Audrow Nash: I'm going forward?
Mohammed Kabir: That's that's
completely open question. We are
open to outside investment.
Because we do want to kind of
grow exponentially, we're kind
of hitting the point where we
want to scale up the engineering
team, the sales team, all of
that really quickly. So we're,
of course open to that. But
everything's on the table.
Audrow Nash: And you have to
find a good fit probably, right?
Because you guys are in a
powerful situation where you're
not exactly burning through your
money. And meeting investment,
possibly under bad terms, these
kinds of awesome. Now, let's
see, I see that we're coming
close to the time that we were
saying we should end. So what
I'd like to do for our last
little bit, is just asked you
guys general questions about
like, where robotic is going?
And then advice things. So the
shot could you start, and I
would like to know what advice
you would give to like a 20 year
old view?
Disha Sarawgi: Um, okay, I think
that's pretty straightforward.
Because yeah, I mean, okay, my
point is not long ago. Yeah,
Audrow Nash: that to someone
else added up? Yeah.
Disha Sarawgi: Well, to two
younger badasses, I would say,
just do what you love. And do
not be afraid, like, if it's an
engineering solution that you
don't know the answer to keep at
it, because that is what
engineers are helpful, like to
think of problems and solve them
even when you do not think of
answers as the first goal. So
just in general, the problem
solving aspect is engineering
appears to me. And that is what
I love doing. And if you're good
at it, keep doing it.
Audrow Nash: Let's see Kabir
same question. Advice for
younger you.
Mohammed Kabir: Vice for younger
me. Um, let's see, I think one
of the big things that's kind of
been a part of my engineering
journey has been open source
software, I feel really strongly
about open source, and also the
stack at corpus, which we built,
it leverages a lot of open
source pieces. For example, we
use ROS 1, we use the px for
autopilot stack. And I kind of
started interacting with all of
these at a very young age. And I
think, kind of working with a
lot of experienced people in the
same field. And that kind of
experience can only come from
being on a team, like
individually, there's only so
much you can do. Like you can
take classes, you can study, you
can look up stuff yourself. But
I think being a part of an open
source software team really gave
me a bunch of skills, which I
use everyday now. I would
really, really advise people to
kind of pick a project you love
or biggest space you love, find
a project in that space, and
then see where see where it
goes, you will learn a lot on
the way.
Audrow Nash: And what are some
of the most valuable parts to
you of contributing to open
source? So obviously, your
learning skills but like what
specific things were most
valuable in your experience?
Mohammed Kabir: Right. So when I
started, like working on drones,
I think this was when I was in
middle school or something. I
started looking at kind of what
the options were if I wanted to
build my own drone, and I didn't
know anything at that point. I
was just like a middle school
kid. And then eventually, I came
across the px for autopilot,
which is this open source
software stack for drones. And
what this lets people do is
there's a certain set of
supporting hardware, and you
keep this open source software,
put it on that and then boom,
you have your own drone, mess
around a little bit with the
hardware, but effectively it's a
it's a pretty easy solution if
you're trying to build something
on your own with no experience
before. And eventually what what
my story personally looked like
was I started using px for as a
user. But eventually I started
contributing back to upstream. A
lot of the things which I wanted
to do, but the features didn't
exist at the time. And
eventually what this led into
was, I became a part of the core
kind of maintenance team, which
maintains the entire project.
And that that branches out into
helping other people doing code
reviews, just a lot of skills,
which there was no way I thought
I would have learned unless I
kind of got into it in the first
place.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Now, let's
see a wrapping up. Is there any
links that you guys would like
to share? So in the show notes,
we'll put a link to Corvus is
website. Anything else worth
share? Sure, we
Mohammed Kabir: have this demo
reel of Corvis. One, which we'd
probably like to show off. I can
send you the link after the
talk. And it'll be that'd be
pretty nice. I
Audrow Nash: think you guys have
social media or anything you'd
like to share the shot? Do you
have anything?
Disha Sarawgi: Yeah, we do have
garbage on the garbage website,
and it was on Twitter. And we
will send you all the links.
Mohammed Kabir: Yeah, we'll send
your Twitter handles and
LinkedIn and whatever else.
Audrow Nash: Okay, great. Well,
it's been a pleasure speaking
with both of you. It's been a
pleasure.
Disha Sarawgi: Thanks for taking
time.
Audrow Nash: Thanks for
listening to this conversation
with Disha and Kabir. Thank you
again to our founding sponsor,
Open Robotics, and I hope to see
you next time