Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Steve
Macenski, who is the Open Source
Robotics Engineering lead at
Samsung Research America. Steve
leads the Nav2 two project,
which is an open source robot
navigation framework. In this
interview, Steve and I talk
about the problem and challenges
in robot navigation, how Nav2
works at a high level, hybrid
planners, and about Steve's
experience working with the Nav2
community. This is the Sense
Think Act Podcast. I'm Audrow.
Nash. Thank you to our founding
sponsor Open Robotics. And now
here's my conversation with
Steve.
Steve, would you introduce
yourself?
Steve Macenski: Hi, yeah, I'm
Steven Macenski. And the open
source engineering lead for a
box at Samsung research. So I'm
the lead developer on the ROS
to navigation stack. And I sit
on the TSC. For us, too, as
well. And the TSC is the
Technical Steering Committee.
Correct? Yeah. So it's like the
the board for ROS, let's say.
So it's a bunch of different
companies that kind of come
together with Idris and ROS 2
to make sure that we can see the
project the right direction.
Audrow Nash: So yeah, tell me a
bit about the navigation stack
or not. And then how that
relates to NAV two.
Steve Macenski: So I'm going to
navigate stack was the the, you
know, the software built at
Willow Garage to do you know,
mobile based application, you
know, primarily for the PR to
robot. But now even in those
early days, they understood that
a lot of the same technology
could be applied to other mobile
platforms. So I made at the time
they made it, it was awesome.
The fact that there was a
software out there that was free
and open source and with a
strong community around it with
documentation and examples and
all that kind of good stuff. But
you know, over time, you know,
that was, you know, in the very
early days of robotics, where
basically the light robot you
could buy if your home was like,
you know, an iRobot Roomba. And
there really were few of any
kind of service robots, you
know, in application. What year
do you think this was? Was this
like, 22,000? Or when do you
think it was like 12 ish is when
started. And then there's a big
push to update some algorithms.
And I think the summer of 2011
2012, when a bunch of insurance
guy came in, and absolute new
new variations of the
algorithms.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so you had
this open source navigation
stack? And that was with Willow
Garage. And then how did that
evolve?
How did that how did we go from
there? Yeah,
Steve Macenski: so it's after
we'll closed in the 2013
timeframe, kind of all major
developments on the navigation,
kind of kind of halted. So you
had folks like David Liu and
Mike Ferguson that continued to
maintain things over time, to
date. So David was, you know,
working at Lucas robotics and
working as a consultant doing
doing various navigation work.
And then Mike Ferguson was
starting, what was the precursor
to Fetch robotics, then later,
Fetch robotics. And so he was
using in the early days, some of
the navigation stuff, I think,
these days, I have to assume
everything's been stripped out
their systems at this point, but
in the early days to try and
build that MVP to get the
venture capital money, that
that's the he was working on on
the napkin stuff, as well. But
then, you know, nothing really
major change from from 2013,
basically, until about, you
know, 2019 or so when, you know,
ROS 2 started hitting kind of
more mature milestones. So I
think with without see is when
Matt Hanson, in the open source
robotics team at Intel, had a
big post a discourse saying
that, hey, there, they want to
work on this roster navigation
stack. They didn't want it to
just be a straight port for
boss, one that wants to redesign
from the ground up based on
like, the current requirements
that are basically is asking
people to air their grievances
about the boss one stack, or
what kinds of things they were
swapping out the stack because
they didn't meet the
requirements. And so that that
actually, that discourse posts,
I still today occasionally open
up and go down a list of refers
to it to make sure Yeah, to make
sure like, okay, oh, like I
forgot about this, we still
haven't addressed this point.
And I'll add that to my queue.
But at this point, a lot of
those lob abroad, things that
people said are have not been
handled for the most part. So
really, Matt, and the team at
Intel, really put like the
legwork in to get this get the
ball rolling. And when they did
that's kind of when I when I
jumped on on the bandwagon to
start working on things. But
that's essentially how that app
to project kind of got going.
And how we got a lot of the
architectural elements we see
today.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So if I
understand correctly, so it was
started at Willow Garage in
2010. Ish. And the as a general
navigation library, and then
ROS 1 came out. And it was
used with ROS 1. So the
general navigation code was
using ROS 1. It continued and
people were using that. And then
ROS 2 came out in an early
version, he said bouncy, and
then you then ask the community
for what was wrong or what could
be improved. And then this is
how we have come to NAV to
Steve Macenski: Yeah, I mean,
that's it It wasn't me that that
was Matt and the team at Intel,
they were really the ones in the
early days when you're porting
stuff over and starting to do
some of the core architecture
elements that were taking the
lead. So I think they had like
six people working on it. So
they there was a lot of
professional software
engineering time put into it.
And in those early
Audrow Nash: days, nice, and how
did you get involved?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so I've
been kind of doing open source
stuff for a bit before that
point. So when I was doing the
robotics team at semi robotics,
I built the STL layer, as well
as the SAM toolbox library. And
so I've already done a couple of
ROS con talks on those topics.
So Samsung was looking to hire
somebody to work with the open
source group on various open
source box technologies. And
they've reached out to Matt
Hanson asking kind of who they
might recommend that would be
good for this. And they said
that, you know, I might be good,
good, good candidate. At the
time, I was leaving Sydney
robotics, and so is really good
transition to go over to Samsung
research, to work on this open
source technology full time,
versus just, you know, working
on these problems that are
specific to Cindy, for the end
products, and then open sourcing
the little bits here and there
that makes sense open source.
You know, now I can start
working on open source things
and make big infrastructure
changes that are that are fully
in the open.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it's awesome.
It's an awesome position to be
in. It's fun. Oh, yeah. With. So
tell me kind of at a high level,
what problems does not have to
solve?
Steve Macenski: For work to
solve? Yeah, so now, nav two is
basically sitting between you
have a bunch of motors and a
motor controller that can take
take philosophy commands to go
forward and your autonomy
application where you want
robots, you say I want robot to
go there. So it kind of deals
with everything in the middle
from the the mapping and
localization systems, which I
consider to be slightly
separated from navigation, I
consider the navigation, one
problem set and localization to
be another problem set. But we
do have reference
implementations that work with
AMC LSF toolbox for that
localization element. And then
on the navigation side, and we
say, well, now that we know
where we are within some global
representation of the world, and
we have this global
representation of the world, how
do we, you know, navigate the
space in order to, you know, go
to our to our final goal. So
this could be in a warehouse,
like the position on a shelf,
where you want to have go pick a
box, or with your Roomba say,
you know, what's this little
pattern I want to nap on the
floor in order to clean my
space? So we solved that problem
of saying, how do we take some
sensor data from from just
hardware and populate a
representation of our
environment, given the current
state of the world? And then
once we have the state of the
world, how do we make a route
that goes from where I am to
where I want to be within that
environment. And then finally,
dealing with the the lower level
system of okay, how I now follow
this path that goes from where I
am to where I want to be
accurately efficiently. And
there's obviously more little
bells and whistles on widgets,
here and there to help make that
you know, either more efficient
or more configurable or deal
with fault tolerances and things
like that. But that'd be kind of
the core problem navigation and
actually tries to solve.
Audrow Nash: So it's, it's
sounds like several things. How
do you? How do you find a good
delimiter? Between math two and
other ROS libraries? Like ROS
to control for example, or move
it or any of these other ones?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so I guess
these all become parallel
pillars. I mean, these are all
by themselves really significant
applications that have their own
specific developer code bases
and don't own individual
ecosystems, and are they
themselves you know,
equivalently complex challenges
to solve. So move that I say in
the most simplistic terms is our
navigation, which was actually
the the the library name from
Willow Garage that became move
it was application. So it's
often the same kinds of problems
as as the mobile robot
navigation that nav two solves,
but for arms, so it's taking
potentially sensor data to build
an environmental representation.
In the case of movement, they're
using Okta map and with 3d
Octrees, then they're using
sampling based motion planning
in order to get a a rough plan
from point A to point B. And
using various smoothing
techniques usually optimization
base to smooth those out to be a
little bit less clunky on the on
the motors earlier while you're
going through the sampling base
planner would give you naturally
and then finally, then having
those the same kind of local
trajectory controllers, we have
Neptune now with the hyperplane
schema. So there's somebody a
very, very analog problem,
pretty much everything they
exist in that one nephew,
rather, and move and have some
sort of direct analog to each
other for the most part. And
then your ROS control is is
kind of sitting in that lower
level on the actual electronics
solving the motor control issue
of saying, you know, I have this
I have this motor and I want to
control this motor to do
something interesting for me. So
if you have a differential drive
robot, how do I take this this
block The command I get for
navigation and and follow that
with, with my my motor efforts,
or for manipulation, which is
frankly, more of what ROS
control is used for has, you
know more advanced impedance
controllers and other other type
of modeling to deal with, you
know, the kind of manipulation
problem. For the most part, the
navigation control systems at
the lower level are, you know,
very simple, right, this is the
kind of stuff that
undergraduates might do in
their, their, their intro to
controls lab, it's not not
overly complex,
Audrow Nash: like a, like a
proportional integral derivative
or PID controller kind of thing
or, yeah, to try to get it to a
position.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, pictures
are pretty, pretty common, as
well as it potentially if you're
working on warehousing robot
where you have, you know,
different different weights of
opposite objects on top of it.
You there's other slightly more
advanced control scheme you
might use, that's based on on
efforts rather than just just
photocurrents
Audrow Nash: Petrit. Now, why is
can you tell me some of the
challenges and making something
perform navigation? Like, what
are some of the problems that
nav two is solving, and there's
some flexibility around the ways
it salts but so
Steve Macenski: yeah, so, you
know, one of the biggest
challenges is just taking both
the representation of your
environment you have from from
mapping or localization or you
know, other previous data that
you've collected and somehow
assembled. And then the current
data you have about the
environment. So if you have a 2d
laser scanner on it, or you have
a RGB camera on it, which
provides you depth information,
as well as color camera
information, in, you know,
radars, sonars tall sensors, I
mean, there's, there's a large
variety of different sensors
that you can utilize that robot.
And most robot systems actually
have multiple these types of
sensors on them. So the problem
is dealing with how do we take
all that sort of information and
populate something that is now
useful to solve the navigation
problem. And so we do that with
a navigation stack with the the
cost of 2d package, which is
essentially a direct port. For
last one, we have some
additional plugin layers, we've
added for more advanced
capabilities, but you know, high
level, exact same package, long
term, we'd like to actually
replace that with something a
bit a bit more advanced. But at
the moment, that's where we're
at. So that's one of the big
problems. Another problem is
saying, Okay, well, now that we
have this populated
representation of my environment
with current sensor data is
being fused into it. How do I
actually plan within that space
so that my robot can can, you
know, achieve its goal? And so
there's a variety of different
methods of doing that,
obviously. So there's, there's,
you know, holonomic planners
that work well with like 2d, or
grid, basically techniques that
work very well with
Audrow Nash: holonomic. It means
it's like a car or something,
right? And non holonomic. robot
can drive like sideways and
things where a car has to go
forward or backward. That's what
all means, right? Or?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, it's a hot
holonomic means it can move in
any direction. So think about a
robot with Swiss wheels, or
whatever they're called, or
yeah, those little roller
wheels. Yeah. Or, or
potentially, where you can pick
the wheels themselves to be able
move sideways. Yep, those are
considered to be holonomic
robots. On a first order
approximation, we also say that
differential drive robots, if
they're circular are also
holonomic. Because if you can
pit it perfectly in place as a
different drive robot, and
you're circular, so your your
footprint isn't moving, you can
you can achieve the same kind of
behavior as with a truly
holonomic robot,
Audrow Nash: because the angle
is facing and then you can drive
anyway. I see. Yeah.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, precisely.
So for those kind of robots,
it's really easy to leverage
just like, you know, your usual
a storage actress algorithm that
you might learn in, like an
intro to algorithms class, but
those are perfectly serviceable,
you probably want to do some
smoothing on it, if you are
doing a direct research so that
you don't have like little
jaggedy lines on thing. But you
know, it's there's there's
different ways we do that
through navigation functions,
which are basically generating
these potential fields of cost
that you're you're tracing on
instead of just like directly
just doing a grid search. But I
mean, at a at a conceptual
level, they're, they're, you
know, the same kind of class of
algorithm. As a star. Yeah, it
is. They solve the same kind of
problems. Yeah, they're, they're
giving you a path through space.
Audrow Nash: Yep. And if I
remember correctly, so for a
star, it's a heuristic, a search
that you say the goal is that
way and I'm going to try to
search in that direction. And
then you find the optimal in a
grid world you'll find the
optimal solution of what's the
shortest path to get there. And
what was extras? Because it is
it more general thing or forget
how it relates?
Steve Macenski: Just breath
first, it just goes in every
direction at the same time. You
don't have there's not a
heuristic that that saying, like
go in that direction, it's just
gonna go out and expand its
hole, find the optimal solution.
Audrow Nash: Okay, and then we
feel for these if you have a
start and an end spot, and so
it's going to search the space,
and it's going to find it. And
we're representing space in a
grid world, or some sort of
representation. And so that's
why you would have these kind of
jagged edges, rather than a
smooth way to get there, per se,
if you go up into diagonal to
the grid.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so So you
had like, basically, the motion
model motion model, so to speak,
that you're using is, is the the
search neighborhood. So you're
saying, I can search, you know,
left, right up down for like the
four connects neighborhood or
say uptown, you know, up, down,
left, right, and then the
diagonal? So that's the eight
connected space, and so that
they'll let you then work at,
you know, how do you plan to go
45 degrees, but you're still
restricted only to these, these,
you know, exactly the angle
increments of either going, you
know, zero 90 or 45 degrees for
your planner. So this works, you
know, fairly well, when you're
working with just a simple, you
know, simple base that like you
might see on your on your on
your Roomba over this kind of
breaks down, it becomes more of
a significant issue is when
you're working with your larger
noncircular robots. So think
about like a forklift, or you're
thinking about like, I think
that's robotic cells, like a big
platform robot, I don't, I don't
know they call it. It's like
something 1500 bucks. The thing
is, and those are obviously
like, very noncircular. And so
even though they are a
differential drive robot and get
pivot in place, if you need to
do a bit bit more work to make
sure that it's a viable the
plant or a space when you're in
a narrow aisle way where maybe
the robot can just trivially
rotate in place,
Audrow Nash: because it could
swing and hit something because
it Yeah, exactly. It's
rectangular or something. Okay,
Steve Macenski: yeah. And the
other big kind of class of
problem that that you have
working with those techniques
is, when you have drive trains
aren't, you know, trivial that
you can treat essentially as
holonomic. So you mentioned
before, like cars like the
Ackermann model, which is the
car model we talked about. So
that that's, that's one example
of where if you just plan a path
as is go here, go straight to
the right, you know, your car
can't do that, right. That's
not, that's not a feasible way
of getting from point A to point
B for the actual drive train at
the robot. So you have to then
take into account, not just like
the the emotion model of saying
this for a cap space, but
instead, using in your search
space, user space planner,
actual motion primitives that
better describe the capabilities
of your drive train. And that's
where we have some of the new
algorithms that Neptune provides
in the snap planner, which is
the hybrid, a star planner, and
the state lattice planner, which
would enable us to set different
search patterns, so that you can
create physically feasible paths
that robots with with
constrained drive trains can
actually navigate exactly and
not not Not, not not not treat
as holonomic.
Audrow Nash: So by search
patterns, human kind of
simulating the position in
space, to try to see if it's
valid from one position to
another. So like, I have a car,
I'm going to try to move it from
one spot to another. And I'm
going to kind of project it out
into the future and try to see
if that path gets us there, or
what do you mean by search?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so So
imagining in this this 2d
example, we said, If I'm at the
cell, I can, the cells I can
recently traverse are either up
down and left or right in this
forecasted space. So that that
will be the motion model that
we're using to, to to expand
search. Because then once you go
up, we apply the same for then
you just keep doing that
recursively. And you get, you
know, eventually like a
chessboard span basically.
Audrow Nash: Okay. Yeah.
Steve Macenski: So with for
instance, let's, let's talk
about the simpler one first. So
for hybrid, a star, which the
name kind of breaking that down
you a hybrid. So you know,
there's something different
about this than a star. So
you're still using this, like
heuristic search algorithm at
its core. And what that's doing
is, is what we're first who is
hybrid sampling, which is that
instead of just naively saying
we're going to, we're going to
visit each of these grid cells
just as the grid structure.
Instead, we're going to treat
our search neighborhood as
primitives of actual velocity
commands the robot can achieve.
So for a car like model, you can
either turn left and drive a
bit, you can go straight and
drive bit or you can turn right
and those are the premises.
Audrow Nash: The turn left a
little bit turn right a little
bit go straight. Yeah, I suppose
backwards as well. And
backwards, or whatever. Okay,
precisely.
Steve Macenski: Yeah. So those
are the vacancies. Yeah. And
then, you know, for the sake of
implementation, the length of
these primitives you want to set
is something interesting and
not, you know, arbitrarily just
like driving the future a bunch
because then you'd otherwise
you'd end up going in circles on
the left circles on the right
and so straight forever. You
have to decide, like, what are
the lengths of these things I
want to work with.
Audrow Nash: Okay, and you want
to swap it basically, so that
you can find things okay. So you
don't go all the way in that
circle, if you turn your wheel a
little bit to the left kind of
thing. Yeah.
Steve Macenski: But because
we're also still working. So to
go back, we're still working in
this grid space, though. So we
need to make sure that we go
small amount, but needs to be
enough. So that guarantees that
we leave our current cells. So
as we're expanding the search
over time, we don't have
situations where we're
revisiting the same cell we
currently had, was certainly
something that can be dealt
with. Yep. Yeah. Or actually,
they, it's all geometry, you
have read the code. And this is
like, you know, six lines, where
I go through step by step how to
mentally drive this, this this
idea. But while the paper itself
of the hybrid star from from
Thron, and folks from the DARPA
Urban Challenge, or grand
challenge, one of the
challenges, they they, I think,
allow you to do that to have
some sort of solution space for
how they select which one to
use. I instead say I don't want
to deal with that problem. I'm
assuming I printed sufficiently
long, so we always guaranteed to
leave a cell. So there are a
minimum square root of two cell
lengths away from each other. So
that way, we're guaranteed for
any time that the proof hits a
cell, it's always guaranteed to
leave that cell in the next
iteration.
Audrow Nash: And are we
ourselves always squares?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, um, well,
I guess they don't don't have to
be. But I mean, the first I have
to they are, yeah, gotcha. They
could be circles. They could be
hexagons, I've actually I did
some, some research and a couple
papers I've, I've just not
written for publication, but
written terms of like, you know,
to take in regarding actually
having an environmental Model B,
you have a hex hexagonal cells,
rather than grid cells. But that
ends up having a whole lot of
other issues. But it's
interesting to think
Audrow Nash: about. Okay, so you
have this grid, and you have a
way of describing how your robot
moves in this grid. If you have
a robot that's like a car or
something you have some idea
for, if you tell it to drive
forward at left for this angle,
or something, how it goes into
another cell? How do you just it
sounds like a hard
representation, because I'm
imagining, if I turn the wheel
10 degrees to the left, like,
and I drive, I'm not in the
middle of a cell, but I guess I
still am in a cell. And you can
use that for planning your
trajectory.
Steve Macenski: So rather than
just so with these grid based
methods, or essentially
visiting, let's say, like, we go
up, down, left and right, yeah,
we could say that, that, you
know, you're you're not busy and
arbitrary place in that cell,
right. Because if you blow that
any, any any space, we blow it
up infinitely, to go to look at
it. So we look a little cell and
make it really big. It's like,
well, we're visiting any random
place we're visiting, let's say
the center or an edge, depending
on how you want to find it, of
that cell and each cell are
visiting the center of, but when
you're working with these motion
primitives, you're right, we
don't actually have exact angle,
these aren't computers that were
ending exactly in the center of
every single cell every single
time. So we do actually have the
cash in the planning sequence,
where within that, that, that
that that cell, we've actually
landed, and then when we go
back, and we visit that cell to
expand it, again, we're actually
not using the center of that
cell, we're again using that
that position within the cell
that we actually visited, which
then, you know, if you compound
that over and over again, to
build a path, that means that
it's exactly drivable in this
grid
Audrow Nash: space. A little
confused by that?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, um, so if
you were, if you were to have,
for instance, like a naive
implementation of this, you
might think about saying, let's
approximate that I had this this
this primitive that I'm
projecting forward at a curve,
and it ends at within a cell,
but not in the center of the
cell, it might be natural for
you to think if you come from an
from like a 2d grid lands space
to say, Oh, well, you know,
these, these, these cells, these
B cells are sufficiently small
that I can just store that as
the as I've entered the cell.
And then the next iteration,
when you when you visit that
cell to expand it to get its
neighbors, you could then say,
Okay, well, let's just pretend
like we started at the center
and expand it again. But if you
keep doing that, then the path
you get at the end of it
actually isn't then respecting
the constraints on that motion
model. Because you're you're not
accurate, you're that the small
errors compound, each of each
individual primitive. So instead
of, yeah, so So doing that when
we when we, we visit, we visit a
cell and we're trying to find
its neighbors, we're not using
an approximation of the position
that we're using. As like the
center, we're using the real
position of the actual cell
coordinates used, so that as
that compounds together that's
going to be guaranteed to be
drivable within the kinematics
of the of the the robot system.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. So how
does it work if I want to go
from one spot to another spot,
and I have these motion
primitives, which say I can turn
and for these motion primitives,
if I have a car? Do you have
like basically infinite motion
primitives because you have the
whole degree of angles that the
car can go or how Is it? How do
you go from one spot to another?
Do you know what I'm asking?
With? Motion permitted? Yeah,
yeah. So you have the continuous
range between, say, minus 45 and
positive 45, that the car can
travel in, that the wheels could
face.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so so we
subsample that space. So
essentially, we have for the
hybrid star, and in the current
implementation that that exists
today, you have a left turn, you
have a right turn either
straight turn, and then you have
the reverse equivalents of those
things. So you have either three
or six motion primitives you're
working with, that are the most
extreme terms, right? The the
your your robot model can
obtain, and it randomly samples
in
Audrow Nash: that space, or just
uses one of one of the six will
expand.
Steve Macenski: So expand all of
them, right. So every time we
visit a cell from an A star, we
expand every single cell, and we
set a heuristic cost at the end
value of that cell that goes
into a priority queue to sort
who I the the most optimal
trajectory possible. And then
when we go back through and
visit the next cell in that
priority queue, you're getting
back out that that next cell
that you want to go to, so
you're not, that's not a goal.
It's not like a the, the, it was
not a heuristic search, and
you're using a set A dexterous
algorithm on this kind of thing.
And right, every single aisle
six, aisle six, aisle six, and
you just be spreading and
spreading and spreading out,
which is problematic. That's
where your priority,
Audrow Nash: so which is very
clever. We're Yeah, it seems
like you're going to do it.
Steve Macenski: Yeah. That's
pretty standard for a star's
that that's kind of, at least to
my understanding, that's how
most people do it.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So you, but
it's not. So you're only using
these primitives of like extreme
angles. So it's all the way this
all the way left all the way
right or straight? If we're just
doing the forward case. In this
case, if I How do you arrive at
a solution where the robot
doesn't drive like incredibly
manically doing all the way left
all the way? Right, on its way
towards its goal?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so that's
where we have a smoothing step
at the end of this. So this we
do this for
Audrow Nash: the house space,
basically, this is this is for
you arriving at a solution. And
then from that solution, you
smooth it.
Steve Macenski: Yeah. So so we
have. So we thought through
this, we have now a path that is
rival maybe, yeah, little
suurvey. But drivable. And so
what we do is we take that path,
and we put it into a smoothing
algorithm, which will, you know,
take out some of those extreme
turns and make them a little bit
more, or I guess, less
aggressive. And then also goes
through the boundary conditions
to make sure that those remain
tight during the entire entire
process. So that part
Audrow Nash: of boundary
conditions and make sure, yeah,
what do you mean by that?
Steve Macenski: So sorry, to
type that word. But so
essentially,
Audrow Nash: we mean, optimal at
night, but what do you mean,
like a good solo error? Or I
don't know what you mean,
actually.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so we
have. So in the hyperstar, paper
that is published that, you
know, an autonomous driving
company might use, for instance,
has a pretty advanced move
there. And in fact, this is the
some of the information we used
to use within the spec planner,
that takes into account, you
know, keeping spacing, the
sames, which helps us
smoothness, using our Fermoy
diagram to help you drive away
from obstacles and then limiting
the curvature so that you you
keep those constraints that you
had during the planning process.
And I think a couple other terms
as well. And those then spin
through an optimization problem
to give you an optimal solution.
Given those those cost
functions, this ends up being a
very computationally expensive
thing to do. And it's ultimately
why I removed that, and instead,
Swift changed up a bit of the
internal systems of how the
search the search, or restrict
operates, so that we don't have
to use that kind of smoothing
technique. But what we use
instead is essentially like a
super, super naive, smoother,
like you might find in like, I
don't know, like, one of those
Udacity nano degree kind of
things, we just go through very
simply and say, like, let's make
these things as close together
as possible. And then iterate
until we have very little change
left in our in our in our
outside path between
Audrow Nash: these things, which
actually things have close to
each other. What I mean by that
Steve Macenski: each of the the
points on the path.
Okay, so
Steve Macenski: in opposition to
land, it's maybe not as
intuitive to somebody who isn't
who's worked with it. But it's
something that that's generally
a very successful way of
smoothing is just say, all my
points my path, I want to make
sure that they're each as close
they're evenly distributed from
each other. And when you iterate
over that and try to minimize
that cost function, you end up
actually smoothing out the path
from from turn to such which is
a convenient and easy Oh, that's
a waste smoothie. I
Audrow Nash: see. It's basically
like the shortest path from
something is straight to it. And
so if you're making all your
points closer to each Other, you
probably are working towards
that. Because they will be
further. That is a cool
heuristic to use to smooth.
Yeah. Interesting. So if
Steve Macenski: you had no no
other, other things doubting
that solution, and essentially
what you're right, and just
being exact, perfect. Just
ignore everything. Yeah, yeah.
But that's why I have to add in
things like, collision looks
otherwise Yeah, definitely all
into it, for sure. Yeah. And
then, because we derive it
kinematics, these will path we
also want to add some weights on
the original path itself. So
that, like, if you have a little
squiggle that could be made into
a straight line, we want that to
smooth out. But we don't
necessarily want something to
turn from a nice smooth turn,
just like you know,
Audrow Nash: Arvon drivers kind
of thing.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, where it's
no longer actually also valid by
the current motion model. And so
I have, I tried this more in the
actual the readme file. And I
don't think it's worth getting
to the specific details of this
at the moment. But essentially,
you can, you can, through
logical proofs, find that the
only time when you break
feasibility is during sharp
turns at the beginning and the
end of the path. And so those
are the boundary conditions,
okay, so the boundary conditions
totally break during this
process. So if you were to try
and drive the robot using just
that pseudo described, both the
start and the end would not be
guaranteed to be drivable. So we
do is we have an additional post
processing step on the beginning
and the end of it, where we use
the Kinect motion model of the
robot that we use previously
during that planning technique
to take the Star Pose and then
sample across the new smooth
path until we find a the
shortest path that goes from the
start the actual starting point
to a point on the smooth path,
or to give us a drivable
connection point between those
two areas. And so by doing that,
then we end up with a smooth
path that also then then meets
the boundary conditions of
drivability, and therefore the
end path is
Audrow Nash: drivable. So I
don't know that I fully
understand that. But can you
think of it as just if the start
and end will be wrong because of
some weird boundary conditions
in the optimization, you just
extend them a little bit. So you
consider like a little before
the start and a little after the
end? Assuming the motion
primitive, just continue with
something like this or?
Steve Macenski: So I actually I
tried that it didn't work. But
yeah, I did. I did try that I
tried a bunch of stuff before I
found the solution that we
currently use. So essentially,
so this is where it gets it gets
a little out into the weeds. So
within these planners, we also
have a concept called analytic
expansion, where occasionally
during our search process, we
take our search position and our
goal position. And we use a
library called Oh MPL, the open
motion planning library, which
is commonly used for sampling
bass planning implementations.
They also have a very good
implementation of the Ackermann
models that you can use both for
sampling but also in our
Audrow Nash: model shows, our
models are for tire with two
steering ones, the front ones
here.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, yeah, like
a double bicycle, or whatever.
Is that? Yeah, yeah. So we can
use that to then say, here's our
start point, here's our end
point and points opposes rights,
their orientation associated
with them, and then give me a
path to where I am to where I
want to go. And then we then
check for collisions to make
sure it's actually valid. And
most the time during your your
planning, right, that isn't
valid, right, it's going through
a wall or something. So you
throw it out and continue
searching, and then maybe
another 20 iterations to try
again, until you find a
solution. And that helps a lot
with the speed of the planner.
So most of your planning time
and a kingdom activities will
planner is spent actually on
just getting to that exact goal,
position and orientation. So if
you can speed it up by having
something they'll find exact
curve fits, that helps you quite
a bit. So we apply that same
concept, then after the
smoothing process to say, here's
our starting point, which is
fixed as our as our starting
point or our end goal point,
which are both fixed. And then
we basically say every, I think
it's like five or 10, or some
some number of points on the on
the smooth output, we find the
feasible solution between those
two things, and we measure the
length of it, and we check the
feasibility for it. And we do
that for you know, up until
basically, you know, for I think
it's bounded, but you know, far,
far into the into the path until
we find the shortest collision
free path possible. The shortest
point here is actually very
important is if you were to try
to find the feasible solution
between your starting point and
a point that's, you know, just
just directly in front of it,
that's how shifted just a little
bit away, you don't get gained
this loop to loop maneuver to
make that feasible. You don't
really want your robot doing a
loop de loop. So we check so we
continue to march through the
path a few times until
essentially that loop de loop
goes away. And that now be a
shorter path, then that full
circular path
Audrow Nash: I'm thinking of if
you have like a piece of thread
or something and you try to move
it, you grab it in the middle
somewhere with two hands and
then you move it close to each
other it'll do a loop and this
is like your hands are the
points and it has to do a loop
to go through both points. Yes
kind of thing.
Steve Macenski: So you Yeah,
exactly. So we we, we don't just
just randomly marks through a
bike five points or whatever,
there's, there's a more
principled approach we use based
on on, you know, certainly the
fact that we know that we build
is exactly a circle. And
therefore we can we can select
interesting parts of the path
based on that on that circle,
the quarter circle. And yeah,
that that's how we constrain the
boundary conditions to be to be
reasonable. And while that
sounds very, it sounds like a
very naive approach to it, I
will say is very effective. And
other things I did, which were
maybe a bit more principled, did
not work nearly as well. So this
is the the solution, ultimately,
we select strikes
Audrow Nash: me that that's
often the way in robotics, where
it's like, this simple thing
works really well, and is fast,
and solves most of the problems.
Like a lot of our heuristics
seem to be this way.
Steve Macenski: Um, yeah, yeah.
Yeah. I mean, yeah.
Audrow Nash: So yeah, I mean,
there's obviously exceptions.
But I'm just amazed how far you
can get with simple
representations for a lot of
things. The so is this.
Actually, once you have your, so
you have your grid world, in
your grid world, you use your
motion primitives to kind of
explore it for to get from one
cell to another, and then you
get this rough path that goes
from start to end. And then once
you have that rough path with
like crazy, if you're driving
like crazy, all the way left all
the way, right turns, so it's
all jagged. Once you have that,
then you run this smoothing
function on it, and the
smoothing function is going to
smoother on it. And that's going
to make it so that you have a
smoother path. And the clever
thing about that is you look for
what makes the points the
closest distance because that's
more likely the or that that is
the more optimal solution.
Right? Is that correct?
Steve Macenski: Yeah. More or
less? More or less? Yeah, don't
wait, don't wait. yet. Don't
only crush important, Vic,
there's so when you get that
path out from my brain star,
it's it's not nearly as this
crazy thing as possible. Because
right, we're talking about this
really small motion primitives.
So if one thing is it's a little
tweak, tweak, you know, you
barely even notice it without a
path when you have something
happening.
Audrow Nash: It's true. But if
you had a robot, it would be
crazy. Like imagine being on a
car that was following that one,
it would turn all the way left,
then all the way right, to try
to do something crazy. So but
Steve Macenski: you also have
like a local trajectory plan
that's processing, that
information has to be smoothed
out yet. But before we get into
that too much, the point I want
to make there was that, because
they're small, they really don't
make that much of an impact it
like super small, like like to
to grid cells wide, you know,
kind of a
Audrow Nash: big grid. So we
have an autonomous car. How big
is a grid cell? In this
Steve Macenski: application?
Yeah, in my example, it's five
centimeters, so it'd be five and
10 centimeters in size. Yeah, so
it's very small. And because
we're we're working on with
optimal heuristics, it's not
like we're like, here's the free
space, and we're Whoo, you're
wobbling all over the place. So
it's very much like being driven
towards that goal in a very
reasonable way. And so that
output path is actually already
pretty, pretty smooth and pretty
good looking. It's mostly just
like small discrete discrete
planning errors that you're
dealing with, because we are
working in this grid space, not
continuous coordinates notes. So
that kind of feeds a little bit
to the heuristic functions that
we're using here. So like I
said, we're able to simplify the
smoother quite a bit, because we
made some changes internally to
the planner for how the search
is performed. So that the two
ways that we approach that is in
our traversal function, rather
than just just looking at the
cost value, and the length of
primitive, we also enter penalty
functions so that we penalize
the path from making those
extreme turns that if it starts,
if it starts to turn, we
penalize it stopping turning or
penalizing, if it's going
straight, to start turning just
a little bit, you know, a
percent 2%, you have something
very small, which ends up making
us the things are quite a bit
smoother on the output. And the
second thing we do is that
rather than just using like a
distance heuristic to say, like,
here's how far I here's my goal,
here I am, just just just
compute the Euclidean distance
between those two points and use
as a heuristic function.
Instead, we use to to
heuristics, though take the
maximum on one is the actual
length of the path that would
represent in Ackerman space. So
we take using that same idea we
talked about with the analog
expansions and the boundary
conditions, we take our current
pose, our actual pose, we find
what that minimum curve would
be. So we set the maximum value
and the value of a a new to this
to this implementation that I'm
writing paper about actually
early, where it takes to count
the obstacles within the space
the same way the the Highbury
star has a similar heuristic.
But it takes that into a cost
aware environmental
representation. So rather than
the smoother having a cost
function in it, that takes into
account the for noise diagram,
which is similar to a potential
field, to smooth out the path
away from obstacles, we have our
actual heuristic function that's
driving the search take into
account the search or the cost.
And during that process,
Audrow Nash: and the potential
field, that's just a way of
keeping things away from
something else, right, it
basically says Don't come close
to this obstacle.
Steve Macenski: Is that true?
Or? Yeah, yes, essentially.
Yeah. So so the NOI diagram is
computing a potential field
where costs are high or low
neuron schools and lower high in
the centers of Ioway spaces. So
essentially, it finds these
like, is a graph of the centers.
And the notes were, like spaces
like, you know, collide with
each other. Which if you're
dealing with a stack
environment, like if you're
dealing with, if you're planning
on a map, that does not change
over time, like you might do an
autonomous driving application,
that makes a lot of sense, your
EQ compute that once super
efficient, knows exactly where
things around the center works
over time. But when you're
working with an environment,
mental representation that's
changing constantly, there's a
bunch of data
Audrow Nash: around or something
and you're driving a robot.
Yeah, okay.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, you have
to, you have to compute that
every single iteration, which is
super expensive, but we already
actually actually have potential
fields that we're working with,
it's already pre computed as
part of the inflation layer of
the navigation stack. So we
actually use the potential field
computed from the inflation
layer inflation to Yeah, so so
we inflate from from political
obstacles, like like my couch
behind me, we're going to add a
potential function off of that,
so that we have more cost, the
closer you come in proximity to
that, that obstacle. And then,
given the radius of your robot,
if it's a circular robot, we
apply then a lethal ban of cost
in front of it so that, you
know, if the robot would be
centered at that cell, the part
of the edge might be heading
heading the couch. So because we
have this this potential field
already computed, we can use
that to drive the robot away.
The robot, the heuristic search
away from the muscles just to be
guessing.
Audrow Nash: So you have because
you have these, sorry, what did
you call them? What was the
cost? Or was it the potential
fields? You have the potential
fields, and you basically say,
this area, because it's static,
we know we don't want to go near
and that one area will be
defined? That's what you're
saying?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, yeah, we
also apply that to, to new
obstacles to right people and
stuff, you still want to run
out?
Audrow Nash: Yeah, for sure. And
it's but it's similar, you can
use this kind of expensive
computational, or this
computationally expensive
representation for static
objects, but then a different
one, that's not as expensive for
moving objects.
Steve Macenski: So the potential
field that we use for an
inflation layer is very quick to
update. So it's actually not
very computationally expensive
at all. And that's why we use
that within within the, the
planning for discipline,
rotation, and not not necessary
what you do for autonomous
driving. Another reason why we
do this, which is like heart,
it's a little subtle to explain,
but so autonomous driving, in
general, you want to stay in the
center of the lane, or you want
to stay in center of a space,
which you are allowed to drive
to maintain maximum distance
away from from everything else
around you, or Cynefin of your
lane since. But in the case of
autonomous robotics, that's not
always optimal. Like sometimes
you do want to do that, that
that's really true. But a lot of
times, maybe you want the robot
to hug, hug a shelf, so that
things could go in the opposite
direction. If you're working in
the scene of a lot of robot
systems, or there's just
different behaviors, you may
want to have that curl in the
NASDAQ, we allow you to to,
essentially by tuning that
inflation distribution on that
inflation layer potential field.
And so basically, because we're
using that information in the
planning itself, that means that
your plants are going to
actually respect the tuning to
have this the tune system
behavior you want to have based
on the current the plantings
that you that uses that
potential oil, so you're
actually getting more
flexibility where you could
still define system to operate
that way if you want to, but you
don't have to you can.
Audrow Nash: That's cool. How
does what do you call it
inflation?
Steve Macenski: So essentially,
it's inflating the cause static
obstacles or dynamic offices in
the city. Yeah, inflates the
cost. And in the the grid map
representation.
Audrow Nash: I was thinking
inflation like in the economy or
something and it's like, I don't
I don't get the map. Okay, okay.
It's inflating the cost, it's
making it larger.
Steve Macenski: Another way of
thinking about it is risk which
I think is really the the proper
term I should be using here.
It's it's the risk that look
Let's say that the race is cool.
Audrow Nash: Okay. And then so
when you are driving the right
when you are planning, what
you'll do is at each location,
you evaluate it for its
potential and or for it for
like, how good if the how good
is the position? And one of
these things that you take into
consideration after being like,
is this valid or not, is the
risk. And so if you want to
minimize the risk, then this is
used in your priority queue that
you mentioned to to sample more
feasible and lower risk
locations.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, and that's
another fancy function that has
that can be tuned. So right, you
can you can sense that. So I'm
super sensitive to risk. And so
I always want to stay in the
center of aisles, that that's
really important to me. So you
can say, you know, I mean,
obviously, nothing would ever
give you a diversity inclusion
path, because that that's
invalid, or they're always going
to be valid. They can say that
maybe like, oh, yeah, I'm okay
if it if it's a little closer
obstacles, because I want to be
able to, like, you know, hug a
wall or hug a shelf or
something, for instance. So
these are all all tuple
behaviors you have access to,
because we're using the cost
information in the search
itself. And using the inflation
layer to kind of see that based
on the behavior of the robot
system, you wanna you want to
how does
Audrow Nash: how does this work?
Is this only true of known maps?
So if I have a known cost map,
then I can use these? Or is it
is the ability to tune inflation
or risk of things? Is it
something that I can do as I am
building a map of the
environment?
Steve Macenski: That's a good
question. Um,
Audrow Nash: maybe you have,
like heuristics for features of
the environment? Yeah.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, I mean,
both, I think I mean, if you
have some, I mean, if you if you
blindfold me, and then kidnapped
me and throw me somewhere and
say, Build me a map, and like,
choose some parameters, right?
Like there are there is a
reasonable band of parameters
space that you can, you can
select, and you know, if you're
in narrow spaces might be better
parameters than if you're a
super wide open spaces. So if I
do nothing, it's like, right,
yeah, I couldn't tell you. But
usually, when you deploy a
robot, you have some general
understanding that kind of
Audrow Nash: working so you can
parameterize it based on
heuristics about what you know
about the space, if it's very
open, or if it's very tight, you
might set parameters differently
that would change how these how
the inflation of the costs map
is generated? Yeah. Yeah. Can
you tell me a bit about the
priority queue? I think that's
really interesting.
Steve Macenski: I mean, that's
just a that's just part of a
star. Right. So I think that
that's, I haven't any, any
resource talking about here. So
search would would explain it
more articulately than I
wouldn't the moment.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Actually.
Yeah, I guess you're right, that
it is just a normal thing of a
star because you're only
searching a subset on your way
to the solution, a subset of
possible options. until
hopefully, your or your
solution.
Steve Macenski: Actually,
there's other ways of
implementing it as well. That's
just at least to me, that was
just my knee jerk reaction
thing, I have to do this thing.
All right, I need to sort by
lowest cost, then oh, ergo,
prior to me. So easy. But
Audrow Nash: so then, for you to
once you have this path that
started as kind, of course, but
I guess the grid cells are so
small, that they it's not that
course, I guess, or it's not
that jerky. But you have this
you perform smoothing on it. And
then you map it to motion from
or you match it, map it to
velocities? Do you get this kind
of for free with the motion
primitives? Or how do you relate
your path to motion to like the
velocities that each of the
wheels should go?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so we
have, that's where the the local
trajectory planning also
referred to as the controllers
within the Neptune ecosystem,
kind of kind of operate. So we
use as referred to as the hyper
planning scheme, which which
move it has recently started to
migrate over to as well. But
this has been a built in feature
of the nav navigation stack
since the very beginning. So we
separate the concerns of
building a route from where we
are to where we want to go, we
separate that from the process
of saying, Okay, how do we
follow that path? And so the
follow the path part is where we
take that path that currently
exists and we say how do I
generate a trajectory? Which the
difference between a path and a
trajectory is the philosophy and
or acceleration and or jerk and
or other derivative information
about the dynamics
Audrow Nash: that's interesting
involved? So I wonder if you
were traveling like really fast
might have changed the path that
you were able to take more
things like this like is this
concern is it always fair that
you can divorce the two
Steve Macenski: I'm in I mean it
can you can you always know
anything all the time? No. So
yeah, there's gonna be some sort
of like weird edge cases, or
Yeah, like, but generally
speaking for a reasonable mobile
robot system that that that's
gonna be a valid way of
operating. I while I'm not an
expert in the autonomous driving
space miners Sending of what
they do is primarily large scale
route planning. So rather than
having like a path, like we have
when we have like, you know,
doing the grid search, they have
like as far saying, like, go to
this intersection turn left, and
then you know, go straight and
for a long time, then do turn,
right, whatever. And these are
just basically like, like event
markers for when it changed
during doing your events. And
you have your local trajectory
planner, which are computing,
like the how do I like stay in
my lane? Or how do I pass a car?
So I can meet that route and
given need? So there is no like
Audrow Nash: path planning half
person?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, exactly.
So in that situation, then you
basically only have the velocity
planner in that local time, per
se, you don't have the goal path
planner at all. So it doesn't
always even make sense. Even
have even even had the concept
of a long term, you know, path
at all, that there are
situations where, especially if
during doing district waypoint
following that you start
Audrow Nash: to so let's see, I
want to get to that in a little
bit. Because that's interest, I
guess, when. So when is path
planning most useful? I suppose,
like when when do you really
need it rather than just kind of
waypoint planning? I guess
anytime you're using web point,
waypoints, you have to get from
waypoint to waypoint. And so
then you have to do path
planning? Or how do you think of
it? Yeah,
Steve Macenski: it's good
question. I guess I haven't
thought about in those terms
before, I guess, I think it
usually like certain classes
application. So help, like,
navigating around like, hey,
means it doesn't matter what
you're going for, I guess, if
you have like an A last mile
delivery application, where it's
like, you know, somewhat analog
to autonomous driving system,
where you have just a such
insanely large environment, it
just doesn't really make sense
to have to dynamically plan from
point A to point D, that's like
70 miles away, or whatever, you
know, you, you, you're seven,
wherever it's somebody is a
little crazy, let's say seven
miles away, are going on
sidewalks. And so you might want
to do some more thing where you
have some, you know, Google Maps
data, or OpenStreetMap data to
say, here are the intersections
and we're going through a sparse
route based on on intersection
information. And then you're
basically just locally just
saying, Go Go towards the
intersection, stay on the
sidewalk, dynamically go route
things, and you don't really
need a depth path between those
two spaces. So A, but then if
you're working in like a
warehouse space, the two kinds
of things you could do is also
have like way points on critical
points at the end of aisle ways,
or whatever, and have a sparse
route going going between them.
But then you can also do a
dense, you know, waypoint or a
dense path planning methodology
to be able to dynamically go
around a lot of a lot of areas,
and I think it just kind of
depends on what kind of robot
behavior you're looking for, you
know, largely static, staying in
these lanes, staying in the
straight lines, or being more
dynamic and able to, you know,
navigate free space more
flexibly
Audrow Nash: Stacia, and then
going back through getting the
so you separate out the planning
of the path to from planning the
velocity commands you were
talking about.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so So this
is all kind of like the
preferred is like, like hybrid
planning, which, which is this
technique of of splitting these
things apart. So then within
within the NASDAQ, we have
several different options for
local trajectory planners within
take that path planner, output
of the of the just the kinematic
plan up, here are some points I
want you to follow and convert
that into that velocity commands
the motor, the most, the most
simple to explain is probably
the regularly pursue controller
that we currently have, which is
new to NAV two, not available.
And last one. And without do
essentially, is pick a point on
the path, that's a at least a
certain distance away, maybe up
to a maximum distance away, it
could dynamically change
depending on the robot speed for
stability reasons. So talks at
some point on the path and says,
What is the curvature required
for me to if I were to pick one
Velocity Command to drive that
to hit that point exactly on the
dot, and then if I curvature,
from a curvature in your current
position, you can then back out
what the velocities do need to
apply in order to achieve that
command. And then so you say,
okay, robot, do this drive this
this direction, you know,
awesome start point on the path.
And then the next iteration,
let's say, you know, one 100 of
a second later or 120 of a
second later, you you say okay,
well now what now what point of
the path am I interested in and
you do the exact same process
over and over and over again.
And as you're driving forward
towards that goal, that goal is
constantly changed on you see,
are essentially following this
carrot over over time. So that
that's, that's that's one very
simplistic way to convert your
path into philosophy commands,
then for your lower level of
Tronic motor controllers to use
a PID controller or whatever to
convert into voltages,
Audrow Nash: not just a current
or whatever. There was a So how
do you? How does it have to work
with it? We talked a little bit
about potential functions for
the inflation. But how does it
work with a bunch of people
walking around or constantly
changing environments? Just re
computed all this? How do you?
How do you think of it? Yes,
this
Steve Macenski: sort of the
sensor data is really important
so that you have information
about what's now changed the
world. And once you have that,
that information, you can input
that into cost map. So this
might be from sensors like
sonars, or RGB cameras provide
you depth maps are going to give
you points as well as color
information, or 2d LIDAR. So for
the vast majority of things,
navigation to operate on a box
with primarily depth, depth
values, it wants to know where
this thing is relative to a
sensor frame. With that said,
it's not hard to integrate
modern AI techniques into as
well we have plugin interfaces.
So this is all possible on the
sun as well. But once we have
this dense information, we have
input that into our into our
grid map representation. And
when we say that we had a sensor
reading, hit hit a person is
walking, we can say, okay,
there's something here and put
that into the grid map as a
lethal obstacle. And then we can
inflate then our cost map with
with that inflation layer we
talked about, which adds that
potential function to it. So
then the next cycle, when we
want to compute a path plan
that's now represented in our
environment, and it can navigate
around it, then most of these
algorithms have clearing
mechanisms so that once this
this obstacle is gone for the
scene, then we can we can clear
it out use a ray casting from
the sensor to that to a clearing
measurement. So basically a
measurement of nothing, right?
If you don't see it anymore,
it's therefore gone. So you can
raycast from the sensor frame to
that to that point, and clear
out any cells in the middle is
clearly these are going to be
unoccupied. If you're able to
view something much further away
everything between that
measurement and okay, it's
clear, which then removes that
lethal obstacle, which then
removes that inflation
perspective. So the next time
you plan it updates in those
days are
Audrow Nash: gone. Gotcha. So is
the general way that you run
this, you run it over and over
again, and constantly are
planning and replanting?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, you don't
have to. But that that is that
is a that is the default
behavior. Currently, I'm
actually there's some pull
requests open. And I'm working
with some folks to kind of
refine the behavior additionally
to remove some some oscillation
behaviors that can sometimes
exist in that situation. But
essentially, yeah, every one
second or so we're computing a
new new path given the new
representation of the
environment. But this is where
the, the way that naturally
structured differently from the
navigation stack starts to
really be helpful is that we're
using behavior trees to
orchestrate these different
capabilities. So the
environmental or non
governmental is with the the
planner, the behaviors that
control the local Treasury
controllers, these things are
all controlled by a central
system to control the flow of
data so that we can manipulate
how the navigation system is
operating. So this is done
through what's referred to as a
paper tree. And I definitely
recommend reading more about
that, then I'm going to describe
it in less than an hour.
Audrow Nash: Like, yeah,
imagine.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so imagine
you had like a tree like
structure like you might find in
a computer science. Course. And
if you have a computer science
background, I'm sorry, read a
book about it. That can't go any
any any less detail than that.
I've heard so good to have
Audrow Nash: these. I've heard
good, differently, like video
games often use it. And the
behavior seems kind of it's like
fallback conditions. So like, if
you want to get into a house, a
behavior tree, you might say,
first try the door. And then if
that fails, you fall back to do
I have keys. And if that fails,
then you see if you can knock
and if that fails, no one comes
then you break the window. And
like this kind of thing, where
it's fall back, fall back, fall
back fall back all structured by
the I want to get into the house
thing, or Yeah, yeah, I think
Steve Macenski: that that's
that's one of the primitives you
work with. Yeah, fallback node
sequence nodes are kinda too too
big control flow types, they can
also define other types with
more more use case specific
here, but essentially, this this
is this is all modeled as a
giant tree. So you have like a
root node, which then has
different branches to it, which
then have our own node for
branches to it with different
methodologies for controlling
the flow of data between are
sort of controlling the flow of
the nodes execution model by
these different fallback or
sequence controller nodes until
you reach your leaf conditions,
which are leaf actions, which
then are you know, do something
or do something valuable thing,
okay. Yeah. And so all the
navigation behavior is then
defined through these behavior
trees, which then can be
reconfigured to do different
things for you. So, if you don't
want to replant every second,
you can replant every 10
seconds. If you don't want to
replant ever, you can have a so
that you use only one sack path.
If you'd like to replan only
when that current path isn't
valid, you can also do that as
well. And these things are all
really easy to implement. These
are all through plugin
interfaces, so you don't even
need to fork and have to, you
just need to implement your own
custom plugins. And then, you
know, run your own custom
behavior tree model, and you
still use the available binaries
from apt to, we try to make it
as simple as possible. We offer
significant documentation about
this because we understand this
gonna be a new concept with
users, where we can't talk about
what our paid for three is, why
should you care? Where's the
node to give you access to why
should you care? What are some
of the examples behavior trees
we offer you? Why do you care?
And then what is our what is the
default behavior and then
walking you through exactly how
the input or the the execution
model of that behavior tree goes
through on tick by tick basis,
you can have a reasonable
understanding about how the
current behavior acts.
Audrow Nash: And so this helps
your program figure out what it
should do when by finding
certain events? Or how does it
like if I if I have, say, we
have a simple example of a robot
getting from one position to
another, and a human gets in the
way or something? How would that
look kind of in behavior tree
space? Um,
Steve Macenski: if so we don't
have the environmental data, set
up the data three interface, so
that that really wouldn't be
important for at least how the
current behavior or navigation
works? Or what would be a good
example. Like if we can trace
through some of what a behavior
tree does, for some simple case
will be a good example for that.
Yeah, let me just Let us pull up
an actual example. So not just
typing stuff up on the fly was
relatively simple. Okay. That's
not simple. Let's do distance.
Okay. So for instance, like, we
might have a sequence which was
in Beaver tree land a sequence
is say, do this task is
successful, do this task is
successful to this task, versus
a fallback which say, do this
task, if it fails, do fallback
to the next one, if fails
fallback, the next one, etc,
within within all the the
children nodes on that control
flow of the sequence or the or
the recovery? So they might be
operating to do to very simply
just to replan every second, or
every time you, you, you or you
travel, for instance. So you
might have a Sequence node that
says, Okay, start just because
sequence out here, I say okay,
go by first child, and my first
child would be a decorator node,
called a distance controller, a
decorator node is something that
has one child and defines the
behavior about when that child
is tick. So for this instance,
it'd be, it'd be checking if
we've moved one meter. Another
example would be if we've, if
there, the time has moved by one
seconds, or that my speed is 10
meters per seconds, or any sort
of random condition you want to
set to define whether or not you
want to do this child. So we
have our SQL code, we go to our
decorator to say, do we want to
actually we compute a path? Yes
or no? It says yes, there we go
down to that, that that compute,
compute a new path, name for
tree node, and that's going to
put them that path on to was
referred to as the blackboard,
which is essentially a parameter
system that is shared across all
the nodes and the behavior tree
so that any node can input or
change or modify parameters on
the other node. You're not use
NG for state with Eva trees
ever. But it should be it should
be the state should be defined
to the tree. This should be
mostly parameters or values that
you need to be in terms
Audrow Nash: of state with. Or
could it be like we've traveled
one meter? That would be
something you put on the
blackboard?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, as long as
it's not state about the
execution of the behavior tree
like you shouldn't have like a
blackboard node that is saying
check check the blackboard for a
one or a zero for without
execute. You could do that. I
mean, you could I mean, nothing
stopping you. But you shouldn't
it should be based on on
computing values separately so
the baby trees think about his
four parameters or dynamic
values but shouldn't
Audrow Nash: be an example of
something you could if you
needed to.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so So
example here is like the path so
once we're once we're in our
sequence in our we go to our
decorator and compute the path,
the way that we get that path
computed to the next node of the
tree to Okay, follow the path is
through the Blackboard. And so
because this node and this node
can't draw To talk to each
other, so they can only pass
values. So we have our Depew
path, update the Blackboard
variable for the path. And then
when when we go back up to our
tree back to our router into our
sequence, and we say, okay, we
compute a path that would go
down to our fall path node and
check to say, hey, there's been
an update to this, this path
block, we're variable, I'm gonna
throw that to my local
trajectory planner. And then
it's going to compute the the
control effort required to
execute. And then if our, what's
nice about the the decorator
node, is that because if it
fails, it says, No, we've not
moved one second, it's going to
fail and go back up the sequence
and be the Sequence node only
continues going down to
children. And when it when the
last one succeeded, it's going
to exit and say, Okay, I'm done.
So it's not going to try to
execute the default follow path,
because it's
Audrow Nash: so it doesn't try
anything further.
Steve Macenski: Yeah. So as a
result, yeah. So so in a very
simple behavior tree with like,
you know, 1234 nodes,
essentially, we just, you know,
just did planning, dynamic
replanting of a of a, of a path
and then throw it to a local
trick and learn to execute.
Yeah, that is the at the core
level, the most simplistic way
of representing dynamic
navigation.
Audrow Nash: How does this
compare to like a state machine
way of representing this
information, I assume that there
are advantages to choosing to do
a behavior tree to represent
kind of these transitions. Um,
yeah, it's
Steve Macenski: preference more
than anything else. So they're,
they're both they're both
execution models, you can use
define how you like your system
to behave. And there's not
necessarily a benefit of one
over the other. It's more about
preference. And maybe certain
applications are more simple to
model one way versus another,
for instance, that the move base
was state machine back in ROS
1, you know, it statically
set. So it wasn't using some
sort of like external state
machine library, that's
reconfigurable. All that kind of
good stuff is, you know, hard
coded, here's our, here's my
state machine. And that works
pretty well. And it's pretty
easy to define simple state
machines to do something like
this, this type of replanting,
essentially, why just described
was the moon base node, except
for we're not replanting every
meter we're planning every
second or I think it's
configurable. So not often, you
won't do it. But essentially,
that that's the exact same
thing. But what we just
described as favorite tree is as
an XML file, which is loaded one
time, dynamically allocates to
nodes, and then an execute. So
you can change your behavior
over time. But there are other
state machine libraries that
exist that could do those exact
same things. And almost anything
you can model as a base tree,
you can also model as a as a
hierarchical or finite state
machine, and back and forth. But
we just prefer in general
working with behavior trees, we
actually ran a study in LinkedIn
last year, asking users what
they prefer to work with. And we
had 70% of the people say they'd
rather work favorite trees. So
this is why we were interested
in trees. But certainly there,
there are other options, and
they're all valid under the sun.
It just depends on you know,
whatever makes
Audrow Nash: it work. Okay, so
nav two has, it's a there's a
lot of, there's a lot of parts
to this. I'm, so it goes from
and actually, we haven't talked
about the cost map that you can
generate through this. So in so
in your initial mapping, kind of
more slam like so actually
creating a map, while you're
driving around it nav through
does this as well.
Steve Macenski: Yeah, it doesn't
do it through like the the slam
library we use is not actually
built into the navigation stacks
of bright you go to github.com,
you know, walk by a slash
navigation to is there's no
slack implementation there. But
we have a strong integration
with a library called slam
toolbox that I largely built.
Well, is it simply robotics then
continue to refine while Samsung
research in the first few months
there? And so that's what we use
primarily for January maps, that
this is where all our tutorials
are based off of this binaries
release for it. So from an end
user, basically, it is part of
the application stack. Yeah, but
it's it's sufficiently complex
that should not belong in the
same place. I think some toolbox
has almost as much code as half
an hour just by itself. So it's
very complicated. There's a lot
going on. So it's worth keeping
these products separated. But
also actually like to remove a
MCL was an attack as well, that
the adaptive Monte Carlo
localization system,
essentially, it's the
methodology for localization in
an existing map. And a MCL is
the very common like
probabilistic robotics
implementation of this of this
algorithm. So it does it works
on 2d maps for these 2d
occupancy grid. So we've been
talking about this grid space
discussion prior and through so
I want to actually remove that
from the stack into potentially
different repositories that I
want to get to the Get get the
point across that nav two is not
specific to me. navigation and
does not require 2d Localization
2d and mapping systems, if you
want to work with a 3d map in a
3d position isn't totally valid,
you want to work with a visual
slab system visual localization
currently valid. I think that
even last one got a bad rap
about that, because a MCL was
included in the stack. And there
were examples of other
localization systems within the
stack to kind of showcase that
you can utilize different
methodologies. So I'd like to
remove that. And it also adds
support for 3d positioning
methodologies as well. So that
way, you know, we get the point
across that you can use really
anything you want. This is just
what we pride by by default,
because it works well. And this
is what other users are.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. So if you
had, say, like a quadrotor, or
some sort of flying robot, you
could use nav to just as well,
because of the plugin
architecture, in the sense or,
Steve Macenski: um, I, maybe I
don't know, anyone using Yeah,
this is mostly ground robot
systems. So it's mobile robots,
surface marine applications. So
that kind of stuff. I mean, it's
meant for like, largely, like,
like you're working on a surface
environment. Our environmental
models don't really work with
like three dimensional spaces to
have like large height
variations. So if you have a
drone that's flying very high,
or you have like a submersible
robot going very low, you don't
have a lot of you don't have the
capability right out modeling
those gotcha effectively. It's
not that the plane runs couldn't
be made to work in three
dimensions, that it's just they
work. That's not the the current
niche that we're trying.
Audrow Nash: So I'm a little
confused about the serve the
last point, then you're you're
saying you want to remove this
boza MCL? Are you and it? Yeah,
they're just quite understand.
So you were so so because I was
assuming this was primarily for
2d planning. So if you want to
move on the ground, or something
like this, are you saying like,
with different floors, or?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, so So
these are two different topics.
So what what is that? How do we
represent our space, and right
now we do this through a 2d
planar cost presentation
environment. So this is a 2d
plane. But you can add layers to
represent things like like
height, height changes, so you
can work on other other train
models. With that said, it's not
really optimal and longer term,
we want to be replacing or
adapting cost map 2d, to be
operating both height
information, as well as risk
information as well as, you
know, AI detection based
methods, methods, so that you
can, you can work it all out
with all these kinds of spaces.
But at the end of the day, the
natural system is serving the
niche of surface robots. So
they're in a surface and the
ground surface on a lake top,
you know, but generally
speaking, working on the
surface. And then there's the
other problem of localization.
So right now we do primarily 2d
Localization using a 3d laser
scanner, which then takes like a
slice of your environment,
right, you don't see a couch,
you see a straight line that
were on the edge of the couch.
And so that has, you know, you,
right, you're throwing out a lot
of information, right, you're
throwing out the the texture of
the couch, which might have some
interesting features for
throwing out the shape of the
couch outside of that, that just
that 2d slice of the world. So
we want to build support,
localization systems that can
take advantage of more
contextual information of the
environment than just 2d laser
scans into 2d Kind of like, flat
Earth world.
Audrow Nash: NACHA. Quick, cool.
Let's see. I want to segue a
little bit. How has, how has it
done for you being so involved
in the community? Can you just
talk a bit about your
experience, working with the
NAFTA community growing? Its
working with developers and
getting an open source project?
Yeah,
Steve Macenski: no, it's
definitely been been different.
So it's, it's a different
challenge to work with people
that aren't paid to work for
you. thing, right? Like, you
know, these aren't, these aren't
my colleagues where we have
like, we get this thing done,
we're all being paid by this
company to accomplish this
particular task. And I'm not
managing people where I can just
say, here's what you must do,
because we must get this thing
done. Here's the project, we're
working on this this month. It's
a lot more. It has to be
collaborative, and you're
building coalitions with
companies and you're building
collaborations with individually
individual people to get things
done. And so, you know, that's
to be a lot more more mentorship
going on. So I have to be, you
know, not just assigning
projects, but talking to people
about what they're interested in
learning where they are right
now, where they want to be
going, what kinds of things
interests them and engage them
and try to carve out project
like individual projects or
small sections of larger
projects that they can work on
that they can have that those
personal growth elements, but
then also contribute back to the
project at large. So there's a
lot of mentorship that goes on
that I mean, would you also
would happen in hopefully
corporate environment as well,
but it's a little bit different.
Because no one's being being
paid to work on this. For
instance, these are all just
volunteers with their off time
or Maybe some companies who are
giving engineers, you know,
every other Friday, you know,
four hours to play around with
stuff or write documentation or
help out with various things. So
it's a lot more collaborative
and building building coalitions
of multiple companies to work on
larger projects together. Since
these are being worked on
primarily on a volunteer, part
time basis, so we're working on
some of these larger projects,
it's often it's either just me
and myself working on something,
or it's me building coalitions
of, you know, a couple students
with a, you know, a
representative company, a, and a
senior engineer at a company B,
or each kind of doing their
kinds of things, and then I'm
popping in to help resolve
disputes or help with design
decisions. And, you know,
implement some sections of this
myself so that we can get you to
continue moving forward. You
know, the smack planner is a
great example of a coalition
project. You know, I put out the
the bones of that, largely
myself after, you know, many,
many months of work that only
contain the hybrid, a star
planter, had some, some bugs in
it, and all that kind of stuff.
And over time his company
started using it, we had a
couple companies go through and
really start benchmarking
performance and help me find
some areas that can improve
things and made some pretty
substantial improvements to it,
that we're currently working
through through merging at the
moment. And then I also have
worked with a couple of students
where instead of just having
this this hybrid ACR planner, I
also want to add a state lattice
planner, so we could model
arbitrary motion primitives and
not just Ackermann models. And I
found a couple of folks that
were really interested in this
thing as well. And were helping
me, you'll build out file
formats for caching information,
building the local, primitive
files offline for what the the
actual printers are of that
search pattern. Other than
acumen models, we have folks
working on improving the analog
expansions to be more efficient
and deal with cost information
more effectively. You know, it's
a lot of folks are working a lot
of different things that end up
coming together to build
something new and interesting.
And so it's a, yeah, a lot of my
time is spent coalition building
and getting new people involved
the project and finding out what
excites them, and where I can
kind of where I can put them the
project that is both helpful for
the direction that we're going,
or even potentially changing the
direction we're going, if
there's somebody who can spend a
lot of time on it, or very
senior that wants to see that
certain thing happening.
Sometimes I'll shift my
direction to kind of help
support them do that do that
thing. Since a lot of
development happens the NASDAQ
is opportunity based, so there's
an opportunity to integrate
something new or somebody has
some time they want to spend
working on this thing. Sometimes
I'll drop what I'm doing, I'll
go watch over there. Because if
I can get if I get if I get some
help in some area, I'm not gonna
say no to help.
Audrow Nash: What do you it's
interesting to hear that it
shifts really to community
building and coalition building.
And you mentioned that it's a
little bit different with not
being able to, like, give people
deadlines and things not easily.
What do you think of open
source? As like a business
model? Yeah, you know, you know,
I
Steve Macenski: don't think
about that, honestly. So I don't
know, I couldn't really give you
too much. I mean, I know like,
you know, folks like picnic,
they're doing this, the Oprah
boxes doing this and some of the
folks I've chatted with as well
are doing this and and I think
that's, that's a good direction
to bring money into a project to
fund development in a particular
area. But, you know, I really
like being able to work on the
hard problems that are necessary
because their gaps and they're
needed, and not necessarily just
working on who's going to you
know, throw money in my face and
say, go do this thing. Because
sometimes it's hard to get
funding for the things that are
really important and you know,
you have over a box I mean, you
must know understand that with
the the bill farm and
documentation and things like
that, it's hard, it's hard to
get some people throw money at
the important things that are
the big gaps that are felt. So
you know, maybe down the line
there's there's a, there's an
opportunity for an app to to
have a similar kind of, you
know, open source business model
to have that funded. But that's
not something that I'm currently
thinking too much about or I've
executed on or have any plans
they need to catch up.
Audrow Nash: So I'd love your
thoughts on that anyways. Let's
see. How can someone get
involved if they want to, like
say someone is interested in
learning more and interested in
the possibility of mentorship?
What should they do?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, the first
place to go to navigation dot
rostered org That's our
documentation website. I spent
an inordinate amount of time
very good documentation site I
am very impressed. Yeah, it's
it's a lot of nickel and diming
it's just you know, a page here
and there one thing every Friday
kind of thing. But yeah, if you
go there you can find our
tutorials you can find our
getting started guides for how
just like get from from
absolutely nothing to installing
ROS to gain the binaries, do
your first demonstrations and
arvis so that that's a good
place to get started with the
actual NASDAQ itself. If you
want start contributing. We have
a community slack that can give
you the URL to do including this
description of this podcast,
that's a great place to, to
reach out, either for assistance
or ask questions or if you want
to get involved, and you want to
see where you can get involved
in that, that slack group is a
great place to be. And then
generally just looking at our
product issues. So our issue
tracker is very active, it's
where everything that that's
being worked on is being
discussed openly, and also
searchable later on. But you
know, don't don't restrict
yourself to those things. If
there are some other features
that you see missing, or some
gaps that you want for your
product or your research or
whatever, you'll file ticket.
Let's let's talk about it. You
know, I'm definitely not, you
know, I'm not God, I don't know,
I don't know, like, you know,
what your what your product
needs, that we're not, we're not
servicing. And I want to
understand these gaps are
because I want to build this in
to be the right, not just like a
navigation system, but the
navigation system, I read this,
I want this to be the standard
library for robot navigations.
That, you know, it doesn't make
sense to use anything else.
Because this, this is a feature
complete, it has so many options
and plugin interfaces, so, and I
think we're definitely getting
there. So yeah, if there's
anything missing, I want to hear
about it.
Audrow Nash: And just going back
to like more for mentoring and
things like this, or what? So if
someone wants to contribute?
Should they already be a
roboticist? Or can they like,
what level? Should someone like?
What level of skills should
someone have if they want to
contribute?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, I mean, it
kind of depends on what you're
interested in working on. If
you're okay with doing some more
like small discrete tasks, and
in basically no experience is
required. You know, in
oftentimes folks that reach out
to that are working on things
like testing frameworks, and
helping me out with with CI
issues and these kinds of
things. So then over time, as
you've built some confidence in
the concepts in the in the the
code base, we can build those
into larger and larger projects
that are maybe more substantial
and rewarding. In general, ROS,
having some rough backgrounds,
especially rough to background,
is always helpful. But you know,
I understand that a lot of
folks, this would be the first
experiences working with wealth
too. So we're always willing to
help work work through those
those problems. So really not
not much required. But if you
are more experienced, have more
background in these concepts,
you can certainly make a much
bigger impact much quicker.
Because, you know, you can
understand the gaps, where
they're important for you and
your research and where they are
in navigation. It's its roadmap,
you can help Phil so it fills in
those gaps with some of the more
substantial process.
Audrow Nash: And what advice do
you have for someone who's at
the beginning of their career?
Steve Macenski: Yeah, I mean,
just just dive in. I think
that's the biggest part. Like
don't, don't wait for someone to
teach you something. I guess.
Like, you know, my background is
in aerospace engineering, my,
my, my, like I did, I wrote
zero, Python for any coursework,
anytime, during all college. I
learned embedded C when I was in
high school, just as my dad is a
software engineer, we did some
projects together, literally,
like my first job, SMB, like day
one, it was the first time I'd
ever really written C++ code on
the plane to San Francisco, I
was reading the C++ standard
manual to learn the semantics.
It's been a while since I've
worked with C. And so it you
know, just just dive in
headfirst and start start
breaking stuff, look at errors
get confused. You know, if
you're willing to be excited and
interested in spending time
doing it, you know, you can you
can go from zero to expert, you
know, fairly quickly. It just
requires grit and the desire
loves Oh,
Audrow Nash: and kind of big
picture question. Where do you
think robotics is headed in the
next two to five years? Um,
Steve Macenski: continuation of
what's happening right now, I
think like, a lot of the
warehouse companies are starting
to go from like, medium scale to
like really like, you know,
everywhere else in the world
happening yet. So I think that
that trend will continue. I
think the delivery robots will
get a bit will be a lot less
Telly off and a bit more
autonomous, hopefully. But I
think there's still a long way
to go there. I think there
there's a there's a missing.
There's a technology gap right
there that exists.
Audrow Nash: What is it today?
What is the gap? I'm
Steve Macenski: going from like
my first like semantic
segmentation and detection
models to like something that's
like super robust and works in
all situations. I think is a big
is a big part of it. I think
there's a lot of there's a lot
of folks working with just like,
out of the box demos of
TensorFlow. And they work well
enough but not well enough. You
could actually just lead a robot
to go do its thing and
especially in the outdoor space,
we have cars and yeah, for sure
everything around it. And I
think there's a there's a
there's a big gap there and in
when you do have the small
number of companies that can go
over that. It's because they had
millions Millions and millions
suspend to hire all the right
people and you know, click this
huge train datasets and all that
kind of stuff and that that's
not something everyone can do.
And I think hopefully we see a
lot more mobile manipulators
starting to reach the market and
actually accomplishing useful
tasks. I guess right now
there's, there's that promise
rifle Bill garage of, you know,
a special box that has had a
product, other folks that have
had products, but they didn't
really go anywhere outside the
research space. But I'd really
love to see those start really
taking off. And I think that
that would get me excited to go
back into the manipulation
space, if I started seeing it at
that, that that will start to
take off again.
Audrow Nash: All right, awesome.
Thank you. Thanks for listening
to this conversation with Steve
Minsky. Thank you again to our
founding sponsor, Open Robotics.
See you next time.