Audrow Nash: I'm happy to announce
this week is our one year anniversary
for the Sense Think Act Podcast.
During this year, we've had 23 episodes
and had about 53,000 downloads.
I'm humbled and honored that
we've reached so many people.
I've also loved the opportunity
to have longer conversations with
great people through this podcast.
I love seeing how they think and
what they're thinking about, which I
think this longer format lets me do.
And I'm happy that I get to share
these conversations with you all
and hope that you enjoy them and
find them valuable as much as I do.
All that to say, we're
just getting started.
I'm excited about our upcoming
episodes, including an interview
with Nvidia, on hardware acceleration
and machine learning, Esper
Bionics on prosthetic devices, and
Plus One Robotics, on exception
handling in the warehouse setting.
Look for these interviews
in the coming months.
If you're enjoying this podcast,
I'd be happy if you give it a thumbs
up or leave us a review depending
on which platform you're on.
And a big thanks to Open Robotics
who has been sponsoring this podcast.
That's all for now.
And I look forward to our next year.