Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Charles Brian
Quinn, also known as CB Q, who
is the CEO and co founder of
green Z. Greens. He makes an
autonomous driving system for
commercial lawn mowers. In this
interview, we talk about greens
these autonomous mowing system,
how they've worked with
manufacturers to upfit their
system into commercial mowers,
how greens he does dogfooding
and about CPQ his experience
with bootstrapping, and raising
venture capital in startups.
This is the SENS think act
Podcast. I'm Audrow Nash. Thank
you to our founding sponsor,
open robotics. And now, here is
my conversation with CPQ. Hi,
CPQ Would you introduce
yourself?
Charles Brian Quinn: Hey, Audrow
Good to be here on the podcast.
I am CPQ I go by my initials
Charles Brian Quinn, and then
the co founder and CEO of green
Z. Greens he had our our big
mission is to free humans from
repetitive outdoor labor. And
we're starting in the green
industry. We have a product that
helps create self driving
commercial zero turn lawn
mowers. So we help big
landscaping crews that maintain
the largest crop in the United
States by square footage to help
them reduce their cost of labor,
Audrow Nash: the cost of living
grass by largest crop that is,
Charles Brian Quinn: if you
think about it, you know, I know
you've had great people on your
podcast that are doing farming
and but if you look at square
footage in terms I mean, grass
is a crop that the we maintain
across the United States in
terms of watering, cutting,
maintaining, cultivating, in
terms of square footage about
about 3x corn, which would be
the next and so there's people
who do that that industry, the
green industry we call it is
pretty big industry and not a
lot of people want to sit stand
or push a mower for eight hours
in the hot sun, especially here
in Atlanta, Georgia, where we're
based. And all over the US
there's a shortage of labor. And
that translates as you know, in
supply and demand to higher sort
of demands on that and and
again, when when it doesn't
people don't want to do it. And
it's also dangerous, dirty,
repetitive, monotonous, you
know, things that we we all know
our robots are very good and
capable of and don't care about,
then it is probably a good place
for us to help supplement and
add robotic workers to these
crews, and our software that's
based on Ross does that.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. See, you
brought up a lot of things I
want to start. So first, you
kind of unrelated to your mower.
You mentioned there's a story
behind CPQ and why you prefer
that
Charles Brian Quinn: out there.
Yeah, I've just always gone by
my initials starting from high
school. And so it's even become
my little moniker, you know, on
every sort of side seq, which is
CPQ I used to even have a
license plate See viki.com And
since 99, so I've been gone for
a while. So yeah, and it's funny
and professionally to a lot of
people were like, hey, you know,
CPQ and they're like, who? And
it's like Charles and they're
like, oh, yeah, CBK it's kind of
a moniker that both
professionally and friendly. I
go by. So Andre Audrow were
close enough. Now you can call
me CPQ.
Audrow Nash: Funny. Okay, so now
tell me about the greens, the
mower or your setup?
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah,
absolutely. So we it's important
to note that what we do is we
are an automated driving sort of
system, right? We are basically
a software package that's
enabled by a set of, we call
them off the shelf sensors. As
you know, Robotics has gotten
very far in the past, Gosh,
20 3050 years, even more
recently with the introduction
of the Robotic Operating System.
And so with the standardization
these a lot of the reps and
things like you know, data
structures, like point clouds
and Ross enhancement proposals
are like being standards for the
Ross community. An easy one
would be like, hey, use meters
as opposed to, you know, inches,
right? Like, that's a very good
rep, one of the three I believe,
says, you know, there's some
good ones out there. And so with
all that, what we've found is
that the time is now to take
some of these sensors, like the
real sense camera, and use that
to basically do a function or
task and so green z, we build
software. That software is
enabled by a set of sensors and
we certify those sensors, we
call it being a robotic ready,
that's part of our robotic Ready
program. So we help these mowers
become robotic ready. And once
they have the sensors, they can
then run our software and our
software adds self driving. So,
we we are trying to like I said
reduce the cost of labor. So
when you think about autonomous
and the behaviors and things
that make something autonomous.
It is sort of self directed at x
You know, again, it's sensing
thinking, perceiving and acting
on the world. And so what we do
is we have a sensor stack that
does that for a very particular
part of the process that
landscapers do, and that these
mowers do, we call it sometimes
we call it cutting out the
middle. And that's kind of a
unique term that landscapers
kind of kind of resonates with.
Because when you get to a job
site, you know, there's a
certain set of tasks to do to
make, you know, the property
look beautiful or safe. If
you're, you know, mowing a
hospital facility that has a
helipad, you know, or right of
way for safety, or on roadways,
or industrial, you know, a lot,
a lot of safety reasons why you
want to keep that, that maintain
that property maintained, as
well as make it look beautiful,
then there's a tougher task you
do. And so our software helps
automate some of that. And,
again, by doing that we help
reduce the cost of labor for
those landscapers, which is why
they like our robotic workers,
but a lot of people assume we
have mowers and we don't,
they're some of our competitors,
who are wonderful, and happy to
mention them here. Companies
like Saif do are building a
automated mower, and that we
unfortunately do not we actually
build a a kit, basically. And we
do it at the factory. So we help
manufacturers and OEMs produce
self driving equipment that's
comes from the factory. Both
strategies, I think are noble.
And I think that it's tough to
compete. You know, especially
talk about John Deere, who I
know that one has been on your
podcast, it's tough to compete
with them, they produce lawn
equipment, I've been doing so
for hundreds of years. So
they've got a lot of learning
ahead of them and distribution
and all that stuff. But so what
we do is, again, add sensors,
and a sensor suite package and
our software that goes on these
existing commercial mowers to
add autonomy. Gotcha.
Yeah, it's it seems like a
clever approach, especially for
a startup to work with a company
that actually makes them ours,
and then kind of retrofit that
with your autonomous system.
Yeah. And the word like a lower
barrier than it is for sure. You
know, in talking about lower
barrier, when we first started,
we did try and like retrofit,
like posts sort of sale and so
we go get these mowers and, and
put all these things on them.
And I'll never forget the first
time we did it, everything
broke. And then we're like,
well, well, let's just make it
more robust. Right? And so we
tried, and what do you mean,
everything broke out, bro. You
know, like, when you think about
how these are used, I remember
the first demo, I saw ED, right,
who's the CEO, right
manufacturing, who is one of our
current manufacturing partners
that were partner with to bring
out our first product. I
remember seeing him demo, and
he's nonchalantly talking as
he's demoing. And he drives off
the curb, and then like drives
back on it and drives back on it
and off of it, and the mower is
just bouncing off the curb,
repeatedly. Yeah. And he puts
down to the deck and the deck,
like hits it and bumps up. And I
was like, oh my goodness, like
the amount of vibration
ruggedization required to keep
what we had originally had, we
just cert put these servers with
an eMag clutch to basically
actuate the the the left wheel
and the right wheel. And it
worked. But you know, it was
very fragile and delicate.
Absolutely. And you know, and
it's funny, like, it's not that
they're our end user customers
are rough on the equipment, it's
just that they have a job to do,
and not a lot of time to do it.
And so the you know, they're
they move fast, they roll over
the curb, they run it back into
the truck and are on to the next
site. So but retrofitting was
very difficult. And so we
immediately moved it from sort
of this post retrofit to at the
factory, that way we can use the
design principles, design it in
with the mower and get that
support.
Audrow Nash: How does that work?
It's like, so do you have to go
to the company and say, Hey, we
needed at this stage? And just
tell me a bit about that.
Because that's interesting.
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah. So
this is part of my consulting
background. You know, in a
previous life, I, we I helped
some of the big companies like
GE Lighting, and some other
companies do software that went
with hardware. And one of the
ways you do it is you go to the
factory, where that thing is
produced as close as possible to
the line. They call the assembly
line or manufacturing line. And
by doing the upfitting is what
we call it. You call it
retrofitting, but
Audrow Nash: it's up fitting
that way. You think about it,
like when you buy a guitar go
has it a little different than
retrofitting, because you're not
getting it all the way in. Like
you're not getting it from the
retailer where it's entirely set
up for the user. You're getting
it part of the way and then
you're adding things and
changing things. Yeah,
Charles Brian Quinn: we call it
a good way to look at it. If you
think about it. If you go to the
Let's assume you went to the
Ford dealer to go get a truck.
When you go they have some base
models. You know the F 150 which
is the most popular are selling
truck and we have a couple of
Ford Yep. And if you go and you
say I want this one, they're
like, great. And you say, You
know what would be awesome,
those, I would love one with a V
eight, like turbo diesel, and
they go great, we don't have
any, but we could get that
upgrade package like we can do
that. And we get that from the
factory, like we'll put in that
order that it'll come down the
line, we'll put it on there for
you. And you can get even more
custom than that. But so that's
the idea is that this is a
feature, we call it a autonomous
mowing that we built that you
could up fit or upgrade and
order. And then it comes from
the factory. So what we've done
is work with, right. And I'm
working with a couple others
right now, that where we go and
we do that, that outfitting as
close to as I said the factory
as possible so that they come
off the line. And then when they
go to the you know, because
manufacturers are people who do
this, the end user customers buy
their equipment from outdoor
power equipment, so much like a
dealer. It's kind of like a
dealership, but for outdoor
power equipment. They sell these
things to do this kind of
activities. They have those
mowers already there. And then
they activate them just like I
guess OnStar or Sirius XM Radio,
if you've ever done that process
that's similar to us, except
you're doing software that does
autonomy, autonomous driving,
that's cool. Okay, is there.
Audrow Nash: So when you
approached the company that
makes the mower and you want to
add these custom features, I
assume they don't have like an
autonomous mower package. So I
assume you have to work with
them to do that.
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah. You
know, when we started the
company, we were sort of like
people were like, you know, we
already have robot mowers,
right. And so if you look at the
idea of a robot mower, those are
those little Roomba like
machines that and they've been
around since the 1970s. That
patent is has been there, I
think since Yeah. 70. And so you
put a boundary wire in the yard.
And so the big commercial mowers
were like, Hey, what is this?
You know, and how is this
different? And, you know, we had
to do a little bit of convincing
to tell them no, no, this is
self driving assisted sort of
like almost like Lane Assist.
And when we start using those
terms, they're like, oh, like my
new truck? has you know that
where it keeps them in the lane?
Probably? Yeah, it definitely
helped. And so we said, hey,
this is self driving, but for
these big commercial mowers,
where it takes over on part of
the operation, and they said,
well, that's not possible now is
it? And we said, well, look over
here, and we built prototypes,
and we did the retrofitting. And
we did all these things. And you
know, and I'll get back to that.
But that's actually the one of
the thesis of the business is
that we have been iterating
since we started and the term
iterate is very important to us.
It means do learn, improve, and
repeat. And the process of
iteration has helped us
tremendously. So I think it's,
it's interesting, as an
entrepreneur, I look back and
say, Oh, it's always been this
way. But I can guarantee you
that, you know, we've been
through several iterations where
we probably thought certain
things, and then we learned and
did and now the new reality is
that that is what we do. So, you
know, every entrepreneur will
tell you, Oh, yeah, I knew
everything to do with the
business. Yeah, they don't
actually what they do say is
they say, Well, we learned a
lot. So a lot of them talk
about, like learning through
failing, right, failing fast,
right? So we were doing a lot of
that in the beginning. And so
that's how we got there. To
answer your question, yes, when
we go to manufacture, that is,
you know, the, the now what we
do is we pitch and we tell them
about this robotic ready, which
is now been proven and
commercialized with a couple of
partners already. So there are
there are a few systems out
there, I would say that are
competitive. X mark is a big
manufacturer who makes Toro are
sorry, Toro, who owns X mark
and, and so they have one that
they've been working on for a
while. And then they even made
an acquisition in our space,
which was amazing. And I'm so
thankful for that, you know,
normally when, when, when, when
a competitor is acquired by a
big manufacturer, it's actually
an incredible opportunity. You
know, like a lot of companies
are like, Oh, that's scary,
because the big guy like has it
now. They slow down. No, isn't
that I mean, it's honestly that.
I mean, I live in a world of
abundance. And so yeah,
investors and everybody, and
there's always enough for
everybody to do. And so when
that happened precedent, well,
yeah, that any legitimizes you
and it also helps every other
manufacturer who doesn't have
that, like will pick up the
phone and say, Hey, I see that
you do this, right. If you know,
there are 46 outdoor power
manufacturers, and you may
actually be hearing some one of
them on the background.
Apologies. That's in our test
lab. But if one of those 46 Like
starts to think that they get
ahead, then the other 45 are
gonna be like, hey, and there
may be another one, you know, a
new one comes online, you know,
4648, you know, so you're saying
new companies, yeah, new
manufacturers or other sort of
entrants to the market. But I
think competition is wonderful.
It's definitely legitimising and
it's a rising tide lifts all
boats. I believe that and I
believe that, you know, my
entire life.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it also seems
like it makes it It easy the
space grows. Yes, there is a
larger events in it so educate,
it's easier to harness all that.
Yeah, yeah. And parts may be
become more easily procured and
Charles Brian Quinn: things like
this. And then you get stuff
like, you know, like, maybe
standards are created, right
that are there to help you too,
as well.
Audrow Nash: Uh huh. So what is
your autonomous driving system?
What's it composed of? You
mentioned a lot of sensors. And
it probably has a big computer
with it. And it has some things
to interact with existing mower
hardware, but tell me a bit
about it.
Charles Brian Quinn: Sure. So
we're big fans of Ross. And
they're not like operating
systems. So and we're big fans
of open source. So while there
are parts of our stack, a few
nodes that we probably won't
open source, just because
they're not going to be useful
to the overall community.
specific use case exactly. I
see. But you know, if you look
at like, say, robot
localization, which we use, you
know, it's funny, we were out
there, I guess, couple years
ago, two years ago, and in the
field, and we were mowing for a
customer. And I'll remind me to
tell you about that becoming an
actual becoming the customer and
doing it ourselves. We still do
that. Now. We learned a lot. We
call that eating around dog
food. But I'll come back. Yeah.
But we were talking about robot
localization, we were using this
package and won one field, we
would be mowing, and all of a
sudden, we'd get to this one
area, and the mower would shoot
and say, Hey, I've got to head
50 miles that way, for my
waypoint, and we were like, that
is a bug. And we're like, that
is really weird. And whenever
flow error, it has to do with
UTM boundaries. Are you familiar
with, you know? So in,
Audrow Nash: I don't even know
what is UTM stands for? Yeah, so
I
Charles Brian Quinn: think it's
a universal time Merkin teal,
and we can look it up. I
apologize. But what it has to do
with is, latitude and longitude
are all straight lines. So you
know, if you're going on Google
Maps, you'll maybe notice that
you can get Google maps of like,
you know, it's a 33 or 90, and
it's all in degrees, right? So
you can do any location on the
planet, you can have a certain
it is a sphere band. So you got
so right, so why can't really
wrap a sphere in a rectangle,
right? There's some area that's
adjusting for that. Correct. So
we, we we most of the lot of
problem to run into, yeah,
mostly libraries take a area and
they'll do it in bounding boxes.
And so you'll be in a UTM
quadrant. And so once you're in
that quadrant, the the space
goes from sort of, you know, it
stays in that sort of area,
right. And then once you move
outside that boundary, that UTM
boundary, and there are like,
obviously 50 or so of those, you
know, as you talked about the
latitude longitude and the US, I
think there's like five or six
that you go across. Okay, don't
correct me if I'm wrong on that.
But there's quite a few. And we
just happened to be on it, that
one site happened to be on a UTM
boundary. So when it crossed
that boundary, it reset to the
other UTM, which was 50 miles
away. So anyway, we found that
bug, and it was great, we worked
with more to push up a PR and,
you know, and push it back to
the community. And now we're
about localization can go across
UTM boundaries. So big fans and
open source been doing in my
entire life. And we'd love to
keep doing that as long as as
long as it exists, which I hope
is forever. And and so you'd ask
us about our stack big fans of
robot localization. So we use a
lot of the base base stuff,
we're not trying to reinvent the
wheel. So standard cost maps,
we're big fans of Ross control.
We have hardware interfaces,
which really help us with, you
know, left wheel right wheel,
differential drive. What else do
we use? We use a lot of the
standard data. You know, I
Audrow Nash: guess they're
missing depth by using Ross one
or Ross two.
Charles Brian Quinn: We are
currently our current generation
stack is on Ross one. And I
think we're on melodic, and I
think we have a noetic running
around downstairs, that works
just perfectly fine. And so we
may upgrade our entire fleet to
that. And then Ross T we've
evaluated some of the packages
we're using aren't quite there
yet. And we've been working
closely with some of you guys at
open robotics, the Michael
Carroll who said, close we're
close. As soon as we are we
would love to upgrade and we can
even do that in field. So but
we're enjoying the Ross one
ecosystem. But yeah, so you
asked what's our sensor stack
and sort of package look like
but autonomous mowing is a suite
of Ross nodes that do a function
and that function is autonomous
mounting. So if you can imagine
our system feels like an
appliance. So it is a ruggedized
computer and I think you need to
go to our site. We're pretty
open with like everything we
use. It's an x86. I actually
just gave a talk at Ross con.
This last one on how to boot to
Ross and seven seconds where I
took this machine and really
minimize the colonel and use the
ubuntu LTS and kind of minimize
that install with the precede to
make it very minimize it boots
up very quickly. Super fast. And
I and just go straight into
Ross, using System D, which
we're big fans of, we like a lot
of the Unix stuff. And so where
there's a lot of custom stuff we
don't, we're sort of not big
fans of it. So yeah, we use a
lot of like sort of trusted
stuff like system D networking
and open VPN and some of the
sort of standard standard stuff
that's been around for a while.
It's very modular, extremely big
fans of node based, you know,
single responsibility, tiny
things that do one thing very,
very well, liberal and the input
that they accept, very specific
in the output that they do. And
so a lot of design principles
for software that we like about
Ross. And our stack does that
very, very well. It also
interfaces with a web app that
we've built, that our customers
love. And that's built in Ruby
on Rails, which we love, and is
probably the best for doing
rapid web application
development. And, you know,
there's a bunch of stuff behind
the scenes there. But I won't go
into all the details. But all
that does a very specific
function, and that is
landscapers by our product, they
take the motor out, they press
map, they mow a area of the
area, they want it to sort of
finish the job for them, they
press go on a little remote, and
it basically just finishes and
Stripe still fills in
everything. So they do the
border. And from there, you fill
it in autonomously, exactly.
Audrow Nash: Okay. Let's see. So
for all of the what kind of
sensors are you using for this
whole? So when you map it? Is
that are using GPS? Or? Yeah, so
what kind of thing are using?
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah, so
I'll start with control and get
all the way sort of there. It
starts with control. And in
order to be, you know, I have a
theory about robotics that a lot
of people when they envision
robots, they think of the Willow
Garage, sort of PR to like, has
to be humanoid. But in reality,
you know, robots are in robotics
as a way to I think automate and
customize what would normally be
considered a human level task.
And so there's a lot of ways you
can do it. When you think about
self driving cars, they are in
in terms, sort of a robotics. So
the first thing you have to do
is get good control. And so what
we do is with let we need
control of left wheel, right
wheel, because these are
differential drive, and a lot of
them have caster wheels on the
front. So they while they have
bias, they don't really matter
and are controlled. And so we
start with left wheel and right
wheel control. And we've been
able to do that with a drive by
wire system. And so that starts
with with Ross control and
having a canvas adapter. And so
we use can which is on you know,
very
Audrow Nash: cool was on his
cannon? Oh, yeah,
Charles Brian Quinn: I think
it's already gonna do you know
it right. What is it? It's the
automotive protocol. Right?
Yeah,
Audrow Nash: I know, it is the
automotive protocol. I don't
know
Charles Brian Quinn: what
exactly stands for. But it is a
protocol, we could probably look
up the acronym. But it is a
protocol that a lot of cars use.
And it's very small, it's very
high speed. And good for
redundancy. Yes, it's built in.
And so we have that can
interface layer that allows us
to left wheel right wheel. So
once we have that we then need
to read. So we use encoders.
This standard Hall Effect sensor
encoders. And on our electric
platform, we can read that
straight from the wheel itself,
they have encoders built in. And
the reason you'll need to know
that is no velocity. And so when
you're able
Audrow Nash: to say hey, you do
your own mapping with this,
you're not you're not
necessarily using GPS, you're
using odometry, large, right,
and then maybe sensors and
things.
Charles Brian Quinn: So you're
exactly right. So we're slowing
down for
Audrow Nash: just a second just
to speak about a hall effect
sensor. So it's a magnetic
sensor, and you can count the
ticks as a wheel spins. So maybe
you have one magnets, or you
could have a bunch of magnets
and you can count do you do?
What's it called where they're
90 degrees out of phase? If you
have to, let's say that you can
figure out the directionality.
Yes, that's exactly correct.
Because one way it's traveling
90 degrees over to get the next
bump. And one way it's traveling
270 degrees or three fourths of
a rotation or three fourths of a
phase? I guess
Charles Brian Quinn: that's
correct. And you can get some
telephones have the gear
backwards. Exactly. So they have
gear teeth that they're reading.
And so then if you know, the
tick count, you know, and you
could just do the math to say
how many wheels and velocity?
Yeah, so yeah, exactly.
Audrow Nash: And you were saying
sensor fusion? Because if you're
using raw odometry, like just
seeing how many times your
wheels spin, there's slip and
all sorts of things that all
accumulate as errors. So you're
dealing with that through some
sort of sensor fusion?
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah, so
you're exactly right. When we
first started, if you just use
our DOM, or odometry, on a very
nice platform that doesn't have
a lot of slip, you go out, you
turn left, you turn, right, you
turn again, you get that square
and in you know what'll end up
happening is you'll be like this
right? And it won't be
distorting. And what I'm saying
is you can't for those who can't
see, it's like a you know,
unconnected square right?
Because of the slip. And so what
we do is we fuse that with an
IMU. And so we have a high grade
IMU we've evaluated many, many
many IMU use small ones we liked
I happen to like some of the
vector NAB stuff because it's
nocturnally calibrated alias
that for the gyroscope. So they
don't even notice all of the
sensor data from it. But yes, we
do fuse a lot of the components
from it. Yeah, the gyroscope,
which tells it which direction
you're facing? Yep. Yeah. So I
did something like this in grad
school, it was like some course
where you use the sensor fusion
of the inertial measurement
unit, and the odometry. And it
gets much more accurate, which
is pretty amazing. So you're
doing now we fuse that along
with GPS, and we do high
accuracy GPS, we have the
ability to run on standard GPS,
but we prefer and for some of
our customers for the straight
lines and tracking that they
want to do. And a lot of the
fields that we are we have RTK
GPS, and are just gonna have
real time kinematic. And what
that means is, is if you think
about normal EPA accurate, yes.
And I think you've had people in
your podcast talk about this
before. But
Audrow Nash: you may not have
this podcast, previous one, I
think so yeah, you get crazy.
Charles Brian Quinn: You get
correction data. So you can get
a very accurate centimeter
level. So we fuse all that now I
can tell you that our sensor
fusion is pretty heavily biased
towards the RTK GPS, because the
quality of it is just super
accurate. Those are
Audrow Nash: so if I remember
correctly, and maybe the price
has come down, those are like
$20,000, or something to get a
good RTK GPS isn't correct
Charles Brian Quinn: or and we
first started down, it has come
down quite a bit. And when we
first started exciting, I
remember we were using an RTK
setup that had a base station.
And you're right, it was 1000s
of dollars for this one and
1000s for the one on the
machine. And gosh, just
recently, I saw that. And a lot
of it's been enabled by a
company called ublox. And
essentially, they have a chipset
called the F nine and F nine P
and that has taken the cost down
to in saying I think we just got
another sensor for I'll admit
it, I think we just got our most
recent RTK for like 129 bucks,
and I'm like, Oh my God, that's
crazy. And so the real the real
kicker, though is that the data,
Correctional Service really
matters. And that's where you're
seeing a lot of the innovation.
So there's a service out there
called SEF. There's service out
there called Point perfect, that
provides what we call n trip,
which is I forget what that
stands for, I think it's a
network transport protocol. And
so instead of having a base
station, what they do is they're
basically like a cellphone
network and every 50 kilometers
from the, you know, from certain
high density areas, they put
their own base station, they
calibrate it with other sort of
known areas. And then they can
send out that correctional data
over the Internet. And so you
don't have to have a base
station. That's nominal. And you
already have that data. It's
gotten really good, low latency,
you know, super high
availability. And with that
correctional data, it's been
really good and very good for
our business.
Audrow Nash: Do you ever? I
don't know with RTK GPS, but do
you ever run into situations
where you're mowing a field and
it doesn't have good GPS
coverage? Absolutely.
Charles Brian Quinn: So we've
had to design a lot around that.
And what happens is in
localization, at least in the
way we've done it, which is the
best practices, you know, by you
know, roboticist, you've done
this before, you have what's
called continuous and you have
your discrete, and I think I'm
getting that right. But in
continuous, you've got things
like, that are just going
continuously. And so that's
Audrow Nash: odometry. And
that's the wheels spinning,
okay? And knowing how far they
spend, right? In
Charles Brian Quinn: your
discrete, you can have jumps,
right? And so, in a good
localization system, what will
happen is, when you have when
your discrete jumps, like, let's
say your GPS shifts, and you
know, it runs out or it's
there's no connectivity, or
whatever, and it says, oh, you
know, I really thought you were
here and you're moving along and
boom, you're over here. A good
localization system will go, I
don't think so I, I had all this
momentum in my ETF sort of
saying bias that I was saying I
was going five meters a second
this way. Yet. Now when when you
say me, I'm over here, I'm gonna
ignore that and and yet back in.
Audrow Nash: So you use
probabilistic methods like an
extended Kalman filter and ukef,
as you were saying, exactly. And
so what that does is you have a
pretty good idea, like you have
a probability distribution that
says I'm most likely here. And
if you get some information that
says, I'm way over here, it's
like, well, it's probably not
very likely it takes that
information into account. And
then it adjusts its belief
accordingly, but if you tune it
in a way, it probably won't
listen to that very hard, or
very significantly.
Charles Brian Quinn: And what
ends up happening the thing
that's worse actually is not GPS
going out, per se, it's the
thing that will mess you up. Is
it is it changing and you should
between a high accuracy and a
low accuracy. So we've actually
designed our system such that
when it starts, if you get a
high accuracy fix, like we go,
and we're like, great. And then
if we lose it, which has
happened, you go down, you know,
big hill and go down, and
there's no coverage down here.
And it just, it's starting to go
out. If the system loses it, the
mower will pause, our software
will pause and say, hey,
something's up. seconds ago was
the last time I got a high
accuracy. And so the mower
pauses, and it'll kind of wait,
maybe it's just like fluid,
maybe it's a fluke or something.
And so sometimes the motor will
just kick back and start going,
it'll get that fixed back. But
if it can't, you know, there is
a chance for the operator, at
least with the mobile interface
that we've built to say, you
know, what, go ahead and turn
off the low accuracy or high
accuracy, and there may be a
small shift in the map. And so
it's not enough to make a huge
difference based on what we've
learned. But it is enough that
you could say, hey, just turn it
off. Because what what's, what
stinks is how, again, going in
between them, and it's
constantly shifting is what will
mess you up. But again, yeah,
sensor fusion, what we do think
about it, like we basically use
our coordinate system in Ross,
right? You have 00, right, which
is where a robot starts, and
then we record right. And so
we're using all this data to
determine where we think, you
know, the next point is, you
know, on the map and coordinate
space, and we're using all these
other systems. So the robot
doesn't think it's at, you know,
lat launch. It's using lat lodge
as a data point,
Audrow Nash: internal coordinate
system. Yeah. Yeah, you
transform it into your primary
reference system.
Charles Brian Quinn: And as all
robotics is, right, it's a
transform series of sensors all
connected with a universal
descriptive robot format. You
RDF you. And that's, we love you
RDF. We use this a lot as well,
because it's all just transforms
all the way down.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Funny. So if
you so for your robot, where
you're driving it, and you
haven't heard it, and 50 seconds
from the GPS, which is your
really good source of
information for driving it
around. Do you have so if you're
using a probabilistic way of
reasoning about where it is,
does that uncertainty just it
keeps, so it received one good
information? And then it drives
using odometry? And yeah, using
odometry. And then, so the
uncertainty continues to grow as
it goes. And at some point, you
say, This is too uncertain, I'm
gonna wait for a better GPS, or
then you trigger this has have
the operators switch the GPS,
from high to low, or whatever it
might be.
Charles Brian Quinn: Generally,
I don't know the, the correct
answer to this. But what's
interesting is, I think, when
you think about cars, and how
they drive so far, you know,
that that where that bias could
really go, and you talked about
even going through UTM
boundaries and things like that,
that's where a lot of that will
grow. In the areas that we're
doing even like, like the the
large acreage, even, it's enough
to do a full day of mowing, and
you're totally okay, running on
that same localization and, and
being able to cover that field.
And we're good enough, then we
haven't run into really any of
those. And what's interesting
is, at that, that's great, you
reset, you turn off, you go to
the next site you turn back on.
And so since it's not long
running, like the second truck,
or a truck going across the US
and really accumulating so much
bias, we've been okay. Knock,
yeah, so the error doesn't stack
up that significantly and so
sign I'm aware of.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Okay, so
then, what? What other sensors
do you have? So you have
odometry, you have some depth
cameras and things like this?
What else? So or how is the how
are the depth cameras use
Charles Brian Quinn: your
perception pipeline we're really
proud of we are. I'm a big fan
of AI and ML, and I think it's
gonna happen. But I'm actually
not, we're not using it, I
believe it's gonna happen. I
believe that some of the AI and
ML modeling and some of the
training and the networks that
are being developed out there
are going to revolutionize a lot
of the tasks that we have to do
algorithmically or
programmatically. And I truly
believe that. However, I think
that right now, it's a bit of a
black box approach. And you
know, that the the amount of
data required to really train it
up for what we would consider to
be good enough, prohibitive. It
is and,
Audrow Nash: and so we need like
a million examples of someone
walking in front of it or
something
Charles Brian Quinn: like that.
And everybody corrects me says,
Oh, we've got synthetic data.
And I'm like, Well, you know,
synthetic data is synthetic
data, like you can only like
change the color of a, you know,
seven times and it doesn't
really add that much.
Audrow Nash: In distribution
mismatches between simulated
data and real data are huge a
lot of times,
Charles Brian Quinn: I mean, I
know because we've been mowing
in the field and you'd be
surprised that the stuff we
really ever Yeah. So what we've
done is we've taken a really, I
guess, a pretty unique and this
goes back to our design
principles approach of really
keeping it simple. And so what
we have is a lightning fast C++
pipeline that does, you know,
ransack, which is stands for I
don't, I can't remember random
sampling. Yes. And what it does
is it tries to consensus, right?
So it tries to find the ground
plane. And, and then anything
above the ground plane is an
obstacle. So, this is not like
we're trying to classify and say
You said, so I, the way I
described our customers is
they're like, visit detect, like
kids. And I'm like, you know, it
does not make a distinction
between a garden gnome and a
kid. If it sees something above
the ground plane, it's going to
stop
Audrow Nash: it'll success to go
back slightly for ransack and
talk about a little bit about
that. So you, you have your
depth camera, your depth camera
points over the ground. And then
what you're going to do is check
a bunch of, it's going to give
you points at different depths,
kind of. So from this, you're
going to try to fit with a math
equation, a plane on that. So a
2d surface, and the one that
matches the majority of the
points is the one you're gonna
select. And that's it's a fast
algorithm. Yeah, so the thing
that's on top of that are
deviating from it, you're like,
This is something thing. Yeah,
is what I understand.
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah, and
not to get into all the details,
but we have some special fun
sauce, we do around line fit,
and some of the other stuff on
stuff to make it really fast and
accurate. And, and then again,
all that's translated into just
a standard cost map. And the
cost map would be, hey, you
know, a, when they see something
that is a, you know, tree or
vertical plane or anything above
that, that that is not part of
that, that that surface, then it
says, Hey, I can't go there. And
so it creates a very large
infinite cost map, you know, to
say, like, kind of out there.
Yeah, exactly.
Audrow Nash: Okay, how do you
deal with like? So I imagine
like the way you want to handle
a kid, in close distance to the
mower, and the way you want to
handle a pole would be very
different. How do you, like if
I, if there's poles in my lawn,
or in my field here,
Charles Brian Quinn: you want to
go around them? Whereas the
other kids want to stop? Right?
Yeah, what's interesting is when
you think about, and this is
natural as as humans to sort of
say, like, let's solve the
entire domain, right, like,
let's do it just like a human
would. And what's interesting
is, having developed this
company, you know, from
iterative and from these basis
is sort of like, how do I solve
the first immediate problem,
which is a job to be done, and
get as far as you can get, as
far as
Audrow Nash: that iterating,
you're speaking about exactly,
Charles Brian Quinn: is that
when you get when you actually
talk to customers? They're like,
Do you know what they're like,
I'm good at going around things.
Like, you know, by the way,
like, I can go right around a
tree, I know where the the
brushes, or the pine straw or
whatever it is, or the roots
there like I can do that. What I
need help with is just the sort
of big valueless. Exactly. And
so what we've done is we've,
we've built our system is such
that it is made for those open
areas. And so when a lot of
people do that, they're like,
Well, I probably can't use it.
Because you know, I, you know,
I, you know, I do this one that
just has trees everywhere. And
we're like, great. The good news
is the mower still works like
you normally do. Yeah, you know,
like, I don't turn on cruise
control, the moment I get out of
my driveway, I hope you don't
either. I only do it when it
starts to get really repetitive
and boring. And I'm like, I'm on
the highway, let me turn on
cruise control. And so it's the
same functionality that we've
developed, right? Yeah,
Audrow Nash: cruise control is a
very good metaphor for those.
Yeah, see, because you use it
when you have a spot that's
incredibly monotonous. Like,
it's just this big, open thing
that's going to take a bunch of
passes. And thus, a big open
field, that's going to take a
lot of back and forth. And so
that's when you use it. But for
the highly custom stuff, like if
you had a bunch of poles or
trees to go around, in which
case you don't engage cruise
control, you keep the robot. And
so your systems are made so that
a human operator can just jump
on it. Like you're not modifying
the spot where the human works,
Charles Brian Quinn: right. And
that's been very critical. Even
when when we first developed it,
I remember a customer early on
telling me, you know, Hey, your
system may be great and may
never break, but this is my
livelihood. So there always
needs to be a way to disconnect.
And so that's one of the
features we design and the
robotic ready. If you look at
our website, there's a switch
from manual to autonomous and,
you know, it's funny, you and I
both know that it's probably not
needed in the future at one
point. But it is a physical
safety blanket type thing when
you do this, the entire system
is cut off, that could have
autonomous control. And so
there's no way for the system to
take over and sort of issue
commands to the wheels and
that's a very fun thing for our
customers that are relieving,
you know a safety blanket that
they like, and it's also a
productivity thing like they can
always sort of say, and when you
say jump on to I want to be
careful to say that that when
the motor is going autonomous
because we have sort of 360
cameras, if you run up to it,
even from the back, it'll stop.
If you even somehow were able to
get up and dodge it or whatever,
be a ninja. And it wasn't
meaning this. But yeah, but it's
fun to talk about, like, if you
were to jump on the back, a lot
of the mowers have a thing, you
stand on a platform operator
presence, if you get on that,
like we used to allow people to
ride on it while it was
autonomous, and now we don't,
because it's not a safety thing.
But it was fun, you can ride on
it while the matter was going to
be pretty cool. But now if
somebody is on there, it won't
allow that. Right? So you know,
we've had our customers try and
put their safety people on it.
And there's videos of them, like
running up to it, jumping on it,
and just stopping immediately.
We're like, don't do that. And
they're like, Well, you gotta
test it. I was like, okay,
funny.
Audrow Nash: So it almost to me,
it seems like a clever approach
to do this, where you have the
ability to toggle between the
two, because it seems like if
you're making a fully autonomous
mower, and you're building the
entire mower for the fully
autonomous case, so you're not
making a spot for the human to
sit and work on it, for the
drive it, it makes it so you
have to solve every hard
problem. And I think that that's
probably like, there's a lot of
them, I'm sure you can speak to
like, how do you know if I don't
know, you can go over these
routes or go around all the
things. But then having the
human do these hard ones, that
seems very
Charles Brian Quinn: clever too
good example would be like high
grass, right? You know, so like,
there's a big, you know, brush
of grass. And we ran into this,
right? Like, you know, one of
our customers got a little
behind, because they don't have
enough labor. And they came out,
they're like, Hey, listen, like
this field is like knee high
grass, like I was supposed to
hit it last three weeks before,
and I didn't, it's like way up
here. And we're like, instead of
the mower was like, like, can't
go here can't go here. Like,
even we have a feature for
avoidance, which you know, and
feel they can just have it go
around. And so it's just
constantly trying to go around
everything. And he's like, it
looks like it's drunk. And we
look at the cameras. And so we
look through the RGB. And we're
like, whoa. And so we did design
a feature for relaxed obstacle
detection. And so we raised the
ground plane of the ransack. And
so we do let him operate with a
higher, but but when we do that,
again, this is all about jobs to
be done. So we trust our
operators, they're trained,
they're certified to do it. And
we, you know, train them on
this. And we said, hey, listen,
when you press this button,
it'll relax it, you know, you
better be sure that there's
nothing in there. And when he
did, he was like, works great.
And we rolled that out, you
know, two weeks later, and he
was like, This is wonderful.
Thank you. Can you can you add
this feature? And we're like,
Yep, sure can. So we keep going
with them. And that's kind of
how we run. Which you're right.
It's, it's, it's the iterative
approach, right? And you You hit
the nail on the head, which is,
how do we augment human
capabilities, you know,
especially were in these highly
repetitive, dangerous, dull,
dirty, monotonous things that
robots are very good at and
likened to, and then how do we
keep the person able to do the
creative, you know, unique,
beautiful, and things that
humans will always be good at
and should be good. And, you
know, that to me is the future.
It's, it's what I love, like,
why I do this, and why I get up
every day.
Audrow Nash: It's also the So
for all those are great reasons.
It's also pragmatic as a startup
to, because you're not doing the
hardest problem. First, you're
not doing every hard problem all
at once. Yeah, you're doing just
the minimum to provide value in
a market, which is fantastic for
I mean, like, I mean, I'm
thinking about autonomous cars
now. And you see huge companies
like, say, like Cruz, who has
like, I don't know exactly, but
like 1000s of engineers working
on this problem, to fully
automate driving. And a lot of
really great things have come
out of that. But as a startup,
it's hard to do because you
don't have 2000 engineers. So
solving an easier problem that
still provides a lot of value,
kind of like what Tesla's doing,
in a sense.
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah. And
again, we're just we're sort of
copying a lot of this crazy has
been amazing. Our product
manager that was just in San
Francisco and holidays and was
like a solid couple around
around he's like, it's
incredibly out there everywhere.
It's crazy. And you that way Mo
Yeah, yep. So it's the only
choice here it's just not evenly
distributed. And what I tend to
think about the off road
capabilities, what we're doing
in the autonomous space where
you know, it's interesting for
us is I always tell people is
like, hey, when we don't know
what to do, we stop. Now, I
think as a self driving car, I
think when you don't know what
to do, like, you can't just stop
in the freeway, right? Yeah. Oh,
gosh. There has to be a lot more
and there's people involved and
plenty for us who are in
controlled environments like we
can in some of the center's
we're working with are sort of
industrial Right. So there's a
controlled environment, you
know, you don't have people
running around. Hell, it's it's
interesting, because people were
like, Well, what about schools
and kids and it's like, hey, why
don't you ask us landscaper,
what they do? And have you ever
seen a landscaper milling around
kids know if the kids are out,
they don't know, period and the
story like manually. So, you
know, so So the automation is
capable of doing now and I think
that the offered space will
continue to have leaps and
bounds. I?
Audrow Nash: What do you mean
off road space?
Charles Brian Quinn: So when you
think there's when I think about
autonomy, there's a lot of
standards right now, if you look
at some of the bodies that are
certifying on road autonomy
through some of the standards,
like the ISO 2626262. Yeah. Or
what I think it is, it's one of
those I just to say, just say
this is until it repeats, but
you have the
Audrow Nash: right Ryan therapy
from clear path you mentioned
next Tuesday, or something like
this, often, okay.
Charles Brian Quinn: And so
those are the those are the
autonomy levels, right? Level
one up to level five were like,
level five is just, you know,
and level five, kind of
interesting, because I've heard
people say that level five would
be like, You tell your car,
like, hey, take me to the beach,
and it takes you to work
instead. Because it's like, Hey,
you actually need to go to work.
Like it's truly self directed,
right? It's like, No, you don't
need to compete. But um, the,
the i digress a little bit, but
we talked about on river
software, there's the standards
and in off road, we don't have
that, like there isn't a body
learning is exactly that that's,
that's determining these, we do
have is a lot of some of the
ones for industrial robotics.
And so their standards like ar
1508, which is a robotics for
automated machinery, and
vehicles. And those are the ones
that we're going for those
standards. And we've been really
lucky, we've working with some
external consultants for risk
analysis, as well as we've got
just hired some validation
engineer from from Rivia. And so
we have a lot of firepower on
that. And I think that are, and
we're working with some of the
industry as well, some of the
outer power industry people
directly to help make sure that
those are safe standards, but
we're doing that in conjunction
with our customer, who also like
has a job that they want to get
done. You know, I tell my team,
we have six core values and
safety first is first. And
number six is customer success.
And they're not in real order.
You know, they're all important.
But if you think about it, like
if safety is like the most
critical, then the safest thing
to do would be to just sit in a
insulated bubble and tell our
customers you can No, because
mowings dangerous, right? That'd
be the safest it is. But in the
end, there's customer success,
and they've got a job to do. And
while it is dangerous, we accept
those risks. And we the reason
we accept this risk is because
we've done enough risk analysis
to know that like, hey, if I do
this safely, and I follow the
procedures and the guidelines,
the risk is low enough, that I'm
safe to do this. And so where we
fit is trying to bridge that gap
between I've got this job to be
done. And I still want to do it
safely and with the least amount
of risk possible. And I frankly
think that when we look back in
the in the future, we're gonna
look back and say, Wow, can you
believe that we had humans
sitting standing riding on these
things that were prone to
rollovers and a huge spinning
blade? Yeah. And we'll be like,
oh, yeah, we used to used to
drive around in cars and smash
into each other. Oh,
Audrow Nash: no, I'm just gonna
say, yeah, yeah, the cars are so
dangerous, but, and it's funny,
because, like, they're still
relatively safe, but they are
one of the most dangerous,
dangerous things in modern
society. So I think, like 50
years from now, it'll be like,
our parents that we were driving
around, like the risk, but
Charles Brian Quinn: it's the
only way to go right now. So
Audrow Nash: it's true. Yeah,
unless you walk or bicycle and
bicycling is much more
dangerous. And city it is.
Charles Brian Quinn: Speaking of
bicycling, you got to get,
you've got to get Brandon from
Luxan us on your podcast, the
homework that he's been doing
with depth a AI and the depth AI
platform. These are our cameras
that basically run AI ml on
them. And they have great Ross
drivers. And we're helping a
little bit with that open
sourcing a lot, but phenomenal
and vegan advice. And he started
this company because he had some
friends who and I won't mess
with his story. But they had a
some accidents. And he was like,
how do we prevent this? And he's
like, we got to get a camera
that faces behind. And so he
tried to prototype one and was
like, you know, how do we do
this and, and with AI and ML
where it is right now he was
able to do it. And so he open
sourced the platform so that
other people are able to do it.
And we're actually excited to
start implementing that on our
next gen, which we've already
started. And so in terms of, you
know, think about like the real
sense and the depth. Cloud is a
great protocol for algorithmic
but like I said that AI stuff is
coming fast. I mean, the stuff
that they can even do, they can
even output a Deaf cloud using
you know, something. Exactly,
exactly. And the quality better
than stereo and these kinds of
things and I've been super
impressed and they fast. So
we're definitely got to get him
on. Because he's, I mean, in
terms of robots, they're gonna
revolutionize it, I think.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. I'll look
into having him on the podcast.
Thank you for the
recommendation. One, one thing
that I'm wondering, like, where
do you see standards bodies
being helpful in these? Is it
because they establish well
defined protocols that are well
thought out? And thus they
reduce risk? Or where's the
value in establishing these
standards? Yeah, I probably
Charles Brian Quinn: not the
best person to ask this as an
entrepreneur who thinks that all
rules are there for somebody
else. I'm kidding. The rules are
meant to be broken. I don't
believe that, but I'll say this,
I mean, I benefit from them
every single day. You know,
like, from, from the headphone
jack, I just plugged into to the
USB that I had to plug in, and
then turn around and then put
back and then do it that way.
Right. Those are all standards,
right? Web Standards. You know,
Ross being a standard, the rep,
like we talked about, I'm a huge
fan of those. And so what I
think where, where I think the
best things get built, is in a
company is leading, and really
driving that. And then it isn't
all driven by consensus and
committee. Now, I'm a big fan of
committees, we're on a few. And
but where I think that you can
get in trouble is trying to
design by consensus, I have a
rule in our company, and my team
will will kill me for saying
this. But there's three types of
decisions that are made at Green
sea. And this is all companies
by the way. There's command
control. There's consensus. And
then with there's consultative,
right, so let's go through the
three. So in command is when I
come come in the room, and I'm
like, Hey, guys, or hey, people,
Hey, everybody, Hey, person's
everybody. We're doing this. And
everybody goes, Okay, let's do
it. consultative is, His command
is pretty good. And sort of
wartime and scenarios when you
need somebody just come and say,
Hey, this is what we're doing.
We make decisions. Yeah.
consultative is very good. And
consultative is very critical,
and probably the one you should
be doing in business. And the
most important, that's the one
where, where someone comes in
and says, Hey, there's a
decision that I'm in charge of
making, because I'm responsible
for this, you seek expertise,
correct. And you said, I'm
seeking your consultation on it.
But ultimately, I have the call.
And that's how all decisions in
business should be made. The
only decision in business that
should be done consensus is
where do we go for lunch? Yeah,
because I just think that the
that watering down of sort of,
like, you know, we've got to get
all everybody to buy in and
fully understand it. You know,
if you had to ask everybody,
just nothing would get done. And
so I do appreciate committees
that are the appropriate size,
that are in that actually have
stakeholders who are committed
and not just in it to sort of
Express power or sort of
lobbying or interest that aren't
their own, then I think you have
very good standards, and I'm all
for that, you know, so again,
you get real world, you know,
and that's what I like about the
ones we're on there. They're not
from, you know, people who are
just trying to stamp this out or
competitive. They are people who
are actually like, nd user, you
know, who benefit from it. And
where I think there's benefits
is that, you know, we've seen
this in the automotive industry,
you know, there are standards
bodies that say, like, Hey,
here's what we think true sort
of autonomy would look like. And
these are some of the things we
do you know, it's funny, there's
a simple one that you know, I
got a new car. And when you go
to the back, there's a liftgate
and there's a button, and all
the iconic, iconic RV, is all
sort of standardized, right? And
so, you know, it seems funny,
like it's an SUV, but the the
Connor icon or Greg, I forget
it, the icon itself is that
looks like a card or something,
right. And it's a hood closing,
but it's I know, when I see that
button, I click that, and I know
that the hood will close. And
that's because of standards help
us all. So we all don't have to
read the manual every time we do
something. They really help with
usability safety, and I'm a big
fan. I do do sense, though, that
there are some that are probably
gotten too big or don't have
appropriate stakeholders that
matter anymore where I think a
lot of damage can be done.
Audrow Nash: How do you
determine if it's too big? Oh,
or how do you figure out the one
size?
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah, I'm
not the one to determine it. I
think it's all context
dependent, but I'll quote Yeah,
he says, because he seems to be
the smartest man on the planet.
He says, What is it the pizza
rule? Right? So if you can feed
a pizza, that group is fine.
It's the fine size but anything
bigger than that? He's like, get
rid of it. So everything is done
in feeding. I think it's I think
it's the pizza rule and maybe
two pizzas. I'll have to look it
up.
Audrow Nash: Something some
small number of pizzas. Anyways.
Interesting. Okay, going back to
your autonomous system a bit
more. So you have many depth
cameras, they're pointed. So you
use odometry, odometry. And GPS.
You're doing some sensor fusion
there and is fusion. Correct. So
we local and global, right? Yep,
go ahead. And then you have
cameras, depth cameras. So you
were mentioning the Intel real
sense, which is structured
lighting, I believe, or maybe it
sends out a laser or something
Charles Brian Quinn: it does in
the outdoor, it probably ignores
a lot of the pattern project
that happens the IR projection
because of just using stereo, or
what doesn't it works pretty
well said is is stereo depth,
right? Yeah. And no, in between
them. Yep. And so
Audrow Nash: you can infer how
far away everything is by the
disparity in the images taken by
both of the cameras and go,
Okay, so you have those, those
are facing all you have, like,
one of them on each corner, or
they're all around
Charles Brian Quinn: the 360.
But what's interesting is that
there are directions that a
mower cannot go just like a car,
right? You know, you can't see a
car can't suddenly move
laterally diagonal back. Yeah.
Perfect. Yeah, exactly. Exactly.
Yeah, exactly. Not morphic. And
so having said that, we have
pretty close to 360. But we
actually have a bias towards the
front being more important,
because that's the primary
direction that it goes. And so
that that sensor is actually a
little bit duplicated. If you
look at our current one, we have
a little bit of overlap. And
those are calibrated, like I
said, to make sure that we can
see. But yeah, so we have very
good coverage around the mower,
and then in the back. But
there's I mean, there are
definitely sort of areas, you
know, sort of here where it does
not move, but the
Audrow Nash: left and back right
kind of thing. Yeah. Yeah. Okay,
cuz you're not as worried about
someone approaching in the
mower, run running them over
Charles Brian Quinn: for an even
go that way. Exactly. And even
the turns that it does, as soon
as it turns it sees you and he's
like, Well, I can't finish that
turn, right. I see.
Audrow Nash: And yeah, these are
you said, it's like two wheel
drive two, and you can turn in
place because the front wheels
or casters.
Charles Brian Quinn: That's
right, he's got all that zero
turn or turn on a dime. Right.
And so what's interesting is
when I first we first got the
the mower, you know, we're I
used to be able to say I was new
to landscaping. Now I can't
write having been in a while.
And so when we would do, we
would go out and we'd be like,
Oh, cool. Let's just turn and we
would just zero turn right
there. And when you do it,
landscapers will go like, Oh,
you just rotted the grass,
because it's true. Can you
imagine? If you have one wheel
that stays stationary, and you
pivot the other you especially
good? Yeah, you actually tear up
the grass. And so our first
turns were terrible. You don't
say don't put one wheel forward
one wheel in reverse. You do
now. And that's what our
algorithm does, right? So that's
what we do is we call it a
perfect, they call it the Y turn
or the you know, and so you can
watch our machine do it, but it
goes forward. And then it
actually uses its own an
inertial I guess. I don't know
what you call it, but it's sort
of kinematically so that it
backs up, and then goes
straight, and it lines up those
casters perfect. And so it
executes what is a very good
turn. And when when landscapers
see it, they're like, Whoa, it
looks like an excuse. That's
right. And it doesn't run the
grass. And of course it does it
every time, which is kind of
fun. I mean, if you're in a
hurry, you can always just you
know, get out of there. Yeah.
Well, what's great about a
robot, right, is that a robot is
one time to do it. And it's
like, I'm happy to do that exact
same turn every single time.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Okay. So do
you have any other sensors?
Charles Brian Quinn: On your
outside? Let's see. So I think
we are. Yeah, so we we've had
ultrasonic video on it. Ultra
problem with ultrasonics is and
that was shortly that some of
our machines still have it, but
we're not using those. And I'm
happy to disclose why that at
the speeds inside times we were
going it was only turning on for
a very minimal amount of the
thing because, you know, we're
going I would say pretty fast.
And we have been insanely happy
with the point clouds. And we've
actually our newest generation
has a lidar that has added a
secondary form of redundancy.
We're actually using the ouster,
and we're super happy with that.
And we actually on our current
gen, we use the live ox LIDAR as
well. And with that, and the
depth sensing cameras, we've got
our redundancy and it's much
better than the the ultrasonics
were really fun. Yeah, they're
very noisy and at the speed and
vibration we were doing they
just weren't adding a lot of
value. There was no they were
not making the system safer,
which was the whole point. They
were adding complexity to the
BOM cost bill of material and so
we just we decided to cancel
them I would be I'm impressed
with some of the new stuff
that's coming out. We're always
evaluating sensors in our lab
downstairs. We have some fun
stuff that I probably can't talk
about, but there is some unique
stuff out there that are in the
ultrasonic and sort of i What
would you would call closer to
that almost audio type spectrum
than visible light, right, that
I think will be capable. But the
neat thing about what we're
doing is, again, if it's a
structured data and we can use
it, then we will incorporate it
as part of our standard and
spec. But as of right now, those
ultrasonics are tremendous. A
lot of it. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. And so for
LiDAR, are you using? Is it a
planar lighter? Or is it one
that's sending out a few strips,
or
Charles Brian Quinn: the live
box is a unique? One that I
think is I am probably not the
best to talk about, we have a
whole systems team that
evaluates a hardware, and I saw
a couple of them come in, and I
definitely saw the pricing of
some of them coming in. We have
stuff in our lab. You know, I
think we, so we're venture
backed. And so what's
interesting to me is, and I've
never I've been always done
bootstrap companies. But in
venture, we're trading a capital
for speed and growth and, and
have making our customers happy.
And so what our team does now is
and it's real fun to be on the
green team, because they don't
come to me. They don't come to
me period anymore. But they
don't come to me and say, you
know, hey, there's a $35 IMU and
$1,000 IMU, which you know, they
buy, they buy two of each one,
and we evaluate it, we choose
the best one, right and, and we
FedEx Ship it like overnight if
we can, right because time is of
the essence. So yeah, they do
that now. And we know that. So I
think the one i The ones I've
seen are the ouster OSC, Ro 128,
which is the highest grade one.
And the reason is because, you
know, we all were software
heads, too. So we're like, let's
buy the 128. Because if we, if
we can software, make it in
software to a 64. Or the lower
Rez like we can do that in
software? And we can figure out
if, you know, yeah, right. So we
can always you can always go
down lines in data and destroy
data, but you can't recreate it.
So I've seen some of the you and
I've seen some of the initial
work on that. And it's been
phenomenal, like the amount of
you know it with our depth
cloud, you can tell what things
are like you can see humans and
you know, because it's hard to
visualize, right? Like as humans
were not good at visualizing a
depth cloud, even though there
are some things to do it with
color and things like that, like
red is close. And blue is far
whatever it may be. But with the
the LiDAR, like the amount of
data in line scanning that we
get with both of those units has
been phenomenal. In terms of
range.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. Do you
think the LIDAR will ever
replace the depth cameras?
Charles Brian Quinn: I, I'm of
course,
Audrow Nash: redundant system.
Yeah, yeah, I'm
Charles Brian Quinn: a prevalent
probabilistic guy, right? You
you, you nail that ahead of
time. And so I think that the
world is full of dirty sensor
data. And you should take as
much of that dirty sensory data
as you can apply probability to
do the task at hand. And
whatever comes out needs to be
the one I don't think that there
is an end all be all. Yeah, it's
funny. I mean, you look at like
the Tesla. And I know that
they're all super deep on
vision. But yeah, we know I have
some friends in the industry
have been doing this well, and
they're like, hey, like, fog.
You know, like, they're like
fog. And they're like, so this
is like a known thing. So I
would not be surprised if, if,
if the future is better than
than humans. And it should be.
It could be. Oh, yeah, totally
using sensors and things that we
don't have. We just, we happen
to see in RGB. So we send that
tend to sort of go for that. But
there's no reason why the world
of a robot shouldn't have be
like an insect that can totally
see, you know, completely
different spectrum than us.
Right. Yeah. Infrared seems very
useful for a lot of things. Like
all sorts of other things.
Audrow Nash: Okay. That's really
cool. The let's see. So, these
are your sensors. And then do
you have a you have a computer
onboard? You mentioned it's an
x86 architecture. What is it? Is
it like a super powerful
computer is the now
Charles Brian Quinn: here's,
there are a couple other things.
I mentioned that so the computer
is not very powerful, but I
would say it probably is. The
main thing though, is heat. So
they're ruggedized industrial
din, rated for fanless for heat
and vibration, and those are
critical. And by the way, we
have hit the limit on those in
Texas several times. It do not
mess around in Texas. They do
not mess around with mowing.
They have practice fields on
practice fields.
Audrow Nash: Wow. That's crazy.
That field for mowing,
Charles Brian Quinn: you think
it's practice fields for
football, but and, and all this,
but it has just for mowing?
Yeah. Well, we have those. We
have those but Yes, but But
yeah, and so we'd be out there
and it was 105 Fahrenheit, which
is I don't know what that is in
Celsius. I should because I'm 30
pharmacists close to. Yeah. And
so our computers are rated for I
think they may be up to 70 or
something like that. which is
nuts 7070 Celsius, which is like
140. So I may be off and maybe
40 and 140 because I'm not very
good at the conversions. Because
I have Siri that just tells me.
But anyway, the point of the
story is that we hit the limit.
And our USB bus died and fell
off. And so all the cameras were
gone. And of course, the mowing
is like, stop. But what's funny
is we were like, We were
apologizing their customer
customers, like I'm done to me.
They're like in terms of human
like, we shouldn't be out here
either. Like at when it's 105
humid, and our you know, yeah.
So they're like, it's, you know,
you're good. You're good. buy
our books. So but what is cool
is we did fix some of that, you
know, when it made it more
robust? Yeah, we've had heat
shielding. And some of the, you
know, exhausts i We got one of
those flot FLIR Thermal guns to
flir measurements. Yeah. And I
was surprised how hot do you
think it does get on the at the
exhaust point of the engine on a
mower in Texas? Like, what's
your guess? I don't know.
180 730 coming off, the exhaust
says, That's pretty well, I
guess. Seven? Yeah, it's very
hot. And so we originally had
our sort of exhaust sort of
blowing towards the back of the
computer, and there's this area.
And so ours would just heat up
to where it stopped. So now we
vented it differently. We've
added some extra shielding with
air, which is another reason why
we work we love working with the
manufacturers, because they're
like, we've been dealing with
heat shielding forever. They're
like, yeah, what you do. And
they just added three things.
And they're like, done, and
we're like, oh, cool. Check,
check.
Audrow Nash: That was easy.
Yeah.
Charles Brian Quinn: I don't
think we're done yet. But
there's that now we do. Also, we
love microcontrollers. So we're
a big fan of, I think we use
Arduinos, we use Teensies. I
think TNCs are the current
generation. And the more we can
do our we have another theory
about probabilistic robotics.
But another theory is that the
more we can do at the low level
hardware, the safer the system
will be. And so anything we can
do that that becomes sort of
rote and is not in C++ or
something high, like at a high
level, I would call C++ a high
level language, even though you
can go low, you know, we can
move that down to the
microcontroller and have a
bonafide you know, thing that
when it turns on, that's the
only thing it does. And it's
dedicated to the really single
purpose. So it's the same reason
you like nodes. In a sense,
you're exactly right. Yep. Okay.
Well, I'm super excited about
some of the Ross to you know,
stuff that you can run, you
know, oh, yeah, a device where
it just outputs a topic. Yeah,
embedded, whatever, right. Yeah,
that's gonna be really cool.
Audrow Nash: Why? So, if you're
using C? Or do you do things
where you're allocating all your
memory beforehand? Or?
Charles Brian Quinn: Excuse me?
Yeah, whereas in C++,
Audrow Nash: oh, you said your
C++, okay. Yeah, the I do avoid
Charles Brian Quinn: microcontrollers,
or C, right? And make sure we're
doing that in whatever the the
microcontroller languages
Arduino, ESP, whatever those
are. But yeah, we're using C++
for the main stack. We still
also use some Python for a lot
of the lower level. Statistics
are very good. So Mo, our
progress monitor and a lot of
that stuff that generates graphs
and gifts and things like that.
Can't be Python for that, for
sure. So yeah, again, they all
speak Ross topics on the back
end. So we're all happy to
oblige, right?
Audrow Nash: When when you put
things on microcontrollers, how
do you test them?
Charles Brian Quinn: Good
question. A lot of that is kept,
you know, sort of very low
level, but it does not have the
same test suite that our Ross
does. Yeah,
Audrow Nash: cuz you're writing
all these things you probably
have like a spool for maybe you
can run, I don't do this, we
Charles Brian Quinn: do. We have
a lab downstairs, I'd have to go
grab our systems engineer who is
probably down there doing it
now. But a lot of input, a lot
of output. I mean, a lot of
graphing manual testing to prove
that it will work as I expect.
And we're huge sponsors of David
Piccante. And his work at Platja
glare, like, you know, I think
we were one of the there's
wonderful, we use it every day.
So we sent him a little love
notes all the time. And I
couldn't be happier with that. I
mean, that's a majority of our
work is actually it's funny,
like we sent we put out graphs
of like, okay, here's what the
lower level microcontroller
encoder reads are, you know,
here's what it looks like. Now,
we replay replay replay a big
fan of replaying data. You know,
we in terms of testing, we do
have a good test suite that I'm
very proud of for robotic stack,
we use the Ross unit and Ross
testing, we throw sensor data
at, you know, we have a
continuous build server using
circle CI and so when when our
you know, we commit code, it all
goes on a circle CI server, it
runs the Ross unit tests and
make sure that the basic knowing
sort of workflow still works.
And we go massive amounts of
sensor data, we we, you know,
have recorded us going through a
field full of obstacles and make
sure that it's like yep, yep,
yep, yep. Yep. And that nothing
you do interferes with the
ability for the mower to stop,
right? Yeah, for sure. Ah, very
cool. But you're right testing.
I would love to see Ross get
better at this, I think, I think
the Ross community would flip
out if they saw what US former
web developers, the kind of
tooling that we have. Oh, yeah,
I was super excited that you had
the guys from foxglove, which
were huge fans of and users of
podcasts, which I know, they
just raised a big round. And I'm
super fans of them and the
testing that they're going to
do. Because I think they're
going to level up our industry a
lot, you know, with with real
time and sort of, you know,
we're, we've got some unique
stuff that we're doing and
working with them where, you
know, an incident happens in the
field. And that may be that a
sensor, you know, sort of
encoded drops, or you know, some
other things, and we can tag
that. And we can say, alright,
what happened, because that's
real world data. And by the way,
we're there in the field. So you
know, they're generating a ton
of data. And so we can't go grab
the entire bag file, which we
used to be, we'd be like,
somebody run out there with a
hard drive. And like, same
thing. Yeah. So we built a
pretty cool system that can you
can tag it. And then there's a
Our Sync type process that runs
in the background. Nice, nice as
a Unix command that will lower
the priority. So that like, the
rest of the stuff can also it's
very low priority. So right, and
so then it'll squirt that data
over that 32nd window of that
thing to a server, and then we
give it to foxglove. And we're,
like, visualize that. Because
that what happened there, right.
Like, why did the mower, see it
saw a corrugated fence and
thought there was an obstacle
straight in front of it when it
was, you know, I mean, 30 meters
out, right. So stuff like that,
right? Yeah, it's been very fun.
I digress. But we could
definitely get better on the
testing side. And if you're
interested in that, and find
more resources that we'd love to
know.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, for sure.
We're getting a little better
with Ross too. Yeah, for some of
the testing resources, but I
agree, it's a big and especially
for like industrial, or, like
for company level reliability.
Like, we could probably improve
a lot as a community total in
this space, I think. Let's see.
How do you update your systems?
Charles Brian Quinn: Very
excited and happy to talk about
that. We part of my Ross CON
talk was a little bit on that.
Now. I love the current system
that I believe you guys use for
packaging, because I am a big
fan of it. I think it's what
it's cat can plus,
Audrow Nash: we use cold con
cold on we're here with Ross
one. So yeah, yeah,
Charles Brian Quinn: well,
there's that. And then blue are
the bloom, that's the one I was
gonna talk about Bloom is the
sort of thing that will create
packages, right. Now Debian
packages for distribution on
Linux. So we evaluated using
bloom and tried it for a little
while. But what we found is that
we were unable to do a lot of
the sort of, we couldn't find a
way to do meta packages, which
we use a lot of where it'll be
like, you know, packages, well,
and also to pulling in other
stuff. So what we did was we
went and we also were targeting
just Debian so I sorry, ubuntu
LTS. And so we don't need to
create RPM, or other things, you
know, generically, and so we're
other Linux distributions or
other operating systems, okay.
So what we do is we create our
own Debbie ends, and we use
Debbie and proper, right, so we
just straight up, generate them,
the Debbie and from, you know,
using the Debbie and maintainers
guide, and all the tools that
exist with change log and all
that stuff. And so then we build
packages. And then we have a
couple of private repos that we
mirror Ross upstream. So thank
you, I mean, that's a new thing
that a lot of people do, right?
And and then we mirror you know,
Ross security and Eros updates.
And so we have our own package
server. And so when our mower
boots up, it runs apt update,
essentially. And if you look at
my talk, it actually runs a
couple things. It's actually
dist upgrade, you know, which is
an automated with why right. And
so basically all our packages
are installed. And then when we
do that, the system is still
running the current one. And so
then when it when you go to
reboot it, it'll actually run
the new stuff. And so we use a
ton of super small postinstall.
There's a lot of stuff, neat
tricks you can do in some of the
like, when after you install
something, you can, you can redo
your config and kind of fixed
files and change variables and
stuff. And I haven't found a
little bit of that lacking in
the sort of automated stuff. So
again, when we control the full
Debian, we can do a lot of that.
And so we've been really excited
by that I would love to, I've
heard that snaps are good. And
I'd be really curious to explore
that. I've even tried to connect
with some of the people that are
working on that. But I'm just
again, I'm a low level sort of
Unix guy and I've been doing
Debian and Ubuntu for so long
that when there was a tool out
there like apt and Debbie and I
was like, just reach for it and
say, Okay, let's do this. Yep.
But it's been fun. The other fun
stuff is there's some neat stuff
we used to use a package called
rep rep row to to manage them.
And then there's another one
came along called athlete that
allows us to snapshot and mirror
these and now we have what's
really cool is when you deploy
code to our mowers The automated
system will run all the tests.
It'll, it'll actually generate a
bunch of Debbi ins, it goes and
installs them automatically on
our experimental mowers. So we
have a couple of tests on the
platform. So on each mower,
you're running the tests or your
CI, run the test on the CI,
which is like a desk, for
instance, that mimics the whole
install, right? And so, but
you're right, it doesn't have a
lot of the sensors on it,
they're all fake right, then. So
you're right. So there needs to
be somebody needs to test it.
And so what we do is we have a
fleet, and I showed you ahead of
time, before we were on our lab,
where we have a couple hours,
some of these mowers are on what
we call the experimental branch
and experimental is just the
Debian wording for hasn't yet
been released to production. And
we use that term lightly, but
they're experimental. And so
they run bleeding edge. And so
what that means is that when
they turn on, they're running
main, which was formerly known
as GitHub master, right. And so
they run main. And so when you
commit code, you can go
downstairs and you can run it on
experimental. And we do we we
run around our lab, and you saw
the field where we met out back.
And so we'll go and run that
around and make sure that the
all the functionality is there.
And as soon as we do enough of
that, we then do a release. And
release is nothing more than the
git pull request that packages
up all everything from that's
been an experimental for a while
we do those every one or two
weeks. And what's nice about
that is we do release notes, and
then we text message our
customers with those, you know,
improvements and features a lot
of our developer, but a lot of
them and then we work them both
in English and Spanish and make
sure that they know that, hey,
the Moto is going to be updated
next time you turn it on, you
know, I think eventually we'll
have to just copy the Tesla
interface where you can download
the update and then apply it.
And then you know, there's three
options. But for now, we are
automating and forcing those
upgrades, because everybody is
on the same one. And we can do
that because we're able to
manage, but I'm sure we'll get
more sophisticated, but we're
really happy with that. And I'd
love to open source more in that
area. It's just when I go to do
it. I'm like, Oh, this is
Debbie. And this is apt this is
you know,
Audrow Nash: it's just a process
very specific to specific to us.
And also, it's
Charles Brian Quinn: like, it's
just a way to use all these open
source that's pretty well
documented. So
Audrow Nash: yeah, I feel like
like a really well written
tutorial or blog posts would be
awesome around that kind of
thing. Challenge accepted.
Because yeah,
Charles Brian Quinn: I'll
definitely make keep doing that
the Ross talks, because we
definitely enjoy that we were
asked to I think this year, and
we're big fans and sponsors, I
hope to sponsor that bigger
level NEXT TIME TO
Audrow Nash: HELL YEAH. YEAH. So
can you talk a bit more about
safety in your design? Or like
making it robust?
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah,
absolutely. I think about this
all the time. From, you know,
the current thing that we're
doing, we've gotten a lot
better, and we're continuing to
get better. You know, safety is
our first core value safety
first. And so one of the things
we're doing right now that I'm
very proud of is that we have a
PhD risk. A person who just
absolutely loves thinking about
risk data and is asked just I
mean, the amount of data and
things he asked for, you know,
he's like, how many accidents
happened in this way that led to
hospitalization through this and
he's like, Okay, we put this in
our system. And he's got things
that he's automated to basically
help us make sure that we adhere
to the highest level to some of
these standards that are out
there. And so our current system
is pretty well documented in how
we adhere to these based on our
understanding interpretation.
And as we get better
understanding, and as we get
better sensor data and things,
it can be updated, and do
iteration. Exactly. And a lot of
the work we do is in validating
those. So the key areas that I
would think that that your
audience might be interested on
are, we are constantly trying to
push the limits of the obstacle
detection framework and
pipeline, so our customers, what
we tell them, and what it
actually does is a little
different, right? So we err on
the side of safety. So our
system can detect obstacles of a
certain size. And I won't go
into that right now. But and
what we tell them is it has to
be of this size, and we do that
for that margin.
Audrow Nash: So you give them
the worst case and you
internally, it's something a
little better on that,
Charles Brian Quinn: right. And
then what they know is they say,
okay, cool, right. And so the
biggest one is people are like,
Hey, does it detect sprinkler
heads? And I'm like, Absolutely
not. You know, like, those are
too small. And I was like, you
know, sometimes as humans even
have trouble, like, you know,
Audrow Nash: right over.
Charles Brian Quinn: And what
the neat part is, though, is
that when I asked them really
like, what what are you getting
at? Like, what? And they say,
Well, you know, if this thing's
going to do the whole thing, it
needs to know that like
remember, you do the boundary
and I was like, why don't you
just like do that part yourself?
And you go around where you
know, those are because you
install them? He's like, Oh,
yeah, I installed all this
finger heads. Right? And then
I'm not gonna hit him, right and
so and I was like, why don't you
just go one lap inside, do a lap
and let the mower do that and
then you take out a string
trimmer edger wieder blower and
you do that detailed
Audrow Nash: work while you do
it. Oh, that's awesome. They can
parallelize their own
Charles Brian Quinn: effort.
Yeah. And so that's pipelining
is huge. In fact, you know, when
I talk about, you know, greens,
the we take job openings, not
jobs, right? There's, there's
hundreds, and there's 1000s of
job openings, just that one of
our customers, you know, for,
you know, workers that they
don't have and can't find. And
so when green Z comes along, it
says, I'll take that really
boring one. And you can, you can
pipeline. So that crew that used
to be a three or five person
crew can be like one or two
people now with a couple of
robotic workers, and now they're
doing the same work that they
were able to do. And they're
able to go home, you know,
sooner and go talk to the kids
and just, you know,
Audrow Nash: do all that. Yeah,
exactly. It's, I mean, it's less
work for everyone to do,
basically, because the robot is
taking over some of it. Yep. At
least taking some of it that was
already there. And, like, not
there aren't enough people for
thinking and sound. Yeah. Okay.
So with how do you how do you
test your robots? So you
mentioned that you go, you have
this main branch, and you'll go
and you test it on your robot in
your fields? How do you make
sure that something is ready to
be deployed to all of the mowers
on in your system?
Charles Brian Quinn: I'm glad
you asked this, because this
circles back to something I
said, let's talk about in the
future, and that is that we eat
our own dog food. And what I
mean by that is that we are
current subcontractors to a
couple of our customers so we
are mowers I'm, I'm wearing the
outfit. I actually have a
uniform, I wear this I have five
of these shirts, and I'm wearing
the lawn mowing shoes. And, and
we have a safety glasses in
here. And, but and we have
trailers and trucks, and we met.
So today we went and we have a
couple customers, they have
sites and we say hey, you know,
can we go out? And they're like,
absolutely. I mean, they're
every time. Yeah, you know. And
the good news is, you know, we
carry the insurance and
liability to it and the training
were OSHA certified and or OSHA
training, excuse me, I don't
think there's a certification.
But and we follow all their
guidelines. And we product and
OSHA is the is the Occupational
Safety and Health
Administration. They're the ones
who would, would dictate that
when you're doing this activity
that you have, and I won't show
you my shoes, but they're closed
toed. Right. So composite or
steel toe, that when you're in
the
Audrow Nash: standards body for
worker safety correctively our
worker conditions are something
okay.
Charles Brian Quinn: And by by
joining and being there that
they'll report on incidents and
things that are unsafe. Yeah,
exactly. In order to understand
they're very big in
construction, right. This is why
when you go to a construction
site, if you're not wearing your
helmet, your hard hat, you know,
you can OSHA can get you in
trouble. So But I digress a
little bit, so we as
subcontractors we go out. And
that's pretty critical for us.
But from a product standpoint,
it's also No, but what we do is
when we go out and we do the
work to be done with that's the
day after is usually when we do
our releases will go and we say,
you know, we tried to push it
before, we're like, oh, that's
just a small fix, let's just put
it into production. The good
news is we can issue fixes
pretty quick, like we've got a
system for doing that we can
hotfix and do a branch off
stable and do a hotfix. And
we've had to do this before, you
know, luckily, some of them
aren't like critical, you know,
that the test suite will cup cut
that out, right. But it might be
some small fix that gets out
there. But in doing so by by
actually doing the job to be
done. We are effectively and
experience, right. And we're
making sure that what I would
call is sort of the eye it's
it's more eyes on the bugs make
sort of bugs shallow, that's the
cathedral bizarre approach,
right is that, you know, as our
customers see these things, and
as we see them, like we can fix
them. And so I tell our team,
you know, and we've strived to
do this, but we strive to make
sure that we can release early
and often and quickly. And I
think that that is probably our
kicker. So we even have DevOps,
time DevOps that just helps us
with developer tooling,
developer happiness, logging,
and making sure that our stuff
is just fast to go out. And I
think that's just critical.
We'll just probably continue to
build that practice internally.
But to answer your question, how
do we know when it's ready to go
is when we feel comfortable, and
we've used it ourselves, and
we've mowed lawns with it, and
it still works, and it passes
all our tests. We package it up.
And we what's interesting is
that we just do a release off
stable. And we package it all
up, bump the version numbers and
then hit go. And it
automatically deploys into all
across our fleet. And so then
that's when we do our text
message to the to the customers
and say, Hey, next time you turn
it on, you know,
Audrow Nash: these are the
changes that will be applied.
Yeah. And most
Charles Brian Quinn: of the
time, they're excited. They're
like, Oh, cool. I asked for that
feature last week. And we're
like, yep, there it is.
Audrow Nash: That's awesome. Do
you I guess, how do you train
people to use your system? Like,
how is it?
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah,
right. Yeah. We're, we're
venture backed, and so we're
very hands on. In fact, we'll we
I've, I've hired some people who
are robotic technicians who
speak English and Spanish better
Spanish than I than I do. And
they go on site and are doing a
lot of that. And we're building
up that practice as well. We
are, I'm a big fan of the quote,
what is it good artists copy?
What is it emulate? Great
artists feel? Oh, yeah. And so
what we did is I asked our
customers, like, who has the
best training? And they said,
you know, and I won't say who it
is, because we're gonna copy
him. And, and I said, Great,
we're gonna do University. And I
said, like, let's just, I mean,
honestly, I mean, I, we're not
gonna steal everything, because
it's just totally different. But
Audrow Nash: it's dropping the
decisions. Yeah. It's like, they
did a lot of things through
iteration. You're just kind of
grabbing that and starting
there.
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah. And
honestly, I think hopefully,
that will leverage and level up
the industry by not starting
from ground zero, right. And so
we have a very good training
program that is very hands on.
And we've gotten very good at
it. In fact, our I'm very proud
of the work that our team does,
they've, they've delivered it
several times. In fact, when we
first started, one of the things
we did that it was very unique
was we did training before we
even had anything, which was
awesome. We invited landscapers
to come train on what we had
now. And they'd ask questions
like, Well, what do you do about
and we're like, how to get to
the thing? Yeah, or, or we'd be
like that we do it with them.
And then they'd be like, I'm
confused by x. And we'd be like,
re explain that. Right. And so
we did a lot. We've done a lot.
And so now if you were to go out
with our gentleman, who does the
train one of our gentlemen, who
does the training right now,
he's very good at it, and even
does some really things that are
unique. Some of our investors
have been in the green industry
for why a while and they talk
about training, being very
specific, where you tell them
what you're gonna tell them,
then you tell them, tell them
tell them and then you tell them
why and then you told them, yes.
And so we do a lot of that. And
then it's a lot of it is from
example, and sort of building
on. So there's like a base case,
like, what we do is we used to
kind of go into like safety and
all sort of stuff. And we're
like, you know, what, just show
the basic use case, then starts
talking about some of the things
that could happen and trigger
those things to happen. And then
the other thing we do that's
really nice, too, is that we
trigger some some things like,
for instance, we very
intentional about when we start
going we say oh, you know,
something happened, he pauses
the MO or whatever. And then he
says, What would you do, and we
have them call support. We have
a 787 P support line, that's
text, message and phone. And
that's staffed by our CIT level
one engineers, which is in some
of us now, which is we all do
support. We all have shifts? And
so we'll answer it and we'll
say, Oh, cool. Looks like you've
got this. Thanks for calling.
You can call any time. The
answer is this. We know what it
is hit resume, and you should be
able to do it. And they go, Oh,
that was easy. And so we
hopefully then they, you know,
because if we just showed up,
and we're like, oh, you can call
support for anything. I mean,
yeah, I do it. But if we have
them do it in a case where it's
really easy, and it makes them
feel good. And we say thank you
and do all these things. You
know, and then we're ready for
it that they go, Oh, well, that
was fun, you know, and then we
also are watching. So we
congratulate him, like we'll
send them a text and be like,
hey, great first map. It's kind
of like they're in on the
project. That sounds thing. You
nailed it. Yeah. And so it's,
I'm very proud of our training.
And that's some of my background
was in a lot of that technical
training, like making the
complex, simple. And so very
proud of our work in that. And I
think we have a lot to do and a
lot of work to do there. But
we're pretty good at it, I
think.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. How long? How
long does it take to train
someone before they're up and
running?
Charles Brian Quinn: It used? We
used to advocate for a couple of
days. And I'd be surprised. I
think the last training we did,
one of our guys shows up and
he's like, he's like they got it
like after an hour. He's like,
Yeah, he's like, and so now what
we do is we hang out with them,
and help them because they need
help. Yeah, just see if they
need any do site selection and
stuff like that, which is crazy.
So we've gotten really good with
the pre work and sort of pre
material. And then when we come
on site, it's very quick. As you
can imagine, these are
experienced operators. And we've
gotten some of the analogies
very good like you you've done
and the system itself has gotten
really simple. It's it's
basically an appliance right, so
yeah, you know, there's one like
cruise control. I mean, yeah, I
mean, they go when I got a new
car, they didn't train me on
cruise control. I was just like,
Oh, there's the two buttons for
it. Got it. Right. It's it's
trying to make it like that.
Right. And I didn't used to be
like that used to be I mean, you
used to watch us we'd have a
laptop and we'd be like,
alright, yeah, Ross launch your
BBs open. Yeah. Oh, yeah. Yeah,
Audrow Nash: it's crazy. Okay.
So, how many of these do you
have? Like how many mowers are I
actually I'm curious about the
business model. So you're
venture backed at the moment but
it will it be a subscription
based thing? Will people own
these robots? Or how will it or
people, people own autonomous
system in the mower?
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah, I'm
happy to share all this, we're
pretty open book with almost
everything except for probably
my, if my employees are on a
pip, that's probably the only
thing I won't share and their
salary. What's that? A
performance improvement plan,
that just means you're in
trouble. And so I think that the
joke is that I, we're pretty
open book about a lot of stuff
in our business, we're not like
a stealth mode startup, and we
never have been. So it's just
easier to just be open on it is,
you don't have to remember what
you told people. And so for our
business model, currently, we're
trying to meet our customers
with how they pay, or how they
charge. And so knowing is a
seasonal business. And when you
think about seasonal workers,
and robotic workers, there's a
cost associated with those
workers. If I wanted to have a
worker, you know, I might pay
them a yearly, you know, you
think about the cost and years
because a lot of these companies
that do commercial have these
contracts that last for a year,
and they're like, Okay, we're
gonna need, you know, X ray
people on this crew and Right,
exactly, well, 3d, we're on this
crew, right. And so our costs
are pretty simple, in that we
charge how our customers pay how
they get paid. And so it's a one
monthly fee for our software.
Now, the the mower itself is,
like I said, upfitted. And so
what's great about that, though,
is that the manufacturer is able
to do that. And what's great
about that is that they've been
able to put their procurement in
their economies of scale on
these things. So I guarantee you
that they're getting better
pricing on a Hall Effect
encoder, from, you know, from
Honeywell than we were able to
get, right? Because when when we
call, we're like, can we get
100? And they're like, you know,
and when they call, they're
like, can we get 50,000? And by
the way, here's our procurement
person, and we probably already
ordered from you anyway. And
they're like, Great, yeah, we
can add that to your next order.
And so there is some new stuff,
but you know, they've obviously
gotten better pricing on that.
And again, more manufacturers
and OEM producers are better at
the storing and producing of
that equipment at the facility
where they do it. And so we
don't we, you know, we don't
have a big manufacturing
facility where we do
Audrow Nash: you don't need it,
you just do the software, and
the testing and sensor suites,
like, figuring it
Charles Brian Quinn: out
exactly. And and constantly
iterating on on the next
generation and our sort of what
we call upgrades and field.
Right. And so yeah, so in terms
of charging the business model,
I would not be surprised if we
move to a robotics as a service.
And I know that's a pretty
popular route to call it. And
some of our customers are asking
for it. So we would love to work
with some of our partners on
doing that. Could you imagine a
day where if you're a
landscaper, and you say hey, I
know from May to October, or
April to October, you know,
however many months that is 878
months? And we said what if we
could give you a mower and a
robotic worker that lives on
that mower? For one fee, and
2500 I'm making up a number I'm
on and they go, that's a dang
good deal. Because, you know,
like, if you think about the
person and the mower, and they
start to do the math, and
they're like, whoa, that's like,
you know, six or seven an hour
in terms of labor, and we're
like, great, you know, like not
to be coy or anything. But like
that said, you know, you can't
hire person for that. I mean, no
person would want to work for
seven an hour, right? But a
robotic worker, and also it
Audrow Nash: can work through
the heat and all the like, and
also won't get tired
Charles Brian Quinn: quality.
Yeah. And And also, we do get
pushback because they're like,
Well, what about in January,
like right now when you know,
some of our customers only known
a little bit or not at all, if
they're in the Northeast, and I
go, Well, what do you do now?
And they're like, you know, fire
them or get seasonal workers or
have them do something else? And
I'm like, well, guess what, your
robotic worker on your mower on
March 1, is ready to mow? And
you know, even if you put him on
the shelf, you know, put him
aside and weatherize they'll be
ready to move. And yeah, guess
what he's gotten like 50 updates
since then. Yeah, is better. And
like has more features and
functionality from all these
people we were known in Florida
has been training in the OFF
time. Exactly. Robotic workers.
Yeah. And what's cool is that
they don't get it yet until they
see it and experience it. And
then they're like, Wow, they're
like, this is software. Like,
I've got software on my mower,
and a robotic worker that's
continually getting better. And
it's hard to see, like, you
know, it's hard to tell
somebody, but when they see it,
and experience it, they get
really, like addicted to it,
right. So our early customers
are, are gonna win big because
they've been early adopters. And
they've seen us through some of
the challenges of things, but
they've also experienced some
pretty big wins. And so I think
that business model will
continue, but I'm also open to
changing it, you know, like
we're very, very customer
oriented, customer focused and
obsessed. And so if they need
something else, we'll do it for
them. You know, and I think that
the, we are we are taking we are
using a lot of capital right now
to do speed and to shore up and
so like, you know, when the
customer asked for something, we
just do it. And when we hit
those economies To scale, I
think we'll have those general
SAS margins that are pretty
high, when we're just delivering
a service. And we don't have to
go out and do training and you
know, all that other stuff,
which is we're on the path
towards doing.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. What do you
so you said that this is you've
always been bootstrapping in the
past. And this is the first time
you're taking venture capital.
Would you tell me a bit about
your experience with this? And
oh, yeah, just talk on it for a
bit.
Charles Brian Quinn: I love
both. I think that there's room
and time to do both. I think, if
you don't have to raise money,
you shouldn't. You know, it is I
think there's a very good use
cases, when you're doing
something is funny. My co
founder, David is really funny.
He's, he's an interesting guy.
And he has a quote that I'll
repeat, he says, you know,
starting a business is hard.
There's all kinds of challenges
people business, the the market,
you know, there's timing,
there's all kinds of stuff he's
like, so if the whole thing is
hard, anyway, why not just start
a big one? Right. And I and I
was like, You're right, right?
Like, you know, why not? He's
like, why not just go after
something massive, like that's,
you know, huge and impactful and
game changing. And, you know,
it's funny, because that's kind
of his investment thesis, right?
Like, he won't invest in like,
gambling or whatever, you know,
like, it's just not, you know,
it's like a bootstrap. Yeah, it
has to be big. And, and so it's,
and so there's a time and place
for that now, bootstrapping, I
absolutely love because there's
something brilliant and amazing
about selling something,
delivering it, getting paid, and
using that money to grow. And
I've done that, and and, you
know, you know, service
businesses are great for that,
you know, restaurants would be
good for that, you know, where
you're just building one and
then use the profits from one
that go to the another and some
robotics companies could
probably, you know, do that
through some model. But if you
are going after something big,
and there's a leap of faith,
more, there's a lot of things
that have to happen, and a lot
of bets that you are capable of
doing and know like if you know
something that the rest of the
world doesn't, and I do and I
happen to know, and that is that
I think software is going to eat
the outdoor power equipment
industry, and totally the most
powerful thing on these devices,
then then I would, I personally
would pay a lot of money now to
be the operating system of the
future. And so I'll trade
today's dollars, hands down
tomorrow's. And so that's what
Yeah, and so placing a bet very
heavily. Oh, yeah. And what's
what's interesting is, is the
mindset shift from going from
Bootstrap to venture has been
tough for me. Because in the
Bootstrap, you know, a lot of
questions I would ask would be
like, how do we pay for that.
And, you know, like, right now,
like next month, or the, you
know, in 90 days, net 90, when,
when, when bills are due, you
want to stay positive the whole
time, basically, right. And, and
now, what I'm doing is I'm
constantly, I'm constantly
trying to build a valuable
company and an asset. And I use
that using capital. And so I do
a lot of things that are hard
that scale and doing a lot of
things that are very unscalable.
Now to prove that is scalable
later. And what I mean by that
is like, we eventually would
like for manufacturers, sorry
for the outdoor equipment
dealers to do a lot of the fixes
for us. And so what I do is I go
above and beyond to make sure
that it is easy, and that
they're incentivized to do it.
And so I pay, you know, more
than their sort of normal rate,
so that they're not, they don't
feel like, Oh, who's this
company? And why are they asking
me to like, put a new camera on
here. And I'm like, Hey, like, I
want you to, you know, I'm going
to use my venture dollars to
make to figure this out and get
better at it.
Audrow Nash: So you get lots of
feedback from them, so you can
improve the process, and
eventually, it will be less
painful thing for future ones.
Think. Interesting. Don't see
where
Charles Brian Quinn: I'm sure
I've, yeah, go ahead. I was
gonna say, and bootstrapping
adventure, I'm sure there's a
lot more people who can talk
more about it. And I know we're
running out of time, and I'm
happy to go into way more
detail. But I also don't know
too much. I'm still fumbling
along as I go. I wouldn't say
that I've mastered it, we have
raised quite a bit of funds. And
every time I tell my friends,
I'm like, Oh, I'm just not good
at this. They're like, look at
the results seem to be doing
okay, but I guess I'm harder on
myself than I am on on anybody
else. Right. So.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Let's see.
So we're a little over the
scheduled time is Are you okay
to talk a little longer? Yeah.
Okay. I would love to hear more
about your, your bootstrap
bootstrapping experience. And
then kind of like if there's
anything that you have learned
there that you can bring to this
venture capital experience.
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah. So
fundamentally, the the impact
the differences of like building
a business that is bootstrapped
meaning we had sold a product,
deliver that product, get paid
and then repeat versus the
venture which is, in my mind,
could be something like that,
but it's It's probably trading a
lot of it's basically going
into, like what I would call a
negative sort of, if you look
at, I guess the best way to
describe it is, there's a cost
of acquisition for each customer
that can get rather large. And
so at some point, you're
basically see this thing where
it looks like your company is
just burning money. And every
new customer you acquire causes
you to take this, we call it the
J curve. And David Scott talks a
lot about this, he talks about
recurring revenue businesses,
that J curve goes way down. And
every time you do it, it really
just looks like you're just
burning cash. But what's the
neat part? Is it that some point
that Jay, you know, can do this
and every recurring business,
you know, a lot of people are
like, well, so and so doesn't
make any money. And you're like,
well, that's not really the best
way right now. Right? Correct.
Because they're creating these
economies of scale. And every
customer they acquire, it might
cost 12 grand to acquire that
customer. But every year, they
make 12 grand, and the margin on
that 12 grand the profit on that
12 grand is very high, the
marginal dollars you do once you
acquire them. And then they also
don't think about net expansion,
which is where each customer
might add more, right? So you've
cost to acquire the network,
Audrow Nash: that kind of thing,
right? So it gets exponentially
better to use the service or
something.
Charles Brian Quinn: And so what
I would say is that the lessons
that I learned bootstrapping,
were just the basic ones, like I
still rely on a lot of them,
like how do I build a good
culture? How do I hire retain?
How do I fire people? You know,
that I don't like talking about
that. But you know, it's
something that you know, you
have to do to put the right
people on the bus and all those
lessons I learned using our own
money, like I have to do now
even though I have venture
money, I still do that. Right.
Like, and I think that that's
where I think you've talked
about it a lot. The analogy I
think you gave in the
agriculture one is that like too
much money can mess you up,
right? If you don't have any
constraints, like that can be
terrible. So one of the things
that we've done differently in
venture and maybe this will turn
out to be a dumb, dumb move. But
I have raised sequentially, sort
of small incremental rounds, as
opposed to giant ones. And so we
don't like advertise, like, oh,
we raised 16 million, like we've
never raised a $6 million round.
And we've done that, because
even though we take a little bit
of dilution on that, like, what
I've said is that, in
bootstrapping, I have built a
grape. And I've eaten the grape,
right? And so grape is pretty
good. But if you're hungry, it's
cool to build a watermelon and
eat a slice. And so when you
think about that, like, that's
what we're doing with green tea
and venture backed is that,
would you rather have a full
grape? Or would you rather have
a slice of a watermelon? And by
the way, the other slices all go
to investors, and people who are
actively taking risk with you.
And you know, and we've done a
really good job, I think of
recruiting in on our cap table,
we call it, you know, our
Audrow Nash: investor
capitalization table. Yeah,
Charles Brian Quinn: they're all
people who are green industry,
robotics, distributors, dealers,
also our various
Audrow Nash: Smart Money,
basically, yeah.
Charles Brian Quinn: I call him
and I'm like, Hey, how many
mowers were sold in there? And
they're like, Well, you know,
you're not supposed to know
this, that. But here you go. And
they don't say that. They say,
actually, here's what I can tell
you. And here's what I know. And
here's, here's this, and here's
what you need to talk to. And
here's seven other connections.
And, you know, call me later.
And I'll have that for you. And
I've been thinking about this,
and they are proactive, and so
we have a very good, that's the
other thing that I think is
unique is that we're bringing
along a lot of people with us,
which is really fun. To me,
there's, there's a bit of, and
what's cool, too, is I'm lucky
in that I was able to
participate in some of our
rounds, which is rare. I think,
for an entrepreneur, I have had
some some success before. And
so, and I always bet on myself.
So I lead one of the rounds,
which is kind of fun, you know,
to say, Okay,
Audrow Nash: what does it mean?
What does it mean? You let
around was it mean, you're the
person that goes around talking
and trying to raise investment.
Charles Brian Quinn: So I'm
always trying to go around and
raise investment, that's
actually my job as CEO. So I'm
gonna do it for what for this
round, I went to my, with my
investors and said, Hey, things
are looking really well for the
company. I believe that we have
hit our next milestone, because
we did. And I said, I'm leading
this next round, meaning I'm
putting in a million dollars in
my own money on this next round.
Yeah. And I think we need this
and does anybody want to come in
with me? And the fun part about
that is what happens is that I
didn't get to put in a million.
I only put in half that but the
there's all SEC D regulation,
you go look it up. So I'm not
like I'm bragging about it or
anything. But yeah, you know, so
so, but I did get to be the
largest investor in that and
then the reason it went down is
because all my other investors
were like, I'm in put me down
for more, you know, like, we're
in with you let's go and and
and, and they aren't always like
that, you know, a lot of them
are like, hey, like, these
metrics are bad. Like, you need
more you know, this, you need
more that? Yeah, they're
prioritizing something
different, but it is good that I
do have an investor cap table
that does believe in us and
we've had the For sure that will
up. And we've been able to
recruit others as well. But that
is a that is a fun game that I
am not good at yet. But I have
gotten better at it through
failure. And the last the last
round was very good. And we
raised $4 million. Very excited
by that. Thank you. We didn't
really I'm not very good at
publicizing those things,
because I'm just not good at it.
And I honestly think it's kind
of like taking on debt. And what
do you mean? I don't I don't
understand. It's kind of like we
take on this capital. And now we
have to utilize it, spend it
wisely. So I don't know. I do
think there's there's something
to be said for celebrating and
always helping your customers.
And so if there's a way to
phrase it, that helps your
customers, but I'm just not big
on the current Zeitgeist right
now, where we're like, raising
is the thing. Like, it's funny,
because the thing that I would
like to celebrate, and we
celebrate more internally is
like, happy customers, you know,
sales and that kind of stuff.
And so that's not really like
celebrated, we don't like a lot
of companies don't say like, we
just sold a million dollars.
Like, yeah, that should be
celebrated probably more than
the current raises, because
raises just mean that, you know,
Audrow Nash: raises you mean
higher valuation and raising
heavy rounds.
Charles Brian Quinn: Yeah. And
and also they without context,
they don't really mean anything,
right? Like, yes,
Audrow Nash: it's just a lot of
people don't share, you know,
the dilution, and they might
have been on unfavorable terms.
Like there's a lot of context
necessary, I
Charles Brian Quinn: believe.
And good news is, you know, I
can't I won't disclose I won't
disclose some of this because
not mine to disclose, but we
have very good, very good terms
on our raise. Very simple.
There's not a lot of funny,
Craps and convertible,
Audrow Nash: no lights, crazy,
veto power. Any event,
sometimes.
Charles Brian Quinn: My see my
co founder is has is the most
entrepreneur friendly, I think
it's gonna come out that he is
and he's had the Midas touch. I
think just recently, he's got a
couple companies that are worth
billions. And so wow. I mean,
he's super entrepreneur
friendly. And so it's crazy how
entrepreneur friendly is, in
fact, he's so friendly, on times
that he's just like, we'll just
what do you want to do? That it
actually makes it makes people
like me who have high
responsibility go, will shoot he
just gave me all theirs. I
better make this a win. Good.
Fair. Yeah. Yeah. And I think
that that's neat that I've
learned that about really good
venture is that they,
Audrow Nash: you know, it's
funny people talk you want to
help us succeed. Yeah, rather
than just they want to take the
maximum cut. Yeah, and kind of
screw you it's
Charles Brian Quinn: been an
entrepreneur too. So with that
also is a nicety. You know,
having been in those shoes,
personally, I can't do it. I'm
you'll never find me being an
investor. I'm terrible at it.
I've done it done a little bit,
but I'm just not good at it. I
like being in the in the in the
driver's ed arena.
Audrow Nash: You're betting on
yourself? Yeah. Yeah, I see.
What do you think is the the
future? Like when you look out?
Next year, two years, five
years? Where do you see green z
going?
Charles Brian Quinn: Ah, well,
we just did a couple of our
vision planning. I'm very big on
goals and goal setting. I have I
just looked at my personal goals
from five years ago back that I
wrote in 2016. And I think it's
incredible. That, you know, Bill
Gates said it, I think the quote
is true to him. He said, People
underestimate what they can do
in 10 years, they overestimate
what they can do in one. And so
I'm a big fan of writing your
your goals and the vision, and
there's a way to do it. And so
if we look, five years out,
green tea, and again, that the
name is actually interesting,
and it may be that green tea is
the product just for green. And
who knows, I mean, not gonna be
Audrow Nash: eventually I mean,
it's the same kind of, like, you
can follow this model in a lot
of areas, I imagine. Right now
you're making mowing.
Charles Brian Quinn: But if you
go back to what I told you that
our big mission is to free
humans from repetitive outdoor
labor. And that is always been
the case. And we will continue
to do that. I just learned the
other day that there's even self
driving trucks get dirty, and 18
wheelers and something they pay
some people to go to these
things where they park them and
then they just do this the up
and down spray to spray them
with like, you know, to clean
the wheels and stuff that's
highly repetitive outdoor. And I
think it needs to be automated
because I think we humans are
not made to get carpal tunnel
doing this within Oh, yeah. Are
they are made to do is say hey,
this needs to be clean. And hey,
that one doesn't need to and you
know, hey, you know,
Audrow Nash: I'm better all the
decision making all this other
fun, high level.
Charles Brian Quinn: So I
believe that green tea in five
years will be helping free
humans from repetitive outdoor
labor. And we'll do that for as
long as it takes. And I think
that that's a big noble task.
It's going to take a long time.
And so a lot of people always
ask are you for sale? And the
answer is no, we're not for
sale. But how much
Audrow Nash: use you started in
2018. With bangzi Is it correct?
Yeah, that's awesome. You're
already getting questions about
that. Well, I
Charles Brian Quinn: mean,
everybody does, right. I mean,
yeah, at least when you sort of
talk to them. Yeah. Big big
people or big players or
partners and things like that.
But yeah, you know, the answer
is no, but how much we
everything's for sale except for
my boy. Right. So, but But the
big thing that they have to
answer is is will they help us
in our mission to free humans
from repetitive labor in the
answer No, then it's not even on
the table. It's not Yeah.
Gotcha. So So if we were to, to,
to sell, to merge to buy to
acquire other companies, they
have to be in support of that
mission and that big mission to
free humans from repetitive
outdoor labor. And if they are,
let's go, let's do it. So I see
us continuing to do that. And I
don't know where it'll take us,
I think we're small. And so we
do a lot of short term planning,
we do quarterly OKRs and
objective key results. And, and
we shoot for we have a yearly
goal. And we have some big
yearly goals, company objectives
that we go for, we have a three
year plan to be very
specifically on more mower
manufacturers, possibly in other
turf areas, other sort of
platforms. And so I see us doing
that, I have a couple other
things that probably are more
internal and not really exciting
to share. But I see that, and I
see us also being a big members
of the community, I would love
to see us open source more and,
and I just think that, you know,
some of the work we're doing is
just doesn't just needs to be
out there. And I'd be happy to
continue to contribute. I'm a
huge fan of open source. I've
been doing it my entire life. So
it's awesome. It's game
changing,
Audrow Nash: for sure. Last
thing, before asking for links
and things. What advice would
you give to someone who's just
starting their career?
Charles Brian Quinn: Mm hmm. I'm
not good at this. My I've had co
founders, my, my last co founder
was very good at giving advice.
And I think he even has a famous
blog article on it. So on the
career, I think it's funny, a
lot of people will tell you, I
can only speak from experience.
So let's just say that I'm not
good at giving advice. That's
what kind of what I try and do.
I'm not very good at it either.
But I would say that finding
something you love is dumb. You
know, like, you know, when I
think at certain levels, you
should strive to work hard and
learn. And, and, and not make,
you know, not not do this thing
where they're like, if you do
the work you love, you'll never
work a day in your life. I was
like, man, if you do the work,
if you do something you love,
you're gonna hate it is the
biggest way to like destroy,
you're like, I love tennis,
you're like, I'm gonna become a
tennis instructor. And now
you're gonna be like, tennis,
for my French. But yeah, the. So
I think career advice for
somebody starting out is get out
there, just do something, like,
do something big and do the
worst tasks that someone doesn't
want to do. You know, like, what
that means is like, okay, so if
you want to go into finance,
great, go figure out how to, you
know, make more Bitcoin money
off somebody else who doesn't
own Bitcoin, that's fine. That's
not for me, I don't think that's
very exciting. I would say find
a company that's doing something
noble or good or sustainable.
And then go do the worst thing
in it, like, go do customer
support, right? Like, you know,
like, or work the, you know, the
worst job. And if you're useful
and good, you will learn and you
will move quickly. You know,
there's plenty of examples of
people who've worked in the
mailroom of the CEO. And it
happens all the time. I have
good friends who, you know,
worked in businesses who are
CEOs now and people are like,
Oh, how did you do that? And
it's like, well, overnight, it's
like, no, of course, not
overnight. You know, they did
something hard and learned and,
and jumped in and did it and,
and weren't afraid to say this
is hard. And what I'm doing is
hard. And it may take a little
while. And that's easy for me to
say because I'm sort of older
and having done that. But yeah,
I mean, I worked as a consultant
for a long time traveling, you
know, Monday through Thursday,
working in really weird
locations, but it was the amount
of learning I could think back
on that it was able to help me
do to build good products for
good customers and do things.
It's just, it's, it's amazing.
So I don't have any good advice
for career you could skip this
section. You know, it's very
valuable. Go do something noble
and hard and boring and, and
learn whatever you can from it.
That's my advice.
Audrow Nash: Love that. Oh,
yeah.
Charles Brian Quinn: Last thing
is do you have any links or
contact info or anything that
you'd like to share with our
listeners? Absolutely. So
Twitter is our more developer
robotics focused, pithy jokes,
and shout outs to Ross. So
that's where we sort of do that.
YouTube is pretty good. We have
a series called how it works.
That's actually pretty good even
for roboticist and sort of non
roboticists, which I know is
your audience sort of emerging.
We share a lot about how the
product works, which landscapers
really love. And so that's
booting back up in series. We
used to do one a month we've
sort of tailed off in December
we to do one, we're back on that
schedule and committed to it
goal setting. And so we'll be
doing a bunch of those YouTube
videos. I'd say that our YouTube
channels fun. We went viral on
tick tock, although that's
probably not going to go look at
that. We have like a couple of
YouTube videos with like
millions of views which is nuts.
Wow. That is nuts. Yeah, I don't
understand that one. And
Instagram is really good for if
you're a landscaper and you want
to see how the product works.
We're constantly posting stuff
from the field. Then like actual
mowing, and actual usage of the
of the robot, which I think is
really fun and good. But yeah,
all those channels are good. And
our website, you know, it
doesn't get updated that often.
But you can definitely go there.
If you're interested in careers,
we, you know, definitely go
there. And I think LinkedIn, I
haven't figured out yet I need
to get better at that one of my
investors is very good at that.
And I need to ask them to do it.
So. But yeah, go to green Z,
green z.com, where get green Z
or green Z on most channels, you
can find us and I think that's
it. Yeah, I mean, I think we
have some open source tool on
GitHub. One of our path planners
is out there. It's good for
research. For coverage. We did
one of the papers and kind of
improved it. So you're happy to
do that. We have some fun stuff
that we're gonna open source
soon on the newer one that we
did. So we don't maintain that
one. Unfortunately, if somebody
like to pick up the maintaining
on that date, they're welcome to
but we have some really other
fun stuff.
Audrow Nash: So all right.
Awesome.
Charles Brian Quinn: Thank you.
Thank you for having me. Cheers.
Audrow Nash: Cheers. Thanks for
listening to this conversation
with CPQ. Thank you again to our
founding sponsor, open robotics,
and I hope to see you next time