Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with our friends
who is the founder and CEO of
MangDang. MangDang makes an open source
robot dog aimed Minipupper,
that's roughly the size of a
shoebox, and runs the robot
operating system. What I think
is so cool about Minipupper is
that it seems well positioned to
lower the barrier of entry for a
good robotics education. I think
this is true for two reasons.
Many poppers inexpensive, yet
quite capable, so you can do and
learn interesting robotics
things with it. And many popper
has a community around it, both
with the robot operating system
for software, and as an open
source hardware platform with a
good number of users. This
community is important so that
people can turn online for help
rather than requiring an in
house expert. I'm Audrow Nash.
This is the Sense Think Act
Podcast. Thank you to our
founding sponsor Open Robotics.
If you enjoy this episode,
please consider subscribing. And
now here's my conversation with
Afreez. I have friends,
would you introduce yourself?
Afreez Gan: Hi, Audrow. Sure.
I'm Afreez. I'm the founder and
Product Manager of MangDang
company.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. And what do
you guys make at MangDang?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, MangDang. When
you set up a company, you have
to give a name. Finally, I left
my hometown. MangDang is my home
town.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. That's a
nice name. And you make the
Minipupper? Would you tell me a
bit about the Minipupper?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, Minipupper is
is a ROS, OpenCV, robot dog
platform meant for education.
actually come from Stanford, the
Pupper project. Another very
awesome. Open Source project.
Yeah.
Audrow Nash: And what does the
Minipupper look like? I think
you have one there, but just for
our listeners.
Afreez Gan: Yeah. This is the
Minipupper. It have LCD display.
Audrow Nash: Yep. So it's, uh,
oh, go ahead. Yeah, I can
describe it if you like, from
how I think it looks. It's it's
kind of like a little Spot from
Boston Dynamics. Like a little
quadruped, robot dog. It has. Oh,
yeah, go ahead.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, you know, you
maybe I think most of the guys
are already see the demo from
Boston Dynamics spotted me. And
as you know, most of the guys
that want to own their own robot
that was to explore. Definitely.
But you know, you notice that
the pricing is so high and it is
hard to to accept it. So. So we
wanted to make a similar meaning
robot everywhere. All right.
Exactly.
Audrow Nash: Yes. And then one
thing that's very different
between the Boston Dynamics one,
and Minipupper is Minipupper
is very small. It's like, how
long is the body? Maybe it's 30
centimeters or a foot long. And
it stands out maybe? Ah, okay,
so eight inches long and it
probably stands What 10
centimeters high, or 15
centimeters high. Okay. 1515 six
inches high. So it's really cute
and then has the LCD or the
display on its front. So you can
have eyes and this kind of
thing. Oh, yeah.
Afreez Gan: We can also add
later and camera sensor to
those.
Audrow Nash: Yes. And then so
how did Minipupper come out of
the Standford Pupper? How What's
the origin of Minipupper?
Afreez Gan: Okay, is a story
beginning 20th 20th At first I
was only a fan Oh was Stanford a
pupper project and sometimes I
will answer some a normal
question. He is a group for
other guys. Other new guys. And
then we made made a good friend
of his amazing car. As the
project owner, and they has
Stanford a paper vendor, we ship
to many staff for the keys
worldwide, and have just started
global to head with sample
paper, we've got a ton of
feedback from as the customers,
what do our customers want in
their products? And What Kind Of
Products Do They like? We learn
that a lot of our crew lessons
and how to make a robot after
more than one years, we will
release the manufacturer
product. Yeah, actually, and
help that brought us to the side
by staff for the PEPFAR and the
Enlightened collaboration with
anything out so really no
creator of a snapper Pupper.
Audrow Nash: How is it
different? How so Minipupper is
a little smaller than the
Standford Pupper? Right, Mike? Is
there any other differences? So
the maybe the Standford Pupper is
I don't know it stands a foot
high or something like this or
30 centimeter side
Afreez Gan: is it bigger than
that? Yeah, about all this
searching certified I remember
35 or
Audrow Nash: 35 Okay, 14 inches
I something like this, okay. So,
how else is the Minipupper
different than the Stanford
popper you made it so that it
could be better manufactured or?
Yeah.
Afreez Gan: Actually, as I said
before, we delivered many
several hangers Stanford a
Pupper device and it got a
market cap and we know actually,
we find Sen staff at a Pupper
project he is awesome project
manager they are also some
problem. So we want to fix them
for what kind of problems Yeah.
For example, about assemble or
somebody we actually optimize
something or some point for
example, way more we're waiting
here. So please yeah, to make it
a more easier to assemble and
remove eliminate something
wrong. This is the assemble and
about as a calibration staffer
Pupper are really no project we
should use a command line tool
calibration. Yeah, in Nicaragua,
we emplacement CUI tool and the
user can use it very convenient.
And just not the same point is
we make a smaller much smaller
to make it a more safe security,
you know, when you're debugging
a robot, sometimes enemy the out
of control exists of performance
is so powerful, it may be a
security risk. So, we make a
huge especially for the children
Yeah, for sure we make it much
smaller. And it is said even for
children and adolescents
software to your point that is a
sample pack for our project is
based around leanings we it is
good for for programmer at the
end of February we Haussler the
software you know we supply is
open source for
the last SLAM navigation and
the Open City functions people
can use data to do a much more
use case and they the document
way especially opposed actually
when when they think How are
released Standford Pupper project
I began I began to follow this
piece of project and by all
those components the firm's USA
and studied as a project at
first. The source code is now
stables document that is not
very well but now it is okay.
But actually I remember I used
it on last two months tools to
rise, staffer the Minipupper project.
So I think if we're, if we want
to release a project, we hope
our user can use it very easily
and very quickly. For example,
when they do they have several
hours, they can assemble it and
enjoy it. So that way we supply
more document or user guide.
Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. That's
nice. I mean, if it has poor
documentation, and the source
code is tough to go through, it
can be such a bottle neck to
like actually getting anything
done with it or trying things on
it. And then the fun robotics
project can be very difficult.
So this sounds really nice if
you improve the documentation
and give it ROS interfaces and
things like this.
Afreez Gan: And saying they were
also held as pre immediate, pre
pre compile that I need. People
are fo user, customer don't want
to compile the source code for
several hours so they can
download the image. And the
flesh is that as the cat, okay.
Audrow Nash: So you can set it
up more easily. To have it all.
Wonderful. Yes. Let's see. So
I'd like to get into I would
love to talk about the software.
But I'd like to get a little bit
into the hardware of the mini
popper. And like what it has on
board. So how you first off, it
has a Raspberry Pi for the
computer, right? Yeah. Yeah, the
main controller is the Raspberry
Pi. Okay. Yes. And then
Afreez Gan: that's also based on
rest path.
Audrow Nash: Yes. Awesome. And
then then you probably what do
you have like a motor driver
board or something that the
Raspberry Pi controls? Or how
does it How does it work? And
then it's connected to servos?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, we actually we
cut some much. Cut them about
connected to earthbath.
Audrow Nash: Oh, good Arduino.
Is that Arduino? I can't quite
tell with the
Afreez Gan: Yeah, we connect all
the servers to our cutter MOBA.
Audrow Nash: Ah, or your custom
board? Oh, okay.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, this could be
the because this is
Audrow Nash: Yep, there's a
Raspberry Pi. Custom board. I
mean, yeah, just pop right in.
And that custom board has a
circle missing from it. And I
guess that's for some peripheral
or something that the Raspberry
Pi that has that sticks through
it. That's very cool. Yeah. So
then, you how many servos? Does
the minibuffer have? 12. Gotcha.
And so for each leg. What's so I
assume that it's three per leg?
Afreez Gan: Three steps.
Audrow Nash: You're so prepared
with all the different pieces
for explaining it. Love it.
Afreez Gan: Yeah. Okay.
Audrow Nash: So you have one. So
you have the, basically that
elbow of the leg, the shoulder
of the leg, which moves one
direction and the shoulder also
moves. Let's see. So you have
two degrees of freedom in the
shoulder. Yeah, you could have
done it. Very cool. And these so
they're servo motors. And you
custom built them right for this
for the mini bumper.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, yes. Actually,
we don't have to cut them a
hater, but we have to, because
at first the we buy all kinds of
ministers from the market, but
we don't, we don't find that
anyone can meet our requirement.
You know, if we, we, we we want
to design a mini size Dhokla dog
and we'd have to use mini mini
serve as small as possible. But
we pies on the shelf. Sir. We
cannot find anyone can meet our
requirements. You know, we can
sometimes times we assemble it
and arrive our robot several
minutes or several hours. So
we'll book break. Yeah. So we,
we, I last week where we spend,
I remember above the three
months to work with our factory
with our sub factory to cotton
was a syrup. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And you
made them? What was the major
challenge in making your own
one? Like, what? Why? Why
couldn't you use the existing
ones? They weren't small enough?
They weren't reliable enough.
You said they break frequently?
Is it just reliability?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, yes, it will.
If you want to make cameras if
you have enough party to add
them. Because if you want to
make a custom component, the
factory will ask your forecast
and your budget. Yeah, if you're
in a party, that there is no
problem. But actually, we have
not much value that at first. So
we have to reuse as many as
their components and also meet
our requirement.
Audrow Nash: So you're saying
the factory wanted to reuse its
existing tooling to make the
servos? Or do I understand,
right? So you can keep the price
down? Because it's already what
the factory has.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, but we, we
could work with cell factory and
replaced the motor inside, we
use the best motor and we can
can we adjust some parameters?
Control power inside is us. So
Mita
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Yeah. Yeah.
And the motors, their servo
motors, so there's no series
elastic components? You know
what I mean, with that there's
no spring in series with the
motor or anything? Or is there?
Afreez Gan: No. Agenda thought?
Or the inside is a third was a
very small motor. Yeah, yep.
Audrow Nash: Is there? Is there
a spring in the motor? Or do you
because you know how with some
of the legged robots, they'll do
series, elastic actuation they
have a spring in parallel or in
series with the motor. So it can
deform and deal with the heart
impact of the motor hitting the
ground or of the feet hitting
the ground
Afreez Gan: that way? Yeah. Are
you doing wait? Yeah, when we
run the robot, there will be
there will be very hot inside.
So, so we have to, we have to
find a solution. How to Win way.
So how to how to make it work
stable. And what
Audrow Nash: do you do? Are you
just downright solution to that?
Afreez Gan: Yeah. Actually, as a
sort of factory and as to learn
how to test and also just some
parameters about the control
board inside sir.
Audrow Nash: Okay, what kind of
parameters? What did they
adjust? So is it is it basically
how far the servo will try to
maintain an accurate position or
what, like how much effort it
will put into that I'm not
terribly knowledgeable about
servos and controlling them.
Afreez Gan: Yeah. Actually, I
don't remember very clear, I
think because they are about to
two centimeters, and one is way
just as parameters and another
solution is the way they think
it they replace that much better
motor inside and other
mechanical optimization.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Now, to
make it so you can handle the
heat and make it suitable for a
legged robot. Gotcha. So is, is
Minipupper is it basically, you
have the control board in the
middle and then you have a way
of communicating to the servos
and driving power through it.
But otherwise the legs the legs
are just the server was
connected. Basically in order,
there's no springs, there's no
soft components, there's this
kind of thing. And it works
because it's a small little
robot. Right? Or is that? Is
that a fair way to describe it?
Afreez Gan: Yes. You mean,
whether it is there any feedback
about a position feedback about
the chart feedback? I'm
Audrow Nash: sure there's
position feedback. I mean,
Afreez Gan: what is this for?
Now? What? Now? Is silver fair?
There are no any feedback. Wow,
it's all
Audrow Nash: open loop.
Afreez Gan: Yeah. But you will
know if we use we always
balances the price and as a
performance Yes. How also used
today by just with many with
many feedback, but a surprising
Yes. So hi. Oh,
Audrow Nash: so your servos
don't even have feedback really?
Yes. Now, what I thought I
thought servos were all closed
loop. But I guess if you
Afreez Gan: if you if so, now, I
mean, you have our country
control algorithm is the open
loop control, it is simple. But
it is also if you want to do
some deep play algorism it is it
is hard to because there is the
open loop is on extraversion we
are designing our next quarter
where we will analyze the
feedback but as I said before we
we have to balance the price and
performance
Audrow Nash: what is the mini
popper now Yeah,
Afreez Gan: about $500 for the
kid gotcha yeah don't put any
also is in our next reversion we
will add his position and
feedback with not much high
price almost the same price. We
find a simple way to get the
position and feedback.
Audrow Nash: Very cool. Okay,
when do you think that next
version will come out? As you
just had this current version, I
think
Afreez Gan: hey, this is kind of
our our next version and we hope
to we can release eight into
outline
Audrow Nash: wow so fast. Okay,
yeah, that's awesome. How do you
how do you get the robot to walk
do you use is there like an open
source robot legged locomotion
lab or is our open source open
source library that you can use
or did you write it from scratch
or how do you do your control
your legged locomotion control?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, this is
another story at first you were
at a frosted away our software
base roster for the Pupper
software we have we have to work
software, why is the base work
it is a similar stamp at the
Pupper paper okay and the other
version is loss worship. Again
the nose warfare we have to
implement the framework to
control the lag very common
framework for the wheel robot,
you know there there is a turtle
bot platform many guys Yeah, it
is a very common framework for
the wheel the project that
badger April, we if we want to
implement as a lag robot based
on Joe's platform, we have to
design and implement has the
framework at first we I asked
several technical guys and it is
has almost I remember almost two
months, how to design it or how
to end Dementor How long do can
we implement as a laughter? We
are very lucky, we found there
are already a good project, you
could have another open source
project. Then Kemper lead by
Biogen, who is located in
Singapore. We are now we are
very good friends now. And
during our project we he also
give us a much have. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Wonderful. So, you
found an open source solution
you were able to use with ROS
and that gets you most of the
way did you have to extend it or
did you put code back into the
original to improve it? Or do
you just use it as is
Afreez Gan: actually way way it
is not only just the integrated
way which we are based his
project that by the way are also
double confirm with you and
discuss with you and how to use
data. Much better. And you
Pupper? Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, you optimize
it from there. So it works
really well. Yeah. Awesome.
Okay, how did you? How did you
optimize it for Minipupper?
Like I've seen some things where
they would have they for you
know, the robot soccer
tournaments and they'd have a
little now robot go and try to
kick the ball. I would they were
trying to make them the now
robots really fast. I think it
was now actually, maybe I may be
wrong. I think it's not an hour
robot. I think it's some other
humanoid robot. But what they
did is they would set them up
and have them race back and
forth with different parameter
sets. To try to find the fastest
parameters. How did you? How did
you get it prepared for mini
popper? Did you do something
similar? Where you're racing
back and forth? Or how did you
find what works really? Well?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, our target
mini perpetuity is for the
education, but not for the race
competition. So we have to make
it as simple as possible to make
other guys to study or catamaran
if we have a freezer robot,
because it is a very small robot
dog and component, the surf is
is a low cost result is the
performance is okay for me
Pupper patter. Eight is a view
want to write very quickly.
Maybe it will not as stable.
Maybe. Yeah. All over. Yeah.
Yeah. But if it didn't write up,
I don't have enough. You cannot
use the leader ADCs encoder for
later to do your system and
navigation because it is another
stable and Amanda,
Audrow Nash: it's shifting
shifting. Yeah. keeps breaking
its map
Afreez Gan: to build as a map.
Yeah. Yes, because
Audrow Nash: you use the planar
LIDAR. Right? On many bumper. So
it's the LIDAR that shoots
straight out. And so if you have
the plane going out, and it's
tipping, tipping tipping, and
you're trying to use that as
your map, that would be really
difficult, I imagine to build a
world map.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, well, you
could imagine and make a that
around more stable, stable,
they're able to do
Audrow Nash: so stability was
kind of the big thing you
optimized for when trying to
make Minipupper walk, not like
speed or anything because you're
interested in it for education.
And that means like, can you
learn with this as a platform?
Yeah. Yeah. And so then you can
try learning about Lidar and
whatever other sensors, your
cameras. Okay, yeah. Tell me a
bit more. So, is this robot
already being used in education
and where and how is it being
used in the curriculum?
Afreez Gan: Humans education,
right. Yes. Yeah, yeah. deoria
we deliver as Stanford a Pupper
our units, we, we found many.
Some of the user come from the
university, most of the
university. Yeah. Even some PhD
students. Yeah. And they, yeah,
they hope they they can they
looking forward acceptable a
robot have a platform to test
their algorithm, maybe as video
algorithm or other AI algorithm.
So wait, you have the with. And
now, as I know, some, some
universities are trying to, to
use me Pupper for their lessons.
And we are also discussing with
how to improve MiniPro. And what
they are looking for. Yeah, I
think it is a long, long journey
to improve the education
platform. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: So it's mostly
targeting universities, not like
high schools or middle schools
or anything like this.
Afreez Gan: Yeah. Actually, at
current our, our level now, the
most students come from the
university, but they are also
some come from the middle
school, high school. Okay, if
we,
Audrow Nash: yes, just starting?
Yeah.
Afreez Gan: Because it's not
easy.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Yes, for
sure. Especially I imagine going
from university like starting
with grad students, and then
going towards maybe undergrads
and you teach them during your
education. And then like, the
further the lower and age you
go, are there like the lower and
education level? I imagine the
harder it is because you need to
develop a more structured
curriculum, I would imagine.
Yeah. Like, with the PhD
students, you say, here's some
documentation on how it works.
And they go off and do things.
And then with the with the
undergrads are doing their
coursework? I imagine you still
have to put together a little
bit of a curriculum or work with
professors or technicians at the
university to put together a
curriculum. Have you done much
of that, where you're putting
together a curriculum around
Minipupper and the kinds of
things that can do?
Afreez Gan: Yeah. Now, we are,
we are just supplying the proper
answers there. based platform.
You know, your university
students have the technical
background. And we only can
supply the the general user
guide and the time period. And
if they have some problem, we
can they can say No, for me, I
Audrow Nash: come to you.
Afreez Gan: Yeah. So we kind of
suppose that. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Any plans
in the future to possibly help
with the curriculum design
around the Minipupper? Or is it
kind of your documentation is in
a sense, the well it is the
documentation you're planning on
using or not? Not necessarily
attaching a course to it?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, actually, we
were planning how to make a
detailed document or user guide,
where we hope to make a a real
education platform, not only for
the university is to say that we
can also hope we'll also have
the middle school high school
students to learn understanding.
We can make a detailed document
for all level users.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Have you
started that? Or is it it's a
future efforts?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, we are. Where
are you in? Yeah, we have online
online document that we will add
as a additional part, standby
snap. Yeah, we hope we can.
Finish is a document we see as
three or five months.
Audrow Nash: Ah, very exciting.
And then maybe you'll see more
universities using it and it
will grow from there. That'd be
very cool to have a very nice,
inexpensive legged robot like
how cool I mean In my robotics
education I was using lucky to
have the thing, but like little
tiny robots that had a lidar on
top and didn't navigation, and
legged robots are just so much.
There I am. I'm so much more
interested in legged robots than
wheeled robots. And so it's
really cool if that can be in
the education program. Yeah. How
do you how do you work to make
really good documentation?
Because I think a lot of like,
many of the robots I've used
that have come from factories,
have had pretty terrible
documentation. How do you try to
make good documentation any, any
ideas on what you can do to make
it as good as possible? Or?
Afreez Gan: Yeah. And of course,
we have many improvements of the
document. And of course, the we
made our first version document,
and user will give you many,
many feedback. And the user can
maybe make their own User Guide.
For example, when it is the many
hundreds of a device to Japan
marking and sun. Japan makers
that make their own token are
very detailed a document, so I
Audrow Nash: will put it back
in.
Afreez Gan: Yeah. So we actually
a lot of money is not only come
from us, but also come from all
the guys, all the customers, we
are cool, and contributing to
the Terminator data, and making
it more and more better.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Very cool.
And so you mentioned a little
bit, you can put a lidar on top
of the menu upper. I think you
can also put a what is it? Is it
an oak D? 3d camera?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, open CV? 3d
camera module? Yeah, yeah. So
yeah, ideas. Lead by branding,
branding team. Branding is open
CVA, a key architect, architect.
And, yeah, he's also the CEO of
Orlok. Sonics company, located
the AAMC. Okay.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So, you put
these sensors on, and these are
so that people who are
interested in playing around
with it. So whether it be
students or I can even see
hobbyists being very interested
in playing with mining like I,
for example, I'm interested in
playing with one of the many
buffers, but so you can put the
sensors on it. And with the
camera and the LiDAR, you can
build a map. And you can do a
lot of different robotics
things. Because you can have the
robot map its space and move
around in the space and do some
understanding of the scene or
the environment. That's kind of
the intention with those to
enable it so people can use
them, or, yeah, it's quite cool.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, you're right,
we've put later this place and
we can put his camera at this
place. Yeah, we
Audrow Nash: do that later kind
of sits on the back. And the
camera sits a bit further
forward, kind of on top of the
body.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, we also, we
also supplies a user guide for
the leader. And as a 3d camera
module, you also can look at our
guide, and now is only the basic
guide. And user can use our
guided tool, Ryan as the sensor.
But if a user wants to implement
that some use case, they have to
study and implemented their use
case
Audrow Nash: themselves. Gotcha.
And so this is and it's running
the robot operating system or
ROS is it running ROS 1 or
ROS 2?
Afreez Gan: I just one
Audrow Nash: plus one. How did
so see? How did you decide to
Well, for us one was the
Stanford upper running was the
Stanford PACCAR running ROS 1
are you brought over ROS 1
for this and implemented or
found that one package that
worked really well? For the Lego
Afreez Gan: auction? Yeah, we've
built a real city environment.
That's our Pupper. Only is the
product leanings. Meaning so
ask.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so this was
you were saying you found that
one repository online that did a
lot of the legged locomotion for
you the control of the legs for
walking? And that was ROS 1
And then you've kind of Gotcha.
Do you have any plans on moving
to ROS to? Or is is ROS 1
the good one for now?
Afreez Gan: It was Ryan's work
very well now. But till we we
are also discussing on several
time how to update the tour ROS
to version. And we hope I think
I didn't need a lot of work to
update updated. Yeah, and I
think we have still not very
clear plan to update two rows
for but we also, we also hope to
update. Maybe I hope we can
update the two rows to people
the end of this year. Yeah, we
can update this version in about
and I want that robot.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it seems like
a lot of companies are kind of
feeling this pain of
transitioning from ROS, one to
ROS to
Afreez Gan: Yeah.
Audrow Nash: There is something
if you use the Python client
library for ROS. One, there's a
thing that it's underscore ROS
py. And you can import it and it
just uses ROS to but it keeps
all the same ROS 1
interfaces. I thought that was
quite cool. Okay, I don't know
if that would ease the
transition. But there I don't
think there's a c plus, like, I
don't think there's a C Plus
Plus client library analog to
that at the moment. But it's a
cool idea to just switch it out.
So you can use it. And then you
can gradually replace things. As
you go from their
Afreez Gan: way I try our best
to move forward step by step.
But yeah.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Let's see.
So when a user orders one of
these mini poppers, it's a kit
and they have to assemble it
themselves. Is that correct?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, we we supply
several, several stos. One is
the basic Acade. You know, you
know, some, some some makers,
they already have their resume
bought, they don't want buy
additional box. So they only
want some some components. So
with supplies, the basic Okay,
and not include them. And then
some, I said I, I hope to buy
all the components, and I can
assemble it easily. Yeah,
sometimes. I hope by is a pre
assembled unit. And after I get
it, I can see jointer right now.
So actually, yeah, we supply
three eSkills.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. That's
cool. And the body of it is 3d
printed. Right. And the legs as
well or several of the
components are 3d printed.
Right?
Afreez Gan: Yes, this is one of
the challenges for our, to our
product. Yeah. We are 3d
printed. You know, if you if you
only make a prototype, 3d
printed, there is no problem.
You can print it with several
hours or many hours. Yeah. If
you want to mass production, for
example, we I traveled to
shinjang. Our lender? I asked
them, I need several 1000 units.
3d printed, it is hard to find
is the vendor. Yeah. Wow.
Audrow Nash: So let's see. And
the trade off is that you can 3d
print and it's really good for
prototypes when you're doing
like one here and one there and
learning. But mass production if
you were gonna make 100,000 of
them, then you go and you get
the molds done. So you can like
cast the parts or something and
it's very efficient, but it's
very expensive upfront, right.
But so that and many popper is
kind of in the middle where your
volume is not incredibly large.
It's not like hundreds of 1000s
It's like 1000s Perhaps. And so
that's why you're thinking 3d
print?
Afreez Gan: Yes. You know, for
for some part? Well, yeah,
you'll see for some yellow
pattern, they actually, at first
that house components are 3d
printed. And then it is harder
for us to find the vendor who
can supply so many 3d printed 3d
printed parts. So some of the
some of the path we actually now
is load from both. And that
sounds really balanced. Let's
Audrow Nash: see. Yeah, the
cost. And the end of the day.
Gotcha. And the so maybe for the
next model that you think will
come out, you said like June or
July or something, I think that
one, are you moving more and
more towards molds for
everything? Like, grab, try to
reuse as many of the pieces as
you are already having molds
for? And then eventually have it
be more? Yeah. So
Afreez Gan: we, yeah, we'll
reuse some sums and both paths?
Yeah. Yes, we have. Maybe our
natural working is, you'll see,
we can we can remove this path,
rest path. This path? Yeah, we
can have a very good platform,
you can. So
Audrow Nash: if you remove kind
of a bump in the front, then you
can have a big flat space to put
sensors and whatever it is you
want. Yeah. Awesome. Let's see,
would you so we're touching on
it a little bit. Would you tell
me a bit about the manufacturing
process of this? And so you were
saying before we started
recording, you go down to
Shenzhen, and they work on like,
it's easy to prototype? And just
tell me a little bit about the
manufacturing down there?
Afreez Gan: That's yeah, you
know, yeah. First, we, it is not
easy. For the hardware. Hardware
device, especially and now was
now situation, you'll have to
you'll have to powerful supply,
supply chain capabilities.
Otherwise, you know, you're you
can talk as your opponent is a
good, but the coolest thing is,
actually I have several years of
hardware products. And I also
have some resource supply chain
resource, so we can get get our
components. Yeah. Yeah, we also,
you know, we use the rest, Pat.
And there is also very hard to
get the book.
Audrow Nash: I've heard Yeah.
Yeah.
Afreez Gan: But we are so lucky.
And we were I'm wondering and
thinking about how, after our
campaign, and we have to prepare
the production, the most
important commodity is Rat Pack.
Before we can buy merch by
either name, and price, after
end of our campaign, it is hard
to get get as much fat. But we
are so lucky. And we bet Westpac
to like our product. Wonderful.
Yeah, we are so lucky. And so I
connected with Sylvester talking
about we needed less hype for
our product. And so, actually,
we've got enough respite from
from ROS back come there. UK.
Yeah. Okay, so
Audrow Nash: it's so funny.
Yeah, the part shortages have
been really tough, especially
for hardware companies. And
especially like, I don't know, I
hear stories about companies
ripping out Raspberry Pi's from
other devices so that they can
use them. So like buy a $200
thing and then rip out the
Raspberry Pi, which was like $40
Before this whole supply
shortage. Gotcha. So it's really
nice that you have the ability
to keep getting Raspberry Pi's.
Let's see. And so
Afreez Gan: here's a theory As a
manufacturer, the leading time
is another risk because of
Audrow Nash: the waiting time,
so parts what is the leading
time
Afreez Gan: while the story is
at first we have to we have a
tool release also our device how
that came to our backers before
the end of last year during
during I poacher our effect, I
also look at our factory last
year and push that progress. But
you know, last year shinjang as
COVID COVID-19 situation is not
very good. And we already have
we have to delay a shipment. So
it is it is very hard to
control. Accurate deadline for
the shipping for
Audrow Nash: the whole world.
Yeah, especially. I mean, it
touches so many places in so
many industries, the raspberry
pies, I don't know where they're
made, but you said it's a UK
company. And then you have the
Schengen area. And then there's
the whole global pandemic
situation, there's parts and
materials that need to come
together. So yeah, I could
imagine that it would be very
difficult to predict the lead
tie for all the parts.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, yeah.
fracture, I really hope many
thanks for many guys for Okay,
well give our madhhab ROS, a
Mac Suissa. Team give us and the
hardware.
Audrow Nash: What's the what's
the process when you go down to
Shenzhen? And you have an idea
that you want to get made? How
does it work? You go to
different companies and or
different factories and you say
I want to make this and then
they work out what they can do?
Or how does it work? How does it
work to manufacture something?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, actually, it
is not a lot of hard work and
tissue work. Because if you know
you want to, for example, I was
cutting myself, I don't know
first. Just terrible kind of
work. But it is a to cannot work
best. So I just leave. I try to
leave a hotel very near that as
a satisfactory. I really, I went
to their factory, and it works
out and then push them.
Audrow Nash: Oh, wow. That's
crazy. Yeah. Yeah, I
Afreez Gan: said, we have to
find a better solution for the
better performance. At first it
is possible, but a real person
day and day. Finally, we found a
solution.
Audrow Nash: I've heard that a
number of times where like, the
CEO or CFO or whoever is
responsible for manufacturing
will go and just basically stay
with the factory and keep
pushing them to try to make
refinements and improve the
quality or get it to work in
some way. This kind of thing.
Afreez Gan: Yeah. You know, we
you know, we are a very small
startup company and before the
campaign layers. I was the only
guy the full time because other
guys I promise. And
Audrow Nash: how large are you
now?
Afreez Gan: Yeah. Now we have
several full time guys. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Several,
like five or several.
Afreez Gan: Right about Friday
for full time and several hours
that are part time.
Audrow Nash: Guys, gotcha.
Afreez Gan: We'll tell you about
10. Guys.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, about 10 guys
with full and part time I see.
Five Guys. Gotcha. Okay. Yeah,
that's it's, uh, you were the
only full time when? Before the
campaign and so the campaign.
That's a Kickstarter campaign
you're referring to, right?
Afreez Gan: Yeah. Yes. That
campaign is not have a funny,
interesting story. And I would
love to hear that. But let me
share your story. Here's our
last story. All right. Yeah, at
first, you know, back to 2010.
Here we are. The term for the
Pupper vendor, and a co worker
is anything how. And after we
release the Minipupper, a
Nathan Kao also told me Pupper
onto their staff at the Pupper
website. And I think maybe we
can seal or deliver Minipupper
just like snapper Pupper. They
put that information on their
website. It was a category one,
get a good visibility. Yeah,
they can send a mail and pay by
by paper or other online
payment. Yeah, so I have no, I
have no any crowdfunding
campaign knowledge before.
Before Ming Pupper, but some
day, nice. And Tao said, why not
try campaign? I said I have no
any background. Maybe it's
impossible or difficult for me.
So some days later, they say
send me a same method yet again.
And again. Why not try campaign?
I Sunday. Sunday I have was free
time. And two was was a media
campaign. I started to study how
to make work campaign. Yeah.
Yeah. So I'm not very clear. You
know, it's hard for me to make
it clear. And we I made a
decision to do a campaign. I
thought whatever the result,
issue shouldn't be very
interesting. Another another
increase in DNS for me. So it is
for sure. Yeah, if you decide to
campaign, you have to prepare
all kinds of lawyer all kinds of
lessons and prepare all kinds of
work. And I also double confirm
with some lenders or some
friends, ask them what how to do
the campaign. Some questions you
can get to the answer easily
about the campaign process, by
the some standard question is
not easy to find his answer.
Because if you want to do the
campaign, you have to prepare
the PR video, the Samza pictures
and the campaign pay design and
all kinds of work. So at first,
we discussed with several
vendors, how to do the PR video,
the if you have enough data, you
can do it and use it. And our
professional. Yeah, lots of
professional team connect you
and then they can do the QA
video. But yeah, the budget is,
for example. 20k dollars. Yeah,
but but not, but at that time at
the different code for me to
decide. Because it's a big
investment decide Yeah,
Audrow Nash: especially if it's
just you, for sure.
Afreez Gan: And the last we I
asked the my friends brain team
to take us to record a video.
But the unities is before before
one week before the campaign.
The guy who happened to make his
PR video heard his hand and he
cannot edit his video.
Audrow Nash: Oh, no way.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, we haven't
prepared the voice because we
have to prepare the video and
the voice. I lost that. Yeah, I
lost. I finished as laughter
snap finals. Voice and
integrators combines video and
audio. Yeah. Gotcha. Yeah. So a
lot although the final PR video
is not so professional, but it
can work it's quite another
Yeah, another another very
interesting is you know if
you're a If you want to make a
successful Kickstarter campaign
you will have to God's
Kickstarter campaign official
platform project we love label.
Ah, yeah, yeah. Yeah. But even
but, you know, we I have no any
other. No any I know how about
the campaign? The question for
me is how to get the project
will have a label? I asked. I
asked another guy hired me to do
the campaign. At first before,
even before was one week before
the campaign I asked him when we
can't get as a project, we love
labor. He said, If your project
is good enough, you will get it.
Yeah. But this is a Das? Is that
the answer I want to get? So I
asked him Well, time and time
and time again. And it is harder
to have data that you like to
answer. But I'm not alike. We
can just retweeting the labor so
I'll try to find the picture
campaign contact window and I
want to African chrome with the
official contact window. So I
the last time that I found
contact window hazard here she
is Heather and I was at design
tech category our pigs trap. And
here's the icing I sent her a
male introduced our programming
power project and how to book a
video conference. I remember one
Saturday afternoon so before the
surprise happens our video
meeting is before the meet here
before the video meet him ice
and we already may we already
made campaign paid but it is
very rough. Very proper. The
video is not to the fixed
version. Some pictures are not
the fixed version looks not
good. And is
Audrow Nash: not very
professional. Yeah. The page
Afreez Gan: actually looks bad.
Okay, but But before before the
meeting with hedsor Western is a
meeting are we saying is
appealing to her and introduce
our more information our me
Pupper our immediate
information. Our video is a
Sunday afternoon. And we are
surprised and added that just
the pneumonia we find our
project already has already give
our valuable project we love the
labor. Very surprised. Yeah.
Yeah.
Audrow Nash: That was so nice.
Very happy. Yeah, I would
imagine.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, very happy.
And the other week as a laborer.
I asked the guy who had who
support me to do the campaign.
Yeah, I we already finished our
target that before the campaign
was our next target.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Yeah. So
interesting. That's crazy. Yeah,
it was a very successful
campaigns. Congratulations. Oh,
yeah. Yeah,
Afreez Gan: thank you. Thank
you. Another Yeah. Another
interesting is open CV open time
away. Branding team will also do
their Kickstarter campaign added
at a time away away, almost to
the campaign at the same time.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Ah,
Afreez Gan: you could see his
brand name is Ken Scott is also
your
Audrow Nash: local robotics.
Yeah. See, see
Afreez Gan: traducida brand new
to me to link the US together.
And wonderful. We are very close
to here wonderful. crew
together, more and more deeply
and granted him are now have
already failed at their Docker
Hub. Yeah, they have a we'll use
our mean Pupper. And we will run
it together. Yeah. More in the
pipeline.
Audrow Nash: That'd be great.
What do you think? So you'll
work together? I guess where?
Where do you see many pupper?
Going? So you already mentioned
that there's another version
coming out? And you're putting
together the documentation?
Where do you kind of see it
going? Maybe two to five years
from now?
Afreez Gan: Yeah. In my dream,
we hope or we have a tool or
product line. Why is education
we really hope to release Good,
good, local data platform for
education. They're everywhere.
Not only universities, but also
middle school, high school
students and other any guys who
like as Loboda they can study
and enjoy as your product
product. And another product
line is the home robot. We hope
Yeah, we hope or we can release
useful and valuable and
acceptable home robot, home
robot we lag from global dark,
consumer, consumer double dark,
but you know, it is alien not do
that. Because we have to we have
to move forward carefully step
by step.
Audrow Nash: What do you mean?
What? What are some of the
obstacles that you must figure
out to move forward? For the
consumer robot dog?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, for the
consumer of our dog, we have to
make it as a product. As simple
as possible. You know, if you
have some technical background,
we can we can discuss how to
calibration. But if for the
normal for the consumer product
that you you don't you cannot
say you cannot teach your
customers to calibrate
Audrow Nash: it. So it has to
have like one button like a
Roomba and then turn on and do
things and also has to be cheap
to
Afreez Gan: hear. Yeah, the
price is gonna be very cheap.
And as the function to the
various stable. Yeah, yes. We
hope we are trying our best
maybe because the end of this
year, maybe we can release our
consumer local Target prototype.
Maybe later this year, early
next year.
What do you think? Oh, go ahead.
Yeah, we have the study was that
year? Yeah. That a
the real requirements from the
customers, you know, during our
staff are probably released
about 580. device. And mini
paper with we already released
about 2k. Wow, this wonderful
device. Yeah. And our next
version I next. I mean, I named
the mini Piper v2, we hope to
really say that the two outlier.
And I hope we can release a
final sound in the outtakes of
the device. If you are released.
The more device the already is,
the more feedback you can get.
Yeah, if you're not to the more
feedback, you can make it up
better and better. Definitely,
Someday, you'll find a consumer
solution.
Audrow Nash: Yes, it seems like
the Minipupper and Minipupper
v2. It's a smart way to one get
feedback as you're saying and to
grow the number of units that
you're making, because the
consumer one will probably be
fairly similar. And you can
refine the control algorithms
and you can refine everything
else about it. So it's a nice
way to go from a small market
that lets you keep growing to a
much bigger market to grow a lot
more, I think sounds like a good
plan
Afreez Gan: to make that fit.
Yeah, because such a very cool
Actually we Yeah, because we
actually we have we have not
much a Makita. To to try. We
have to areas them very
carefully. Yep.
Audrow Nash: I see, yes, it's a
very much taking what you have
getting a little more
reinvesting it back into your
company grow a little bit
bigger, and do the same thing,
grow, grow, grow, grow, until
eventually you can be a big
company. Ah, I hope to look back
in the future and see you guys
be enormous. And very successful
company. So with the consumer
robot dog that you're imagining,
what will it do? So is it is it
just gonna walk around? Is there
the the human interaction part
seems really difficult for that,
but what's going to be kind of
the thing that people buy it
for?
Afreez Gan: Ya got to dot your
point? Yeah. I was asked by many
guys the same question. Yeah,
yes. In my opinion, in my
opinion, it is. I think no one
can give a very clear answer.
For example, if that answer is
very clear. I think,
Audrow Nash: oh, everyone else
has already done.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, I think a
marketer is very clear. And as a
product feature is very clear.
We have no opportunity for the
startup company, the big company
will. But for me, I believe you
can make it after three or five
years later. I think those are
the home home robot market that
will come. I believe it doesn't
matter what kind of a home robot
looks like. I believe he should
be as a lateral robot, but not
the wheel robot. So so so if the
if it is the leg robot, we can
we can immediately add a four
leg or two leg for now, maybe?
Finally. I think AI is used for
leg because it is more like two
animals. Yes. So yeah, I believe
was the maintenance. So we, we
moved with their target stamp I
stamp. But I did that first.
Maybe in the end of this year or
early next year, our first home
robot prototype, or maybe you
can think that it is a mobile
smart speaker on mobile. Yeah.
Yep.
Audrow Nash: Kind of like Amazon
is doing and a lot of these
other companies. Gotcha. Yeah,
and legs. I mean, like carpet is
not a problem if you have to
like step up onto the carpet or
stairs or anything. Like if you
have a legged robot, there's a
lot of advantages for getting
around the home. Especially if
it's a consumer products, like
you buy a Roomba. And it can't
go in the like little dip in the
living room or something like
this that has a stair to editor,
whatever it might be. So legs
clearly have those advantages.
Four versus two is an
interesting discussion for is a
lot easier, I think as a
roboticist because you can be
passively stable at anytime
because you can have three
points of contact or this kind
of thing. Yeah.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, you'll think
maybe five or 10 years later, a
few days. Home robot with four
leg you may be feel very good.
It is like animals, but maybe
you will find as they are two
leg like a human in your home.
Maybe it is not feel better.
Audrow Nash: It's like a little
human. Yeah, it's a little
stressful. I could see that. I
wonder I mean, birds birds have
two legs, also. So like chickens
and things like this. And we're
not terribly intimidated by
them. But I think a chicken
shaped robot would be very
funny. Like it's not a design
that I see. I think ever but
yeah, I see what you mean. And
then also easier to manufacture
probably point like feet are
really hard as far as I
understand for you like buy big
needle robots? Because like, a
lot easier with like sore
points, like you're doing with
Minipupper?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, the most of
the most time consuming data
users use lag. Yeah. Here, yeah,
we have a tool. Now what I need,
I still need about three hours
to assemble it, and additional
half an hour to calibration it.
And our next version all my
Takita is Katherine was, you
know, I need more than three
hours to assemble it.
Audrow Nash: And you've done a
lot of that's yeah.
Afreez Gan: But other customers
maybe need more time to assemble
and enjoined? Yeah, one extra
version? I hope the assemble. We
can assemble it within one hour.
And don't need to any more
calibration. Any maybe the auto
calibration?
Audrow Nash: That would be nice.
Yeah. Yeah. Let's see. Bigger
Picture. I'd love to so
segwaying a little bit. I would
love to hear your because I
mean, I'm in the United States.
I would love to hear your
impression of kind of the
robotics industry in China. And
the manufacturing is very
interesting. So like, I don't
know, how do you how do you
think of it?
Afreez Gan: You me as a robot I
manufacture?
Audrow Nash: Yes. In the
Schengen area, and then around
China? Just yeah. I don't know
how, like for the whole robotics
field, how how do we how can we
think of Shin Jen? And? I don't
know.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, I think,
shouldn't they, the supply chain
is a huge one for us in general.
And you can find all kinds of
vendors. And they can't give you
some solution. But if you want
to do some innovation, you have
to you have to design the
Pycelle you can find all kinds
of solutions. The common
solution, it is easy to find a
common solution in ancient in
Makeda, and a winner. But if you
want to make some innovation
product, or you have to design
it myself.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Gotcha. And
so if you do design it, oh, go
ahead.
Afreez Gan: I mean, if you
review, product, manufacture a
common hardware device, it is
very easy. Because it certainly
is a very convenient.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So if you
say you do come up with
something new like you with your
servo motors that are a little
different than what's been done
or maybe I don't know anything
else that's new. How does it
work? To get a factory in
Shenzhen? Making it like do you
have to work with them a lot? Do
you kind of give them what you
need? And they'll figure it out?
Or how does it work? Yeah.
Afreez Gan: Yes, about you can
also find many vendors initially
market and during a tutorial
deliver staff at a Pupper, I
already know some sub so
vendors. So we asked them one by
one and compare their service
and as a technology background,
and their selectors. The better
battle rounds and then to
discuss to to give give them our
detailed requirement and discuss
our solution discusses the
solutions maybe, you know, as
the forecast. Now the fourth
category is to not match and
you'll need I didn't not a very
easy to to push them to some
ketema Yep.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Unless
you're making I don't know a
million of them or some crazy
number. That it's really worth
it for them to customize. This
kind of thing. Yes, yeah.
Afreez Gan: Yeah, yeah, I want
an extra wash. I will resist
that serves, because, you know,
if you're wanting to do some
innovation or some big change,
to make it simple, you will have
to redesign some, some key
components.
Audrow Nash: Yep. Gotcha. How,
how is the I mean, this kind of
two questions. How are you guys
funded? And how is the investor
climate in China to you?
Afreez Gan: Okay, so the first
question is, how to get the data
right?
Audrow Nash: For you, so are you
are you bootstrapping Are you
putting your own money in and
are you accepting investment
from people from? Are you
locally funded? Does the
government help with your
funding? Or I'm just wondering
how the funding so far so are
you guys
Afreez Gan: different? i Let's
go back to Stanford as a
Stanford a paracord project. And
at first saw it I used my own
money to buy all the components
about Africa and and they enjoy
it and Alaska, i becomes the
vendor of the temple Pupper and
the bigger because after we said
rotis castle with Nathan Kao by
mail or videoconference, Nathan
asked me whether it is possible
to supply as a kid from China
marketer because China supply
chain is convenient and as the
price is, is lower. So I look
around and all the components
from the Kenya market and
deliver a stamp or the Pupper
with with low price. But
frankly, speaking of the day,
the some profit after deliver
several hundreds of staff for
the Pupper project we got we got
some profit. And I use a profit
to developer Minipupper. So
yeah, so when the Pupper
campaign after the campaign, we
got much more funding. And then
we use that money to developer
our next version. So Ron and Rob
Yep. Actually, now or now. Now
it is. I I didn't actually i not
i did not use the notch in my
own money.
Audrow Nash: In the latest mini
popper? Yeah, yeah. Nice. That's
great. Let's see. And then, um,
do you think going forward? Will
you take investor money or try
to bootstrap the whole time and
keep becoming?
Afreez Gan: Yes. We have as a
plan to get investment maybe
later this year. And we are so
lucky. And we actually now we
already got to the incubator
wacky incubator program approval
in Hong Kong. Congrats. Yeah,
they will. Yeah. They will give
us some support and not only
offers some funding, but also,
you know, in Hong Kong. The VC
environment is very, very
convenient. Yeah. Yeah, well, we
can. Yeah, well, I hope we can
get our first round an investor
later this year, and then we can
use the fun to to look more.
More technical guys, and
accelerator our, our rd and
marketing.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Yeah. Let's
see. So beginning to wrap up.
What do you think? What do you
think robotics will look like?
Going forward? So the next like
two to five years. Where do you
think we'll be in robotics?
Afreez Gan: Yeah, I'm very
positive. Go to the robotics
market. And you know, now,
vision technology, speak as a
voice or re as maker Ria, voice
technology. There are many, many
solutions. And I think that we
are already ready. The only need
the only thing we need to do is
how to combine all kinds of all
kinds of functions or
technologies into a total
product require the product, and
they release it to the customer
with acceptable price, and
variable use aka. And I think
I'm very positive, but I think
maybe within five years, three
or five years later, I think
most people will see more and
more robot products. And I also
believe, within three years we
we can release as home robot top
consumer product will be sold in
no time, but some company will
release it. Okay. Well,
Audrow Nash: I hope it's you
guys. Fingers crossed for it.
Yeah, let's see. So we're
wrapping up. Is there any links
or contact info or anything
you'd like to share with our
watchers and listeners? Yeah.
All right.
Afreez Gan: Also, talk a minute
and a resource of Amitabha is
your company data on our GitHub?
Link? I think you can get all
the all the things on our
GitHub.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. All right.
Very good. Thank you. Nice
speaking with you. Yeah.
Afreez Gan: Thank you so much.
Yes. Thank you so much. That is
amazing. Hi, everyone. Okay. Hi.
Audrow Nash: Thanks for
listening to this conversation
with our friends. Thank you
again to our founding sponsor
open robotics. If you enjoy this
interview, please consider
subscribing. See you next time.