Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Dayo McIntosh,
who is the CEO and founder of
Yateou. Yateou is an early stage
startup that makes wellness
products and has a customer
facing robot ADE, that
personalizes customer orders.
One thing that I found cool
about Yateou is that they put it
on a truck that's kind of like a
big food truck that has a big
window so that customers can see
it working to make a customized
order. It's an interesting way
to draw people in so that Yateou
can start a conversation with
them about wellness, which is
where Diana's interest in the
idea started. I enjoyed talking
to Dayo to hear about her
experience with Yateou. Her
background is in robotics. So
it's interesting to hear about
how she came to using her robot
arm ADE, as well as hearing
about the challenges she's
encountered to get to where she
is, such as having her truck
with the robot stolen. And it's
also interesting to hear about
the clever things that she's
doing to manage the complexity
in her growing new business. I'm
Audrow Nash. This is the sense
think act podcast. Thank you to
our founding sponsor open
robotics. If you enjoy this
interview, please consider
subscribing. And now here's my
interview with Dayo. Hi, Dayo,
would you introduce yourself?
Dayo McIntosh: Hi, Audrow My
name is Dayo G. McIntosh,
and I'm the founder and CEO of
Yeto.
Audrow Nash: Would you tell me
about Yateou?
Dayo McIntosh: Yes, yeah, so is
this sustainable clean beauty
and wellness brand. We create
products that are all natural
vegan, cruelty free and
ethically sourced. And the
unique thing about what we do is
that we've incorporated robotics
to bring that technology front
and center to the beauty and
wellness industries.
Audrow Nash: And how do you use
robots?
Dayo McIntosh: So right now we
have our essential oil
mixologist robot called ADE.
ADE is the first consumer
facing robot for the beauty and
wellness industries. And
currently we have ADE stationed
in a moving truck, making it
mobile so we take Addie to
different events, markets and
things like that. And people can
interact and interface directly
with ADE to create customized
and personalized personal care
and wellness products. Gotcha.
What,
Audrow Nash: what does it look
like?
Dayo McIntosh: Addie is a Kuka
robot. It is about two feet
tall. And it's a manipulator.
It's an arm. It's a robotic arm.
And again, it sits in a truck
with a transparent glass that
people can see. See and watch
ADE in action.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So you said
Abby, Eddie's the next
mixologist. What does that mean?
What does that actually doing?
Dayo McIntosh: So similar to a
bartender, right? We have ADE
going to different dispensing
vats to create products, again,
tailored to each individual
person's like personal care and
wellness goals. And once. So for
example, we have an interface
and someone like you would go up
to the interface, for example, a
screen a tablet, and say, hey, I
want to mix this ingredient with
this ingredient. And I want it
to smell like this. And that
would kick it into gear. And
that's how we create
personalized products.
Audrow Nash: Super cool. So for
this, is there any like? So if I
say my skin is super dry, and I
want it to smell like oranges,
or something like this? Does it?
Does Addie come up with a recipe
or dive to say I want to this
much I don't know, shea butter
in it or this much whatever. How
does that work? Is it
recommended based on goals? Or
is it like I know the
ingredients.
Dayo McIntosh: So the full
picture, the full rein skill of
this is to have give consumers
the options to customize and mix
and match however they want. But
rolling out we're going to start
out with pre made orders that
people can adjust. So it's more
of an adjustment than a full
blown customization feature.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Oh, gotcha.
And how does so for ADE to do
its mixologist work? How does
Addie actually go to the
dispensers or other dispensers
robotic to does that he push
into something and it comes out
like a soap container or how
does it work?
Dayo McIntosh: So the dispensers
are not robotic. So they are
actually wine bottles that we've
added dispenser or would you
call it droppers to them sort of
thing. And the idea behind that
is that we wanted to eliminate
as much or I wanted to eliminate
as many possible holdups by
limiting the number of
automations or automated pieces
we had in this operations. So
ADE is the only robotic
automated piece in this whole
setup, and it goes to each
bottle depending on what you
select and pushes up on the
dispensing nozzle, that's what I
was looking for pushes up on the
nozzle, and that releases a set
amount of liquid ingredients for
the product.
Audrow Nash: So it's kind of
like one of those soap
dispensers and restrooms where
you you push the thing and a
little bit comes out
Dayo McIntosh: exactly, it's
exactly like that, or something
you'd see at a bar, for example,
I don't know if you've seen
those. Those dispenser actually,
I think they have them now at
home, like you have those mobile
bars that you can install in
your kitchen. And they all have
like nozzles that you attach to
the bottom of, of Yeah, like a
cocktail bottle or liquor
bottle, and then you just push
up on that, and then you get
what you want.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And then
how do you how do you control
Addie? For this? So does it does
that he know the position of all
of the different ones. And you
can say option one, option two
option, it will go push option
one, option two, option three.
Dayo McIntosh: That's exactly
how it's set up. Yes. And
currently it is not fully
automated. And that's what I'm
working towards. So for the time
being, we use the Teach pendant,
what we call a teach pendant.
It's sort of like a controller.
So think of like a game, a game
controller, for example that you
use to with your console. So
instead of that, like we have
this teach pendant, and I can
call out the different positions
that I want ADE to visit with
the Teach pendant, and that
keeps adding together.
Audrow Nash: So how does the
Teach pendant what I'm imagining
is like a big pen kind of thing
with maybe like a bunch of QR
tags or some some fiducial
markers on top and you like hold
it into a spot and there's a
camera looking at it and you
click it or something? And it
says okay, here is the location
I want? Or is that how it works?
Dayo McIntosh: No, think of a
really industrial looking
tablet. Oh, okay. So that's
exactly what the Teach pendant
is the controller. And so like,
on this tablet, we have all the
different programs, we have
different positions. And if I
want it to go to bottles one and
seven, I enter that into the
Teach pendant on to the Teach
candidate and make that
selection and click press or go
play. And that again. gets it
going.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So you
select all of the things you
want it to do on this. Exactly.
It's like I want I want it to go
to one and seven, whatever. And
then it will grab the bottle,
bring it over there. How do you
get it to know the initial
positions of the bottles where
it has to push to get the stuff?
Dayo McIntosh: I'm sorry? Can
you how do we?
Audrow Nash: So if you if you
have all the dispensers up? How
do you? So if you add a new
dispenser to the right, say a
bit further away? How would you
tell it that there's one over
there that it could go push for
option 10? Say
Dayo McIntosh: so right now
everything is controlled, we
have a limited amount of
dispensers, we have 20 of them.
So 20 positions that are set. So
if we're introducing a new
ingredient, we're taking
something else out. So like it
doesn't go beyond the set
parameters that we have in place
right now. And
Audrow Nash: warming up for the
first ones. So for all 20 of
those. How did you tell Addie
all those positions.
Dayo McIntosh: Um, so that was
programmed. We programmed it.
And I worked with engineers to
come up with a programming for
this. And so that was hard
coded. Yeah. And so adding those
position one is, you know, to
disagree. Yes. Away from Me. And
yeah, so you can get to all
those positions. Without knowing
what exactly is there, right.
It's just going to position.
Audrow Nash: Yep. And how does
so if you want to do you want to
make a custom mix for someone?
Is it kind of like these
different dispensers will top
off the bottle. So you have
like, maybe you can pick the
framework fragrance and that's
like one dispenser, and you can
add some extra attribute like
extra moisturizing or whatever
it might be. And that makes it a
little bit custom but is it
largely made already, and you're
just adding like a little
topping to it.
Dayo McIntosh: Exactly. It's
largely made already and what
we're working on right now So
you can make adjustments to the,
to the recipe.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Very cool.
Yeah. So and then this is all in
a truck, and that truck has a
big sheet of glass. So you can
look and watch the robots
working. Can you tell me a bit
about that?
Dayo McIntosh: Yes. So when I
set out the goal, and again, the
vision still for this is to be
in a brick and mortar store, to
be sort of like the central
point where people can come
together. And it's going to be a
safe place for self discovery
for exploration, like finding
clean, natural ingredients and
products that work for your
hair, skin and wellness in
general. And so that was the
goal. But living in the Bay
Area, we all know that real
estate here is really expensive.
And so when that didn't seem
feasible, I had to think outside
the box, and that's where the
idea of the trucking came about,
I really liked the idea of
having this experience, right,
we're building this experience
for people that will sort of
engage them and get the
conversation going about what
they're using, in their, like,
on their bodies, for example,
and what their overall personal
care and wellness like regimen.
Resume is. And so that was the
idea behind this. So you walk up
to the truck and and immediately
you get this experience, right,
you're walking up and right in
front of us is robots, you know,
working to create a product
tailored for you.
Audrow Nash: And so the way that
it looks for the customer is
they come up to you and your
truck or whoever you're working
for it. And then they talk to
you for a little bit and then
you poke on your teach pendant
or whatever you call it a
tablet. Yes. And then do you do
you hand ADE a bottle? Does
that ego pick one up? Or how
does it work?
Dayo McIntosh: So right now we
have it set have different
trees, the different bottle
sizes in the truck. So when we
make the selection, it knows
what bottle to go to based on
what we've selected. So if we
pick a small bottle, it will go
to tray one. Medium bottle tree
two, large bottle tray three.
And so that's how it's currently
set up. Yes. So we don't do any
of the like handling of bottles
or ingredients like everything
is housed again in the truck.
And ADE manages that whole
setup. So the same?
Audrow Nash: How does that he
pick up the bottle? Because that
seems like a kind of tough task.
So you have some sensors, like
you have a camera or some sort
of like physical sensors or
something for telling where the
bottles are?
Dayo McIntosh: Or how do you
know. So that's something that
we're putting into place. But
right now, everything is hard
coded. So we can't afford to,
you know, move anything. So
those trays are bolted into the
ground so that regardless of
where we go with the trust, like
nothing moves, and so that
position is always constant. So
it always knows if they want a
small bottle, I go to this
position. Open up my gripper and
there's going to be something
there for me.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, but so
getting a bottle on a tray. The
tray is fixed, but like it has a
bunch of bottles on it. Correct?
How does it go and grab a bottle
on a fixed tray? Is it just you
have like a bunch of bottles
sitting in kind of like, I don't
know, separate sections for each
bottle and it goes in it knows
that this one is empty. Now it
goes to the next one.
Dayo McIntosh: How does it sell
a bottle? So everything that
we've done right now has been
like really rudimentary, right?
eliminating any, any potential?
Yes, any uncertainty or any
Audrow Nash: possibility of
vacation for small, medium and
large and you replace it every
time or
Dayo McIntosh: Yes. So we have a
long tray and I feed in the
bottles or whoever feeds in the
bottles. And then we have it on
an incline. So whenever ADE
grabs up, it slides down.
Exactly, exactly. It's clever.
Yeah.
Audrow Nash: I really liked the
approach you're taking, which is
like, keep the problem as simple
as possible, because you can
always grow and there's no need
to like automate everything,
especially while you're testing
out an idea. Right. And so I
really like it that it's so
clever because you have three
spots and the bottles just slide
down into it.
Dayo McIntosh: Exactly. So one
of my biggest fear when I
started doing this, I did a lot
of research about a lot of like
consumer facing robotic
applications, right. And I found
that the number one problem that
customers or people seem to
speak about was that these
different applications they were
always down like they weren't.
They weren't working. They
weren't working often. And the
problem with that is if you have
so many are different stations
that are all automated If you
run the risk of like one or the
other going down, and so you're
constantly fixing a problem. And
so when I set out to do this, I
wanted to simplify it as much as
possible, again to begin with
and figure out the rest as we,
as we grow as we as we move
forward. And so like everything
is super simple. What I'm
building right now, yeah, yeah,
it's it's been good so far.
Audrow Nash: And how so Okay,
now ADE has picked up a bottle
from one of a set of spots. So
you say a small medium or a
large bottle, or whatever the
sizes are, she grabs one, and
then pushes and adds a few
different things from the
dispensers. I assume the bottles
have no tops. Yes, correct. So
you can squirt right into it.
And then does ADE like, is
there like a little door or
something where ADE puts the
bottle for you to give it to the
customer? Or how does that like
the whole process now?
Dayo McIntosh: Okay, so let's
say you walk up to the truck,
you're like, Hey, do I want this
product. And I wanted this way,
I input that selection onto the
Teach pendant that keeps adding
together, it moves over to the
trays with the with the product
bottles grabs a bottle, small,
medium, or large, takes that and
goes to the dispensers on the
wall. So if you selected product
number one and seven, for
example, it would go to product
one, or dispenser one dispenser
seven. And once that's done
dispensing, it would deliver the
bottle to two cutouts that we
have in the truck. So in the
truck we have we cut out two
doors, think of it as a trap
door, two doors with a revolving
revolving tray. So as you would
place the bottle on the tray on
the inside of the truck, we
would revolve that tray and it
would appear on the outside of
the truck for the customer to
grab.
Audrow Nash: Cool. Okay. So,
with this, how long have you
been doing this? So how long
have you had the truck setup
with?
Dayo McIntosh: Ooh, two years.
Two years? A little over two
years? Yeah. So we started doing
our beta and showcasing it in q4
of 2019. And then, as we all
know, COVID hit right, the next
year. And so all of that
shutdown. And actually it was
stolen. And so that set us back.
And so we've been in the process
of like rebuilding. So that, you
know, as things have opened back
up, we can get back out there.
I'm showcasing and doing what we
do.
Audrow Nash: So you don't
currently have an Audi
replacement ADE.
Dayo McIntosh: Yeah, it's a
funny story. So now I currently
have two ADDYs. So the original
ADE was still the truck was
stolen with Abby. Yeah, they
It's wild. They ended up
destroying the truck. Taking the
computer, the brains behind it.
So it is a manipulator, right.
It's just the arm, the hardware,
and then you have the controller
the brains behind it. So they
took that I'm guessing they took
it for the wires. So that was
missing. And so I have to start
over purchasing you ADE. And so
now I just have the manipulator
the arm for the first one.
Audrow Nash: That's crazy. I
can't believe just how did they
steal your truck? With this? Did
it like at night? You just found
your truck missing or Yeah, kind
of thing? Are you in the Oakland
area? Or were
Dayo McIntosh: you? No, I'm
actually I would consider this
the suburbs. I live in New work
close to Fremont and just across
the bridge from like Menlo Park
and Palo Alto. So yeah, that
that was devastating. Yeah, like
I said, it was right before the
lockdown. So no one was working.
Everything was shut down. And so
we just started rebuilding at
the end of last year.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. I just had
a friend who had his car stolen,
and they just found it recently
been so crazy that
Dayo McIntosh: it is. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Your robot
truck.
Dayo McIntosh: And my robot
truck. Yeah, like a whole truck.
I was like, how do you steal a
whole truck? But yeah, that
happened. So it's part of the
year two story.
Audrow Nash: Gosh, now, so two
years a lot. Some have some
difficulties with like the truck
being stolen and COVID. But how
have customers been engaging
with ADE and how has the
experience been and the times
that you have been in front of
people?
Dayo McIntosh: So um, so we
debuted ADE unofficially at
Afro tech. So the time which is
November berth 2019, it was just
a really great opportunity to,
like, showcase Addie, and have a
crowd of people where we could
get feedback and just kind of
gauge people's reactions. And so
that was a really awesome
experience, we got a lot of
feedback, we got a lot of
interest. And we were really
excited to launch after that,
based on the interest and the
excitement that we found, or
that we received, being at that
event. And yeah, so it just,
again, all of that, the lock
downs, the theft, all of that
set us back, but we're gearing
up again, to go back out there.
And we know that we're going to
have the same amount of like
excitement and interest that we
had initially. So that's what
motivates us to keep going. And
that's what we're looking
forward to.
Audrow Nash: And the any like
funny stories about people being
just like, thrilled or anything
when the robot gives them their
custom product or anything.
Dayo McIntosh: So when we
launched, we weren't actually or
when we did our beta back then
we weren't actually in
operation. So everything is just
like, online right now. You can
buy premade products online, but
we haven't actually ever started
selling via adding those
evolving demos. And again, yeah,
we were we were all of our plans
were, you know, shifted by but
in disarray, by everything that
has happened. Yeah. When
Audrow Nash: that happened.
Yeah.
Dayo McIntosh: So we were really
excited to again, have this
experience of actually selling
with Addie and gauging customer
experience, user experience.
And, again, getting that
feedback. I think that's really
important. As we iterate and as
we grow. Right. So
Audrow Nash: what So you
mentioned it a little bit, but
the hope with Addie, is it
start? So basically, people come
for the robot, and then it
engages them in meaningful
conversation about their self
care effectively. Yes, that's
yeah, the draw of the robot and
then maybe build a community
around this. Yeah.
Dayo McIntosh: Well, so at ease,
definitely a novelty, right. We
haven't built into a truck. And
I don't think right now is with
the right love until like, it
makes me super excited. And and
robotics is the future of so who
knows what will happen. But it
is a novel team. And the idea is
that the efficacy of our
products will bring people back
to say that it serves two
purposes. First, it's
experiential retail. So again,
you're having this experience,
people have this fun, it's
you're having conversations,
you're having community, right
around this really fun, this
novel, really interactive,
unique experience, right. And
then the other hand is
operational efficiency. So we
envision a time where the second
it will be put to use in the
back fulfilling orders and
manufacturing. And so that's
that's the goal, the single
robotic arm can turn out based
on our calculations, let's say
about 500 products in a 24 hour
period. And even more than that,
so that definitely kicks into
gear, what we're doing, and
we're able to put out huge
volumes, as control all of them.
Audrow Nash: Doing it manually.
How long would that take? You to
do?
Dayo McIntosh: Yeah. I mean, 500
Do you have someone like making
that? I would say maybe, like
less than half of that.
Possibly. But then you don't
have people working? 24/7 Right.
Like,
Audrow Nash: definitely. We
manual and repetitive and like
yeah, not
Dayo McIntosh: rather, exactly.
would rather people would rather
the humans use that time to
engage and interface with
customers and have meaningful
conversations versus doing this
manual? Taxing indexing work?
Audrow Nash: For sure. Oh, what
a cool thing. Yeah. Let's see.
So how, I guess how did you pick
a Kuka arm? Like those are?
Like, I believe pretty expensive
arms? They're like really nice
arms? Yeah. I think like, I
mean, you don't have to give me
the exact number but I think
like $40,000 for like one of
those arms. Something.
Dayo McIntosh: That's That's
exactly right. They are quite
expensive. That is a very good
question. I have to this day I I
don't know I just have this
fascination with Kuka
specifically have this fixation
on Kuka. And it again, it's
unexplainable. I don't know why.
But I think the few times I've
been around robots, they've been
cool. Cuz so that may explain
that. But as far as the cost,
you're absolutely right. They're
all super expensive. And for
someone who's like
bootstrapping, And so big
expense all at once. It's a big
expense. And so when I set out
working with limited funds, I
send an SOS and this is what I
call it an SOS different
robotics groups that I was a
part of asking if someone if
anyone had any, like, used
robots, you know, that they
could sell sell to me for a
certain amount of money. And
someone happened to respond. And
at the time, she was the CEO for
Cafe X, the coffee robot in the
Bay Area. Cool. And she just
responded and say, Hey, we have
this, this arm in the back. It's
been there for years. We don't
even know if it works. But
you're more than welcome to have
it. Yeah. And so that's how we
got started. So I got that for
like a fraction, like maybe 10%
of the cost of what so what
else? Yeah, yeah. So that's,
that's my wild, wild acquisition
story. The very first
Audrow Nash: one. Did you did
something similar for come
through for the second one? Or
how did
Dayo McIntosh: for the second
one, we just got? We're able to
use the insurance money? Payout
from the last Yeah, to
Audrow Nash: whatever. I mean,
that like it works out for I
mean,
Dayo McIntosh: it I mean, yeah,
I would rather that didn't
happen. But like, I know, you
know, that was that was great,
right, that we had this option?
And because replace Yeah, we
could we could very easily
replace what was so
Audrow Nash: I'm glad it was
insured. Gosh,
Dayo McIntosh: I know. Yeah, it
all worked out well.
Audrow Nash: And then. So now,
actually, would you would you
tell me a bit about your
background? Because you've
mentioned so you're not an
engineer, but you this whole
project? Like? How did you come
to this?
Dayo McIntosh: That is a very
good question. Like I get that
question a lot. Because it just
doesn't make sense. Right? And
Audrow Nash: well, it doesn't
matter. It's I think it makes
sense. But yeah,
Dayo McIntosh: I love robotics.
So for me personally, I've
always been fascinated by
innovation and just technology
in general. I think that's just
my personality. There's this, I
have this very curious nature.
And I'm again, fascinated,
that's that's the only way to
put it fascinated by how things
work, and just the innovation
behind it. And so when I started
set out to create a business, I
wanted to incorporate that
fascination with innovation with
robotics into what I was doing,
again, knowing that this is the
future. So I tell people, I'm
not an engineer, I'm not a
technologist by any stretch of
the imagination. My background
is actually in project
management and program
management. And I've done that
for the last. I did that over 10
years across the energy, oil and
gas tech industry and real
estate industry. And so I think
those the acquired skill sets
over you know, 10 years has
really helped me in my
bootstrapping efforts with the
limited resources I have to get
it and yet so to where it is
today.
Audrow Nash: How did you so how
did you pick that you wanted to
I mean, that just the all the
decisions along the way are
really how did you pick Consu?
So robotics okay, I get it.
You're fascinated by technology.
And so you wanted to do
something with technology didn't
Is that how it started? But then
like, how did you get into
beauty products? Or like self
care products?
Unknown: Yeah. Yeah, kind
Audrow Nash: of marry the two
ideas
Dayo McIntosh: that's yeah, I
was laughing because yeah, go
on.
Audrow Nash: And then fit them
to the together and say we can
make a robot through the final
mix further. Yeah. It's
interesting how you how you've
arrived at this
Dayo McIntosh: Yeah, like
hearing you say it and hearing
people say it I had made it is
crazy. Like I could never have
you know, orchestrated this on
my own. I think things just came
together and lined up in a way
that made so much sense. And now
looking back I'm just I guess,
amazed at what has transpired.
So I started yet so after going
through a really challenging
point in my life. I don't know
if you're familiar with, you
know, the stats that the medical
community has put out has put
out about the lack of safe
products in the market. And like
the toxic ingredients and
chemicals that we've seen, okay,
so the beauty industry is
unfortunately, notorious for
lacks regulations around the
ingredients and chemicals in a
lot of the products that we use.
And not only that, it hasn't
always been inclusive, it didn't
always cater to everybody,
right? There were certain
demographics that were left out
such as myself women of color.
And you learn that the average
woman uses about 12 products on
a daily basis that exposes her
to about 168, chemicals,
ingredients, a lot of which have
now been linked to everything
from like allergies to cancer,
and even reproductive
dysfunction, which hits a bit
too close to home for me. And so
that's my story. That's the
background of of this, right.
And so going through that really
challenging point in my life, I
decided or determined that I
wanted to take better care of
myself, I wanted to invest in my
well being, I wanted to be
conscious about the products
that I was using, just as I was
conscious about the food I was
eating, right. So I, I tend to
eat healthy. And so I wanted to
also have that reflected in, you
know, the rest of my my well
being, like the products I use
and things like that. So I spend
time doing a lot of research,
but I was really disappointed
with the lack of safe and again,
inclusive products in the
market, things have gotten much
better, because there's more
awareness now. But at the time,
it was just sorely lacking. And
so I started mixing and matching
products in my kitchen, I
started creating products for
myself. And that process was
just very restorative and very
therapeutic. And so I wanted to,
I guess offer that to others who
were on similar paths who are
looking for solutions that were
chemical free, non toxic, vegan,
cruelty free. And so that's how
yet to get started. And from
that, the idea of marrying
technology to that because
again, where the world is
evolving, right? And so I wanted
to evolve or create a brand, the
company that will be around and
relevant not just for today, but
for the future. And so that's
where the idea of robotics came
into intervene and marrying that
together.
Audrow Nash: So the desire to
start the company because of the
lack of options, lack of
inclusive options, and then the
lack of safe options that came
first. And then yes, you then
had the idea to put the robot.
How did you fit the robot into
the like, how did you go? This
is how I can use a robot in this
situation?
Dayo McIntosh: Like the aha
moments? Yeah, I don't. Again, I
couldn't even tell you a
pinpoint like, this is exactly
what happened that, that set
that in motion. It's just
something clicked at some point.
And I was like, I'm going to use
the robots to create this really
awesome experience for people
and get that conversation
started. And who knows, it may
have been I mean, I've been
primed from, you know, maybe
robots as seen throughout my
life, or just different
impressions. I can't exactly
pinpoint, you know, the specific
moment and the specific moments,
but it just clicked one day, I
was just like, and this is what
we're doing. And we're going to
incorporate robotics and it's
all going to like mesh. I like
the way you said it. I say this
a lot. We married the apothecary
with robotics. And that's what
we're doing at marrying this
Audrow Nash: security. Or it's
what's apothecary, I don't know
the word.
Dayo McIntosh: And the classic
carry is for Yeah, in the past
where you'd go to have I guess
someone that came to a
pharmacist back then create
these like potions or
concoctions that you use for
you. Exactly. So I like that
idea of being very authentic,
being very traditional, right?
We're not we're not using
product or ingredients that
people have never heard don't
know how to pronounce. It's all
natural stuff. Right? And so
just again, going with that age
old idea and marry that with
this technology. I think it just
checks the box for me of this
beautiful like the old for
representation. Yeah, exactly.
Just marrying the old and the
new. Yeah, it's I think it's
beautiful. So
Audrow Nash: yeah, no, yeah, I
like it too. And one thing I'm
struck by is your care about the
experience rather than just like
pumping out products. How did
you decide to focus on the
experience more than like, say
just making a bunch of them and
like promoting with ads or like
whatever other companies often
do.
Dayo McIntosh: It goes back to
So yeah, tell means exceptional.
And it's from yerba. It is
Nigerian so Yoruba is a true I
live in Nigeria. And yet so
comes from the Yerba tribe. So
yes, it means exceptional
because we acknowledge that
there's no one size fits all,
when it comes to beauty and
wellness, like we're all
different. What might work for
you might not necessarily work
for me and vice versa, right.
And so, the idea behind this was
that people have this platform
to create products tailored to
their unique goals and needs and
wants. And that was the idea,
the driving force behind like,
the name, the brand, everything
we're doing, right, the
individual individualization and
personalization of creating
something for you, that will
force you or encourage you, or
empower you to invest in your
well being and take better care
of yourself. Because when you do
that, when you feel good, when
you look good, it all translates
to every aspect of your life and
your your quality of life is so
much better. And so that is that
is what we're about, right? We
want people to have a better
quality of life, so that they
can really enjoy the one life
they have to live.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Now, I
don't know very much about like,
I don't know, like, I mean, I
use lotion, but that's about the
extent. Okay. Can you tell me
like, I don't really know, the
so if I didn't use lotion? Or if
I, and then all the what are
some of the other products? And
what's kind of the importance of
all of these? Like, you say you
feel really good. And that's if
you feel really good, you're
more confident or things like
Yes, but how does it kind of
fit? And how can it specifically
help a person to invest in their
own? What do you call it?
Dayo McIntosh: Well, being well
being? Yes. So we don't do like
makeup, right? We're more about
the personal care. So it's,
again, if you think about all
those chemicals and ingredients
that are toxic and affect your
health. That's what we mean
about feel good, right? It's not
an artificial, we're, we're
really concerned about actually
feeling good. You know, like,
you're healthy, you're, well,
when you're healthy, you're
happy, right? Imagine if you
have allergies, or you have
cancer as a result of what
you're using. It affects your
outlook, right and your, your
carriage in general, just
because you're you're miserable,
you're in pain or your whatever
it may be. So imagine being
well, you're well, you're
healthy, you feel good, you're
able to enjoy
Audrow Nash: things in life that
you want to do that you
Dayo McIntosh: want to do. Yeah,
and I think it seems, or right.
And it might seem so yes,
exactly. And it might seem so
trivial, but like things like
that really matter. And again,
it's it translates to every
aspect of your life. If you're
healthy. And well, you're,
you're happy, you know, because
you're not afflicted by, you
know, all these other things
that might, you know, casts cast
a shadow or impact you
negatively, you know,
Audrow Nash: yeah, you're never
I don't know, it's like, if
you're healthy, you don't think
about it. But if you're
unhealthy about it.
Dayo McIntosh: Oh, you think
about it. Yeah. And your
constant. It's a constant
reminder. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: And so you can't do
other things, because you're
preoccupied with just like
health and existence and this
kind of Exactly, exactly. You're
saying allergies, you said
reproductive issues. cancer,
cancer. Yeah. And these are
these are coming. Like they're
positively linked to products
that are often used in the
beauty industry.
Dayo McIntosh: There are links
to chemicals and ingredients
that we see in everyday products
that that we use, and that's
alarming, right? For sure. It's
alarming. And again, these are,
it's it's new research, right?
The the medical community is now
linking them to these things,
but it's because of the
awareness. So there's a
organization called the EW G and
there's several other ones
coming out, that are focused on
bringing awareness to things
like this so that we can change
or the government can change
those lacks regulations, like we
need to do better, because
people are ill, they're they're
unwell because of I mean,
there's a direct correlation
many times. So if we're able to,
like make those adjustments and
make those changes, just imagine
how happier how, like, better
off people would be in general.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, they get on
with their lives rather than
worrying about things or what
exactly yeah, and have lived the
life they want to live rather
than what they're Yeah, they're
having health difficulties or
unable to have kids. Yeah,
something like that.
Dayo McIntosh: Exactly. And so
we're going to, you know, get
that conversation started with
ADE. Big engage people draw
them in again with this, you
know, fascination, this novelty.
But really we're after the, the
the core of the matter, like the
meat of it is that we want
people to be intentional about
how they take care of themselves
what they use, so that they have
a better life.
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah, I really
like that. Yeah. So what's the
what's the range of products
that you're mostly offering?
Dayo McIntosh: Yeah. So we
started off with Hair Skin and
aromatherapy oils. So right now
we just offer oils and butters.
So you mentioned you use lotion.
And butter is similar to lotion,
but it doesn't have water. Like,
the consistency of lotion is
like very light. Yeah, butter is
very thick. So think of mushy
butter. Yeah, exactly. Oh, do
you Okay, yeah, exactly. So we
offer things like that. Again, I
talked about the hair for your
skin. And then the diffuser
oils, there are my therapy oils
or the fuser oils. So essential
oil blends, that you would add
to your diffuser. And it just,
it's it, it changes the mood,
right, it has an impact on your
mood. And those are, again, when
we say we say well being,
because that encapsulates
personal care, beauty and
wellness in general.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And just
for the essential oils and
things that so that the world
smells like the oils, right? So
like you put it in something and
it like bubbles it or something,
and it makes it so that
everything smells really nice.
And you're saying that's tied to
mood and things like this. I
admit I'm really
unsophisticated.
Dayo McIntosh: That's fine. A
lot of people don't know about
this. But it's so essential oils
have because they are very
natural. They're very potent, do
derived from plants from roots,
whatever, they're potent, and
they're effective, right?
They've been known, we can make
any claims because those haven't
been cleared yet. But they've
been known to help with, like
stress to, to help with
depression many times, like
there's a long list of what are
the benefits of essential oils?
Again, we can't make any direct
claims, because there's still a
lot of like research and that
needs to go into that. To make
them you know, things that are
allowable of sorts. Yeah. So
they've been known to, to help
with certain things with health,
right, and the well being and
they've been used for years for,
you know, for a long time only
say since the beginning of the
world, but very long, so So
yeah, so we're just tapping into
the benefits of those things.
And again, when you defuse these
things, they they help with
those ailments. Like for
example, we have a blend we call
sleep. It has camo mill, it has
cedar wood, and it has French
lavender. And that is to help
you have like a retinol. Yeah,
it does. It smells amazing. It
helps you have like restful,
peaceful sleep, or sleep. And so
again, it all ties back to
improving the quality of life.
Right? If you get good rest your
you function better during the
day, so yeah,
Audrow Nash: yeah, I mean, I,
like even I am not speaking
about the efficiency of any of
these towards like actually
carrying anything, or fixing or
reducing. But even from like a
habit perspective, which I'm big
into habits, like if you play
the same music at the same time,
every day can make it easier to
get into a specific state of
like consciousness or something.
And so if you were to do the
same essential oil, and you
smell it, and it's like, Okay,
now it's sleepy time, this kind
of thing that could be very
valuable. Yeah, exactly.
Ingredients. So you're not like
poisoning yourself while you're
trying to get good.
Dayo McIntosh: Exactly. Right.
Yeah, exactly. So like we're
very conscious about, again,
like, the stuff that we're
giving people because it
matters, right? We source
everything from like one
supplier that works to like
local farmers that are paid well
above, you know, what others are
getting because again, all of it
matters like it all. It all ties
together. We're very social
conscious brand. And that ties
again into our mission to help
people live their best lives.
Sam,
Audrow Nash: so you, you say
where, who else is in our How is
your team and is it how many
people are helping you guys out
yet? So
Dayo McIntosh: I am a solo
founder. And but I have built a
village and I've had like
incredible partners along the
way that have helped me get to
where I am. It's it hasn't been
easy because again, it's so much
easier when you have a team. And
you're you have a co founder and
you guys are able to share the
burdens of building a business
but specialize to some level to
exactly. But yeah, it's been me
from the concepts of design, the
operations, all of it. And I've
just been really resourceful
about finding the right people
along different paths of the
journey to come on board to get
me to the next level.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Do you. So
how do you work with software
engineers and things like the
people who programmed the arm
about the specific positions?
And what to do?
Dayo McIntosh: How do I work
with them?
Audrow Nash: Like, do you hire
like a do contract?
Dayo McIntosh: Or? You do? Yes,
yeah. So they've been
contractors. I've had a couple
of books, one of them has really
been instrumental in getting it
to where it is. And I tell the
story, because it's part of our
startup story, right? i He
happens to work at Tesla. And
when I set out to, when I
acquired the arm from Cafe X, I
didn't know what to do, right? I
had, again, limited funds,
you're like I have. Now I have
this now what? What do I do with
it? I didn't know what to do
with it, and hired some people
who had no idea what to do with
it. Because Kuka tends to be
very proprietary. And it's
pretty, as far as I understand.
Yeah, with a lot of the stuff
that he do, and not a lot of
people really know how to use
the Kuka. But I live in New
York, which is right next to
Fremont. And I remember that
Tesla, just down the street from
me and happens to be one of the
biggest customers of poucos. And
so I just started super clever.
Okay, yeah, I just started
spamming is what I call it
spamming Tesla employees who had
like, robotics or anything like
that, on their LinkedIn profile.
And that's how I met my engineer
that again, that has been really
instrumental in in the build out
for adding so yeah,
Audrow Nash: gotcha. That's
really cool. That's so funny to
spam. Yeah, the talent.
Dayo McIntosh: I am the queen of
spamming.
Audrow Nash: I've heard this a
lot from startups, where it's
like, you have a task, and you
need someone with a specific
skill set. But you probably
can't hire them fully. Because
you're bootstrapping. Yeah,
yeah. So you can contract them a
little bit. But the clever thing
that I've seen a few companies
do is hire someone on like a
contract basis to do a specific
task. And you look to the top
companies like Tesla, because
the they're basically a talent
filter in some ways. And also,
like, especially you being very
clever, and going, Oh, Tesla
uses a lot of Kuka arms, I can
find someone there. Yeah. So
that seems like,
Dayo McIntosh: like starting
starting a business forces you
to think outside the box. I
mean, for sure. Many times your
back is against the wall, and
you either sink or swim. And so
it's in those moments that I
would say your your all your
creativity. Yes. Let's use that
word creativity really.
Desperation masked as
creativity. Yes. Yes. Correct.
Yeah, that's when it really
comes to light. And so yeah,
that's, that's how we got to
where we are. But speaking about
hiring people for specific
tasks. Outside of the engineer
that we used, have gone to have
used the Upwork. I don't know if
you're familiar with. They seem
cool. Yeah. Some a lot to to get
people on board for what I need.
For example, as we're looking to
fully automate adding a portion
of that is something we call a
PLC, programmable logic control
controller. Yeah. And then
having an HMI like the human
machine interface for the tablet
I talked about. So like people
are, you're tapping on the
tablet, you're tapping on the
screen, and that keeps adding to
Garin. So all of that is powered
by this PLC. And that has been
the most challenging part of
trying to automate versus
finding someone. Yeah, who can
who can develop that or build,
you know that on top of what we
have, and so I've gone to Upwork
work several times to try to
find the right talent.
Audrow Nash: Has that been
successful for you generally, to
find someone who's good with DLC
stuff?
Dayo McIntosh: Um, generally, I
mean, we're still, you know,
working that out, but I think
Upwork Upwork is a good is a
good resource for for startups
or founders who are looking for
contractors. Yeah. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Yeah, the
PLC stuff, as I don't know too
much about it. But in my, my
impression of it is it's like,
older factory robots. Or maybe,
maybe not, maybe not even older.
But like factory robots, they
would have programmable logic
controllers. And that would be
how you control the robot. And
it was like, this was like, from
the 60s or something like this,
that it was used? Oh, really?
Okay. And maybe maybe way off?
Maybe 80s? Maybe you I don't
know. But it's amazing to me
that those skills are still
very, like, there's still if you
if you are a PLC program, I
think you can make a good
salary. But it's, to me, it
sounds like painful work
Dayo McIntosh: is just really
challenging. And then you factor
in the Kuka part, which a lot of
people don't have experience
with. But yeah, PLCs is what
it's sort of like the brains,
right? Especially if you have
different different components
outside of the robot. So we have
a payment system, we have the
HMI, we have the robot. So the
PLC serves as, again, the brains
the the project manager, in a
sense like that, that knows when
to call each component into
action.
Audrow Nash: For sure, like the
high level organizer of
everything,
Dayo McIntosh: yes, yes,
exactly. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: How do you? I
guess, what's next for you guys?
Like we're Where do you think
that's always headed.
Dayo McIntosh: So we definitely
want to get back out there, that
is a dream that was deferred.
And so we want to pick up right
where we started, which is
hitting the road with adding
demoing, but now actually
selling now that we have
products and, you know, products
that people can buy. So that
that is in the works. Right now,
we partnered with this company
full speed automation to work on
the automation part of of what
we're doing. We say they've been
a part of
Audrow Nash: it, like from the
web to distributing or what what
part
Dayo McIntosh: No, just just the
ADDIE part the operation of the
process, from when a person
orders to what ADE does next.
And then the final piece of
that. So they've been a really
great partner so far, the
ability in the first no code,
sort of automated platform, for
manufacturing for robotics in
general. And so they, they saw a
potential opportunity to, to
utilize their program for a
robot and see what it does. And
so we're able to work with them
to see what comes of that. And I
think that will be done in May,
and will finally be able to take
it out. And again, yeah, hit the
ground running and see what
happens from there.
Audrow Nash: And then growing,
so you'll be selling your
product. And then I guess you'll
figure out how to reinvest it at
the time. Whether it's making
more of the operation autonomous
or I guess, yeah. I don't know.
I love the idea of a robot like
food truck doing a service. I
think that's the coolest thing.
Dayo McIntosh: Yeah, I mean,
there's so many places we can
take this. I mean, one of the
things again, because this is
experiential, like we see an
avenue where I talked about
having it at festivals, or like
even private and corporate
events. So something akin to
like a photo booth that you'd
see at a company party, but
instead are like a wedding and
you have custom, you know,
diffuser oils, essential oils
for your guests, and they get to
like play with a robot to create
that. So there's that avenue.
And then we're currently in the
process of trying to patent our
application. And so being able
to like monetize that, I think
is is the next next step. Like
if we're able to do that I think
that changes the game right? It
changes everything.
Audrow Nash: So you mean get a
pat and then maybe you'll
license it out or something so
others
Dayo McIntosh: exactly there's
that yeah, or franchising. Do
vending so, so that is again
another path that we can take
but for the immediate Future
were focused on, you know, the
road, just getting back to the
road with our one truck and then
leasing it out the truck out for
like events and things like
that. So that is the immediate
future. And yeah, we're excited
to see what happens with that.
Audrow Nash: Do you think your
first show will be in May? Or
your first I
Dayo McIntosh: mean, at the end
of May? Yes. And we're actually
moving we're relocating to Reno.
So we, Reno, Nevada, Reno,
Nevada. Gotcha. The tech scene
is really up and coming there. I
noticed. It's also well, it's
close to the California it's
close to the Bay Area, which I
love. So I feel like that's,
that's still an option for me,
right, I can very easily come
back as needed. And then
finally, it's just a great, I
think it's going to be a great
exposure, because you have
people from all over coming to
Tahoe, or like that area for
vacation for whatever it may be.
And so you have this element of
like a big fish in a small pond
type deal. We were able to get
Yeah, so able to build brand.
Brand Awareness quick, quicker
than we would here and just meet
the right people and meet the
right investors, all in that
area. So that's what I'm
gambling on. And we'll see what
happens.
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah, I like
it. I like that.
Dayo McIntosh: Big fan. Yeah. I
mean, I mean, we'll see what
happens. Right. And I think your
worst case scenario, we can
always come back. But I think I
think that's that's going to be
a great dreaming, ground for for
us to like really gloat, grow
and flourish? For sure.
Audrow Nash: Do you want to our
once the ground has been hit,
and you're off? What do you
imagine will be the first people
you'll hire? That that's easy to
be co founder? Oh, it's easy.
Dayo McIntosh: That is easy.
Straight up, I need a marketing
expert, that my first hire is
going to be someone highly
skilled in marketing in the
beauty industry. I am I am great
at executing I'm great at
operations. I'm great ads, you
know, creating. I mean, I think
everything I've done so far, has
been has been great, right? And
the ability to do that. But one
area that I struggle with is
marketing, especially in the
beauty industry, which is key
like that is crucial for a
beauty brand. And so finding
someone who has that background,
that experience expertise, all
of that is is the critical hire.
I need I need that person. And
quickly. So yeah, that is that
is the first first hire for
sure.
Audrow Nash: Hell yeah. And then
investment are you? Have you
taken any money yet? Are you? A
well? Are you looking for angel
investors? Are you like, where
are you at in terms of funding?
Dayo McIntosh: Yeah. So I, I
went, this is just an idea. I
was part of a founder Institute
accelerator. And so there you're
kind of like, coached on like,
like, pitching, trying to raise
money. But it was just an idea
and such a wild idea that it
just wasn't. I mean, I wasn't
having like serious
conversations, right. And so I
just decided that I needed to
put my head down, build, have
traction, and then go back to
the table for these people to
take me seriously. And so that's
what I set my mind on doing. I
got a business loan, an SBA
loan, cashed out my 401 K. And
that's what has gotten me this
far. I am now at the point where
I do need to get some sort of
investment. I have, you know,
working prototypes, some
traction, you know, and I feel
like I can now go back to that
table to have those, those
conversations. And so I'm just
starting down that path. Again,
I think Angel invests investors
are who I need at this point,
before bringing in any
institutional like larger, like
venture venture capital
investors, probably so yeah, I
just I need someone that
believes in the vision and the
dream and sometimes when I sit
in front of investors, they
don't quite get it. And so I
know that they're not the right
partners, right? I need someone
that that is like I bind I see
where you're going with this and
I'm excited because I See the
potential. That's who I'm
looking for. And that's what I
need. So
Audrow Nash: you're starting a
conversation, and then you'll
have quality products behind it,
is how I kind of see it. And the
robot is a great way to start
that conversation, get people
excited. Like that. I mean, I,
I'm trying to imagine like other
beauty products, were there,
like we would have, we would be
at a wedding or something like
some special event. And it's
like, it would just be like, a
shelf with their things. Whereas
you like people will come over
and see, it'll be like a big
hit. Yeah, because everyone is
an experienced robot work? Yeah.
Dayo McIntosh: Yeah, you have it
a sweet 16 party or a bar
mitzvah? Or whatever. Like,
it's, it's an experience. It's
like, I mean, just like when the
photo booths came out, right?
Like people are constantly
looking for entertainment or
experiences at their events. And
so this is just going to be one
other option for them.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. And then it
starts off, it kicks off that
wellness conversation, too. And
also the conversation about a
lot of the other companies or
maybe not a lot, I don't know,
many other products having
toxins and unhealthy things.
Yeah. So then making people more
conscious,
Dayo McIntosh: more aware, yeah,
I feel like healthy eating. I
mean, similar to the path that
that took, right, it just became
a thing. And like maybe the last
six, seven years, maybe maybe
more in the Bay Area in
California, but around the
country, if you really got that
urgency, or that we started to
see change in the last five or
six years around healthy, like
healthy eating organic, things
like that. So I think this is
going to take that same path of
progression. You starting the
conversation, and then people
become fully aware, and they
start making those necessary
changes. Lifestyle changes.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Let's see
what are just kind of a bit of a
side tangent. But what are some
things people should look out
for in products to make sure
they're not putting toxic
products on them?
Dayo McIntosh: You've heard of
like, parrot beings? Well, you
may not have heard of it, but
like parabens. fragrances. You
want to avoid things like that.
And there's there's a long list,
which I know there's some debate
about that, because you can't
cut out all like chemicals.
Right? Yeah, I mean, even like,
you need some of them to numb
and things like this. So
exactly. But it's just being
mindful about what you're using.
So the US compared to I think,
the UK, Europe, has they have
better, better regulations?
They've limited the ingredients
and the chemicals that can be
used. And yeah, you know,
they're they're doing well, I
mean, they still have those
companies and those companies
have adjusted right to meet
those, those charges. So I think
we can do the same thing over
here as well.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And, like
going back to the angel investor
talk, and you don't have to
answer if either it's too new or
whatever. But what would be like
a meaningful amount of money
that you'd be looking for
investment, like how much would
kind of be a nice step for you,
to help you keep the vision
going.
Dayo McIntosh: I'm looking to
raise 500,000 At this point, and
I've kind of projected that that
will be like a 1212 month runway
to get us to profitability is
what I'm looking at in my mind.
And that's to hire the right
people to get the inventory we
need for you know, some of the
proceeds that have come our way
such as like b2b opportunities,
and then fully automating Addie,
and having that in house
manufacturing that I that I
spoke about. So that's, that's
what I'm looking at raising
right now. And then we'll adjust
as we move forward.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And what
what lessons have you learned
from this whole process? Like,
what were some of the biggest
takeaways, if you had to do this
all again, other than lock up
the truck?
Dayo McIntosh: I'd say start,
first of all, start small and
start with just start somewhere.
I find sometimes I'm very much
of a perfectionist and it can be
crippling right and it took me a
while to actually get out the
gate because I wanted things to
be perfect. So it had to be a
certain way had to look a
certain way and sometimes you
need to be in the market and and
generate feedback from people so
that you can build a better
product right? That that would
be my advice to myself, even if
I could start over, it's just
start go with the strength you
have start where you are. And
then you can build on that as
you go along. And then when I
got started with a premade
products, there were just so
many things that I went to
market with so many options,
because I wanted everyone to
have an option like for
themselves, right. And it's very
hard to like market that and to
build on that when you get
started. So I always say start
small, get a small, niche
following people that are crazy,
absolutely crazy about what
you're building, like fanatical,
even about what you're building
because that excitement that
that passion, like spreads and
grows. Right. And and then
you're able to draw more people
in. Based on their their, their
excitement. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Also, I mean,
I've heard of this whole idea of
like, I don't know, there's
like, if you have 10,000 fans,
or if you have 100 fans or
something, like if you have that
group. So if you have the 10,000
fans, and they are, let's say
1000, and they give you $1 Each
or something like that, sorry,
if you have 100 fans, and they
give you $10 Each, they're kind
of the same thing. Yeah. So if
you if you have like that core
group that really likes what
you're doing. Yeah. And have a
small audience that's just like
so behind you. And they really
have this kind of thing.
Dayo McIntosh: Yeah. And again,
that excitement that passion is
contagious. They talk about it.
People get curious. Exactly. You
have the people that are curious
now because they've heard so
much about this. Yeah, it's just
it's just I think the way to go.
And it's a good lesson lesson
for me going forward.
Audrow Nash: Yes. Do you have
any, any ideas on how to like
foster that? Have you as
anything you've done work to yet
or? I don't know. I'm wondering,
how's it? How's that going? It
seems so far.
Dayo McIntosh: It seems well, go
ahead seems like
Audrow Nash: a challenging
thing, because in theory, it
makes a lot of sense. I'm just,
I don't know, the practical way
of getting there seems a little
murky to me.
Dayo McIntosh: Yeah. I used to
think social media was like, so
easy. Like marketing in general.
You put up a picture and like,
you know, people come or
whatever it may be, but I'm
finding it. It's Rocket Science.
Like there's a, there's a method
to the madness, there's, you
know, it's, I mean, you have to
know what you're doing. And
again, back to the beauty
industry. People are hesitant to
try the unknown, right? Because
you're talking about their
health, which is kind of ironic,
because we're trying to, like
help them do better. What are
you talking about your health
and like overall, like
presentation and Outlook, right?
So people are very cautious
about what they use. And so
they're very hesitant to try
something new or something that
hasn't been validated by a
celebrity or an influencer, or
someone like that, that they
will trust. And so that's one of
the challenges that we're
running into is, is finding that
partnership or finding someone
who can sort of give that that
validation or that blessing to
take us to the next level. So in
the meantime, we're just, you
know, trying different things to
see what works. And then just
trying to have conversations and
connect with people, too. Yeah.
To grow from there.
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah. Can you
imagine any other ways that
robots will be used in your
whole process? Or I mean, so you
have the arm as a mixologist and
you have an arm as kind of a
front show? mixologist? Can you
imagine any other ways robots
can use or
Dayo McIntosh: what do you mean
by French show? Like, wanting to
manufacture? Okay, so yeah, so
we haven't won in a
Audrow Nash: Trump manufacturing
one?
Dayo McIntosh: Yes, exactly.
Yes. So the patent we we filed
doesn't limit us to just like
robotic arm, if that makes
sense. So we have like, it can
it can look like whatever form
that is, you know, provided it's
approved, right? can look like a
different form. And so, in the
future, like we're going to
explore what else we can do with
that. Again, as you know,
technology evolves as people
become more familiar and
comfortable with robots in
general. We can we can really
explore that then down the road.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Well, I
look forward to seeing that.
Dayo McIntosh: Yeah, me too. I,
again, I'm so excited about what
I'm building here, right because
I married this and passionate
about, you know, having making a
call positive impact on the
world. And for me, that looks
like helping people like live a
better life. Because that's
connected to my personal story.
And then like just dealing with
innovation robots in general,
like how cool so I'm super
excited to be, you know,
building this brand where I get
to marry those two things and,
and just see this crazy dream
come to life. It just makes me
really happy and excited. So I'm
just, I'm very excited to see
what comes of this. I don't know
where it's gonna go. I don't
know what it's gonna look like,
you know, five years, 10 years
down the road, but I am excited
about the journey.
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah. I love
that. Yeah. Yeah. See? So
wrapping up. Is there any
contact info, website info,
anything you'd like to pass on
to our listeners and watchers?
Yeah,
Dayo McIntosh: you can find us
online on yeto.com. And that's
why@eou.com. On there, we have a
contact form, you can reach out
to us on there. You could also
send us an email at Hello at
Yateou, which is why@eou.com. And,
yeah, we respond really quickly.
And yeah. If anyone is looking
for technical specs on the robot
we have it's a Kuka agilus spot.
The smaller one is a QR six or
700. And the larger one is a QR
six are 900. So that one is
slightly bigger than the one we
had previously. And it has a
longer reach.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Thank you.
Yeah.
Dayo McIntosh: Thank you so
much. I really enjoyed chatting
with you. And yeah, I, I hoped,
you know you're able to. Well, I
can't really say that. So it's
good to see. I hope you have a
good move. But it was nice
chatting with you. Audrow. Thank
you. Thank you for the
opportunity.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Oh, yeah. All
right. Hi, everyone. Thanks for
listening to this conversation
with dial Macintosh. If you
enjoyed this interview, consider
subscribing. Thank you again to
our founding sponsor, open
robotics. See you next time.