Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Maria
Telleria, who is a co founder
and the CTO of Canvas. Canvas
makes a drywall finishing robot
for construction sites. One
thing that I think is especially
interesting about Canvas is that
they are working closely with a
trade union. In case you don't
know, quoting from the AFSCME,
a large trade union in the
US. A union is an organization
formed by workers who joined
together and use their strength
to have a voice in their
workplace. Unions help workers
negotiate for better wages,
benefits and job safety, among
other things. I'm not very
knowledgeable about unions. But
my impression before this
interview, was that unions often
slow the adoption of new
technology in a trade. And I
think most robotics companies
I've talked to avoid or try to
automate unions out of
relevance. So I was surprised to
hear how Canvas is working
closely with a trade union, and
that both canvas and the trade
union seem to be benefiting from
the collaboration. In the
future, I expect to see more
robotics companies following
Canvas's lead. Since I think
working with unions can help
robotics companies understand
their problem, get into
industries much faster, and
avoid resistance from people
already in the trade. At the
same time, I believe unions can
benefit from automation in
canvases case, their drywall
robot helps to reduce the rate
of repetitive injuries that end
people's careers. And they help
a trade that is significantly
short on people to meet their
demand. I'm Audrow Nash. This
is the Sense Think Act Podcast. Thank
you to our founding sponsor,
open robotics. And now here's my
conversation with Maria. Hi,
Maria, would you introduce
yourself?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, Maria
Telleria. Yeah, I am co founder
and CTO of Canvas. And we're a
robotics company bringing
drywall finishing robots to the
construction industry.
Audrow Nash: Now, tell me about
your drywall finishing robot.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, so when
we, you know, we come from a
research background, and we've
been always looking at why are
robots used? In other words,
they are used, but not really
widely use outside of
manufacturing and logistics. And
read I think is a challenge that
probably many in the audience
know that construction
environments are much more
difficult for robotics. And so
my co founder, Kevin, Albert,
and myself, were always driven
by like, hey, let's bring robots
to another place. We got
fascinated by construction,
right, the size of the market is
huge, the problem, but then, you
know, you kind of keep digging
and digging. And that's where we
found drywall finishing. And we
pick this test, because it is
particularly painful in terms of
like a lot of wear and tear on
the body. A lot of like
repetitive steps, you know, long
schedule, even if the work is
not consistently being done,
because you have drying steps.
So really, the goal was like,
Okay, this seems to have all the
adult dirty dangerous for
robotics. Let's go at it. And so
yeah, robot is, I keep saying
tool because it is really meant
to be an augmentation of the
worker. So we do have a worker
in the loop, they are a key part
of the component. They're a key
part of how we actually solve
this problem, the unstructured
environment. But it is, you
know, this robotic system, it's
a robotic arm with very
specialized and the factors that
allowed it to spray on the joint
compound, which is where you
apply on the drywall sheets to
cover kind of the seams, and
then a sanding and detector that
sends it down so that it looks
smooth. And that robot arm is on
a mobile base that allows the
right to reach all the different
places in the construction site.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So what
does it look like when the robot
is actually doing its spraying
and sanding? You kind of just
position it near a wall and it
goes in slowly covers everything
with its arm? Or how does it
look?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, I mean,
maybe this is where a picture's
worth 1000 words. So pull up the
video to share it you.
screen here, you know this is
pretty much a quick peek. But
I'll describe it as we go right
now really, you know, starting
with the idea that there is a
lot of construction going on.
This is what the job site looks
like when we come in. It has
been taped. So you have to apply
the state between the jump the
different drywall sheets that
you come in, and you go ahead
and install that spray and the
factor that you see there. A big
part here. I'll pause it to talk
a little bit about it. Because
you mentioned like, right you
position it, like keep our
promises we have to build our
map to make this happen, right.
We don't have a map when we
start you know there is things
like bid models. So the models
the building information model.
It's kind of like the had
construction sites, right? They
do exist, they're pretty
detailed, they have everything
done that. Rarely, by the time
we come in are those that
accurate because nobody's
updated when like, things had to
move a little bit, you cannot
make that decision as long as
not something structural people
can move a wall a little bit
because of whatever recent
happened on site. So one is not
accurate in two, they don't
often get shared all the way
down the chain of people who are
working right there kind of more
useable design and modeling
stage rather than in the build
stage. So most of our customers
just have a floorplan, so 2d
plan, and they say, right, I
gotta finish these walls. So one
of the key things that we
implemented was said, we can't
depend on them having a male
have been mobile, excuse me, and
we can't depend on the BIM model
being accurate. So we're going
to have to map ourselves. So
basically, the robot comes in
recruit scans to space
identifies the different areas
that it has to treat. And then a
key part here is that it splits
them up into workspaces, right,
this goes along with the fact
that the robot arm can only
reach so much right just like
your arm, you at some point, you
have to use your legs to move
along. So by splitting up into
these workspaces, we really
think of the mobile base that
you see this pretty big base
position said roughly to this
spot, and then the robot arm can
use all of its precision to go
ahead and target it in a blank
here, you see our operator
select the workspace is the
rows, columns that he wants to
do. And then you see how it
sprays the material work life is
very consistent code across and
making sure that we target the
low spots and and then by the
end of it, right, you have a
full coverage of your machine.
This part we can touch on later.
But one of the hardest parts
with construction is reporting
back on what's happening, right,
a lot of the problem is when
work is done manually, you have
to kind of call people up and
get kind of an update on what
happened. And really report them
back. I think that's one of the
secondary effects of robotics
and logistics and automate in
manufacturing is that you also
get that data for free. So we're
just showing a little bit of
what's possible here. When the
robots in the loop, you know,
the supervisor can get updates
that are live and they're very
accurate. And then the next day,
same robot arm mobile base,
different end effector. So we
put the sanding header comes in,
it uses the same map that we
created the day before, and it
starts standing away. And this
is, you know, again, a lot of
our development has gone around
the sanding, because it is a
very soft material, right? If
you reach out across the wall,
you could scratch it with your
nail, it's so soft material that
you need to make it look really
flat. So you have all of these
things that you have to work
around to make sure that you get
the night consistent finish. And
this is again, talking back to
the data reporting that you can
get back. This video is a
little, I think, from 2020. So
this has 25 projects completed,
but we're now in the more like
40 plus range. Oh, that's so
exciting. And doing.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. The video
was very informative. Oh, yeah.
Okay. So let's see, what what
exactly does the Operator do?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, so I think
the operator really does all the
things around it that allow the
robot to be successful in a
structured and dynamic
environment, right. So they do
things like selecting which
areas you want to skip, right,
there might be a reason that you
don't finish that right then and
there. They can provide feedback
to the machine as well on the
quality so that the machine can
tune in and get that feedback
process from it. You're also
doing a lot around coordinating
around with other trades, right?
So the reality is the
electrician is also in there,
you know, the floor guys coming
in the painters right behind
you. So that coordination with
all the different people, but in
reality, we they really are the
ones that at the end of the day,
they're the quality assurance,
right? They make sure your
feedback or even sometimes a
little bit of manual work to
ensure that the final bullet so
that the machine really takes
the 90% plus of the brunt of the
work. But they're the ones who
are skilled who have this. So
our operators are tapers,
they're journeyman takers who
have been trained and the
skilled and so they can pick up
a tool if they need to, like a
manual tool and fix up anything.
But more importantly, they have
that eye in that training to
say, Okay, this needs a little
bit more here. A little bit less
there. Okay, that's how you get
a wall to look.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, so you said
they're called tapers. So that's
the construction role, like job
role for someone who would do
this. It's really interesting to
me that you are having the
person who would do this
normally be the robot operator.
Can you tell me a bit more about
that?
Maria Telleria: Sure. Yeah. And
I like spend a little bit on the
call papers because you string
this paper tape across it so
right that's where the name
comes from. There you know it's
more like drywall finishers.
It's kind of the more formal
term but everybody in the
construction side be like oh the
tape you know, construction they
ended up getting to that to the
point do you string tape your
tape? Up to your point the plug
why? Right because we can have
gone a lot of different ways.
But as we really thought about
it, again, to ensure that we get
that quality finish, we needed
that expertise that skill level,
there's going to be things that
may never make sense for the
robot to automate, right?
Imagine somebody decided to make
like a gothic column out of
drywall, you could do it, I
don't think I'd want to spend
the time programming it because
you'll never see it again,
right? But a worker has the
years of experience that
delicate touch that adaptability
that a robot doesn't do. And
it's okay, I'm going to start
the robot here, finish the brunt
of my work. And I'm going to use
my skills where it's really
needed, right to provide that
feedback or to finish some
delicate part of it. And for us,
really to be successful there.
You needed somebody who could
work with a robot, right? So
it's like, oh, we have this
great, skilled, talented person,
we augment them. That's the way
to go. Right? As opposed to
maybe bringing in somebody who's
like a robotics expert. Okay,
maybe the robot kept running,
but not sure that well, we?
Audrow Nash: Yeah, for sure.
Okay, that's so interesting. And
so what are some of the
challenges? So if you brought in
a robotics person, the robotic
person may not know anything
about the wall, but can keep the
robot running, as you're saying.
But so if you work with a taper,
then, like, what would have been
some of the challenges of
working with the taper kind of
bringing the robot to the craft
instead of the craft to the
robot? is what it seems?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, yeah,
that's a really good way to put
it, it really is making it super
easy to use, right. And so
because we want their time that
they have, right, where the
robots running autonomous to be
doing other things, like we
said, coordinating, tackling
tough spots. So it's really
about like, making like a tool,
right, they learn it, they do
come to a training and Canvas,
but after that, they should just
keep on running. Right? They
it's sort of be asking them
things in a robotics manner,
right? Like, would you like to
increase your workspace? Right?
That might be a little bit or
like, Hey, your inverse
kinematics failed to solve like
that, that would have mean
something to them, but something
like, Hey, what's the body look
like to you? Right? And that's
more your, I guess, specific
example, for example, we
wouldn't be like, is the
thickness, you know, 1.2
millimeters as specified? They
don't, that's not what it works.
But we could say like, Hey, do
you think this needs more
material added? Right? Yeah. Are
there most faults? Are they have
spots, that's language that they
know, that then we can translate
into? Okay, they said there was
low spots, we gotta build up
more material here, you know, go
from 1.2 millimeters to 1.4. So
I think it's a lot about think
about translating things to the,
you know, the words around them
that the craft words, if you
will that make sense. And then
really making sure that your
robot is a tool, right? Not
something that has to require
programming. We also haven't
really kind of on site support
within the user interface. So
when they do run into these
problems, which they might,
there's somebody just on the
other end, to keep them running
and to do that kind of debugging
that you'd expect a roboticist
to do.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So what
does the whole step setup look
like in terms of even the
infrastructure behind the robot?
Like, I guess it gets to the
business model? Is it like you
lease the robot to a company and
then you surprise the service?
Or how does it work?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, we are
doing a leasing model for the
customer. So they come to get
trained, they trained their
operators, and then they lose
the machine, you know, for year
long leases. And then they have
different projects that they
would move in, we help them with
the logistics of moving the
machine since it's something
new, but from the other part,
right, they pay per day, and
then they have access to all the
support around so they have
remote support that they can
call that's usually the what
they would normally use. But if
you know something really big
happened on site, there's also
people from campus who can go
and support them on site. And it
was a problem if needed. It's
very rare. But it is something
right now, we're only in the Bay
Area, because one of the things
we wanted to make sure is like,
be really successful in a small
radius, such that you can ensure
that your customers get their
work out the kinks, keep them
running, for sure. Actually,
when we first started, we did
the service ourselves. So we
became drywall subcontractors,
and hire tapers onto our
payroll, and have our own people
running it right. And that was
really important. Because for
the customers, I'm excited about
the idea of a robot. I'm not
really sure how it's gonna work
for me. So we said, Fine, you
buy drywall at $1 for you know,
certain dollars per square foot,
a canvas the same amount. And
we'll get it done, right. We
just got into AP robots that do
it with our operators. So that
was the first two, three years,
once they started working and
really like saw how it works,
and they're like, oh, okay, this
works into my workflow. They
started saying, Okay, now we
want to run it right? We want to
scale up with it. So that's
really the transition point
we've entered around the middle
of last year is really saying,
okay, the robots that a state
that you guys can run it will
rent it to you and we'll help
you make sure it's successful.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. That's
really Cool. So it sounds like
it was extremely iterative to
get to where you are now, would
you? Would you tell me a bit
about that like, so now, I
assume you guys are somewhat of
drywall experts. But like, you
have this problem, and you think
it's going to be a valuable good
big value add kind of thing. And
then you start in this way that
you were talking about where you
work with the contractors, and
you basically become the
contractors, but hire people to
amend your robot. And then
growing that to the point where
it's like useful enough that you
can just give it to that
contractors to do with
themselves. Like, just tell me a
bit about that whole process?
Maria Telleria: Sure, one of the
big things from the beginning
has been testing on site as
quickly as possible, right. So
the very early tests, like, I
mean, probably now I'd be
embarrassed to call that a
robotic system. But you know, it
has to be moved manually
Audrow Nash: to cart. It's so
funny that one
Maria Telleria: of our team
members is much stronger than
being so he had to come to every
site because exactly how to
position the robot. But it was a
way to do point break on paper.
And in the lab, there's a lot of
value. But we all know that the
real issue is this. So we took
out that, you know, cart with a
robot arm demonstrated that they
kept iterating, right? We're
like, Okay, we can't hire, you
know, just a person to move the
robot. So we ended the mobile
things, and all of that. In with
that we did learn a lot about
drywall finishing itself. But
even before very early, when
we're going to do drywall
finishing. Yeah, let's hire
somebody who knows what the
drywall finishing is. So we
brought on team members who, you
know, years of expertise, you
know, journeyman unique people
themselves who just been trained
in that skill. And when I sat
next to them, I really said,
Okay, how do we get to that
level? The really interesting
part, their radius, and we were
both learning from each other,
right? Because people have
optimized the street incredibly
right standings that were
sparked. So they bought to my
stick to reduce the amount of
Sandy. You know, so when we've
reached brought them in, and
what I think a lot of people
think with robotics is like,
Okay, well, let's do what the
person does. But we have to take
a step back and be like, your
constraints are different,
right? Yep. Standing robot
doesn't care, you know, I'll
say, we'll spray whatever you
tell it to do, it'll do it. And
so if you remove that
constraint, maybe you approach
it differently. And so you sold
the video, we applied all of the
material in one go, and then
Stanmore versus a person applies
that day over day slip, slip on,
sorry, slowly building up the
profile that they want to get,
and then just stance a little
bit at the end. So
Audrow Nash: is it so it dries
like you, you keep letting it
dry, so it drives very evenly,
because you do like thin layer
after thin layer, where each
layer can be quite even. And
therefore the whole thing
appears even?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, it's
really minimal. That minimal
sanding and you need to use kind
of the data breaks of the sheets
gonna look like this, there's a
gap between them and use the
edges to apply the material, but
then that shrinks. And as it
dries, so then the next day, you
come in with like, a little bit
bigger, and you use the next
data. And this is how people do
it, right, because they need a
reference point, they need to
touch the wall. And it means to
your point, they have to be thin
layers, they have to wait till
it dries, even though maybe
they're done for the day. And
they're like, Oh, I wish I could
apply the next coat. Because
it's right, you can't do
anything. As we looked at me,
like, oh, robot doesn't need
that data, right? It has this
really good map around it. It
can spray material very
consistently versus a person,
right? Imagine trying to move a
point one meters a second, for
eight hours a day, might be a
little hard. It was sitting with
each other and be like, Okay,
you guys do it this way. But
you're also really good at
adaptability, you're also
getting the world's best
feedback control system through
vision to touch right, the
amount that they gather through
their touch is incredible. And
then we said, well, robots don't
have that. But they have really
high repeatability. Right. And
that's it, they don't get tired
of sanding. So is it Oh, and
then let's make the process a
little bit differently. Let's
make a process that the robot
can be successful at, apply all
the material ones, and then sand
a lot. But you're really using
the things that the robot is
good at, and not depending on
what people are good at.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So I
imagined during this, there's a
lot of like, picking the brain
of the tapers, and your roll up
your roboticists to really try
to understand kind of like,
what's the whole process what's
actually being done, not just
the way that they do it, so
you're not trying to recreate
what they're doing. And then
from there, you try to then
optimize for what's best with
the robot, given the way that
the robot behaves and what it's
good at and what it's not.
Maria Telleria: Exactly, yeah, I
think that's the right way to
think about it is like what are
you trying to accomplish? Not
necessarily how but let's start
with what are you trying to
accomplish? And then we can work
out the how and the actually are
the people we had to reassess
our superintendent. You know,
she came with all this
experience. So one of the first
things she was like, You guys
have to take care So you don't
have all the engineers out there
we take. I don't think we've
passed her quality standard yet,
but she lets us run the robot.
But it was a little bit of like,
yeah, I understand why you're
doing it. And it was seeing
those things and understanding
that we're like, Okay, well,
that would be difficult for a
robot. What were you trying to
do is create this profile? Okay.
Well, there's other ways to
create a profile, right? If the
same constraints,
Audrow Nash: can you tell me
some of the difficulties about
spraying and sanding that you
guys came across?
Maria Telleria: Definitely in
the spring side, right, that
that consistency, you are the
one deliver delivers about three
and a half gallons per minute.
So it's a lot of material coming
pretty fast. And you have to
apply it fairly consistently. So
that all sounds for you don't
robot can do that. The problem
is more. And I guess, upstream,
if you will, the materials that
have been developed so far have
been for people. And so they're
not very tightly controlled
materials, right? The viscosity
varies widely, which when you're
assuming that you have the same
viscosity, and you get the same
result, that assumption, yeah,
exactly the problem versus but
from the manufacturer side,
they've always had the person in
the loop. People like their own,
you know, viscosity, so they add
a little bit more water a little
bit less. So it's, for them,
it's also not worth it to
optimize to a certain thing,
because people are so varied.
Right? So you, that was one of
our biggest challenges. We're
working with a material that is
not designed for robotic, right?
Imagine like paints that go into
painting your car, I'm sure
there's very little variation
when they go into that paint
shop. Right? And then the robot
sure does its thing, and it's
going to be great. We were
working with materials that
weren't designed for that. So we
had to think a lot about like,
how do we close the loop on
that? And again, hey, how do we
use the operator who knows that
to help us close the loop? So
the the helped us a little bit
with preparing the material to
the right one, but also
providing that feedback of it's
still in? Well, I would say
that's the biggest challenge
with the spraying is the
material itself and modeling
that.
Audrow Nash: So how does it
work? Now the person gives you
feedback on how it is, but they
do some prep work. So make it so
it's like a fairly consistent
viscosity, or
Maria Telleria: we'll kind of
give them some guidelines, but
they do have to the material
comes in, it's a little too
thick for spring. And so they
have to thin it down with some
water. But this is where we've
seen right at the beginning, we
were like, only at this amount
of water, you know, and that's
where they provided the feedback
and a lot. So that we started
being like, okay, let's be more
descriptive, get into this type
of consistency, right makes me
think of the baking shows, to
the peaks. So we started being
more rounded, like, Okay, what
we really need to do is to get
it to this consistency. And then
they use their own feedback
system to be like, Oh, well,
this batch was a little bit more
liquid, I'm only gonna add half
the water that I normally do our
dispatch in this actually
temperature dependent to when
it's really cold and material.
So yeah, everything that could
be different about it are
processing. So as a couple,
everything is variable. And we
need to declare a process that
achieves the right result, even
with all that variability.
Audrow Nash: Have you ever I'm
sure you consider this, but I'd
like to hear your thoughts on it
anyways, did you ever think of
working with a manufacturer of
these materials to try to like
get them to control it pretty
consistently. So you could, I
don't know, work with it more
easily.
Maria Telleria: Like where your
head is that we have, and
they've been really great. I
think they also see a place
where introducer robotics,
robotics also allows you to
maybe improved on the materials,
because again, your constraints
have changed. So they've been
great. We've been working with
them for since the beginning,
really. But you also have to
manage that when, like, what's
already acceptable on site. So,
you know, we kind of did it in
parallel said, like, let's work
with, again, as few barriers as
possible for our customers. So
you know, no map, no, this.
Okay, let's also develop the
site because there is a future
work, you know, don't have a
better result. So that's
happening. Yeah, they've been
great. I think they also see the
vision and especially their
scientists get excited, right?
Because, like giving them a new
design space, the design space
for people, is this, the design
space for robotics, like, Oh,
you wanted 1.3 millimeters
thick? Done? We'll do that for
you. And then what? Well,
Audrow Nash: that's so funny.
Yeah, it is interesting. It's so
it's so interesting to consider
when you change the constrained
space, like you were working
with people, people are really
good at certain things, not good
at other things. And now you
take a robot totally good at
different things and bad at
other things. And so it's like,
okay, you can use the best of
both. And this is very
interesting. It's an interesting
spot to be.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, they're
just like, Oh, these ideas like
constrained space of cost,
because it is a very labor
intensive task. The materials
budget, if you will, is very
small, right. It's all when the
cost has gone to labor.
especially as things get harder
and harder, it's just so with
the materials manufacturers will
also have that conversation of
like, hey, maybe you can have a
little bit more expensive
material, if it gives you more
productivity. That works, right.
And so they also start seeing
the idea of maybe there's
greener materials, you know, or
materials would better, and
properties, right? What if we
could have better sound
absorption in your drywall
walls, or you get into really
cool spaces once you start
opening up that space? And so I
think we're really excited for
that future where you a robotics
coming in also change some other
of the upstream
Audrow Nash: assumptions. Yeah,
it's so interesting. So if you
can almost, I mean, like, if you
take this to the limit, where
you have like, infinite robots
flying this and all the dry
walls are, so then you have the
robots already. And then it's
basically free to have the
robots do it other than like,
the cost of energy and
transporting them and this kind
of thing. And then maybe, like,
really nice, highly optimized
materials, because and then the
materials cost rises. But the
total cost even in like, would
be less because the robot would
be affected, effectively free
labor. That would be very cool.
I like where that the like, new
potential optimisation space? Or
I don't know if space you can
optimize? That seems awesome.
Maria Telleria: Oh, yeah. For us
the you know, it really, we will
always have that operator in the
loop. So it's about their costs,
because there'll be time
spreading it over more square
footage, right? If Yeah, I
produce 1000 square feet in one
day. That's something if I could
do 2000 square feet. Now there's
that ROOM FOR THEM materials,
there's that room for that
optimization? So no, I think
that that gets pretty exciting
for us. And it also protects
their themselves where they can
have a longer career while we're
working with better materials
and better things. So it's kind
of this win win by really
thinking about that
augmentation, because it's about
the how much can that person
produce? Rather than replacing
them? Not necessary? It's better
to augment what they can do.
Right? Yeah, not necessary,
Audrow Nash: and probably not
even possible to because you
need their expertise. I was
thinking, it's a little bit like
the grocery store model, like
the clerk where you have one
person Manning 10, registers,
but this kind of thing, but it's
also different in that the
person is highly, highly
skilled, which may puts it into
an interesting space.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, that's a
really good analogy. I think
this idea of like, I can
supervise more, but you know, my
job does change. Right now
they're much more technical it
is, they're much more customer
success, right? Making sure that
they're making these things.
It's kind of how things evolve.
But if you completely tried to
remove the person, I think once
your body senses to that gets
really hard, why not utilize
them with their best, like,
utilize their, you know, their
adaptability, their smarts? We
don't have to wear down their
shoulder to get this word. Yes.
Audrow Nash: It sounds awful.
For sure, for so with this, I
How, how has the building
climate, like economic climate?
And in that, like I've had
several interviews, where
there's shortages and people to
do different work, is there a
shortage of tapers? Or is it
like, does this let you stretch
it taper to do what 20 tapers
could do? Or like, is there a
big shortage there? Also,
Maria Telleria: construction is
facing an incredible shortage,
you know, across all traits.
vaping is definitely one of
them. It's you know, one in 40%
stand shoulder surgery. Oh,
that's so bad. Yeah, yeah. And
you know those things, right.
They maybe fix it, but it's
never the same. And so they
often either have to retire
early, or you know, work live
with that pain, which
Audrow Nash: is that's because
of the sanding, the like,
Maria Telleria: sanding, that
repetitive motion on your
rotator cuff. Right? Oh, god.
Yeah, ceilings, also really
hard. There's also a dust, which
the sandy part? Exactly. They
optimized to reduce it, but it's
still there. And even if you're
not standing that much use the
tools that they pick up, you
know, 10 to 20 pounds and their
hours. Yeah, that's crazy.
Somebody's just wears down on
you. It's icy really? Yeah,
think about that. The it's been
really hard for like the union
where we work very closely with
to recruit new people. You can
see that right. It's like, such
a really good paying job. Like I
said, it's amazing the skill
these people have, but when you
put them in front of like, maybe
he'll return 50 Your shoulder
will be blown out because their
shoulder. Exactly. And you're
definitely be hurting. You know,
at the end of the day, you're
gonna have a long day and you're
just Yeah, so I think it's hard
for them to bring in thankful
dust themselves, right? They're
having a really hard time
bringing people in, even with
the people we have. There's a
lot of work right, we have to
double our building stock and
there's just not enough people.
The shortage in construction is
just outstanding. Yeah. So how
do you bring new people in and I
think that's giving them to so
then you are excited to do that
work like Oh, for sure. You
know, I could protect myself and
then also for those people that
You do bring in getting more
done.
Audrow Nash: You're letting them
be, like craftsmen with
underlings kind of thing. It's
like the apprentice model. But
the robots are the apprentice in
a sense, that does some of the
work. That's really cool. What
do you so just Just curious on
your perspective on this? So do
you think it's the more skilled
jobs that are harder to fill? Or
the less skilled jobs in the
construction industry? Like, is
it? Is it the tapers or I don't
know, the general construction
worker? That I assume the
shortage is in both? But are
they kind of is it more in the
tapering area or more in the
general worker? area?
Maria Telleria: I don't know
exactly. But my sense is, in
general, everybody's having a
shortage, but you see it in
those harder on your body. So I
think they all have like our
journey men that we work with is
a believe a four year process to
get trained. So it's a long
apprenticeship. Similar
electricians have to have their
apprenticeship. But the wear and
tear is not equivalent across
trades. So I think trade like
drywall finishing, in particular
suffer from that, like, well, if
I'm gonna pick a trade, I might
pick one that is not as hard on
my body or before, they were in
a different time. And people see
you like our controller, and
they get excited, right? They
this is things that grown up
with, it looks like an Xbox
controller. It's a robot. So
there's also that like,
engagement of like, I'm working
with a really cool tool. So I
think between that in making
their day to day just be a lot
less painful. Yeah, it's the
right way to bring people in.
Audrow Nash: I imagine it's like
the you keep that because I
imagine that they got into it,
because they enjoy it somewhat
like the meticulous attention
required for this kind of task.
I imagine like I mean, I love
programming. And it's like the
same kind of thing, I imagine
where it's, I enjoy the details.
And so I can imagine them
enjoying the details. And in
this case, they get to they love
the inspection, they love going
this needs a little more of
this. And then the problem
solving that probably goes along
with it that I don't understand
what it would be. But so you let
them do that. But you let them
delegate all of that repetitive
work to the robot. That seems
really great to me.
Maria Telleria: Like you said,
Yeah, that's right that the
people have on their workers you
know, they love Yeah, created
that your wall looks amazing,
right? This those walls, they
call them like walls where you
have like, the skylight that
shines on it is glossy, when you
know, the architect really went
out laughing to get something
like that they look beautiful.
So there's a ton of pride and a
lot of our feedback with them
working especially on the user
interfaces, how do I give you
that ability to use your crap to
use that and get that
engagement, right? Because they
do want to keep that in theirs?
You know, they want to keep that
pride that's building up for
years of training, you know,
that you're, you're that person,
not everybody can do it. Right.
So even if I gave you the robot,
we could easily get you trained,
probably faster. But I don't
Audrow Nash: click a giant hole.
And it's like, no, no, it's
good. Other than that, yeah,
just put that picture as the
plant over there. Yeah, that
sounds very funny. Okay, so what
what other challenges did you
have with so sit spraying the
big challenge was the viscosity?
Were there big challenges with
sanding as well? Or was that
kind of straightforward?
Maria Telleria: No 10 Things
really where we started with a,
like a research phase, because
sanding requires contacting the
surface, right? A lot of the,
you know, robots started a lot
in welding. That was nice,
because you have that little bit
like, I don't have to be perfect
as long as I can get the arc
across it good enough, right.
And then of course, you say,
well control everything around
it, and then we're gonna get
there. But the moment you needed
to stand, you needed to have
that contract. And it's not
just, you know, the, I guess,
this sense of the wall, but
like, your angle of approach,
and that soft materials I was
mentioning, so that was a lot of
our work was like, how do you
make this thing happen without a
perfect map? Right? We do map
our own space, but you're gonna
get there's still
Audrow Nash: accuracy, right?
Yeah. So that's three
centimeters. Okay, that's pretty
big. For a precise job.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, exactly.
And so part of that is just your
project is
Audrow Nash: probably not more
than not much more than three
centimeters.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, it's about
Yeah, I'm gonna go two inches,
but like half inch drywall is
very common. I mean, we put up
Audrow Nash: yeah, that's three
centimeters or something. 2.4 or
whatever it is. Or so you.
Maria Telleria: So you might not
be right, you know, know
exactly, plus or minus. So
really about thinking about how
do you approach that Walbert? I
have a good guess where it is. I
have a good guess of the angle
that it is. But I want to make
that really soft contact, right
because I can scratch it. I'm
going to create more damage. So
this is where other research
came back to compliance. We
really thought that one of the
ways to get robots out into the
world is make them compliant,
right? They don't have To be,
have a perfect map as long as
you can tolerate that. And by
doing compliance, so we build a
ton of compliance into our
sending end effectors such that
you do your best to get the best
map, but then you say, at the
end of the day, I'm going to
have to, you know, start this,
the reality to like, the joints
will be like hump or zip. And
you don't want to like fault or
cut through that hump, you
actually want to write it out,
that's what people do is that
reflect is just the illusion of
flat. So you also need that your
Sandy had to kind of write that
hump and spread it out. So it's,
that was a lot of work. And, you
know, we have like, four years
of research with the government
before even doing this that
leverage.
Audrow Nash: So what do you mean
compliance in this? Is it like,
springs? Or do you mean like,
what what do you mean by
compliance? I guess?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, in
general, we're looking at it,
achieving it whichever way you
want, right? Because spring is a
perfect example where it allows
you to right absorbed that
positioning. Exactly. So we
look, you know, their spring
scampers, but also under your
control side, how do you detect
that compliance and react to it?
So you don't have to have all of
your compliance be mechanical,
some of it can be coming in from
your control system?
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So do you
do a mix, where you might have
some, you might have something
so you have the sanding head,
and then you might have
something where it can kind of
move a little bit given, like
with a spring? I don't know,
keeping it kind of facing
forward. But like giving up
giving a little bit if the wall
is a slightly different shape
than you expect? And then you do
it in hardware? Or in software
to where, hmm, and that's, you
kind of just do emulate
additional springs in the, in
the motors or what do you? What
kind of approach is that?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, there's a
few ways. But one could just be,
you know, enabling, or sensing
that mechanical displacement, if
you will, that you're having and
then utilizing your software to
give you a larger range, right?
So you're coming in like this,
and you're already detecting but
you're going to hit your heart
stop, you go ahead and like tilt
your arm, which some of it is
more like a feedback. But
there's other ways, right? How
you run your control system
around it, allowing me to, you
know, be tolerant, right? My
ultimate goal is not perfect
position. My ultimate goal is
perfect force, right? constant
force it elsewhere control
system.
Audrow Nash: Your goal is
constant force is that is that
that's really useful for
sanding. Interesting,
Maria Telleria: okay, that this
goes back to that hump where you
want to write those out and
like, apply the right force to
level it out. But I don't
necessarily want to grind down.
Yeah. Because that's even going
to get through the other side of
drywall. One of the big
challenge rates is it's not just
the drywall, but it's how it was
formed. So if somebody didn't
hanger very well, you have that?
And then how it was framed?
Yeah. So all sudden, you start,
like, there's a lot of personal
for sure. Yeah, they're the ones
who fix everybody's mistakes.
Everybody, it's true, right?
It's like accumulation of the
error that then you have to then
they refined back. So you need
that. That approach of, you
know, let's move that out, not
necessarily flattening it out.
Audrow Nash: So if you have a
hump in your drywall, so it's
hanging, and there's a hump, and
you're trying to apply a
constant force throughout it.
Now what I'm thinking, if you
had a point sander, like, then
it would just make everything
deeper, like shorter into the
material by the same amount, but
because you have a, I don't
know, a sander that has an area,
and you move it around, it kind
of averages everything out. And
that's why constant pressure is
important. Is it correct or?
Maria Telleria: Yep, that's
correct. Yeah. And then you also
have to look at, you know,
having your compliance also in
your tip tilt, so that you can
can also write out that thing.
Good. both axes, right. You want
to be able to
Audrow Nash: adjust different
ways. Yeah, I was. My
explanation was 2d, but yeah.
Yeah, I imagine the same thing
holds true. 2d and 3d for that.
Okay, and how do you get your
initial map? For the robot?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, we use a
lidar system to create our map,
you know, and then from the
point cloud, because this also
has to be fairly fast, right?
Anytime that you're not running
the tool, it's not productive
time. So from the point cloud,
find the planes and then work
off of those, subdivide them
into spaces. So it's a little
bit it's, it's a different
application, right? So much work
around LiDAR, some point clouds,
but it's what are you trying to
do with it? For us? It's finding
surfaces, right, as opposed to
maybe identifying objects like
an autonomous car has to do.
Audrow Nash: So do you? Is it
like a person carries around
something or do you drive your
robot by it or how does it work?
Maria Telleria: We drive the
robot by it. So the operator
they have a little like, do a
little loop and they get some
feedback from the user interface
if we're getting a good little
good map, and then they also get
to do once it pops up, they can
use again their smarts to say
like, I'm missing a wall or
something like that.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Was that
part pretty straightforward? Or
was that there? Was there
challenges there too? Yeah,
Maria Telleria: I would say,
definitely feels more
straightforward because it is
mostly a technical challenges.
And you know, sometimes I get
excited when we find just
technical.
Audrow Nash: Because it'll be
one thing that's relatively easy
and fairly established to Yeah.
Maria Telleria: Don't get me
wrong, right. It took a lot of
work and optimizing and getting
it right. And we're all still
tuning and stuff. But it is
something that like, it's well
within our control. And probably
one of the, it's a little bit of
a challenge. But also exciting
is the technology advancements
on the lighter side has been
incredible for starting. So a
lot of it has actually been
like, Okay, should we upgrade to
the next LIDAR? And that means
retuning our mapping algorithm
and so play that trade off. Yep.
But yeah, I like those
challenges that are mostly
technical, not that the other
ones are interesting. But
definitely, when you're trying
to change people's perceptions,
or construction business
alignments, you're just like,
well, that's a lot harder.
Audrow Nash: Oh, totally, I
think. To me, it seems like
successful companies are founded
on just a few very hard
challenges like one or like two
or something like this, this is
your sanding and spraying. But
if it was like every single
thing is an incredible, like
moonshot, then it probably
wouldn't be a good long term bet
for the company, because one of
those moonshots will be a giant
bottleneck, or those kinds of
thing. So it is nice when you
have just an engineering
problem.
Maria Telleria: definitely agree
that we think about it, it's
like, let's make sure you're
successful with like, just just
two or three challenges they're
picking up. Yep. And then we
talked about material
development, that's great, but
don't depend on that. It's a
longer timeline. But so we work
on some of this research on the
side. And as those kind of get
proven out, we end up but you
cannot keep this team running on
more researchy stuff.
Audrow Nash: And it's almost
like a parallel thread to the
main value add for the company.
So it's like, we're going to be
around in 10 years and like,
then maybe that'll kick in. And
we can have these conversations
now. But they're not like,
you're not waiting to be a
profitable company before. For
that to work. It's like, we got
it we can we can just make do we
have to mix it to approximately
the same consistency. And it's
all fine.
Maria Telleria: Exactly. Yeah,
just sure you provide value at
that point to the customer,
right? Because they're like,
that's great that you're gonna
do that in seven years. But I
have a project tomorrow, what
can you do?
Audrow Nash: And venture
capitalists are like, Oh, seven
years, I think you'll start to
be it's like, oh, it's a
robotics company with all got
all the infrastructure and
funding that that requires?
Yeah,
Maria Telleria: exactly. It is
definitely yeah, that's where
you I think you really want to
show this inability to get out
on site sooner. And so having
those things and I act, do you
know, where we began, where it's
like, keep the person allowed
them to do that helped you get
to that place, right? And that's
why it's both, I think, the
right way to do it for Mark
values, but also the right way
to do it. When you look at the
problem, you're like, Okay,
let's do that. Let's get the
person in there and help us get
out there.
Audrow Nash: And so I'm, I'm
torn between two segues for this
the first one. So how are you?
So we talked, I mentioned just a
little bit with like venture
capital in this kind of thing.
How are you guys funded?
Maria Telleria: Yet, we're a
venture backed, we raised our
series B, about a year, a little
bit over a year ago. So it's
been great. We previous to that,
like I mentioned a little bit
was we were doing research for
the government. So we did have
some NRA dollars. So it was a
great way to develop the A get
back to your point, to many
problems. So research was a
great place. So we worked with
NASA and Office of Naval
Research, they were really
looking at this, you know,
compliance in the spaces. You
know, they're the most
unstructured of spaces. So then
we we sold some of them. Yeah,
in construction, much better.
And yeah, once we really found
that application, that was
another decision for us is like
the, you know, the Swiss Army
knife of robotics. That's pretty
hard to do, right? Trying to
solve all those problems. So we
knew we couldn't just be the
construction robot that did
everything we've said, let's
find one trade, one task that we
do really well. Yeah. And then
from there, we can expand. And
so once we found the task, and
we had demonstrated that there
was value with the current
technical challenges as opposed
to future, that's when we went
and fundraise around and did a
follow up round in 2020. Gotcha.
Audrow Nash: That's exciting.
Oh, yeah. Can you talk a little
bit about kind of bringing on
investors and the process of
that because getting really
savvy investors can be a huge
benefit, but getting ones that
have like incredibly draconian
clauses and flood their funding
agreements can I've seen it kill
several companies? So I Assuming
you guys are doing fantastic,
like, it sounds like things are
really good. But would you tell
me a little bit about kind of
picking the right investors?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, I think a
big challenge is when your
hardware, you're already
probably looking at a different
space of investors, right? At
least here in the Valley. It's
like, there's so so many
investing firms, but you should
research what they invest in,
what are the pieces, right? If
they've never done a hardware
company, let alone a robotics
company. They might not be the,
the right fit. And early on, we
talked to everybody. And then
very quickly, you realize, Oh,
you guys are used to software,
and all the software? And maybe
that's, you know, you guys are
great. But do we really see
like, are you set up in a way
where your fund can support
something like where you wanted
them to have secondaries because
we know this is a longer process
that you kind of like they can
come in and reinvest in the
future around so like, have you
researched, you know, they're
putting x amount into your first
round? Do the reserve some
amount? They don't have to use
it. But do they reserve some
amounts so that when you're
raising your next one, they can
reinvest it? It's just a nice
way to support that it I think,
it just shows that they thought
through like, look, this is not
going to be one round hit,
right, we are going to have to
develop it just the nature of
Harvard, it's a huge, awesome
win rate, the defensibility is
much higher, but it is a longer
path. So a lot for us was really
a search problem, right? Find
those people who do, who
understood us. And then to your
point of like kind of that
relationship, who supported one
that company we wanted to build,
but also brought in maybe the
areas that we weren't so good at
right and provided that guidance
and really served as advisors at
the center.
Audrow Nash: Now, so you
mentioned you have like 40 jobs
or so done so far. So I assume
this means you don't have that
maybe you probably have less
than 40 robots with this, which
makes me think less than, like,
it's not a manufacturing
problem, really for you guys,
because it's kind of so this is
interesting to me, because it
changes possibly the type of
investor that you would want to
get. Would you tell me a bit
about this?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, that's
definitely a big challenge,
right? It's We're just two
things, the way that we're
looking at it is breeding a lot
of value with one machine. So
we're not going to be a consumer
electronics, Molly, right, where
it's like literal value, but you
still didn't really know that
you're doing great, right? It's,
it's a much different approach
is much smaller volumes, but
create a lot of value for them.
So that already changes your
perspective on how you're going
to manufacture. Right, you're
not talking 1000s of units to
your point, right? We're talking
10s of units now and then
scaling up from there. It's your
design space changes from when
building it right, there's maybe
manufacturing methods that you
don't have as high X as you
might, you know, you can't
injection mold every piece, you
have to come up with another way
because you know, every move is
so expensive. They're like how
many un 20,000,020 20
Audrow Nash: million. That's
that sounds.
Maria Telleria: So it just makes
it a little bit but it so it
just comes again to pay you
create enough value and then
your product of the lifetime to
support it, right? Because it
can be an expensive product. But
if it runs over the lifetime,
and brings in the revenue, you
can actually have very good
payback periods. And that's been
a metric for us, like, Hey, make
sure this robot pays itself back
in within a year. And then you
have a five, five year lifetime.
Yeah, it's a good business
model, right, as opposed to
maybe it could be something
cheap. But if it only brings so
little value, so I think you're
really like have to look at
payback periods, to see if your
hardware has the right thing.
And then work with your design
team to say, Alright, how do you
get a good cost? What with
without access to maybe the
cheapest manufacturing methods
that are out there?
Audrow Nash: Definitely, yeah,
it's a totally different problem
for this. And you can also kind
of embrace that it's not going
to be like the one off thing and
try to get it so you can make 10
of them at like, not very well
or not, like not as optimized as
possible to be the lowest costs.
But then you're focusing on kind
of the longevity of it, and then
it kind of pays itself back so
you can invest a little more.
How do you so I'm just
wondering, and maybe I'm a bit
naive with this how do you with
robotics being fairly new and
things coming out all the time?
Like you're getting a robotic
arm maybe it's fairly well
established? Maybe it's not and
then some of the light are how
do you predict how long
something will last is there?
Like like this kind of thing is
an interesting problem to me
because I don't know that every
part would have a track record
for many years.
Maria Telleria: Now you're 100%
corrected. Not every part has
said some parts do or mobile
basis actually we retrofit a
construction based on these
things actually fought for like,
I feel like you find everybody
years later be like, maybe
change the batteries. So it's
kind of going through your
components, and then also build
your model to be realistic,
those things that you're not
super sure about, or maybe
sensors that maybe they do have
the lifetime. But do you
actually want to keep it for
five years and be using that old
or the company could
Audrow Nash: die, and then it's
like, you have to support and
they had a closed, like a
closed, proprietary sensor
driver that you can access for
this kind of thing, no longer
works on a bun to 2026, or
whatever it will be in a couple
of years.
Maria Telleria: That's right.
It's a what we found is like, I
build that into the model. So is
that either we're not so sure
that the lifetime will be the
five years that we target? Okay,
just built in, that there's
going to be replacement parts,
or the ones that we're like,
we're not sure we're gonna want
to use this either company's not
stable, or, you know, there's a
much better sensor, why would I
still be using, you know, five
year old LIDAR technology when I
can get this one? That you build
that into your models? Like,
hey, there's gonna be so many
1000 flowers, so replacement
parts that I do over the
lifetime? Do I still get a good
payback period? Right? Does it
still pay itself off if I make
those changes, but of course,
you also don't want to be
changing them every minute, just
because it's a better sensor,
you gotta make that ROI analysis
for, for component, but do your
best and then keep really good
track, right, as we're out
there. We've been running now
for almost four years. So we
know that those machines are
still going. So that's good. But
you also have to keep track,
what things take your replays?
Was there any leading indicators
that could have told you that
you needed to replace that
before? A true failure? So you
know, predictive maintenance is
like this awesome future that,
you know, manufacturing and
logistics already has so many
cycles, but we're making sure
to, like collect the data. Now,
even if you're not sure what
you're looking for later, if you
have a failure, you can go back
increasing? A little bit more?
Yeah, what was my leading
indicator that would have told
me to replace it?
Audrow Nash: That's so
interesting, I've never really
thought about that. I really, I
like that perspective, you kind
of gather the data and then
after, and you just, like,
preemptively are gathering it,
because perhaps you'll be able
to see trends in the future. And
it's probably fairly cheap to
grab now. That's really cool.
Yeah, and I guess manufacturing
and logistics probably has that
down. But that's very cool for
you to apply to your systems.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, I think
some years ago, maybe the data
would have gone expensive. But
now it's so cheap that sometimes
when we do we need all this
data, that it's worth it to keep
it and then look back. And
there, there has been some
things where we've been able to
kind of look back and go, Oh,
okay, we saw that here. We saw
that there. Right? This is
starting to be at least
something to look out for,
right. And we put maintenance in
the week to service our
customers right after every job
that comes in and gets
inspected. And so we can at
least check for those things,
you know, and identify those
areas that okay, maybe built
into the model, that being a
batteries will be your place.
And let's go ahead and adjust
for that in the cost.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Now, this
question, I don't know if it's
too early. But I wonder what
you're thinking around these
lines. So in my understanding,
when you take venture capital
money, they're typically
expecting an exit I hear like,
the timeline they say is 10
years, but it's often a lot
closer to five. I'm wondering,
and so there's several different
types of exit events. You can be
bought by someone you can IPO.
Or you can wait, I don't know if
there's other things too. Are
you where do you think do you
think you'll have what kind of
liquidation event Do you think
you guys will have at some
point? And what are thoughts
around that? I suppose.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, I plan
around and we've always thought
is like, built a successful
company. So build with the goal
of IPO or something like that,
in your mind. If you're doing
that successfully, the other
liquidation events? Yeah,
exactly. It's your think when
you build too, like acquisition,
you get into a really tricky
spot, right? Where like, you're
now trying to guess what they
want, or you build so much into
them. And then they're like,
actually, we decided we don't
like B vs. sustainable company,
right? Build a company. That's,
you know, at some point, you
stop taking venture capital, you
can produce your own things,
right? We want to expand drywall
finishing is our starting point,
we want to expand and really be
the tool that you just know that
Oh, but structure you use
Canvas, great tool that you use
to make everything. And so make
sure that your models and your
plants are built to a point
where you do have that feature
where you can support that r&d
And the new product lines off of
what you're
Audrow Nash: growing and keep
building. I see. Yeah. And then
that
Maria Telleria: way, it's under
your control. You're building
what you want to build. And it
should mean that all your
liquidation takes care of itself
possible, right? And
Audrow Nash: you're basically
aiming at the one that gives you
the most option, in a sense by
being such a compelling business
as opposed to overfitting to one
customer buying you or I don't
know, or I've seen people be
like companies be bought when
they like Miss A funding round
or something like this, this
kind of thing. But if you stay
competitive and keep, keep
growing what you can do and stay
profitable? I mean, that sounds
fantastic. And then you'll be in
a wonderful situation to like,
get the best investor and all
this other stuff. That sounds
wonderful. Oh, yeah, shoot for
that. For sure. It's just an
interesting thing, because it's
a trade off in a sense with
venture capital, as opposed to
so you get to grow quicker, but
you are on their timeline to
some level, because you they are
expecting some sort of event
where they'll be able to get
their money out for more. And so
just working with that.
Maria Telleria: That's right.
And that continued progress
towards that event. Right. So
like, increasing validation with
ROS No, it's It's definitely,
you know, a decision that you
have to make and look at and for
sure, yeah, like you said,
speed, they definitely have the
what you need. If you want to go
fast, you just gotta make sure
that you can deliver and, and
you look each other in the eye,
and you're very honest, and
like, this is what we'll
deliver. We're looking, you
know, we talked about building
that successful company, what's
your timeframe? What's the
timeline? Do we all agree that
that's a reasonable timeline,
right? Have they been like, in a
year you have?
Audrow Nash: A five years, but
we meant to? We want a unicorn
immediately. Yeah.
Maria Telleria: And that was
actually that's a perfect one
for us with the expansion,
right. We knew that having been
in robotics for a while, like,
staying in the Bay Area was the
best way for us to move really
fast and iterate, right? And we
knew if we started shipping
these across the country or the
world, we're spreading ourselves
thin. And now you're dealing
with operational problems, as
well as technical problems. So
it's like, iterate here, the
market is big enough here. And
so we lay that in front of our
investors from the beginning,
like, Look, we're not going to
be that grow everywhere,
quickly. Nope. Because that one
area Exactly. Nailed it. And
then almost half the customers
be like, Why don't you come over
here?
Audrow Nash: I'd be wonderful.
Yeah, that funded growth would
be fantastic. When they're like,
We have a big project over here.
We need you over there. It's
like, I don't know, it's
logistically challenging for us.
Maria Telleria: And then we can
support it right, then your
support team is not eight
engineers that have to your
right your time. Yeah, exactly.
Audrow Nash: I'm always
surprised. companies doing that,
when they're like, we're here
and there. And they're there.
It's like you, there's 10 of
you. It's like how, but
Maria Telleria: that has been
the approach. I think that a lot
of firms and venture capital
firms have pushed and for some
models, I think it makes sense,
right? The first set the market
is more important than anything.
But once you when do you have
hardware? It'd be that easy.
Yeah. And it's
Audrow Nash: logistically a lot
of challenge to coordinate. I
mean, you have to like so even
if you're not going to fly one
of your skilled engineers there
when the robot is down for some
reason. It's still like, Okay,
now you need to train a few very
highly skilled technicians in
the area, and coordinate with
them and give them updates and
all sorts of things. So that
sounds hard to me. It sounds
like a smart approach to stay
just in the Bay Area. That's a
hell yeah. Let's see. So now the
other really interesting thing
that I was thinking about with
the Segway earlier, you are
working directly with unions
with your robot, and then just
tell me a bit about that.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, when we
first started writing, we were
learning about construction and
found drywall finishing. It was
actually interesting, because we
weren't thinking as roboticists,
I would hear drywall screenful
We were thinking of being in the
sheets. And it was talking to
construction. People were like,
oh, yeah, that's hard. But let
me tell you. We don't think we
had even thought about that. And
no, it's like this perfect. That
was it. As we looked at a right
one was look at your market,
right? And we want to we just
talked about it, we want it to
be in the Bay Area, state type.
commercial construction is what
makes sense for robotics, right?
Unless you have a pretty big
house, maybe the logistics of
moving the robot might not make
sense instead of the square
footage your house has to do. So
we knew that there was like a
minimum project size that it
makes sense to maneuver a robot.
And so that was like, okay,
commercial area. It's a Union
Market. Right. And I think that
could maybe upstairs a lot.
People will be like, Alright,
Audrow Nash: here's me. Yeah.
But I also don't
Maria Telleria: know, it's a
little bit of the reputation,
right, like unions are hard to
work with. We just said, Let's
go talk to them. Right? Like,
why assume this thing is I'm
sure they, you know, have heard
things like robots just wanted
to take your job. So we each
have our own biases. Let's just
stop. And so we reached out to
them and just said that pretty
much I think we even maybe we
have that prototype with the
cart. It was it was pretty
rough. But we were just like,
hey, we don't have the tool yet.
But we want to invest our time
to develop a tool for your
trade. What do you think? And
kind of like we're like, Yeah,
but they're just like, all the
things we talked about. Like we
can't get new people in the
trade. You know, there's more
work out there that we can do.
And we're kind of tired of you
You know, all the injuries that
we have and everything. And the
last piece to their product,
they have recognized that in the
past, they had to post new
technology. And the result had
always been loss of market
share. So they're like we we
post certain things, we lost
residential. And so there was
also like, that really nice
reflection on there and like,
okay, that's exactly what what
did we oppose, you know, painted
our union to split the drywall
finishing and painting even
those two different traits. And
so they had lost a lot of the
big market by opposing the
airless sprayers. And so they
were like, Okay, we learned our
lesson. Let's got it. And then
we, there was also that
seriously being like, we want
you all to be running the
machine, right? We want the
tapers to be the ones running.
So I think that was also like
where we both were looking at it
as a shared future. And then we
committed when we became a
subcontractor. We said, We'll
sign the union agreement, right,
we want to work with you all
here in the Bay Area. And so
they've been great. They've let
us test at their facility, they
have this really cool facility
with all these like doors and
windows, right? Because they
have to train around them. And
so we bring the robots. So they
just been amazing introduction,
we run user studies and a user
interface with their members who
maybe never seen the robot says,
hey, if I just showed you this
with you, what would you think
it does? And so they've been
really a great ally in building
this and then supporting it, and
then getting people trained in
using it.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So with all
the, I guess, the so the union,
their job is to protect the
people who are in this trade.
And so then you're coming to
them. And you're saying, well,
they recognize that the people
are hard to find people are
leaving with injuries, they're
losing share, because maybe
other people are coming in, that
are not people in this union,
and doing similar jobs. So then
you come and you say, I have
this robot, it's going to make
it a bit easier for your people
to be efficient, they won't get
as injured. And then now you two
are working there, you and the
Union are working together, you
being canvas. And now then
there's a bunch of mutually
beneficial things that are
occurring that you were saying,
which is like they're helping
with training, they're probably
helping you understand the
landscape. A good bit better.
Would you tell me a bit about
that?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, I mean,
the cool thing about the union
is like, all of the people who
do this are on Well, in the
market that we serve are in the
union. So we have to sell to all
the different customers, right?
We don't sell to the Union, we
sell to the people that employ
them. Yeah. But they have kind
of like the gather knowledge of
the market, right? They know
which companies busy, we know
which company likes what,
because they have to work with
them on a day to day basis. So
they do have kind of that more,
if you just talk to Yeah,
exactly. What are the customer,
you might get, like, a little
bit of a bias or something. But
if you talk to the hub that
hears that, you know, these 20
customers? Yeah, exactly. They
can help us. Okay, we're hearing
this helpless translator oh,
what's happening is blah, blah,
blah, or no, that's customer
specific. Let me tell you a
story. Right, like the
background like, Ooh, yeah.
Yeah. And then they speak for
the people right at the end of
the day, because the customers
is the labor right is not like
their employees that you paid
the union wage. So they also are
better to speak for the people
doing the work than maybe our
direct customers who are more
part of our costs, right? People
are part of our costs, but
they're not necessarily our
employees. So I think it's also
good to touch that there.
Because if we just touched our
customers, we might miss
something about the people who
are doing the work, right.
They're just one step removed
from them.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, that's
clever. It's funny, because it
sounds like it sounds like it
was initially a hard decision to
decide to go to the union. Like,
it's like, do we just avoid
them, and then try to do
whatever. And then it turns out
to be this big advantage.
Because they connect you to
everything they kind of let you
in on this. And then it's like,
once you're working with the
union, now everyone in the union
is aware of this great thing
you're doing.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, that's a
very good summary. I'll say the
first decision was stuff. I
think there was a lot of people
advising against it, correct?
I'm sure. I've seen it not play
out well, or different things
are like, hey, maybe go to them
once you're pretty well
established. Right, you know,
negotiation table. And we just
decided to go with the approach
of like, Hey, pretty honest.
This is what we have right now.
It's not great. But we see the
potential. Do you see the
potential and by having that
relationship early to also felt
a little bit like there wasn't
like, they would have heard
about us, right? And they would
have been like this like you're
developing around, versus like,
know when customers can have you
heard of the trophy? Like, yeah,
we're working with them. We're
like, oh, so it also helps with
our customers and even their own
labor force who might be scared
if they heard of this thing
versus the union telling them,
Hey, this is why we're
supporting it. Let me explain.
So it also helps with those
misconceptions that you have.
Audrow Nash: That's interesting,
does it? We're so I'm not
terribly knowledgeable about
unions. Is this union, like
local to the bay? Or is it
California wide? Or is it us
wide or international? Or how
does the union work?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, it's both
right. There's the larger
international national unions
more more national, but they
have kind of their locales, and
they can run independently. So
when we say working with the
union, it's been directly
working with the DC 16 Is that
district council that we work
with directly because they
represent that area. So that
also made it easy. It was like
this conversation directly with
each other. There's a larger
union of unions, if we will, but
they all kind of report. They've
been great at saying like, hey,
once you guys are ready, we can
also introduce you to our
friends, right. And I'll say
thanks. But at the same time, we
were in like, Let's not fight
off too much. Let's start by
this your piece of the
agreements, were only with them
to start with.
Audrow Nash: And as you were
saying earlier, make it so
they're pulling you over, like
please, please bring your robot
over to us and somewhere else.
Okay, has there has there been
any challenges working with the
union?
Maria Telleria: Trying to think
I think there's always maybe not
union specific, but just working
with the labor force, right,
that has misconceptions about
recordings? It's always
difficult, right? I think
there's a lot of that, you know,
why are you here? But no, I
don't think there was anything
specific about the union, right?
The agreements get to be more
complicated, but lawyers will
understand that. So as an
engineer, I don't have to figure
out what a collective bargaining
agreement is. Yeah. But that the
details, right could be
overwhelming if you're not used
to. But this is worth getting
people who understand this, what
are their ultimate goals? Let's
find a way right? Because that
agreement, for example, didn't
have anything about a robotic
tool. So we have to work with
them to make sure that that was
covered. So just that I would
say, that's maybe more work.
That might be the only difficult
but the challenges around the
workforce have been more
general, rather than like Union
specific, more just the
misconception. Yeah. So
Audrow Nash: how do you how do
you address those
misconceptions? I guess you can
show them your robot. But any
like, I don't know, stories or
approaches you found that have
been really useful. I
Maria Telleria: think the best
one has been not me telling them
that it's okay. But people like
our team for tapers who have
trained with them, explaining to
them why it's a tool. Why are
two men right? I think there's
something about like, somebody
who's lived your shared
experience, who understands how
tough the work, so I can shout
it from the mountains. Oh, that
sounds interesting. But what do
you know, kind of like, yeah,
which is fair. And then both.
That's why having again, our
team members are experts be part
of campus, one of the directly
would tell us if we ever, were
not going in the right
direction, right, they could
race it, before we kind of
stepped into it in front of
everybody. They can raise it.
But then when we go on site,
they're usually the ones that
are most of our direct customer
success in the field is our
field team. Who knows? And so
when they expect, like, Hey,
I've been using it for two plus
years, let me tell you what is
good about it, like, let me tell
you what it's not. Let me tell
you what parts are why it's
exciting for me to use it. I
think that goes a long way. And
then of course, being able to
say like, look, we're working
with your union, like, you know,
what you've signed on to be kind
of like this agreement of
working together, making sure
that we're protected. And so
that also helps go along with.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it's very
interesting. And it's funny to
me, but makes total sense that
they are most except, or people
are, in general, most except
accepting of something when
someone kind of in the same boat
is like, no, no, this is really
good. As opposed to like, I am a
tech person. And I say this is
good. It's like someone who also
does this job is like, this is
great. This really makes our
lives easier than they support
it. Let's see. So another so
where do you see yourselves like
where do you see Canvas going?
In the next like five to 10
years?
Maria Telleria: Look, two big
areas, right? One is expansion,
like we will leave the bay area
that's coming sooner rather than
later. Right? We've tested it.
It's been successful on sites.
Now it's time to go out there.
We have the you know, we have
our support manuals, we have our
you know, instruction schedules
to feel comfortable that as we
expand, we're not going to be
stretching ourselves. So that's
one of the big areas in Yeah,
five to 10 years right cover the
metropolitan areas in the US
right New York, Atlanta. Hello,
so at least to start, right,
where there's concentrating
building. And then the other
area is on the, like I
mentioned, I want cannabis to be
the tool for other traits as
well. The benefit we can provide
with drywall finishing, it is a
particularly good trade for it.
But it's not the only trade and
a lot of the challenges that we
already solved our common right,
we live robot localizing
yourself breaking down the task
into workspaces, all of that are
common to other tasks. So I'm
excited by also starting to look
at those other pieces. And how
do we change the end effector.
To be able to tackle a different
trade or different types of
Audrow Nash: gotcha, that's
really interesting to you think
about how to use the same
platform, like basically a vase
with an arm. And what tasks is
going to do that makes a lot of
sense,
Maria Telleria: then you can
start optimizing in two ways,
right? One is like, which task
required the least change. And
that's exciting. But you also
might want to optimize by which
tasks are next to you in the
construction cycle. Because if I
can optimize protests, that
happens right after or right
before drywall finishing, I
don't have to move my robot
twice as opposed to maybe one
that's, you know, three months
before drywall finishing. So
there's two ways to optimize I
think, and we look for that
space of like, not too different
technically. But also, hey, I
want to target things
surrounding drywall finishing to
start to get the most use out of
my mobilization costs. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: And if there's any
intersection in those two
optimization problems, then you
could probably do that. And that
might have been what spraying
was after you did, Sandy.
Exactly. Gotcha. What do you So
you mentioned that, how do you
handle the logistics of getting
your robot to the actual
construction site?
Maria Telleria: We, like I
mentioned, we use a mobile base
or started with a very dumb, but
fake your bus to mobile base
that is using constructor, so
you know, it's a flatbed or just
a truck with a lift gate, and
put it into the machine, drive
it in and out at the site. And
then when we when the sites when
we come in, usually, you know
they're close off, elevators are
in place and everything. So
you're just gonna writing in as
if they were bringing in another
man lift, as they call them,
right? Just because people need
to realize we haven't talked
about that. But one of the big
wings of the robot is it can,
you know, lift up to in finish
up to 17 feet. Wow, that avoids
a person having to go up and
down. So it's all based on lift
in that norm that really
constitutes kind of a component.
Cool. And so but these are
common in the sense of people
have to go to the 17 feet to
finish. Yeah, yeah, we move it
very similar like to that they
moved this where you the
operator has the remote control,
they drag it around site, no
autonomy there, we just say,
Hey, this is complicated.
Operator, one to one move the
robot to the site. Yeah, once
you get into a space, now you
can start talking about some
autonomy.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Yeah. And
it's quick enough to just have
them drive around. And that's
really nice that it lifts to 17
feet, because I imagine I
imagine now, it's like, you're
hurting your shoulder through
repetitive motion of a heavy
object for eight hours a day.
But also, you're up high. And
I'm sure that there's, as you
get tired, there's more
accidents occurring when people
are like on a ladder, finishing
and you have to like, go down,
move the ladder, or if you're on
one of those, I guess if they're
on a lift, it's a little bit
different. Like one of those a
little
Maria Telleria: bit. Yeah, they
they'll drive it but in general,
your productivity usually goes
down to half a woman that is
about eight feet, because up and
down. Because think of the
material, right? You don't have
all of it. So you're coming up
and down. And like you said the
the moving and injuries. Yeah,
there's one of the biggest
sources of accidents in any
construction. Trade is that you
know, the moment you're on a
ladder, and it's hard, right?
People are tasked with, hey,
finish this much by this time of
the day. And so there is also
pressure to run. And so you
start seeing the ladder
scooting, or the you know, the
Audrow Nash: screws are, like,
hurt, and they bump over when
they're pretty good at it. But
yeah, you shouldn't do it.
That's why I imagined like even
like, if you could walk on it
for a little bit by tilting it
back, that would be horrified.
Maria Telleria: But it is this
pressure right to get the
productivity number sense. I
think it pushes people to, you
know, rush through things. So it
leads to more injuries versus
again, if your tool makes you
more productive. There's other
ways for you to hit those
productivity or get a better
update. Right? Hey, early on,
were this ahead or this much
behind? Let's, you know, let's
plan tomorrow. But even right
now, they have a hard time,
right? Because it's so hard to
track of all the work. So the
work the boss might just be like
faster, faster, and they're
actually doing really well.
Audrow Nash: Yes, actually, this
goes to something you mentioned
earlier. Reporting. Can you tell
me a bit about how your robot
does reporting on the task at
hand?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, I think
because we have that map. And we
can correlate back to the work.
We can report you know, the
square feet finished. And so
that already used to win. But
the other part is we changed the
process. So we apply all the
with the material in one day and
then sand in another day versus
a manual task right now it's
multiple steps. So if you're the
supervisor, you have to walk
around the site, figure out
overdue in step two or three,
and it's hard to tolerate that.
Audrow Nash: It looks the same,
basically, exactly.
Maria Telleria: If you're in
three, are you going to achieve
the final quality? And four,
because it's dictated by number
of steps, but the reality is
that they could be charged up,
right? If you're not doing a
good job in step one, you're I
don't care. You know, if your
step four, you're not done. So
they have a really hard time
tracking, what is the progress
on site, right? So they're just
doing their best to keep up with
the, with all the different
inputs to check everything out
and then calculate versus a
robot intrinsically right? You
ask it to report exactly where
are you in this? Like, I'm 50%
done, or I've done 400 square
feet? Because here's what I do.
Versus if I ask you to report
you'd have to look around you.
That was a little bit. This was
Yeah, I think I'm 30% done. But
you know, I'm not sure.
Audrow Nash: That's funny. Yeah,
it's nice that you can really
improve that reporting process
make it so much better. Like
you're like, we are 50% done by
square footage. And we have done
step one and step two, or
something. That's really nice.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, we found
that our customer spent like
four min, which are kind of the
supervisors spent four hours a
week just walking around trying
to figure out what that has
been. Yeah, exactly. That's,
that's a hard process to like,
and then coordinate with
everybody else around it, versus
I think this is the kind of the
exciting future of construction,
if you have all of these
progress reports, right? That
optimization is much easier to
say like, oh, well, we need more
painters, because they're
falling behind. Drywall is going
fast enough, like schedule this
and construction schedules could
start reducing versus right now,
because of all the variability,
they have to build a lot of
pillows and nobody wants to get
rid of those pillows. So you
know, projects take a long time.
Audrow Nash: Yes. Gotcha.
Interesting. Yeah, it would be
nice to make it more efficient,
because of those buffers that
are built in, you can remove
them, because you can have
really accurate reporting where
the robot goes, I know exactly
how far I am. And exactly when
I'll be done. That's really
nice. That'd be really cool,
too. As you guys grow and cover
more and more of the whole
construction space. You can grab
the all of those adjacent things
and make them really efficient.
That'll be super cool. Well,
let's see. So we're coming close
to the end of this, I'd love to
talk about you and your path for
a little bit. Before we end. So
can you just like at a high
level kind of say how you got
involved in robotics, and then
up to your consulting, which
then led you here? We're not not
necessarily consulting. But you
What are you doing? Taking
government funding? This kind of
thing? How'd you get here?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, happy to.
So I'm actually my co founder,
Kevin Albert, founded Rotary, a
research company within other
lab, which is really cool lab in
San Francisco that is, you know,
kind of academic life. But
imagine if the output is not
papers, but spinning out
companies, so they get a lot of
money through research, but take
on these challenges. I look,
they're just not ready for VC
funding, right? It's just way
too out there. But say, Hey,
this is where research money is
really great. And once you
figure out what company you want
to build, research, money's not
so great that they spin out into
your thing. But we had John and
I had originally met at MIT. I
was finishing up my PhD, and he
was at Boston Dynamics. And we,
you know, MIT and Boston
Dynamics, we're collaborating on
a project for the government,
research money, we're looking at
making really small robots. So
it's a little bit of a different
space. But the idea of like, Can
the design and the control
approach for the robot itself
allow you to go different
places, right, so these were
almost thought to be disposable
robots that were really small.
And so we met there, you know,
kind of connected, it was a cool
like, project, because it's so
out there. And, you know, for
us, students getting to work
with Boston Dynamics was also
really cool, right? These are
awesome. These are big dog he
was working with on that and the
algorithms for that. So it was
like, just such a cool
experience. You know, that. I
graduated, went and worked in
Lincoln Laboratory for a year,
which is I was still really
excited by new technical
challenges. It's a national lab,
right? They get to work on
really cool things, like, design
of telescopes and satellites. I
thought it was really cool. But
I had a really hard time with
the timeline to my project,
getting to see the time of day,
right it was these are like 10
year plus projects, because you
gotta go through everything to
get to launch so that they
didn't match as well. But I was
moving to California and you
know, you start contacting
everybody, probably anybody
who's moved across the country
who can give me a job. It was
funny that somebody was like,
Oh, do you know this guy? Kevin.
He was, he was like, oh yeah, we
work together. It's like, well,
he's hiring. He just got a grant
from the government to do these
compliance robots. Why don't you
connect? So it was like kind of
a fun, like, reconnect and be
like, hey, I want to move out. I
hear you have money. So the
source kind of the line where
he's got money to hire me.
Audrow Nash: Wow. That's so
funny. You're moving out. I hear
you have money. It's so funny.
Yeah, let's be friends
Maria Telleria: again. It was
yeah, it was just really cool.
Because, you know, the vision
was there. You know, what, once
he explained what his vision was
of like redesigning robots,
right, not just, from a software
perspective, all the way down to
the hardware, really rethink
robots, such that you approach
the problem of unstructured
environments, right. And he had
come from Boston Dynamics who
did that, but he wanted me to go
a little bit more into a
solution for industry, right at
that time, Boston Dynamics was
very research driven still. And
so yeah, it just kind of came
together in, like I said, we did
for two years of like,
discovered research. And then
once we cracked it, we said,
this is it, let's found it. And
let's, let's make our company
and fundraise. And it was funny.
At the beginning, we thought we
just leased the robots right
away. Or it does make sense. But
it was listening to our
customers and everything that we
were like, Okay, this will be
less friction. If you hired us
as a service, we can train our
own operators, they can sit next
to the engineer and complain
about everything that went
wrong, right. And so that's what
led us to the self contracting
route, to at least get the
machines out there and really
make it frictionless for the
customers while the machine was
getting to, you know, from that
prototype to that product stage.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Awesome.
That's cool to hear your whole
story, how it's kind of come?
Well, I mean, parts of it. It's
so I don't know, it's cool. I've
been struck recently by how many
companies start by doing like
contracting or whatever, for
government related research, or
they start doing government
research. And then that's like,
solving a lot of the problems,
kind of as you were mentioning
earlier, and then once you find,
like, Okay, this problem can be
solved by robots, then you can
jump out and do a company around
this. So that was the compliance
where Kevin was doing this was
did it? Was it this idea of
Canvas and dry wall robot? Or
was it just general, and then
you found this application?
Maria Telleria: It was more
general, it was really thinking
about compliance. And we had
gotten down to the level where
like, everything was, you know,
air driven. So like, the robot
was super compliant, which was
great for like, you know, we
were especially underwater, we
were actually hydraulic driven,
but you were super compliant.
You could sounds like a really
cool approach, but had a lot of
technical challenges for us as
we started solving. Exactly.
Some of them. It was also
looking at each other and be
like, Okay, we found the
application, what do we really
need our research, and that's
where it was like, okay, more
about the compliance at the end,
effector, you know, your whole
arm doesn't have to be
inflatable, for compliance to be
there. So we also have to leave
a lot of our research ideas
behind because they were more
research than they were
solutions, or
Audrow Nash: what was so what
were some of the challenges. I
don't know about? I guess I
don't know too much about your
past with this. But it sounds
like coming from academia to now
being in the startup, what have
been some of the challenges for
you?
Maria Telleria: Oh, I think the
biggest challenge was maybe the
mindset shift, right? I lost a
lot of academia, but also, they
didn't want to be in academia.
So Lincoln Lab was kind of these
happy middle steps, right?
Because you were still Yeah, so
I kind of baby stepped into the
world outside of academia
Audrow Nash: seems like most
into the real world that you can
be to me, because it's entirely
merit driven for this kind of
thing. And can you actually
provide value? So it's, I don't
know, you're saying baby steps,
but then it's like to the
bleeding edge kind of thing.
Maria Telleria: Yeah, there were
big, big show. No, you're right.
I think the first two were baby.
And then it was like,
Audrow Nash: Yeah, for sure.
Maria Telleria: It was probably
the excitement was always like,
building something new, or, you
know, designing something new
and different. You know, there's
a lot of ingenuity that's
optimizing and getting a better
cost or precision, but I was a
little more driven by, I want to
create something new. And so
that was kind of the thread
between academia. But then also
being like, you had to make sure
that you were okay, letting go
of those things. Right. And I
think that was yeah, that was a
real test that we were ready for
that lunch was like, can you
guys leave behind the things you
don't really? Right? I think
some people can't. And that's
hard, where you develop with
research and then you find this
perfect opportunity. But then
you take that same research
solution and try to apply it to
the real world and it starts
breaking on your academia rights
and things like that. Got you
up. Paper doesn't mean it's
gonna get you anything else.
Anything else? So I think that
was a good test for us. Like, if
we were ready for the launch was
like, Ooh, we really need this
arm that we've been working on
for, you know, Blood Sweat Tears
around and we were like, No, we
don't, we can move it to this
and you know, buy an off the
shelf. It was the time to do it.
Audrow Nash: That's so
interesting. It's so interesting
to hear that it was like a
process of letting go. Because
you can't carry all this stuff
with you. And so you have to so
that you can move forward.
That's so interesting. It's cool
to me how that's like a
psychological shift was
required. It's kind of thing.
Yeah. I would have never thought
of that. That makes total sense,
though. Very interesting. And so
coming from academia, kind of
getting into this and actually
being, I guess, what is your
experience been? Like? How have
you been thinking of this whole
startup time? I don't know. What
are your impressions so far?
Maria Telleria: It's, it's
awesome. But it's hard to like,
tell people were like, I want to
join a startup. Which one? Like,
I don't know, a startup on? What
are we doing? Just? Yeah, I just
started just for the road. I
think for me, it was more like,
I want to do this, the way to do
it is to do a startup, right? It
was more like the venue to do
it. And so then it was really
cool. I want to be in a company
that solving this problem,
everything okay, then you have
to build it right. As opposed
to, I just want to go through
the because it does have its
hard parts, right. I think it's
it's also interesting,
especially coming from very
technical background, both of us
like, at one point, you really
say most of our problems are not
technical. We get jealous when
the other one gets to do a
little bit of technical work.
Like, how do you hire people,
right? People have concerns that
you have to address, how do you
build a company that has good
values? And as things get tough,
you stand by those values,
right? And so those kind of
challenges, like you're not
thinking when you first pick it
right? You're like, how are we
going to solve it technically.
But as you've kind of grow,
those become some of the work
that you really have to do. And
I think there it has to be that
you have to be excited about
building company, because
otherwise, it'll just feel like
wearing down like I just want to
do and at that point, you might
say like, Hey, let's bring in
somebody to do the company
management. And I'll just do the
technical work. But we both kind
of really liked also the idea of
like forming a company that are
excited to go into everyday. So
that's why we got neck state in
those positions. Yeah,
Audrow Nash: I really like this
how it seems. So I mean, to me,
it seems like often the best
robotics companies are ones that
didn't decide to use robotics,
because like they weren't like
at the beginning, I'm going to
use robotics, they were like,
oh, robotics happens to be the
best way to solve this problem.
And for you with this company,
it seems like an analogous thing
where it's, I don't really want
to do a startup. But it seems
like the best way to make this
change that I would like to
make. I think that's really
cool. It's not and then it
sounds like also, as opposed to
the viewpoint of I just want to
be in a startup. It's it's a
very pragmatic choice. And you
are sustained by like, a larger
mission, which is to make this
change to kind of help this area
as opposed to I just want to be
in a startup for that startup
sake, it doesn't, I have no
greater mission for it, I
probably just want to be rich
one day, or whatever it is that
I think of startups for this
kind of
Maria Telleria: thing. Some
people have this idea of like
the payout is going to be great,
or I'll get great experience.
And that is a really good
target. Because you get the
Yeah, for me, it's definitely
more like, okay, I get to build
this I get to put into center,
right. It's like if something is
not the way I want it to be like
it's up to me go change it,
right. Make the company that you
want. So I think that gets me
through the days that are not
Assisi, Korea, and also through
the high skips you grounded,
right? Yes. This is like, oh,
oh, so much responsibility. To
do it, right.
Audrow Nash: Oh, for sure. Have
you? So in your experience
consulting or in academia? Did
you ever lead teams? For this?
Like, did you ever lead large
groups of people? Because it
sounds like you're very involved
in this now. And how has that
been for you?
Maria Telleria: I learned a
little bit even from in grad
school, I always enjoyed kind of
the mentoring side. So
undergraduates, you know, one or
two, yeah, one or two people.
And it's a little different,
right? Because it's it's smaller
scale, you can spend the time so
I knew I had enjoyed that I'd
done like, the, you know, class
projects and been kind of the
lead. So I was happy to go that
route, right. Like, I was like,
I want to make this versus other
people very quickly. Like, I'm
an IC. I'm great at it. Right?
But that's, that's what I want
to do. And you know, if you come
in with that self awareness,
it's always a lot easier as a
founding team, right? If
everybody knows, but once I
started another lab with Kevin
Right, it was like, thinking
myself and another person To
start, and then we started
growing, we needed more
engineers. And you know, he was
CEO. So he was running kind of
the sport. And I just kind of
said to him like, Hey, you cool
if I start managing this group,
right? It's, you're starting to
get a little bit late and things
like that. Yep. Of course, yeah.
This gradual, and I got to grow
with it, right? Because at first
it was like, three, report, and
then five, and then 20. And then
you're just like, Oh, so you're
just like, okay, it all cut out?
I love me the time to grow with
it. I imagine some other
companies have these humongous
steps. And Oh, totally, you just
roll with it? Yeah, so far, it's
allowed me to grow it. And then
the other piece of thing, like,
what areas are you weak on, get
somebody, you know, just be very
self aware throughout the whole
journey, because otherwise,
you'll just kind of bounce, you
know, hit your head against the
wall and be frustrated when
you're just gonna enjoy this.
Or, and or, I'm not that good at
this, either get training, get a
coach, but also probably get
somebody within the company to
help you with that.
Audrow Nash: For sure, yeah, I
think being really realistic.
And being like, I'm good at
this, I'm not good at this, and
US addressing whatever it is,
like I'm good at this, I'm gonna
do more of that. I'm not good at
this, I'm gonna hire that out.
These kinds of things that I
don't know, a very deep
connection to reality seems like
a really important thing to
startups success, in my opinion.
Maria Telleria: 100%
Audrow Nash: What would you so
advice for like, a 20 year old
you? Or something like this?
Like? What, uh, what advice
would you give to someone who's
like 20? Now, just starting
school, or in the middle of
school?
Maria Telleria: Yeah. From the
technical side, I would say
like, explore outside of your
domain, right? Your politics in
particular requires that cross
domain. But I think in general,
we're just seeing more and more
like jobs blending, right? I
don't think there's as there are
very few people who do one only
one thing, right. And so I would
say explore, really, even if
you're a mechanical engineer,
take some software classes, or
even sit in on those, like, get
yourself in there, do some
projects that maybe expose you
to that. And then that'd be the
other side of like, I was lucky.
And it just interested in
business, right, taking some
business classes at MIT and
participate in some of the
Entrepreneurship Center work.
But that exposed me to it. So I
think for people who are
thinking like, maybe I want to
do a startup, there's a lot of
opportunities to dip your toes
while in college and doing like,
you know, learning about
business plans and stuff like
that. And just kind of see back
to that really sick. Like, maybe
that's not for you, you know,
you might be really happy in a
big company, or something or you
know, a big national lab doing
just research or academia, but
kind of go out there and test it
out, rather than I think
sometimes you don't you didn't
like to hear the latest thing,
and that's what you're going to
do. I'm not going to be a
founder, I don't know what that
means. A lot about experience
using that time in school, it is
about getting the grade, but
it's also about like, what
awesome opportunity for your
students experience, like the
lectures that you get to go to
right that you're just never
gonna have the time to do that
kind of exploration, like do it
then and it's true. Get to know
really who you are back to that
self awareness, the more you
discovered, then the less 30
It's a lot harder to be picky.
You're self aware, for sure.
Audrow Nash: With all the life
things that come up. Yeah, for
sure. Okay, awesome. Where do
you so if you look out like two
and five years, where do you
think robotics is gonna go?
Maria Telleria: Definitely think
that there's gonna be a huge
growth in other markets, if you
will, or other areas, right? I
think logistics and
manufacturing, logistics and
manufacturing will continue to
kind of increase. But to some
point, we're getting to like the
optimization problem, rather
than the adoption problem. And I
just think areas like
construction, but there's so
many other ones are really need
that kind of productivity game,
we always look at that plot, if
you plot like manufacturing,
productivity versus
construction, manufacturing,
like 300% infrastructure and
decrease so we've actually
gotten less productive over
time.
Audrow Nash: And it's regulation
that just isn't it.
Maria Telleria: I think it's
Yeah, regulation. Just exactly
like your regulation, and then
don't give people new tools. So
you say I'm gonna make it a
little harder, you know, reboot,
people use these stills, for
example, to finish the line.
That's not very safe. I'm gonna
remove that. But you still have
the same tools. What's gonna
happen, right, or even the
designs got more interesting
people, architects got real
designs, but you still have the
same tool from 50 years ago.
Something has to give in product
and base what's given and so for
me, I really see robotics,
especially with the sensing
technology that we've gotten in
the computational power, but
also the approach of people
started approaching them
differently, right, more than
the Cobots more the
augmentation, you start opening
up the idea of like, okay, maybe
a robot is not a fixed equipment
but a tool I just see that
really exploding. And people
really being able to protect
their bodies more by having
access to these tools that all
of these kind of things are
coming together at this time. So
I don't think it'll be just
construction construction will
be one of the big ones, but some
of the other spaces will also
get really interesting.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Do you
have any links or contact info
you'd like to share with our
listeners and watchers?
Maria Telleria: Yeah, we always
encourage people to go to our
website at Campus dot build in
Yeah, you can reach out to over
you know, LinkedIn or over
email. It's just Maria Canvas
dot build. But we're always
excited. We also have an
Instagram that got to post a lot
of pictures on site. And I like
because you get to see the
reality right of like, what it's
like, you can see those nice
pictures where everything's
clean and the robots there. It's
beautiful. And then you see the
ones where there's buckets
everywhere that you go around,
and you're just like, oh, that's
why it's hard to be in an
unstructured environment. Yeah,
Audrow Nash: for sure. Oh,
that's so funny. All right. Hell
yeah. Well, this was a blast.
Thank you, Maria.
Maria Telleria: Thank you so
much. It was fun to get to talk
to you. Awesome. Bye, everyone.
Audrow Nash: I hope you enjoyed
my conversation with Maria
Delaria. Thank you again to our
founding sponsor, open robotics.
See you next time.