Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Youssef
Benmokhtar. Yousef is the CEO of
GelSight of Boston based company
that makes high resolution touch
sensors. In this conversation,
we talk about how GelSight's
touch sensors work, their new
collaboration with Meta AI,
formerly Facebook AI, to make a
new low cost sensor called
DIGIT, the digitization of
touch, touch sensing and
robotic, how GelSight is
investing in community and open
source software. And we talked
about Youssef's professional
path in several industries. This
is the Sense Think Act Podcast.
Thank you to our founding
sponsor, Open Robotics. And now
here's my conversation with
Youssef Benmokhtar.
Youssef, would you introduce
yourself?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Absolutely.
Youssef Benmokhtar, CEO of
GelSight and a high tech
executive for the last 25 years,
and excited about this interview
and sharing my thoughts with the
audience.
Audrow Nash: Tell me about
GelSight.
Youssef Benmokhtar: So GelSight
is a MIT spin off, we have a
very unique technology, we have
an imaging based digital tactile
sensing technology, which
basically allows us and our
customers to get a 3d
information of anything that
sensors in contact with,
regardless of the material
properties that is in contact
with, that's the essence and the
core of our technology.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, and so you
have several products that all
kind of work this way. Can you
tell me at a high level, how
they work? Like, how are you
looking at? How are you
understanding the deformation of
the material and inferring touch
information?
Absolutely. So we have
a unique proprietary elasomeric
material. That mean, so it
basically means it's a material
that has kind of elastic
properties where it can conform
easily to surfaces that is in
contact with, but still keeps
some rigidity to it and has
optical properties to allow
basically to be integrated into
an imaging system.
Audrow Nash: I'm picturing like
a transparent silicon. Is that
something like very similarly to
Youssef Benmokhtar: that?
Absolutely, you're right, it's
something very, so it's
basically a polymer like
material that lets lights go
through it. So the essence of
our technology is we have this
material, we we coat it with a
reflective surface. And we
basically eliminated with RGB
light, and place a camera behind
it. And now we have the ability
to, to take scans with these
cameras, using a technique
called photometric. 3d
reconstruction. And that's
basically the essence of gel
sight technology.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so let's see,
I've looked at some of the
images, and they're quite cool
from this technology. So it
looks like you have, so you'll
have the gel. And it looks like
you have the light shining from
different sides of the gel so
that it gives you different
shadows when the gel is pushed
into by an object, is that
correct? Or how does that work?
Like? How do you set up the
lights? Basically?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yes, I think
the lights is really more about
getting the most uniform light
possible. at different
wavelengths we use, we use red,
green, and blue. And making sure
that the surface is uniformly
illuminated, what each one of
these different LEDs. And then
we have a proprietary algorithm
that's using the images captured
at each one of these wavelengths
to reconstruct 3d from that.
Audrow Nash: Why, what's the
significance of different
wavelengths? why did why are
they necessary?
Well, that's the
principle of photometric 3d.
Audrow Nash: I guess, I don't
know very much.
Youssef Benmokhtar: So that's
something that I'm not an expert
on. I think that's something I
co founder could better explain,
since he's the kind of the
inventor and the one who
developed the algorithms, but
he's basically, you know, having
three images done at different
wavelengths. And knowing what
those wavelengths are basically,
being able to get those three
different images, he's able to
build an algorithm that that
builds 3d information from that.
Audrow Nash: So I'm wondering,
like, maybe this is wrong, but
this is how I'm thinking of it.
Perhaps having different colors
lets you separate them in the
image space, so you can get more
dimensions like you get
different views. So you get
different views from each of the
lights. Because each of them
casts a shadow. And so if you
have, say you do red, green and
blue lights, now you can
separate it into red, green and
blue in your image. And you can
kind of tease those apart. And
that might be more useful for
analysis and inferring 3d
structure. Does that make it
kinda like that? Yes,
Youssef Benmokhtar: it's kind of
like that. Yeah, absolutely.
Audrow Nash: Cool. And you
mentioned that the sensor is
reflective. Is that just on the
side that's touching some
object? Or? Yes, that's
Youssef Benmokhtar: correct.
Yes. Because basically, you need
that, that reflect that
reflection is what allows you to
build that 3d scan, basically,
Audrow Nash: is it reflective,
or just opaque for this guy is
actually it is reflective? What,
why do you want it reflective?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Because you
want to basically, you know,
keep the light within within the
system, you know, again, in a
very uniform way, so any kind of
light dissipation outside will
make the computation of the 3d
very difficult. So Oh, so you
want to have actually, you know,
I think opaque is actually
another way to look at it, but
you need to think about it as
it's very opaque, like light is
really not going through.
Audrow Nash: Oh, so you mean,
you're keeping all of the light
within the system, it probably
helps. You don't have to
normalize it, or something,
because you know, how much light
is in it. And thus, you can have
very accurate calibration, when
it corrects
Youssef Benmokhtar: graduate,
you avoid having to D noise and
other things like that.
Audrow Nash: Okay. So, what I'm
imagining that we have the
lights behind a piece of gel,
the gel at the front of it, and
the part that we'll touch
things, has some sort of
reflective or opaque like thing
that doesn't let light through.
And you push into the top of the
gel, the part with the
reflective part, and it deforms
it. So that, and then the gel
deforms, and you see kind of
like shadows or something within
the gel that you use to infer
how the 3d how the gel is being
deformed in 3d, correct?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yep, you got
it.
Audrow Nash: Now, let's see what
So how long has this method been
around?
So the company was
founded in 2011, I believe the
first papers describing the
concept were a few years before
that. Yeah, so I want to say
maybe 2009 is the first time
that this kind of idea was
described. And then our co
founders, Ted Ellison, who is a
professor at MIT, and his
student, Chemo Johnson, wrote
those papers, and got actually a
lot of interest, not only from
academia, but also from
industry. And that gave give
them an idea to say, Well, why
don't we just, you know, found
his company and and, and try to
do something with that. Just
respond to the, you know, what,
what they felt was a strong
demand signal.
Audrow Nash: Hmm. Why? I'm just
wondering, what makes like, I'm
sure that, like, so I have a
little bit of experience in
computer vision. And so thinking
about like, Okay, we want robots
to touch things. Now using some
sort of gel and looking at how
it deforms, to me, it seems like
a, like, kind of an AI solution
a lot of people would come to,
in terms of how to understand
touch. But I think that a lot of
companies have tried this kind
of approach. And I'm sure
there's something hard about it,
that has stopped a lot. Like the
fact that this technology is
taking so long, or is like just
coming about now, what's been so
hard about this technology.
Youssef Benmokhtar: I think
what's been hard, you know, in,
especially in the robotics, you
know, field is that, you know,
sensors were bulky, expensive,
hard to calibrate, so hard to
get actually repeatable
performance over time. And, you
know, really just low
resolution. And when I mean low
resolution, I mean, it's really
low resolution. So what we're
hoping at GelSight is that we
are solving all of those issues,
you know, with the, whether it's
the DIGIT which is now you know,
something that is, you know,
completely, you know, mountable
on a robotic hand, right. That's
what it was designed for. With a
price point of $300. That's what
we announced with Facebook. It's
available for $300
Audrow Nash: or meta now?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yes,
absolutely, absolutely. Right.
And also, we because we're
imaging based, right, the
resolution of our sensor is
actually directly linked to the
resolution of the sensor, the
cameras that we're using the
image sensor we're using. So,
you know, in the case of the
digit, I believe it's a, it's a,
you know, it's a VGA resolution
sensor. So you getting, you
know,
Audrow Nash: so for VGA, that's
like, that's one of the display
ports. And so is that 640 by
480, or 20? By 480. Correct? No,
why would know that? But
Youssef Benmokhtar: okay, yeah,
yeah. So so, you know, suddenly,
you know, you have, you know, a
million plus pixels to play with
all the other technologies out
there will give you in the
resolutions in the 10s, or
hundreds, you know, pixels for
the same surface. And now,
suddenly, you have this
amazingly high resolution
available to you at $300, in
something that you can mount.
So, you know, now, when you
starting to think about
applications, I think you have
something that is actually even
better than the resolution of a
of a human finger. So it puts
things in perspective, I think
AI technology helps to, you
know, bridge that gap that
existed before. That's why
That's why we believe it's
exciting. And for gel sight. You
know, we had also this
reputation of being extremely
expensive and big, you know, our
standard products on the 20 or
$30,000 apiece. But hey, we are,
you know, we are a company
that's able to do things, you
know, for different
applications. And in this $300,
you know, sensor shows that, you
know, we can do things at low
cost.
Audrow Nash: Yes, and I want to
talk about DIGIT quite a bit.
But I want to still talk, I want
to make sure I understand
everything pretty well, before
going into that. So one of the
big things that was really hard
with getting this into robotics
previously was probably that the
sensors were extremely bulky, as
you were saying. And so how have
you guys made it smaller? Like,
how, how have you reduced the
bolt?
Youssef Benmokhtar: It's a great
question. You know, the, what
Wally actually attracted me to
jail side is that at the core of
the technology, which which I
described, and I think you have
a good understanding of now, the
three pieces, you should think
about them as a modular
approach, a design approach, so
we can really be
Audrow Nash: modular and that
they can each be improved
independently,
Youssef Benmokhtar: correct, and
then put back together as a
system. So for example, into
your question about
miniaturization, we can design a
gel material a polymer material
that is specific to an
application like robotics,
right? And actually make them in
any x, y, z dimension that you'd
like, you know, it's almost, you
know, infinite from end to end
design space. And until that we
can, you know, put in LED
illumination, you know, in a
fairly easy way, these are not
big, you know, type of
electronics. And, and then the
challenge becomes more about the
image sensor that you use, and
most importantly, the lens and
the field of view of the lens.
And how close can you get it to,
you know, to this elastomeric
materials that we have, but you
can play with that, depending on
what the application isn't
Audrow Nash: work one more time
really slowly. It's so Marek, or
what is it? Elasto Merrick
sorry. Elasto Merrick. Yeah,
okay.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yeah, I try
to avoid using it from now on,
but that's yeah, I'm just
thinking they're so
Audrow Nash: clear pop
deformable polymer, Paul, yeah,
Youssef Benmokhtar: it's a gel.
You know, internally, honestly,
we call it gel. The easy way
that we think about it. But But
then it's to your question. So
what we did is that we basically
found what is the right surface
contact surface that would be
attractive to robotics
applications? And then how small
how thin can you make that
sensor by playing around with
the, with the camera module,
basically, and the field of view
of that lens? And, and that's
how you get something like DIGIT
in that kind of size. There are
ways actually, that we have
developed a gel site to make it
even thinner. So it we DIGIT is
not the limit of what how small
we can make things.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Okay, so we
keep mentioning digit. Let's,
what is digit? Could you tell me
a bit.
Youssef Benmokhtar: So DIGIT is
a basically a tactile sensor is
a digital tactile sensor imaging
base. It's basically in a job
site technology and in a meta
design. Facebook made a I should
say, sorry, has, you know,
identify the need to really have
this small, easy to integrate
into robotics hands and fingers
sensor to be able to develop,
you know, AI algorithms for a
bunch of different applications,
object manipulation, you know,
pose estimation and things like
that. And basically, we are
their commercial partners to
bring bring that sensor to the
world, we share the same vision,
we believe that digital touch
and feel is the next sensor to
be digitized. To do that, yeah,
that's right. And to do that,
you actually just need to make
it easy to use and affordable
and small. So that's, that's,
that's what we're doing
together.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, so DIGIT is
something that meta AI or
formerly Facebook, AI, research,
I don't know, organization or
part of Facebook that does
research and development for
that. So they created DIGIT and
they open sourced it. Correct?
Correct. So it's freely
available online. And then you
guys now are taking this and
building it at scale for this so
that you can buy it, and it's
out of kind of the research lab
and into the world. What, so it
was a research paper with maybe
like a demo and this kind of
thing. How long ago? How long
ago did Facebook or meta
release? This? The DIGIT design?
Youssef Benmokhtar: I believe
it's over a year ago? I don't
know the exact date. Wow. But
over a year ago,
Audrow Nash: yeah. And then how
did you guys? How did you begin
a collaboration to work on this
and produce it at scale? Like,
how did that how did it occur,
that they produce a paper and
now you guys are actually
manufacturing lots of these?
Well, I think the you
know, that's also a great
question to ask Mehta, but my
understanding is that some of
the researchers at MIT, I had
experience with GelSight during
their academic research. And
this is where they've learned
about tactile sensing, they've
learned about the GSI
technology, and you know, kind
of, you know, use that, that
knowledge and gain expertise in
academia, and wanted to actually
focus on AI, I think more than,
than building hardware. But such
a hardware does not did not
exist, and, and hence the need
to design it.
Audrow Nash: And you mean, it
didn't exist, because you guys
have your product line, but it
didn't exist in a way that was
affordable to like, put 10 of
them on to iRobot? Hands, one at
each fingers end? Correct.
Youssef Benmokhtar: And in the
right form factor as well, you
know, we had was way too big,
correct?
Audrow Nash: You know, so did
they come to you? And they were
like, Hey, we think it'd be
really cool if you guys could
work on this or, I mean, can I
know these details? Or can you
disclose them? I'm curious.
Youssef Benmokhtar: You know,
the way I would answer this
question is, I would say, we
have a shared vision. And, you
know, it was very easy to align
on this partnership because of
that shared vision. Yeah, and I
think, you know, when two
parties basically have the same
ultimate goal, which is, you
know, let's bring tactile sensor
to the masses. And, you know,
make it attractive for people to
want to research with it. Then,
you know, the rest actually
became really easy to do on in a
straight if part. And I believe,
you know, and I hope that this
partnership actually is just at
its beginning, and more more
will come from it.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. So So what is
the nature of the partnership?
Exactly.
Youssef Benmokhtar: So at the
moment, it is really about
GelSight, commercializing the
DIGIT design, and that's already
available for for people to
purchase through our online
portal. And it really, that's
the extent of, of what we have
agreed to do at this point. You
know, as I said, you know, more
is being talked about, I think
now, you know, that we've
reached that one.
Audrow Nash: Nice, what can you
hint at what additional steps
will occur or what they might
look like?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Well, I
think, you know, it's going to
touch upon a few different
things, you know, One of them
is, we believe at Dell side that
we can have a complimentary
offering to the DIGIT sensor
that will be attractive to the
robot robotics crowd but also to
the hobbyist market. And this is
basically aligned with our
vision that again, that we want
tactile sensing to be available
for any engineer, any
technician, any hobbyist to use
in their creative moments, for
anything, and I think, to do
that, you need to actually think
beyond DIGIT and just offer a
more universal sensor. So you
know, something that could be
mounted to robotic hand if you
want to, but you can also use it
as a digital microscope and a
high school class. You know,
something like that. Right? So
Audrow Nash: is that is that the
kind of resolution you're
getting with this approach? Or
Yeah,
Youssef Benmokhtar: so what
we're planning to do is actually
having a much higher resolution
sensor than digital. But a
similar or even smaller form
factor. And our partnership with
DIGIT would be with with meta
would be that we will probably
want to leverage their open
source community, and make our
sensor compatible with with
their Python community, you
know, libraries and everything
else like that. So that we have
a kickstart, you know, when
people want to use our sensor,
they already have libraries
accessible to them right away.
So that this is where I see the
next step being. So this is not
something that is done today,
maybe it's you know, I'm going
to be scolded by, by my metal
friends that I'm already talking
about something like this. But,
you know, regardless of that,
you know, this is the direction
we're taking. And this will
happen, because it's a, it's
something that we are jealous I
believe in.
Audrow Nash: And I want to talk
a lot more about the different
libraries or ways of
standardizing this. And it's
quite cool if you make a sort of
universal sensor, or you may
maybe like a universal way of
visualizing touch data and
relating it. But going from
actually creating, alright, so
you had DIGIT was released as a
paper, you guys agreed to start
manufacturing them. I assume
that since it was coming
directly from the research
community, that it wasn't built
in a way that's exactly the
easiest for manufacturing, or
the best way for manufacturing.
Can you tell me a bit about
those challenges? Because I
assume you have to take
basically what exists? And then
like, make it robust and make it
reliable and make or whatever,
grow it up for?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Correct?
Yeah, absolutely correct. You
know, it's always it's always
over simplified, you know, how
difficult it is to take
something that looks like you
can make 10 of them in a lab.
And now suddenly, you need to be
ready to make hundreds and 1000s
That's exactly why I think gel
sites it wasn't the right, you
know, the right partner for
meta, because we already know
how to make products like these,
we have an existing business,
you know, we know how difficult
it is to do in volume and the
repeatable way. So yes, we did
have to learn on the spot,
really quickly about the meta
design, and then how to improve,
you know, some of the
manufacturability issues that we
encountered, as we were always
rebuilding them, but that that
was something that was expected.
But this is also where Joel site
expertise is, we, you know, we
we had some quick cycles of
learning that we did in the
early phases, when you build the
first ones, to make sure that we
have a pretty high yield and
building this gel material for
digit, which mean pretty
Audrow Nash: high yield and
building this Gel it well, like,
you have to manufacture gel, and
then you can cut it up and you
want it to be I don't know, get
a lot of it at once or what. And
some of it has quality issues or
Youssef Benmokhtar: Well, you
know, like like anything like
any any part of a product that
you that you make, you know,
need to pass, you know, some
some specifications. And, you
know, this gel material, which
is kind of the secret sauce, you
know, that we have, and we build
it for different applications,
you have to make sure that it
has the right optical density
that you want that it's cut and,
you know, in the right shape,
and that the coatings are, you
know, opaque, like we talked
about before to make sure that
the light uniform uniformity is
going to be good that you don't
have, you know, an unacceptable
level of cosmetic defects that
will affect image quality, you
know, those kind of things. So,
this is what we're, you know,
experts in and it took, you
know, took us a few cycles
Learning to get right so that we
can start making hundreds of
these are 1000s of these.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so it's
interesting. A would expect that
that's the case with the
challenges of making a lot of
them. Were there any particular
things that came up that, you
know, you had to change? From
the DIGIT design?
Youssef Benmokhtar: You know, I
it, candidly, the biggest
problem we had were components
supply. You know, in these days,
you know, like, I'm sure you've
been hurt hearing around
shortages. And what was the
challenge, I think for both,
both parties actually was to
find replacements compared to
the digits original component
choices, just because of supply
issues. So I would say the
biggest challenge we had was
honestly, around that is
actually, you know, finding
alternative chips and things
like that, qualifying them and
getting our hands on it,
honestly, has been the biggest
challenge.
Audrow Nash: What an interesting
thing. So you had to like, find
it called for a certain part and
you had to swap it in, use
something else and validate that
it did the exact same thing,
Youssef Benmokhtar: correct?
Correct, then, you know, and
develop the firmware because,
you know, the original firmware
was meant for another chip, so
you have to make some
modifications and that kind of
stuff. That honestly was the
biggest challenge. The rest of
us, okay.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so, just and
I haven't I don't think we've
said DIGIT is like, how large is
DIGIT? And what's it? What's its
case? Basically?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Oh, I think
it's about, say, three quarters.
Yeah, it's a little over an inch
deep. I think it's 28
millimeters, if I remember
correctly. Just over an inch.
Yeah. And I think I wouldn't
need to get a specs on that. But
I want to say it's maybe half an
inch, and little bit over maybe
three quarters of an inch in
width. Anyways. Yeah. And then
in height, or then it's probably
another inch in height. Yeah,
slightly below that. Probably.
So it's
Audrow Nash: kind of like an
extra thick human finger.
Correct. In terms of size, and
it has a little pad on it. That
has the gel.
Youssef Benmokhtar: The Delta
data, yeah, the
Audrow Nash: gel material and
the gel material. It's kind of
it's like framed by the case
material. Correct. So you put
something on the gel material.
And it will measure the
deformation there. There's the
edges on the same side as the
gel.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Correct?
Yeah, there is a there is a
bezel I think the bezel is like
one and a half or two
millimeters. I know fairly thin.
Yeah. And the the gel itself is
you know, I forgot what it is
like three to four millimeters
probably high. It kind of a
slightly dome, like, you know
shape just like your finger
would. Basically yeah, yeah.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, like the tip
like the last DIGIT of your
finger. Correct kind of thing.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yeah, you
know, what's another thing maybe
that would be interesting to
you. The way I look at these
tactile sensors like DIGIT is
almost thinking about having a
camera inside your finger. So
imagine if you had a camera
inside your finger and it would
actually be able to see anything
that the forms your skin as
you're touching things. That's
pretty much what DIGIT is. Yeah,
you know?
Audrow Nash: Uh huh. So just so
I can picture the internals of
it a little bit so you have the
gel surface? Yep. And if so,
then we have the camera and the
camera could be so if the
sensors facing down and the gel
is at the bottom, the camera is
above looking at the gel
Correct? Do we have it does the
camera touch the gel? Or is it
just like a sensor pad that
touches the gel or how do we get
our
Youssef Benmokhtar: know the
camera is is offset from the gel
there's a the gel is mounted you
know think about it mounted on a
like a plastic window if you'd
like okay and the camera is
behind that I guess small
distance you need to have a
minimal you know distance
between the camera and the
Audrow Nash: yeah gel. I was
wondering if you could like use
the gel as a lens or something
like this but I imagine because
it's not like a pinhole camera
you would get a lot of light
going and bouncing all over. So
be very it'd be like a very
blurry image as opposed to a
crisp image kind of thing. So
you need that separation as
opposed to not having a lens or
having a sensor pad directly
into the gel.
Youssef Benmokhtar: You need to
be able to image that area right
so you need a little bit of
distance to be able to see that
surface.
Audrow Nash: Now for robotics
just like wondering, how do you
connect to it? How does it? How
does it work as a sensor? What
exists for libraries? Like all
these things?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yeah, so,
you know, so connect
connectivity is done through a
USBC type, you know, of
connectivity. And then, you
know, you basically have
Audrow Nash: high data flow or
something through USB C, or was
there any reason to choose it
other than it's a nice ports,
the
Youssef Benmokhtar: most common
port, and also, you know,
robotics actually does care
about real time information. And
so you can run it, you know,
easily at 30 frames a second,
you know, you know, it has even
the capabilities, I think,
should run a little bit faster
than that. But you want to have
real time and USB was was, is
basically a good way to do that.
And then you basically, you
know, you know, program, the
sensor using all the firmware
that meta has made available on
PI touch. So that's how
basically, you, you connect it
to your your computer, have
access all the Python libraries,
and you're ready to go.
Audrow Nash: What, so I don't I
don't know too much about the
available libraries for the what
do they let you do? Like, you
assume you can get 3d
deformation, but is there like,
I mean, there's for vision for
computer vision, there's like
open CV, or open computer vision
library, I believe, started by
Intel. And it's a big open
source library has been around
for a long time. And so that
lets you do a lot of basic
computer vision things. So if
you're working with a camera,
like almost right out of the
box, after you figured out the
install, you can like detect
faces, or do object tracking or
something like this, is there
any such things that let you
kind of identify what you're
touching or identify properties
of what you're touching? Yet,
and these libraries,
Youssef Benmokhtar: you know, I
think the meta team is, is kind
of adding things on a regular
basis, but it's all the basic
things you get are, for example,
you know, the ability to just,
you know, see an image, you
know, so even even a 2d
interpretation of the image or
3d representation of the image,
see where the sensor has been
touched in. So if you look at
the surface area of the sensor,
which area has been touched, you
know, which is an interesting
information, you know, in
robotic application, that they
typically called pose
estimation. And from, that's the
kind of the very basic
information that they give, you
know, the purpose of mirrors, as
far as I understand it, is to
then in turn this into creating
datasets of deformations of that
gel based on the type of objects
that the robotics hand or
gripper is, is manipulating. So,
you know, you kind of train
models to say, you know, let me
grab this example, if you say,
this is, this is a cable, right?
And you basically have your
robot kind of holding it in all
kinds of different, you know,
orientations, and different
forces and things like that, and
all that is captured in their,
you know, in their datasets. And
it's used to basically, you
know, create AI to basically
say, Well, this is how I
recognize that this is a cable,
you know, touching the sensor?
And then can you do things like
that, for example, like, you
know, reorienting that cable and
space, because you want to move
it from A to B, you know, those
kinds of things. So, I Yeah, you
know,
Audrow Nash: to me, I'm saying
it's similar to like, image
segmentation, or something like
this. So we do all of the, when
we had like image net, or some
sort of thing that has a bunch
of labeled images. So we have
cameras, the cameras take
pictures, and then we say, Okay,
that's a cat, that's a tree,
that's what whatever. And then
you do that a lot of times, and
then maybe one approach is you
can have a more complex image,
and you can identify the
different parts that are in it.
And I think now they do that
typically with like bounding
boxes, that they just slide over
the image or something, to try
to figure out where in the image
might be a cat, but they're
getting more and more
sophisticated. And I'm
definitely not aware of this,
but are aware of the like
cutting edge of this research.
But it seems kind of like that,
where the intention is to start
with very simple identifications
of things. And then perhaps
eventually a robot can grab a
chunk of stuff from a messy,
messy desk and identify that it
might have a few cables and
whatever. So it could look for
things or
Youssef Benmokhtar: I think
you're right, I think, you know,
the Holy Grail is actually to be
able to provide that kind of
intelligence to robots the same
way that you've you've mentioned
about image recognition, you
know, forecast And dogs and
other things, right? It's kind
of the same idea is, you know,
if I want to be able to do
complex object manipulation in a
robotic application, or you
know, to do, you know, kidding,
right, and other things like
that, what to do kidding, for
example, if you want to, you
know, take, you know, you have a
box of a whole bunch of
different objects, you don't
really know what those objects
are, but you want to basically
put a certain class of objects
and put them in another box, you
know, but this time classified
by the type of objects. This is
something that actually very
difficult to do. The word
Kidding, kidding. Yes? Like a
kit?
Audrow Nash: You No kidding. So
like you're assembling kits,
correct thing? Correct. Okay.
I'm not heard that before. Yeah.
So if you're, if you're grouping
objects by type or something,
for example, I, yes, go ahead.
Youssef Benmokhtar: You know,
the other thing could be if
you're trying to just assemble
things that today, I really only
done by humans, because humans
have the kind of dexterity you
need to do those kinds of
assembly of complex assemblies,
you know, handling, you know,
cables, or handling, you know,
types of fibers and things like
that are just, you know, really
hard to do for a robot, you need
to have that kind of sensitivity
feel that humans have. So
providing this kind of
perception capability to robots
may allow them to start doing
some of these more complicated
tasks.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And I
imagine that it's not terribly
interesting to be like, Okay,
now we can grab this and
identify it as much as it is
that you can use it in like a
sensor fusion kind of context
where you say, I think that I'm
grabbing this, and I grabbed
something. Does it agree with
what I expect to feel given
this? I think that would lead to
more interesting applications of
this kind of thing.
Youssef Benmokhtar: You're
absolutely right. You know, one
thing that's really interesting
is that machine vision, and
computer vision is extensively
used in in robotics today. But
one thing that happens is,
especially in a robotic hand,
for example, is once the hand
grabs something, he can't see
anything is occluded. It's no
idea what it is, right? So I
think complementing vision, with
tactile information, is
something that's going to be
extremely useful.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Now, so one
thing that I'm wondering as a
roboticist with this is, so say,
I want to like screw in a screw
with this. So I want to pick it
up with my fingers, and I want
to screw it in. So maybe I can
pick it up and identify it. But
I think that highly like I'm
imagining the gel is quite soft
for this. And that deaf
formation might make it hard to
control whatever you're picking
up. Are there? Is this kind of
it? Would you think that this is
correct? And are there
strategies for using these
sensors with tasks do you like,
identify it, and then move a
little lower and then to factor
or higher, so that you can
identify what it is and then
pick it up with rigid grippers
that you kind of know what you
have? Or is it is it more
complex and how you grip it.
Youssef Benmokhtar: So, you
know, first of all, you know,
the gel that we use in robotics
application today is actually
not that soft, at least not to
the human touch is actually it
would feel, you know, it will
have this kind of elasticity
feel to it, but it's still
pretty hard to actually, you
know, if you're grabbing a, you
know, a screw, for example, as
you as you mentioned, you would
actually not really need to, you
know, pass it on to another
robotic arm. To do something
else, you actually will have a
very good understanding of what
the screw is how you know, how
hard you actually grasp, it will
actually give you more
information about it's about its
shape, we actually have done
some experiments that you might
find interesting to us are
actually tactile sensor as a
hardness a relative measurement
of hardness, because same
similar to, to human skin,
right? And human finger, if I'm
pressing on something that is
really, you know, soft, you
know, I really don't have a lot
of feedback on my, on my skin,
it's actually very, very light.
But if it's really a hard
material, I my my my skin will
get indented really fast. Well,
it's the same thing that happens
to us with our sensor. So when
you're holding an object and
actually pressing it, pressing
it against another, it actually
also gives you gives you that
that really interesting
information about the potential
hardness or softness of the of
the object that is touching. So
it's really look
Audrow Nash: at the deformation
of both objects, the gel, and
the objects are kind of infer
the hardness of the object is
Youssef Benmokhtar: it the jail
by itself would tell you how
hard the object is that that
whatever you're holding is in
contact with, you know, just
just by, again, you know, just
imagine we have a video, I
think, on our libraries of a
gripper holding a fork. And then
we have hardness samples. And as
you push the fork into the
harness sample, you see how the
tactile sensor deforms,
depending on the hardness of
that sample, and the hotter it
is and the more deforms, right?
So this is actually how you get
a relative hardness measurement.
Audrow Nash: does this require
that you have 3d knowledge of
whatever the object is that
you're doing? Or at least you
know, like, say the width of it,
or how far it is between the two
sensors are? How much of it
should be pushed into the
sensor?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Um, I think
3d helps, but I don't think it's
even necessary.
Audrow Nash: Oh, it's, I think,
intuitively see how it works. So
Youssef Benmokhtar: well,
because you know, all I really
care about is, you know, for
example, is the depth of the
indentation. But not necessarily
the exact shape of the object,
you know, is how deep do you get
into the gel their formation,
for example. But if you have the
shape, then you can also say,
oh, now I'm starting to
recognize that that's the tip of
a, of a fork, for example.
Because you can add that to
object recognition.
Audrow Nash: So you think if
we're picking up like a screw or
something, and we have, say you
have the two digits, or whatever
would be next after DIGIT with
higher resolution, and you have
it between the two sensor pads,
between the gel on the both of
the sensors. Now, you can kind
of see how it is pressed into
both of the sensors. And you can
infer in 3d how the screw is
oriented, correct with respect
to the sensor, and then from
there, you can figure out how
it's oriented with respect to
the rest of the robot, because
you know, how the fingers are
positioned with respect to the
rest of the robot, this kind of
thing?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Absolutely,
that that is possible today, we
actually have, we're doing that
at a job site, we, we build,
basically, a 3d point cloud
model of an object that the that
we want to our grippers to, to
manipulate. And based on just
the contact area, we actually
able to infer the orientation in
3d of the of the 3d Point Cloud,
which is, which is a really cool
thing to do. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: So when you say
point cloud, you mean, mesh,
kind of thing. So it's not
you're using your sensor to get
the 3d information. And it's
creating like a mesh
representation of the object
that you see. And like a 3d
graphics or not, I was thinking
LIDAR initially, which you get
all the points, and then you can
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yeah, it's
not Yeah, I think a mesh is a
good, good explanation to it for
it.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Just making
sure I understand.
Youssef Benmokhtar: No problem.
Okay.
Audrow Nash: Then, so, you know,
what, meta or formerly Facebook?
Like, so I know, they had the
one robot that would turn and
look at you. And it was used for
like video calls and things like
this, like an echo with a neck
kind of thing. Amazon Echo with
a neck? Do you know what their
interest is in tactile sensing
and find manipulation? Are they
going to get more into robotics
or any ideas here?
Youssef Benmokhtar: I think it
will be a bit of a relation of
mine. Well, it's definitely
started as research. But I think
the the idea of providing this
intelligent perception tool to
robots is what is compelling to
meta, as you imagine, you know,
robots being able to do more and
more tasks. It became obvious to
them that it needed to have
additional sensing capability.
And that vision and sound was
just not enough for robots to be
able to, to do the kind of
complex tasks that the human
does. And, you know, I think,
you know, in their very grand
vision, I believe that Robotics
has a place in their Metaverse
story, in the sense that, you
know, you have to imagine a
Audrow Nash: verse story, you
mean the kind of 3d world
they're creating?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Correct? I
think, you know, you know, I
look I define, you know, I have
my own simple definition of
Metaverse is really basically
the, you know, the the
integration of the digital and
the physical space into one. And
to do that, you know, you want
to have the ability to replicate
or duplicate any task that
happens in the, in the physical
world in another world. And
robotics is part of that other
world, although it is a physical
object, or equipment, you know,
you want it to be able to
replicate what humans do to
provide, you know, services just
like a human would do. So if you
if you imagine, for example,
doing remote collaboration
through a robot, you know, or
somebody who's coming to your,
you know, a robot coming to your
house to do house cleaning, or
to, you know, be your, you know,
the person that's actually
bringing you water, if you're in
cabinet incapacitated in bed or
something, because you're sick
or something, well, if you don't
have those capabilities, I don't
think you're going to be able to
perform those kinds of tasks
like a human would. So and
that's in that perspective, I
think this kind of research is
probably very attractive to them
in the long run.
Audrow Nash: Is there is there
work on kind of the other side
of this where it's, so right now
your sensor allows you to get
really accurate 3d deformation
information, so you can push an
object into it, you can see the
surface I like the videos, or
the pictures are amazing. Like,
where you see a fingerprint? Do
you see the $1? I think I think
I saw that somewhere where you
see like a $1? Or if you put it
on $100. Bill, yeah. And see the
press throughout the like,
that's crazy. Yeah. But is there
is there work in the other side
of this, where, okay, we have
this detail 3d information, can
we display it elsewhere? This
kind of thing. So like, if I
push into it, and I feel like
like, say, my finger drags
across a larger one of these
sensors, can that be replayed in
a 3d space some other way?
Youssef Benmokhtar: So I think
you're, you know, it's
Audrow Nash: outside of what
your company does with Joe?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Not
completely, because I think what
you just described is, I mean,
to me and tell me if I if I
understood correctly, what your
question is, um, you know, I
look at tactile sensing being
the, you know, the the input to
another output, which is
haptics. Right? So what you just
described to me is, okay, if I,
if I know how it feels right to
touch it with my sensor, I give
you a digital signature of that
texture of that feeling. Right.
So what do I do with that? And I
think once you do with that, one
of the things you can do with
that is actually that becomes
the input that you need to have
true to life haptics
experiences, right? Because if,
you know, eventually, one day
haptic technologies would be
just as high resolution as our
sensor technology. And they've
been in and they're gonna need
right to know, well, how do I?
How does woodgrain feel? How
does cotton feel? How's that
silk feel? How does glass feel.
And I don't see how you get that
information. Without a sensor
like ours, which gives you
millions of pixels of
information to derive a digital
signature of any texture out
there. So when you think about
the need one day, to have a
digital twin of all the surfaces
in the world, all the feeling
the textures of materials in the
world, you're going to need to
characterize them through a
digital tactile sensor. And
that's going to be very useful
to people working in haptics, in
my opinion,
Audrow Nash: the combination of
those, so if you if you go from
good texture sensing to haptics
that makes me that to me with
meta, makes a lot of sense, it
would be kind of like, Ready
Player One or something like
this, where you have like,
sensations and stuff.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yeah, I
think, you know, we're, what
kind of the microphone to the
speaker, you know, if I use the
sound analogy, right, okay. And
I think in our world, you know,
where the input to haptics and I
think that's, that's just a
simple way to look at it, you
know, where, yeah, where the
camera work with the camera to
the display. You know, that's,
that's, that's how I look at our
company.
Audrow Nash: Yep. And so now,
you mentioned at the beginning,
how the digitization of touch,
can you tell me a bit about kind
of what you believe are the
implications of this and how
important it will be and how
technology will go that way?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Well, I, we
believe it will say that
honestly, that the next sense to
be digitized this touch, vision
was first and we know what
happens once CMOS sensors
became, you know, broadly
available, not only obviously,
it helped to and
Audrow Nash: that's what they're
made out of, what is it
complementary metal oxide? I
don't remember. Yeah, I
Youssef Benmokhtar: remember, I
think
Audrow Nash: so. metal oxides,
so that's what those are made
Youssef Benmokhtar: of. Yeah,
but those digits basically it
translated photonic information
to electronic, you know, an
electronic signal. And, you
know, and today it's used
Audrow Nash: to get digital
images as opposed to like, the
old, I don't know, film roll,
correct. Like,
Youssef Benmokhtar: they're
really original, you know, you
know, picture taking
technologies, you know, that
that, you know, with with the,
you know, the silver oxide
things and you know that Kodak
was, you know, famous for for a
while. But so we digitize that,
digitize that, and then we
basically make copies, yeah, you
can make. So first of all,
you're able to miniaturize it,
make it, you know, widely and
broadly available to everybody
be able to take pictures,
videos, and so on. But most
importantly, it actually allowed
computer vision to take off
because now you have access to
the, you know, billions and
billions and billions of images
to be able to derive, you know,
information from using machine
learning and deep learning
techniques. You know, and then
audio went through the same
revolution. You know, without
digital audio, there would be no
speech recognition. And, you
know, no, Alexa, no, Google now
No, Siri, you know, no music
streaming, you know, like, no,
no, Spotify or anything like
that. No Apple Music.
Audrow Nash: We'd ever record
player and that'd be it.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yeah, which,
which I liked a lot to the
handle. Exactly. It sounds
really good. But but none of
these other things would have
happened, because now we have,
again, you know, the, you know,
trillions of hours of sound and
audio bits that can be used for
algorithms to train and respond
to the next step
Audrow Nash: rise. I'm surprised
that video or images came before
sound. To me, it seems like
sound is simpler, because it's
one dimensional, as opposed to
images. But, I mean, I guess
we've been interested in cameras
for a long time,
Youssef Benmokhtar: well, you
know, the human, the human
brain, you know, 30% of our
brain activity is used by the
visual cortex, right? So, I'm
not surprised that we were more
attracted to sound to to audio
to video, sorry, then. But, but
I, I think the next one is
really touch, we are
multimodality creatures, that,
you know, for humans to really
do what they do best they need
all of their senses. And, you
know, the next one that that I
think is ripe for digitization
is tactile, or touch, touch and
feel. And I think it's going to
open up a brand new type of, of,
of applications, you know,
starting with, you know, with
robotics, but also some of the
other activities that we've been
doing a gel side and, you know,
in understanding surfaces and
features of surfaces for years.
Now,
Audrow Nash: you want to mention
some of the other applications
that use this technology.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Sure, you
know, I think at a really high
level, we have found that we are
really nice fit whenever we
count an application that has
been using actually human touch.
So believe it or not, in
aerospace, for example, there
are still some companies that
are using the fingernail test
test to decide if a scratch on a
part is a problem or not a
problem basically, meaning that
it needs to be reworked or
tossed. By basically just finger
meant notice, well, basically,
you put your finger in the
scratch and you actually feel
how deep it is, like you say,
Well, yeah, that one that think
is too deep, we need to do
something about it. That's
crazy, it is crazy, absolutely
crazy. But for us, you know,
using our sensor, they able to
get now repeatable, accurate,
fast measurement, quantitative,
not subjective, and you can make
decisions right away that are
the right decisions every time.
And our, our technology is the
only one that allows to do that,
because vision is not very
effective on metallic surfaces
that are, you know, hard to take
pictures of it's very highly
reflective, and so on again, you
know, definitely yeah, but the
the beauty of art technology,
because it's such the same way
as human touch. It doesn't
really care what the surface
properties are, whether it's
like, you know, glass metal, you
know, you know, transparent,
translucent and we don't care
reflective, you know, we you
know, we wire sensor with the
foam to any material, it
doesn't, it doesn't really
matter. So, this is where we
have to put the seen success and
our in our initial commercial
efforts have been around
providing measurement
capabilities to companies that
are interested in understanding
specific features in their
applications, like scratches and
dents in aerospace or, you know,
measuring coatings in the paint
shop in automotive, I mean,
it's, it's basically anytime
that you have I think human
touch being used or where, where
basically using a cow A
traditional camera system just
not going to work because of the
type of material that that we're
dealing with.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, shiny ones.
Exactly. Okay, yeah, that'll be
cool if touch becomes digitized.
And then we have a way of
communicating, and then it can
maybe enable all the haptic
stuff that we were speaking
earlier. Correct. Really, really
cool.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yes, I've
tried many of the current
haptics technologies. And it's
just a very disappointing
experience. It's basically, you
know, the vibrations you feel,
regardless of what you're
supposed to be touching in a
digital form. And that's,
that's, I think, past the first
second of Oh, wow, I'm feeling
something, you actually just
say, Yeah, but that's not how
it's supposed to feel. And they
have really no other way. I
think today, you know, all I've
seen is varying the varying the
frequency, or whatever technique
they
Audrow Nash: do with a pen or
something, and it will you drag
it across a surface, and it kind
of spoofs by putting forces,
Youssef Benmokhtar: for example,
for example, if it's, if it's
haptic glove, you know,
sometimes they have, you know,
kind of vibrating membranes on
your tip. So you basically
change the vibration, you feel
that you're touching something.
Audrow Nash: It's a similar
approach to like how sound
works, right? Because I mean,
we, with the digital sound, you
represent different frequencies,
and then you combine all those
frequencies together at their
respective amplitudes. And then
you get the appropriate sounds.
Kind of like that. They're
emulating that but in a touch
space to try and you're saying
at the current moment, it's not
very convincing. No,
Youssef Benmokhtar: it's not the
resolution. And, and it's not
actually matching what it's
supposed to be.
Audrow Nash: Do, are there any
technologies that you know of in
this space that are promising?
Or maybe we get the really good
touch information? And then
that'll help us have that? I
don't know, we'll use that good
information to build better
emulations of what they look
like this kind of
Youssef Benmokhtar: thing I'm
not aware of I mean, I'm aware
of a lot of companies working on
it. So I'm sure that progress
will be made. It is a difficult
problem. I haven't seen anybody
who cracked it yet. But I do
hope that the digitization of
tactile sensing will help
haptics companies because it
will provide them with, you
know, a library of how things
should feel. And I think that's,
that's an important part of it.
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah, that'd be
nice, though. It feels like so
I'm not very aware of much
research in the haptic space.
But a lot of it seems to be
like, can we emulate this
texture? Or can we classify this
texture in a good way that we
can possibly emulate later, and
this kind of thing, and if you
have really good information
there than that, I mean,
especially like, if I'm a
researcher that's trying to do
haptics things. And I go use one
of your sensors and generate a
whole library of what like, say,
a woodgrain looks like and then
from there, I can randomly
sample or, I don't know, build a
model based on all that data
that I just took myself, which
is really awesome.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Right? And
you know, what, one thing that I
think also, you know, might help
to accelerate, you know, the
adoption of digital touch, I
think, is also the the use of
this digital understanding of a
surface. For applications like,
you know, let's say, you know,
I'm a textile company, I've
designed something. And in the
US, I'm having it made in
Southeast Asia. And one way to
verify that what they've made is
exactly what I want is actually
to compare the digital signature
of it. Oh, that's super cool,
right? Which today, they don't
really have I think the only way
they really do it is by
exchanging samples.
Audrow Nash: Hmm. Right. You're
saying like, if I want something
from some company, and I say it
has to be made to my
specifications, and they say,
Oh, I've done it, you can say,
Oh, I've padded it everywhere.
And I see that the model is, I
don't know, not within tolerance
in this one dimension or the
wrong shape, or whatever, it
might be something like that. So
you can verify
Youssef Benmokhtar: it, you
would verify the texture.
Exactly, you know, it does the
texture match what I designed,
right, so I'm designing it here,
I want the texture to feel this
way. Here's a digital picture of
what that texture should feel
like you know, build it and then
measure the digital signature on
your end and see if it matches
Audrow Nash: be cool if this was
also used for like counterfeits
and things for like say like a
high end clothing brand. They're
like if you press your device on
it, you can see the quality of
the fiber versus polyester
version that looks similar thing
like this, cuz I imagine you
could look and see the
differences.
Youssef Benmokhtar: You're
absolutely right. We actually
had inquiries around exactly
that front because we well,
yeah, because the thread counts
you know is different.
potentially counterfeit
material, you know, counterfeit.
Shops are becoming extremely
good. It's basically becoming
very, very hard to tell, you
know, to from fake. But one way
actually, is to get a digital
signature, what it's supposed to
be like, and look at it. Yeah.
So you know, it is part of our
vision, you know, it, you know,
for us, if we could find a way
to build a product and the
software behind it, to provide
to all of the custom offices out
there that wants to verify, you
know, is this real? Or is this
fake? And they basically could
scan the materials and say,
compare it to their database and
say, Well, this is how the real
one is that that is just a, you
know, a much more efficient way
to do it.
Audrow Nash: That's super cool.
Do you also, I'm imagining
applications in healthcare, in
this kind of thing, like, Oh, I
think I have a lump here for
something. And you could press
it into it, and you could maybe
get good 3d information about
what you're seeing, and then
what that means for this kind of
thing.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Absolutely.
And, you know, we, we've had,
again, in his in the history of
GelSight, we've had inquiries
for such applications. Yeah, we
haven't really pursued them at
the time. You know, for a small
company, you have to choose
where you want to spend your
Audrow Nash: money for you guys.
Youssef Benmokhtar: We're only,
you know, we're 20 People just
about today,
Audrow Nash: and we're How do
you do most of your money spent
up until this point where you're
doing digit, which is, if I
understand correctly, it's like
the first fairly low cost sensor
that you guys are making. So
spend low volume high margins on
how you've been operating. So
extremely, NEC, probably
assemble in house, and this kind
of thing.
Youssef Benmokhtar: So I would
say in our chemistry, type of
works, I think around the gel is
done in house today. But we have
started to outsource some part
of that process. And then the
electronics assembly piece is
outsourced. So we don't we don't
do that in house. So we you
know, we've been preparing
ourselves for scale. And you
can't do that by, you know, just
assembling that in our office in
Boston. So yeah, we definitely
we've already started to build
that supply chain.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. What
do you how do you imagine growth
looking for you guys? Like what
do you? What do you think in the
next like two years, five years,
this kind of thing? I know, it's
a projection of something that
hasn't happened. But like, what
do you think
Youssef Benmokhtar: our focus in
the next couple of years is, we
just launched our series two
metrology products. So we're
kind of putting out commercial
efforts on the deployment of
that solution, which we just
launched this October. And then
we basically planning to push
the commercialization of DIGIT
obviously, which is, you know,
something that is important to
us, and then this next
generation local sensor that
will hopefully have in the first
half of next year, but the thing
Audrow Nash: you were saying
that would be more accurate,
smaller, correct, then this kind
of thing, okay,
Youssef Benmokhtar: great,
because, you know, the thing is,
we need to, we need to create an
ecosystem around tactile
sensing. And that's, you know,
again, the shared vision with
with metta and, and to do that
we need to invest in bringing
products that are in that kind
of cost points and ease of use,
and form factor, and also invest
in marketing, you know, to make
it known. And that's what we
basically we're focusing the
next, you know, six months to a
year is let's, let's make
tactile sensing. available, that
everyone knows that everybody
knows about it. Everybody who
has any kind of curiosity about
what can I do with this? We want
to remove all the barriers, all
the obstacles and make it easy
for them to get it.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, I'm seeing so
I'm seeing DIGIT where you guys
similar to what was it? Is it
Leptin, the FLIR the thermal
camera, where it's like they
made the I think it was the FLIR
and it was the fairly low cost
thermal camera. Like I don't
know, it was a few $100 where
previously it was they were very
expensive. So are you are you
following kind of a similar
business model? You think at the
moment with digit
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yeah, I
think it's actually makes me
smile that you're mentioning the
laptop camera. I actually worked
on it in my past life. Yeah,
Audrow Nash: I worked with it
not on it.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yeah. So
yeah, I think I think it is
about building that community.
You know, we we want to make it
available. We want to make it
affordable, but at the same time
we need tactile sensing to be,
you know, used in real
applications by customers that
give us that market credibility,
right when I, when I work with a
company in aerospace that is
actually saying, using your
technology saves me hundreds of
1000s of dollars a year in, you
know, reduced rework costs or
maintenance costs. That is very
important for Josiah, because he
basically said, tactile sensing
is not only about a long term
dream, a long term vision, it
actually actually has
applications today. So, we are
continuing to work hard at
having our sensors being used in
real applications. But at the
same time, we want it to be, you
know, we want to create that
that community, that hopefully
is going to be very, really
large, and in the years to come.
That will consider the use of
tactile sensing in their future
products. And to do that we need
to continue with what we started
with digit.
Audrow Nash: What kind of
software push are you guys
doing? So I know that meta AI is
contributing a lot in the
software space, it sounds like,
but are you guys maybe making
libraries that expose the data
type and make it useful for a
lot of common applications, a
lot of common hobbyists or
makers, this kind of thing.
Youssef Benmokhtar: So for the
for the, I would say, the low
cost part of our portfolio, we
we intend to follow the metal
example, and make our make
libraries open source make them
easy to access?
Audrow Nash: Does anything exist
yet? Or it sounds like it
doesn't yet
Youssef Benmokhtar: we have a
few we already have our you
know, our 3d reconstruction.
technique, you know, can be
available for people to leverage
on our sensors, our pose
estimation, you know, algorithms
also, we have, we're thinking
about other things, you know, we
have anti slip, for example, for
robotics, which could be
interesting, you know, detecting
than an anti slip, yeah, I was
gonna ask about that, right, you
know, detecting that something
is slipping from grasp, from
your grasp, you know, so these
are all the things that we, you
know, can put available for
community to use. So, we have a
few, but, you know, we, we need
to accelerate that and as part
of our plans. So on the low end
side, I would say, we're going
to follow the open source model,
we're going to try to make it
everything that we develop, make
it available for the community.
Audrow Nash: And part of that is
growing the community, correct
that gotcha, correct. So it's
interesting that that's a
pragmatic choice, which is quite
cool. To me, as someone who
really likes open source, that
it's kind of a pragmatic choice
well to do open, it's very
Youssef Benmokhtar: pragmatic in
the various, you know, in the
sense that, that that ecosystem
today does not exist, it's very
small. So, you know, for us to
grow it, it would be, I think,
it would not be smart on gel
site to make it difficult by
having a closed source system,
you know, or make it, you know,
Honorius, you know, for people.
So, open source is the way to go
to create a community, and we
are definitely embracing it.
Now, on the higher end, you
know, type of product, there we
are, you know, continuing to
develop applications. And those
are soft, you know, including
our software suites that
customers are, you know, paying
for, whether it's with the
purchase of a of some of our
systems, or as a just a, you
know, an applications we just
like you do with enterprise
software. But even then, you
know, even there, we are
planning to also invest in, you
know, machine learning, and AI
to bring in more services to our
customers in a future where,
instead of just offering a tool
that provides them with the
decision making capability at
the instant, is also the ability
to leverage the data, the data
that's coming out from the
sensors over time. So as you're
building a database of images,
in an enterprise environment, do
something with those images over
time. And we think that machine
learning and AI can can help us
bring more value to our
customers. And that's another
part that's going to be
important for Joseph going
forward.
Audrow Nash: Do you mean keeping
it for yourself or putting it
out into the community? And so
you get a bunch of data, and you
can train machine learning
models on it or whatever it
might be? Will it be like you'll
release a public data set? Or
you'll keep it in half?
Youssef Benmokhtar: They will do
both, I think on on the consumer
like, you know, market, you
know, we, you know, we will
likely publish some public
datasets, you know, to help how
the community leverage those
datasets. But in the enterprise
space, when you know the problem
to solve, you know, there, there
is a way to just monetize
directly that data set by
building services.
Audrow Nash: Do you think? Are
you guys do you think? I mean,
so many questions around all
these different things, because
the software and open source
that is really interesting. But
so one of the things that really
kicked off the all of the
advancements in computer vision,
as far as I understand is like
the release of image net. And I
think it was, I think it's image
net, and might be some others
thing, but it was a big data set
with benchmarks effectively, for
you can compare how good your
algorithm does. So you have a
bunch of images, those images
are labeled, and it asks you
what is this, and then you can
run your algorithm on it. And
your algorithm is right, say 60%
of the time and the current
state of the art is 70% of the
time and you've thought you know
how what you're doing compares,
do you think it's in your future
to create anything like this for
a touch?
Youssef Benmokhtar: I hope so, I
really hope so. Be awesome. It's
a it's a very ambitious goal for
EDA for a company of our size
today. But it is part of our
story. And it is part about how
we want the company to grow.
And, you know, we we believe
that that is something that
needs to happen. And we hope
that we'll be the ones to, to
build it.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, if I remember
correctly, ImageNet was done by
Fei Fei Li, and I think she was
at Stanford. And so they just
received a big grant, I think,
and then went and did it. So I
don't know, something like that.
I may, I may be wrong about the
story, or who were anything, but
it'd be quite cool to see you
guys do a touch library that
would really accelerate this
whole space. Are you doing
anything? So I mean, I met open
robotics. I'm wondering, do you
have ROS? Like, do you have any
way to interface yourself?
With Yeah, I should. I
should have mentioned that
before it or sorry? No,
actually, our sensors and, and
our software and firmware is ROS
compatible?
Audrow Nash: Suite? So which ROS
by the way? ROS 1 or ROS 2?
I don't know, that's a
good question. I'll ask my
robotics engineer. But but it is
absolutely our you know, that
we, we intend to support, you
know, anything that we need to,
to, to, again, to accelerate
adoption. So ROS is definitely
something that we keep keeping
an eye on and supporting.
Audrow Nash: If you one thing
that would be cool. If so as you
are working, because if robotics
is a big interest, and a lot of
the robotics community uses ROS,
one thing that's very nice to
have is something standardized
in the ROS community. And the
way to do this is through a ROS
enhancement proposal, it'd be
very cool to create one of these
for like a data structure that's
really good for touch. But
actually, maybe it's just an
image, which is kind of nuts, or
like a 3d point cloud or
something like this. But if if
it is a non standard datatype
creating one of these ROS
enhancement proposals would be
really cool. And then we have
this as like, this is the de
facto touch type that will be
used in the ROS ecosystem. So
other packages can also use it
and build off of your standards.
I'm making a note.
Audrow Nash: Awesome, that would
be super cool. And I'm, I'm
happy to see that you guys are
already supporting ROS even. I
bet. I wonder if it's ROS one. A
lot of people are moving ROS 2,
which is quite cool. It's
getting steam.
Youssef Benmokhtar: I can I can
ask right now. I don't know if I
get an answer right away. But
Audrow Nash: I mean, it doesn't
matter too much. Yeah. Let's
see. So now I want to see how
much time we have. So we'd like
another 15 minutes or so. I was
the one thing I was really
curious about your sensor was
vibration. And so a lot of time
or as far as I understand if you
have like a gripper and you have
an object in it, and the object
is starting to fall out of the
gripper, it'll create
vibrations, so you'll be able to
sense vibrations or something to
know if the object is slipping,
which you've mentioned. Yes. And
I was wondering with the gel,
how this would be like perhaps
if the gel deformed and then
slowly came back, it would be
very hard to get vibrations or
if it was very springy, it might
be easy, or you might get a
bunch of noise if it's to spring
back. I don't know. Can you talk
a bit about the slit of
different objects through your
sensors?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Yeah, I
think you know The really I
think what we do is we have come
up with a way to measure the
local forces at the sensor
surface. And, you know, based on
that you basically, you know,
Audrow Nash: you just assume
that it's normal to the
deformation. Yeah. So why don't
formation surface and the force?
Correct. So
Youssef Benmokhtar: what we do
actually, we imagine, like you
printing a dot matrix on the, on
the membrane of the sensor,
right?
Audrow Nash: I don't know what
you mean, dot matrix,
Youssef Benmokhtar: it's
basically a matrix of black
dots. Right? Okay. So
Audrow Nash: that's what you
mean. Right? Yeah. And thinking
like that product, like in math
or No, no, yeah.
Youssef Benmokhtar: It is very,
you know, yeah, just exactly
what what it sounds like, a
bunch of dots. Yeah. So now,
when you have a camera, right,
every time that you press on the
gel, those those dots, you know,
location basically get get
changed based on how the touch
the surface is being, you know,
being touched. And based on
that, I actually have now an
idea to, you know, to know, what
is the local force vectors
basically, on the entire matrix.
And as you're moving across the
surface, on also scan, detect,
basically, the changes in that
local, those local forces. So if
you're, if your object is
starting to slip a little bit,
you know, then you basically see
the vectors kind of all going
into one direction, with a
relative intensity also showed,
and you put all of that
together, you're able basically
to detect that, you know, the
object is, is actually starting
to just slip in some way. So
it's, it's, it's a pretty neat
way, actually, to provide this
additional information. And one
of the key things, you know,
you're a much better, you know,
much more expert than me in this
field. But, you know, one of the
difficulties I understand them,
and trying to get force
estimation, in robotics, and
robotics, arms and fingers, is
actually the sensors that
measure forces are not at the
tip of the of the drives, a lot
of times, right, so this is, you
know, so when you get forces
emissions,
Audrow Nash: this is
specifically a problem when you
have like a high gear gear
ratio, if you have low gear
ratios, a lot of times you can
infer the force at the tip
pretty accurately. But if you
have a high gear ratio, there's
all those gears in the way and I
don't know if this is correct,
whatever it makes it, so it's
hard to do.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Correct. But
in our case, here, whatever, you
know, in our case, we actually
can provide you with a local
force estimation at the tip,
which could be also very
interesting, depending on the
applications.
Audrow Nash: So for for the
local force estimation, at least
with the digit, it probably
can't, like if I I'm imagining,
like I had a robot that was like
going to pick up something with
a forklift. And I wanted to feel
what's on the end of the
forklift. I imagine you can't
put a lot of weight into these
sensors, he has this shake in
your head. But is there any way
to make them more robust,
because like, if I if I'm trying
to grab something that's heavy,
I probably can't use the sensors
on the end of grab them,
I would say, you know,
you saw you shaking my hand in
my head there. Because in the
case of DIGIT, right, if you
putting very heavy weights on on
a hand, you know, equipped with
DIGIT, I just think that I think
the mechanical housing would
just crack. That's was when I
was just not meant for that. I
don't think the issue is really
the gel as much. But the key
again, as I said very early in
our conversation, you could
design, you know, the sensor for
different applications, right.
So if you're basically looking
at an application where you need
to apply a lot of force on the
sensor, then you can design a
formulation that allows you to
enter to do that, you can also
design, you know, the thickness
of the gel to be, you know,
maybe thick enough to allow for,
you know, a lot of pressure to
be applied or thin enough to be
able to apply a lot of pressure.
So, we actually have done that.
We, we, you know, we have a
customer in forensics, who were
doing some role. Yeah, we were
doing some tests, like like
crime ski. Yeah, absolutely.
They, they basically use our
technology to measure bullet
casings, and compare them to do
to a central database to
basically be able to provide
like a biometric. You know,
confirmation that that case came
from this gun. You know it with
a with a 90 plus percent
confidence. It's actually used
in, in, in trials and in crime
labs and things like that. So
that's true, pretty Pretty wild,
but in that particular
application, they use more of a
benchtop type system that from
us, but, you know, they can
apply, you know, six to 10
kilograms of force. Very
locally, very, super localized
in a small area. We've done some
tests on some other things, you
know, where we we go to 1520
kilograms of force, again, a
very, very, very tiny area. So
I'm not, you know, I think our
team could design things to be,
you know, used in applications
where there's a lot of weight,
apply to them. It just needs to
make, you know, business sense,
to be honest, I think that's
really the main, the main
challenge main
Audrow Nash: limiter. Yeah.
Gotcha. What about, what about a
sensor without bevels? I'm
thinking about it. So you have
currently the edges around the
gel pad. I'm wondering, like I
imagined for robotics, it'd be
really nice to not have those
edges, because you're limited.
If I'm trying to touch into a
hard surface, does the gel
extrude? A little bit past?
bevels? It's not so you can?
Gotcha. Yeah.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Well, maybe
I should, yeah, it should not
interfere. But I understand your
point. I think if you really
want to mimic the human finger,
you should not have any bezel at
all, and you should actually
have a curved sensor. There is
hard probably, it is hard to
make. But it is not. Again,
conceptually, you know, are the
technology as I described it,
right of having some kind of a,
you know, polymer like material,
some illumination, a camera
behind it, as long as you can
image that curved area, and be
able to reconstruct that 3d
surface of it. It works. So I
don't think there is again,
Audrow Nash: a just you can
calibrate it pretty robustly,
regardless of its shape. I would
think so then
Youssef Benmokhtar: absolutely.
It is a complex design, a
probably will take, you know, a
lot of development to make
something like this. But
fundamentally, I don't see any
limitations from the technology,
it wouldn't actually be feasible
to do it with curved sensors.
Audrow Nash: That would be cool.
Yeah, I was just thinking, maybe
they'd be like edge effects. I'm
imagining like a soft mattress
or something where the edges are
easier to fall off than the
middle because it's kind of
gives more on the edges. And I
was wondering if that would make
it more difficult to sense
accurately on the edges. If you
had no edges, but perhaps it
wouldn't matter, because you
just calibrate what it looks
like for transformations?
Youssef Benmokhtar: Right, I
don't think would be an issue.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Okay, so I
would like to segue a little bit
to talking about you for this.
So you've mentioned that you've
been in tech for the last 25
years. And did you say you have
been leading in tech for 25
years? Or what did you say at
the beginning? Yeah,
Youssef Benmokhtar: I've been
kind of, uh, you know, in
leadership positions, you know,
for 20 plus years. I spent half
of my career in the
semiconductor world. So I I am
still biased to being a chip
guy. At St. microelectronics, I
worked. In the end, a fab that
is now closed in Phoenix,
Arizona is where I started my
career after grad school. In
operation management, at that
time, I'm an industrial and
system engineer by trade
Audrow Nash: was the first thing
what and
Youssef Benmokhtar: Industrial
and Systems Engineering. That's
what I studied in, in undergrad
and grad. And so worked in
Phoenix, I worked in France, in
semiconductors when I left the
semiconductor world, I was
leading the eight bit
microcontroller business unit at
St. Micro. Okay. And came back
to the US to join a company
called Digital optics
Corporation, which I moved from
like from electrons or photons
at the time. Yeah, it was a
company that was using wafer
level techniques. So still
leveraging my semiconductor
experience by actually build
micro optics, you know,
diffractive optics waveguides
and very tiny refract reflective
lenses refractive lenses.
Audrow Nash: I'm imagining just
tiny cameras,
Youssef Benmokhtar: very tiny
cameras, very tiny cameras,
Audrow Nash: because I don't
know what a lot of the words
you've just said mean. Yeah.
Youssef Benmokhtar: So, so I did
that for for a while. That's
actually where I, you know, met
the FLIR guys that were
developing Krypton at a time but
I can't I can't really say much
more than that. But I know a lot
about leptons. And we we sold
actually that that activity to
flare. That's public
information. And I decided to
move to California at the time
because as a technology geek
that I am, I've always felt that
where else can you be but in
Silicon Valley. So after we sold
the site in North Carolina, I
moved to the Silicon Valley, I
worked for OmniVision, for a
little bit, launched their
liquid crystalline silicon
business. And joined some
friends of mine that were in a
company called Photo nation,
which was a computer vision
company. core expertise in, in
face technologies. They've been
doing it since the mid 90s, I
think before many. So face
detection and tracking,
eventually recognition and eye
tracking, Iris, iris
recognition, things like that,
like that cool. And got an
opportunity to join, Magic Leap
do matter reality startup where
I spent almost five years as
their as VP of Business
Development, which helped me
really get access to incredibly
amazing technologies, because to
build the kind of AR headset
that we were building, you're
basically at the edge of
innovation on every front. Oh,
that's cool, which was amazing
for me. So amazing learning
experience, and decided to take
a break, spent a little bit of
time with the family. But I was
as I was doing that, I got
introduced to JL sites, and
really fell in love with the
technology, it kind of had that
similar wow effect when I saw it
the first time as I had when I
experienced Magic Leap in, in
late 2015. And I started digging
into it. And I basically noticed
that companies in every sector
showed interest in GelSight, and
I and I really, you know, it
really intrigued me like it
really piqued my curiosity, to
say, so what should we really be
able to do with this company,
you know, and, and after I met
the, the founders team, and, and
the staff, I basically decided
this was the right choice for me
is to join, joining the company,
it didn't help it grow towards
this vision of making digitized,
you know, their sensation of
tactile sensing. Reality. And
more importantly, I think just
bringing tactile intelligence to
the world, and you know, so
basically bringing these two
pieces of imaging based digital
tactile sensor, plus AI, as the
way forward, you know, for the
for the company. And that, to me
is super exciting. And, you
know, I've, I've enjoyed every,
every minute of it.
Audrow Nash: Now, one thing that
strikes me hearing about kind of
your path, is you kind of like,
pivoted and kept learning and
like, I imagine reinventing
yourself, like each stage. Can
you just tell me a bit about
that, like the experience that
kind of your heuristics? And I
don't know, how do you? Yeah,
Youssef Benmokhtar: that's a
great question. I think what
gets me excited, is learning new
things every day. And, you know,
it needs to have that component
in my life to motivate me, and
help me get up in the morning.
And, and that's what I've been
doing. You know, every time even
when I spent 13 years at St.
Micro, I basically had maybe
five or six different roles,
because I kept kept moving and
being promoted within the
company. Because as soon as I,
you know, I kind of figured it
out, I started getting bored on
I need a new challenge, I needed
a new challenge. And, you know,
the company had been really
great to me by offering many,
many ways for me to get to
advance but it made me to learn.
And I always take it as a person
who will challenge to, to learn
about new technology, and to
envision the best that can
happen with any technology that
I'm that I'm, you know, getting
the chance to work with. And
that's just who I am. I'm just
driven by, by this constant need
to, to learn. So yeah, that's
what drove me here.
Audrow Nash: How do you find
something that's exciting? Like
how does gels like get on your
radar? Or how does augmented ray
or the the headsets you were
working on? How do these get on
your radar for you to consider
switching your area to and keep
learning in that direction?
Youssef Benmokhtar: You know,
I've been blessed over the years
to, you know, build a network of
people. that, it first of all
know me, and they know what I'm
capable of doing. But it also
made me know that I need that, I
need that new challenge. So I've
had actually the opportunity to,
you know, like the Magic Leap
opportunities just to a friend
of mine at our work within the
optics company, he's just like
us, if this is for you, you need
to come and please take a look
at this. And that's what really
happened. And I think in gel
side, it was a bit of the same.
It just basically, by
surrounding yourself with people
that appreciate you for who you
are, and actually just know you,
and they know, you know, when
something really interesting is
out there. You're the guy they
think about, it's like, Hey, you
should take a look at this. You
might be interesting,
interesting to you. So that's
what I, that's what I've done.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. That's
cool. It's interesting how the
network can kind of make you
aware of different
opportunities. And but you hear
about everything through your
connections, in a sense, they
kind of filter correct the
topics, and also can recommend,
like, Hey, this is super cool. I
think you'll love this.
Youssef Benmokhtar: And, you
know, the other thing I would
add is, like, my key motivation
is that curiosity. So it's not
about the, necessarily about the
the short term financial stuff.
So, you know, when I, when I
left Magic Leap, I had the
opportunity to join other
companies, and much bigger
companies that would offer me a
package also can never afford,
and even if we have a very nice,
yeah, so So even if we do really
good, you know, it might not
even match what I could have
done somewhere else. But it was
not interesting. You know, it
felt like, you know, to me, I
would be one person amongst many
not necessarily working on the
most exciting stuff, or they
being very limited in your
scope. You know, that that's
Audrow Nash: not interesting.
Yeah. And that's not a good use
of your time,
Youssef Benmokhtar: I can't see
myself being happy there. I
think to be happy, I just need
that, that I need that
challenge. I need to be learning
some things. And that's why I'm
here. That's great.
Audrow Nash: See, so. All right.
What advice do you have? For
someone, let's say, finishing
university? Given like, the
current climate of everything,
what advice do you have for
them?
Youssef Benmokhtar: I would say,
you know, really work at
identifying what really gets you
up in the morning and, and gets
you excited about contributing
to to our world in a positive
way. You know, at the end of the
day, it's, it's what's going to
matter in the long run. It's not
the material things, it's really
about, you know, Have you have
you had fun, you know, have you
learned things? Have you helped
others learn, have you out
helped others grow? Up, you
know, that, to me is really, I
think what young people should,
not young people everybody
should really think about,
that's the advice I would give,
that's the advice I give to my
own daughters. But that's what I
would say it's just, you know,
you have the foundations, you've
learned things. That's just the
beginning in life is going to be
about continuous learning. And,
you know, do something where you
can leverage what you've
learned, but also when you're
never stop learning, and where
you can actually then, you know,
share your experience, share,
share what you've learned with
others, you know, help help
others also get ahead. I find
that find out to be find that to
be very satisfying. You know,
for me, you know, that the best
thing that I once in a while
hear about is my, some old, you
know, colleagues of mine from
many jobs ago, you know, tell
me, you remember that advice you
gave me, you know, on such a
day? Well, I just wanted to let
you know, I did it five years
ago, and I feel that was the
best decision ever. That to me
is you know, when I hear things
like that, which I've been,
again, lucky to hear quite a few
times in my life. That that what
makes me happy and I want when I
hear that I was like, Okay, I've
done something. Good. So that's,
that's my advice.
Audrow Nash: Let's see. And then
one last question. Is there any
specific things you do or habits
or things like this that you
think have been very useful to
you?
Youssef Benmokhtar: I don't know
if I have good examples there
because I think I would be
scolded at. At home. I think
it's also spending time, you
know, by yourself, I think just,
you know, we've just taken time
for your own, you know, your own
being just well being just
reflecting on what matters, you
know, to you enjoying, you know,
this this earth that we live on,
you know, I do a lot of, you
know, I enjoy that very much.
I'm kind of a, sometimes too
much of a loner, but I enjoy
that. I mean, I enjoy taking the
time to listen to the wind
blowing on the leaves out there
in Boston is really nice right
now. And you know, things like
that. It just helps you to be
grounded, I think and just
enjoying the little things. I
like that, you know, very much
it has helped me. The other
thing is I don't sleep much. So
if you don't sleep much. You
have time to do work.
Audrow Nash: All right. Do you
have any links or website like
contact information, anything
you'd like to share with our
listeners?
Absolutely. I mean, I
would encourage everybody to
visit gelsight.com. We also have
our contact page there. If
you're interested in what we do,
or if you just want to give us
comments, please contact us. We
would love to hear from the
audience. You know, we you know,
we're here to basically help
digital touch happen. So if
you're interested in that topic,
we'd love to hear from you.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Okay. It's
been a pleasure.
Youssef Benmokhtar: Thank you.
Same here. Absolutely.
Audrow Nash: Thanks for
listening to this conversation
with Youssef Benmokhtar. Thank
you again to our founding
sponsor, Open Robotics, and hope
to see you next time