Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Tobias Holmes.
Tobias is a Quality Assurance
Manager at Blue River
technology, which uses computer
vision and robotics and
agriculture. Blue River was
acquired in 2017. By John Deere,
we begin this interview with an
introduction to agriculture and
the problem that Blue River is
working to solve. This includes
talking about row and non row
crops, and herbicide resistance,
both of which I knew very little
about before this conversation.
After establishing the problem,
we talked about how blue river
systems work, quality assurance
and testing and hardware,
machine learning and weed
spraying the acquisition of Blue
River by John Deere, the future
of robotics, in agriculture, and
on education. This is the Sense
Think Act Podcast. Thank you to
our founding sponsor, Open
Robotics. And now here's my
conversation with Tobias Holmes.
Would you introduce yourself,
Tobias?
Tobias Holmes: Hi, I'm Tobias
Holmes. I am currently the
manager of quality at Blue River
technology here and in
Sunnyvale, California, a
subsidiary of John Deere
Corporation. And, and yeah, I've
been working in robotics for
about seven years now.
Audrow Nash: Would you tell me a
bit about Blue River?
Tobias Holmes: So Blue River,
the company started out what
what our co founders, Jorge
Harada, and Lee reading. A
couple guys from Stanford,
decided that they wanted to
bring high tech, you know, high
tech tech high technology into
the agricultural space. So years
ago, probably about 10 years
ago, they started out going
carried harvesting. And you take
what's out there harvesting,
Carry, carry weeding, sorry,
carrier weeding, and in 30 days,
yeah, so basically being able to
look at a carrots and be able to
clean up the weeds that are
around the character that the
character actually gives you
more read more of the harvest,
you get more of a yield from the
harvest. And and that was
something that that was
interesting, there was a problem
that was happening in the world,
they were in the tackling that
using various robotics
technologies, and talk to a girl
who was like, Hey, you guys have
a nice technology here. But what
I really needed to be utilized
is in leading of row crops, and
so Blue River transition from
Audrow Nash: What are row crops?
I don't know that much about
agriculture. And I don't know
about how carrots maybe are not
row crops. What's a row crop?
Tobias Holmes: So row crops are
when you typically think about a
farm and when you're on a farm
where a grower grows, they grow
their crops into these like, you
know, very uniform rows across
their entire field. And that
this allows them to get the
maximum amount of yield from a
particular crop you're trying to
grow, it maximizes the space
that you have, in order to to
get the most out of it.
Audrow Nash: So you just plant
them, like optimally spaced in
lines. And why why are carrots
not row crops? I would just
assume everything is planted in
a row.
Tobias Holmes: So carrots
typically are, you know, they
kind of they're kind of
scattered around. And, and you
just kind of like throw the
seeds as you go out and implant
them. Wherever they're last row
crops, we actually like very
used machines that are very, you
know, particular about where
they grow, where they are,
there's less, there's less
ambiguity, and the in what our
place, they're very, very
structured and very, very light,
you know, every 10 inches, you
know, just depending on
particular crop, they're very,
they're 10 inches of space from
each other 30 inches, you know,
from the next row, it's very,
very prescribed, whereas non
real crops are, you know, they
kind of they kind of are planted
in a row, if you will, but but
but what, what, what typically
happens is you plant a couple in
a row, and whichever one is the
best, the best vibrant one after
a little bit of time, you kill
the other ones, and then you
keep the you keep the one that
you want. And so river did that
kind of work in agriculture in
California. You can imagine
there's lots of vegetables,
fruits that are grown here and
they've grown in that manner.
You planted a couple of them, as
you go down and the ones that's
the most viable, that's the one
you keep, you kill the rest.
Audrow Nash: Okay, and you kill
the rest so that the one that
looks most viable, or best at
that time, has more resources
available to it less to compete
with in that spectrum is a
better harvest. Maybe.
Tobias Holmes: That's right,
it's so better quality
ones.That's, that's right. You
know, you want to give that, you
know, every, every person wants
to bigger to see or strawberry,
bigger, juicy carrot, whatever
that is. And so, so and so that
allows you to say, okay, hey, I
planted these in a nice bed of a
fertilized ground. And whichever
ground is a is is a, you know,
whichever one out of the of the
three or four, that is more
viable. That's the one that I
keep, and then I kill the rest.
That's right. So as you get more
and more, you get more yield is
what we typically call it, a
grower typically, is concerned
about the yield of the crop that
they they are planning, and they
want the most yield for for the
amount of planning.
Audrow Nash: So they have a
certain amount of space, and
they basically want to get as
much product, carrots or
whatever it might be, as
possible for that amount of
land.
Tobias Holmes: That's absolutely
right.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so with row
row plants, row crops and non
row crops like carrots, does the
machinery change for because I'm
imagining like a big tractor
driving down tracks? And so I'm
thinking for the non row crops,
which you said are kind of in
rows anyways, does is it like
squishing a bunch of them? Is
the row was I would imagine it's
going kind of in the seams
between the rows of plants.
Tobias Holmes: And so yeah, so
you can imagine it, there's like
these little mounds of dirt you
create, and even something
depending on where you are in
the country on the world. That
can be different, but But
essentially, you're maximizing
the land space, and you're
maximizing the ability of that
particular seed to to be the
best year. And so the
transition. And so the
transition is, is you don't you
don't carve out so much land,
because you don't know, when you
know, particular crops like that
are fruits and vegetables, you
don't know which one will be the
one that actually takes hold and
is the champion, if you will,
that part of the land to give
you put three or four of them
down to see which one is really
taking the resources out of the
ground. Yep, in a row crop, you
know that, hey, if I plant the
seed here, this probably gonna
grow if I plan in perfect
places, you know, soy bean, and
the particular row crops that
we're talking about soy bean,
cotton corn, if you plant them
there, they're probably going to
be just fine. The thing that
will be the resource, so the
resource wouldn't be the
resource like pool wouldn't be
weeds, it would be the... Excuse
me, I said that wrong. And a
vegetable crop, you want to
plant multiples, because you
don't know what the crop itself
will take? Yeah in the row crop,
you know, the crop itself will
take but then there's
competition as weeds. And so now
you have to kill the weeds and
vegetables and fruits, you need
to plant multiples, because that
that we'll see may just not grow
right on its own. So you can't
just plant one and I know that
that one's gonna, but you got to
plant multiples. Because you
know, out of the if I plant at
least four, one or two of those
guys are going to grow. Yeah,
and then you and then you take
the best out of the out of the
group was in row crops, I plant
a seed that seed is going to
grow the only competition is
weeds. Yeah. And, and so and so
in that situation, you know,
you're planning, you're planting
seeds that are going to grow,
you just now need to make sure
that you you provided the best
environment in order for it to
grow.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So if I
understand correctly, when you
have the non row crops, you just
have like a hump of soil that
goes back in a row effectively
denotes a non row crop and you
just like throw seeds all over
it. Right plants will come up
anywhere in that big wide row
and kill the ones that look less
promising to save the ones that
are more promising. Okay. And in
the row ones, you just have a
narrow row where the seat seat
seats easy. And they Oh, yes.
Right. And so in the non row
ones you are killing the
competing ones of the same
species that are less viable.
And row row ones you're more
concerned about killing the
weeds that are competing with
the crop you're interested in.
Is that correct?
Tobias Holmes: Absolutely.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so with going
back a little bit, so with Blue
River they were starting with
these non row crops. And then
feedback from customers was we
are interested in row crops.
Continuing from there, what
happened?
Tobias Holmes: So Blue River had
to make a shift right that the,
the technology, the actual even
even the agro agronomical When I
say agronomical, I'm talking
about the Cool World, the word
the the way that you know, you
do something in agriculture,
Audrow Nash: Is it like
economical but for agriculture?
Tobias Holmes: agriculture, so
So in this case, we have all the
seeds that are out there, and we
want to get rid of the ones that
are not viable. So how did you
do that, in a way an
agricultural? And so and there's
multiple ways you can play, you
can spray herbicide, you can go
in and dig up the ones that you
didn't want, you know, or you
can you can you can even apply
her fertilizer, and that's what
Blue River did they apply
fertilizer. And what happens if
you apply too much fertilizer to
a plant? It'll explode it, you
know, it'll just grow so fast
that it can't exploded. Realize
think about that is not that
that fertilizer is in that soil.
The other plants that makes the
one that is viable, ie that one,
how can can grow stronger,
because now you have made a very
fertile environment. The ones
that were weak exploded, but
this guy that is not weak, took
that took that fertilization and
use it and grew better.
Audrow Nash: So again, not
knowing much about agriculture,
why does it... so it explodes,
it grows too fast, and then it
can't support that or something?
Why? Why? Why does it die?
Because it grows too fast?
Unknown: Because it's just it's
just the fertilizers a kind of
Yeah, how to put that it is
something that encourages the
plant to grow very fast, but
good plant has to be able to
handle it
Audrow Nash: Does it grow to...
is it like a startup in some
sense, that takes venture
capital funding, and it
basically gets a huge
investment, but if the money, so
you grow rapidly, and then
expenses are coming, so then
the...
Unknown: Essentially, you're
going too fast. And I would put
a similar startup somewhere
going too fast if you don't have
the funding, but the but you
don't have the infrastructure if
you don't have the
infrastructure to handle it.
Right. So that viable crop,
right, that one that is like
it's gonna it's gonna sustain,
that one has already has gained
all the things necessary to reap
the benefit of that fertilizer.
These other ones are set in such
a non capable state, that when
you you feed them fertilizer,
they, they grow so fast, but
they're not capable, they're not
ready for it. In other words,
Audrow Nash: So they grow before
they're ready, and they
overextend themselves.
Unknown: There you go, it's too
much, this is too much ploom.
And a guy,
Audrow Nash: I'm thinking of
like Napolean now and having too
big of an empire, and then it
collapses.
Unknown: It collapse. And you
could think about it as you
could think about it, as I have
too much resources that I cannot
contain it, I cannot help hold
it within my infrastructure. So
I need to so I so what happens
is it just explodes. Whereas the
plants that are the plants that
can handle that they take it in
and they use it and grow, which
is what to expect when you get
you know, like, like an
investment or an increase. And
it is a ridiculous amount.
Right? It is a it would be like,
you know, you give somebody
who's never had a business
before in their life, you know,
30 million, right? Like, they
don't they wouldn't know what to
do with that property. Right?
Yep.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. It's like
getting rich, quick kind of
thing. And then it just goes
away. Okay.
Unknown: They have no ability to
deal with it. Right and no
ability to deal with it. Yeah.
And the thing about that is that
that money doesn't go anywhere.
That money is still out in the
environment in the system. Yeah.
And that and and that next crop
that's next to those to those in
those plants that get killed
that way, reaps the benefit of
it. So you're fertilizing. So
it's kind of a two pronged
process. You're gonna fertilize
your soil anyway, because you
want your plants to grow. But
the ones that are not viable,
you fertilize it to the point
where they're going to die, but
that overlying fertilizer still
stays in the ground and allows
the ones that are not going to
die, to grow, to flourish to be
better. You harvest those, that
ground is still very fertile
with all those resources that
you come in are still there. You
can go plant again next season,
the grounds fertile, it grows
again. You do this process
again. So you're, you're kinda
you know, it's kind of a cycle.
fertilizing the ground but also
getting rid of the the the weeds
to the crops that are not going
to they're not going to make it
right if you give those guys an
extra shot, so that they so that
they they're not going to make
it and then...
Audrow Nash: Is this row crops
where it's weeds that are
competing, or we speaking about
non row crops, or both?
Tobias Holmes: That was non row
crops. So in row in a row crop,
it's a different environment and
that's what I was talking about
agronomical tools, right. And so
in a row crop. You know,
fertilizing the weeds is not the
way to go, right? You don't want
the weeds to grow. You want to
deplete the weeds, you want to
show that was removed?
Audrow Nash: I see. So that was
with the non row crop, what
we're talking about with over
fertilizing them. So you do it
to the non row crop that are not
promising. And thus, they grow
too fast, then they explode and
die. Not literally explode,
probably. But for the row crop,
you're saying now we have a
different strategy?
Tobias Holmes: That's right. And
that's what I'm talking about
the agronomic the strategy,
right is that so and so in
agriculture, in plants, you can
imagine there's this a variety
of plants and in the agronomic,
the agricultural world is just
as varied as humans, right,
there's just life itself is just
so varied. And it's even more so
in the plant world. And so
different strategies are needed
for different types of plants
that you're going. And in a row
crop situation where you know,
the seed is going to take, you
know that when you plant that
seed, it's going to come up and
it's going to come out of the
ground, it's just a matter of
how much yield you're going to
get from it. Your strategy there
is different because now you're
not competing with others, like
seeds, you're completing what
you're competing with, what we
are completely different plants
that are trying to suck the
resources away from the plant,
you're trying to, you know, the
cash crop is what we call it.
And, and so in that situation,
you actually want to kill, you
want to alleviate that leak, you
want to alleviate those plants,
Audrow Nash: Alleviate is a
funny word for that. It's the
problem, you're alleviating the
problem, and thus you're killing
the plant. I see.
Unknown: It's killing the plant,
it's killing the plant. It's
making sure that that plant
because you never really kill
it. You never really kill it,
right? Like like those, those,
Audrow Nash: But you remove it
as a competitor for resources.
Unknown: So you think about
plants, you think about life,
life always wants to persist, it
doesn't really die, right? It's
hardy. That's absolutely true.
Audrow Nash: Only the cash crops
die occasionally.
We purposely we purposely
harvest those, right, but the
weeds are just there. And the
interesting thing that happened,
so just go back, you know, 30
years, they had what roundup
they had they had, you know
chemicals that could that would
you know they have their crops
genetically modified, you can
spray the entire field, we call
that broadcasting. So you spray
the entire field with herbicide,
the plants that you were trying
to keep were genetically
modified so that that herbicide
did not kill that plant. But it
killed everything that wasn't
anything like that all the weeds
that were in that plant that had
a modification in it to that
herbicide. And so all those
plants and what you would see if
you could go down a growth field
and would be what we call clean,
you would only see the crop that
the girl was trying to grow,
meaning there was nothing else
but everything else was dirt in
the field or soil. Only the crop
was there. And that now was the
American agriculture for 3040
years, you know, using these
genetically modified plants.
Okay, what happened was is over
time he is talking about life
and how hard it is you kill the
just dude, you killed all the
weeds that were susceptible to
that herbicide. And the only
ones that are persistent were
ones that were able to fight
through the herbicide. And so
now they became they build up
the herbicide resistance.
Valerie's so now they are the
old herbicide resistant plants
are the only ones that are
reproducing. So now when you
reproduce you're only be
producing herbicide resistant
plants and that is causing a
huge air a huge battle man
gotcha because now you now the
plants are being able to build
up resistance faster than the
engineers can build up new
technologies to actually kill
those those resistant plants.
And so now now you're not you're
having, you know, what we call
unclean fields, fields where
growers are spraying. They're
planting crops and these
herbicides are resisting it. And
so now they have to come up with
something different different
chemicals different ability to
get rid of the plants.
And that's in the timeline of
like the 30 years you said...
Unknown: So 30 years, 30 years
we've been using the Roundup
herbicide, we've been using
herbicide, or I would say the
last 10 years is where they
really become maybe in the last
five years is where they really
become prevalent herbicide
resistant weeds, to the point
where they're, they're, they're
starting to, like, you know,
hey, the strategies that growers
use, and there's multiples, as
herbicide, there's a there's a
will be called a field fighting
you call when you kind of just
trim up the dirt in the row to
kill some of the weeds. There's
multiple techniques, but but
like I said, you know, alleviate
the problem, you want to give
the crop that you're trying to
grow and get killed from the one
that you're trying to sell the
best opportunity to win in the,
you know, in the competing of
resources that are in the
ground. So you want that crop to
get as much of the resources as
you can, and to provide, you
know, the weeds and other
things, less resources so that
they die off?
Audrow Nash: This may be a silly
question, but why not just make
an incredibly resource dense
field and have a bunch of weeds
but also have your cash crop?
Unknown: Because the weeds the
weeds are. The weeds are.
They're called weeds, right?
They're just plants. Yeah, but
we call them we undesirable not
cash plants. And the reason why
is because they they're very
effective and sucking the
resource in that you won't your
cash crop will not crop, they
will take over.
Audrow Nash: Starving it of
resources and they grow way
quicker.
Tobias Holmes: Their genetics
are so that they will take over.
And those viable those viable
crops that you really want that
you want to keep, you know,
which was you know, when you
think about, you just think
about society, and you think
about, you know, just biology
again, in the world, you know,
things that are valuable to
humans, particularly the humans
are things that are scarce. So
things like you know, cotton
soybeans, plants that you could
eat plants that you could, you
could read, you know, something
that was due Sunday, they
weren't just plentiful
everywhere, and everybody could
just have it and it was great.
In order to make that,
especially for the population of
the world today, you have to
very strategically go and grow
it. Right. That's kind of how
the world got as populated as it
as it has, is because we no
longer just kind of go hunt and
gather and just go find where
they're where the right stuff is
off the tree as it grew
naturally. Because in order for
it to grow naturally, you would
have to get in an environment
naturally, that just didn't have
enough competition with all the
other farmers in the area, so
that that thing could grow.
We're very specifically saying,
Hey, we like apples, we like
strawberries, we like
Audrow Nash: soy, whatever else.
Yeah.
Tobias Holmes: So we have to
definitely beat off the fauna
that would that naturally just
grows, that naturally will just
take over. It is and isn't, you
know, necessarily beneficial to
us. It's right, it's plant life,
but we're trying to specifically
grow plant life that's
beneficial to us. And all the
other plant life around is like,
hey, I want to use this. I want
to take this spot up. Yeah,
you're and they don't use much
energy, right, that the reason
why those things are valuable is
because fruits and things like
that need a lot of energy from
the ground. And so, so it's easy
for these other things that
don't bear fruit that don't give
us any benefit to grow and
rapidly take over the land
because they don't, they don't
need a lot of energy because
they don't provide anything of
value to us. Fruits and you
know...
Audrow Nash: Stuff that we can
harvest from them.
Unknown: You can think of the
things that that humans care
about us the fruit, right. And,
and those things. Take energy.
The things that we don't provide
fruit, necessarily don't don't
take a lot of energy. And they
they're prevalent. They're
everywhere. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: And by fruit you
mean anything we can harvest.
Right? So like, I don't know,
cotton? Like the seed probably
is not a fruit. But you mean
that as in something we can
harvest and then use? Is it
correct?
Unknown: Yeah, absolutely. So
the bulk..
Audrow Nash: The fruit of the
labor.
Tobias Holmes: There you go.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Gotcha.
Okay. And then so what was the
strategy for row crops?
Unknown: So the strategy here
for row crops is to, it's a cool
thing that Blue River did, is
because you're talking about
agriculture, you're talking
about a customer in a market
that's been around since the
beginning of the United States,
right? It's this goes way back.
John Deere has been a company
for hundreds of years in the US.
That's awesome. And so the
agriculture is is a mainstay in
the United States. And that
customer in that in that market
is not very open to drastic
changes. They've been doing
things the way they've been
doing it for the past 20 years.
You're not just going to come in
here and say, Hey, I got the
spaceship or I got this cool
technology, they're just gonna
make your you know, they're very
adverse to those kinds of things
because they know what they've
been doing. They've been doing
that for for, you know, for a
long time. And they're very
adverse to very crazy out of the
box changes. And so what we did
was okay, you already use
herbicide, you're already
spraying your entire field,
with, you're broadcasting your
entire field with herbicide to
cover every anchor, right. So if
you got 1000 acre field, doing
spraying the entire 1000 acres
with herbicide, even though
there's only beads in certain
pockets of that field, so you
just bring everything but Blue
River did was with the court and
we did have this novel was a you
know, add a camera to that, to
that a sprayer, the same spray,
you always been using the same
technology, you used to use any
like pointed out things, we
added a camera, the camera can
look at the ground, it can tell
where the weed exactly located,
and then we spray onto the weed.
Instead of spraying the entire
field, you only spray where the
weed is.
Audrow Nash: With the herbicide?
Is it correct?
Tobias Holmes: That's correct.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha.
Tobias Holmes: So now you only
kill the herbicide you only
spray where we need to spray the
herbicide. And you can imagine
like you're reducing the cost of
the grower, you're reducing the
the herbicide that's in the
ground, you know, causing
environmental impact. And, and
so and so now in the give the
girl the opportunity to use the
same technology that he's used
to using, but being more
effective and more efficient,
and you give them the
opportunity. I was talking about
the herbicide resistant weeds,
you give them the opportunity to
use different chemicals. Yeah,
that's right. That's right.
Because before you sprayed
everything, so you have to use
an editing modified herbicide in
crops, because you want to be
able to spray everything, you
don't want the crop to die. Now
if I can just tell you, I can
just hit just the wheat and not
everything else. Now you can use
different chemicals, different
herbicides to target the week.
There you go.
Audrow Nash: Now do you need to
use genetically modified crops
for this? Because you're killing
things in the same field with
some sort of herbicide? Or like,
do you want them to be slightly
resistant to it? So that
something in their system is not
like say you spray this one weed
in this field of cash crop? And
does that impact negatively the
cash crop that's around it? Or
is it a small enough and precise
enough dose? That it just kills
the weed and doesn't damage the
crops? Or is it a trade off
between the two.
Unknown: So nothing's ever
perfect, right? So there's It
depends, depends on the cash
crop, you're using some cash
crops, you, you want to be able
to, you want to be able to
genetically modify them so that
you can spray the crop as well
as the week. And then depending
on depending on the cash crop
itself, you don't want to spray
it at all, you want to spray
justly. And so and you think
about you know, the situations
and the variances of fields, the
variances of crop types, the
variances of wheat, you know,
you have all those different
things, and depending on the
situation, you want to apply a
system that works for your
situation, right. And so the
focus of Blue River, and John
Deere in overall is to give the
customer the ability to tailor
their system to their situation.
And give them a system that that
effectively will work for them,
given the situation. So some
situations you can genetically
modify, spray, just the wheat
and a little bit of the crop and
it doesn't hurt some situations
you want to be able to spray,
you want to target test that
weed only and you don't want to
spray the crop at all.
Audrow Nash: One thing just to
clear up: Would you talk a bit
about the relationship between
Blue River and John Deere.
Because we mentioned it but just
to like explicitly talk about
how they are related.
Unknown: So Blue River was
around right there was a startup
company I talked to you about
the founders. Yeah. And and
eventually they you know, not
just John Deere, but other
agricultural companies were
interested in purchasing Blue
River and I think John Deere won
that war, the war if you will,
and
Audrow Nash: It's nice to have a
bidding war.
Unknown: Sure. So the use of the
technology and the viableness,
and the need, I think is real,
like it is absolutely 100% a
real problem that's happening
across the world. And it needs
to be tackled it like it has to
be tackled. John Deere was was
one of the first people to say
hey, this is a you know, not
just not even just this
particular problem with the
herbicide resistance,
Audrow Nash: Yeah, yeah.
Unknown: Just, you know,
applying artificial intelligence
and in high tech, high tech, you
know, things into the
agriculture, agricultural world,
that now that's a new thing,
right like that these these,
these companies, you know, John
Deere particularly, have been
operating and using, you know,
machines for for, you know,
hundreds of years. And they have
grown a Technic technological
advances, but, you know, they
haven't been implementing, you
know, artificial intelligence
and, you know, high definition
cameras and high, you know, a
very high power computers. Yeah.
And so, so making the next step,
I think John Deere thinking
about making the next step, and
where does agriculture have to
grow, you know, and for the
future, to continue to sustain
and to continue to maintain, you
know, for the population that we
have on this earth, that these
technologies need to be in, you
know, integrated into the
agricultural industry, and saw
Blue River as you know, what the
way that we want to tackle the
problem using AI, using very
high performance computers,
using, you know, advanced
technologies, you know, they in
robotics, they saw that this was
a nice day, this was a nice, a
nice integration into their
company, gotcha them to give
them the ability to, you know,
to use robotics to robota size,
if you will, their machinery
that they had already had, that
they already built, they already
make.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So we then
see, we're spraying herbicide on
the weeds in a cash crop, a row
cash crop field, is this kind of
the, I guess, where does Blue
River go from there before being
acquired by John Deere? Or is
that is that kind of the core
competence of the company?
Unknown: So So we essentially,
you know, the mentality is give
me up to give the, the CRO or
the plant by plant knowledge, so
that they can make a smart
decision. Right, so we have
cameras, we have artificial
intelligence, we have the
ability to make real time
decisions using robotics, right?
So we use robotics to be able to
say, hey, real time, this is
what this plant needs. And that
was Blue River, and still is,
it's blue rivers, you know,
driving force, you know, you can
look at the plant real time and
decide right there. What does
this guy need. And that is, you
know, when you, when you think
about any, any person who's in
agriculture, or, you know,
planning biology, they will tell
you, the plants that grow the
best are the ones that are taken
care of individually, this plant
needs this, this one needs a
little bit of pruning, this one
needs some fertilizer, this one
needs, he has weeds growing
around it. So Blue River was
allowing you to do that and, you
know, skill level, you know, not
not your pot in your house, you
know, where you kind of hand
doing in the field, in the field
and 1000s of acres with a
machine, you know, that you can
just kind of let it do its
thing. And you as the grower
don't have to sit there and do
that.
Audrow Nash: And is it only is
it only spraying plants? Is it
also trimming or any of these
other things that you've
mentioned.
Unknown: So you can you can
imagine the technology can be
advanced, if the original, you
know, this initial, like
induction into the market is
spraying plants for herbicides,
because that is a very prevalent
problem. And it's something that
Blue River was already doing.
But you can imagine.
Audrow Nash: It's cool, because
you can retrofit existing
systems. So that's very nice.
Tobias Holmes: Retrofitting
existing systems, developing new
systems that are very, you know,
optimized. Yeah. Then and then
extending the see and sense
technology, kind of like, you
know, we talked about this a
little bit, you know, seeing and
think and actuate, your podcast.
That's exactly what Blue River,
you know, long term, you know,
overall, that's the goal is to
be able to sense the
environment, do something smart,
and then actually do something
smart to the ground or do some
smart and get world sense. This
is exactly what your podcast
says and think about it, think
about agriculture, all the
different things that you have
to do, you have to plant the
seed, you have to take care of
the seed when it's down in the
ground at the fertilizer, you
have to weed it, and then you
have to harvest it, and then you
take it from harvest and you
have to get it out to the market
so that they can be sold. So
there's just a lot as there's a
wealth of, of tech, you know,
this, the agriculture industry
is just I won't say behind but
just has been doing things a
certain way for a long time and
it's a fertile ground. For new
technology for New for new ways
to go about to bring that that
sense. And they can actually
wait, you know, paradigm into
that world. There's, there's
just oh my god, it's just so
many different ways and
opportunities. Yeah, that's
absolutely right, John, John
Deere and Uber are being
acquired by John Deere to get us
right in the forefront of it.
Because, you know, that's the
one of the biggest agriculture
companies in the world. And, and
so and they do all that they do
everything, you know, from
planting, to harvesting to, you
know, to tilling the ground to
getting it prepared, and as well
as other industries
construction. Forestry.
Audrow Nash: So what do you what
do you mean? Oh, are you saying
John Deere does these?
Tobias Holmes: Yes, yes, yes,
John Deere. And so Blue River,
you know, bringing in the sense
and think kind of a mind frame,
into an industry and until a
company that already has its
footprint across our world and
all established? That's right,
all.
Audrow Nash: And they're,
they're I mean, they're domain
experts at the actual markets
that they're servicing. So
agriculture, and then other ones
you mentioned. So then
partnering with them, where you
guys are being you're helping on
the sensing and thinking side,
and then they can kind of use
their existing systems are
retrofit your systems into it,
or even add your systems design
your systems
Unknown: Integrate them,
exactly. Really great, really at
the foundational level, right?
Let's develop new systems. But
let's rethink how we do this. We
know how we do it already.
Right? But we do it, we did it
already with previous Well, you
know, what previous experience,
now let's bring in this new
technology, and let's rethink
how we could do it. You know, if
we, if we bring in, you know,
different sensors, cameras,
lasers, and sensors, you know,
smart algorithms, and different,
you know, different ways to
actuate in different ways to go
about doing something. And then
now, you know, and now change
the future, right? Like, you
know, you could just think about
all the different ways, you
know, that AI Robotics has
changed the world, and it's
gonna continue to check the
world, you know, before you have
to have a human in the loop,
right? Yeah, human beings,
humans just do it fast,
literally, when it's asked. And
now, you know, you can provide a
smarter machine that can do that
can do this task.
Audrow Nash: Or one person can
do a bunch of fields and
effectively have a bunch of
like, robot workers on the
tractor doing the hard manual
things. Absolutely. Very
focused, intensive. Absolutely.
Let's see. And then. So with
Blue River? What? Wait, so I'm
just curious, I guess, how was
it? You were around? When John
Deere purchased? Blue River?
Correct? That's correct. Yes.
How, how have things felt to
you, as things have changed with
that? Like, how is the focus
changed? Or what kind of
problems are you guys working
on? What's interesting about
being acquired, and the process
of that?
Tobias Holmes: I think it's,
it's very, like, for me,
personally, it's been very
interesting just to see a
company transition from you
know, very, you know, startup,
you know, environment, you know,
get out there and fire in the
belly, we got to make something
we got to continue to, you know,
develop this product that people
are interested in, grow into
now, you've been acquired by a
company, that is totally has the
resources to make sure that you
grow, but we need to grow it in
a direction that is actually
going to be viable, and actually
going to be, you know, a product
is actually going to be put out
to market, and customers are
going to receive and use, and,
and having all of that expertise
and that knowledge of all those
years of John Deere
manufacturing, agricultural
sprayers, and any piece of
agriculture milled with the high
technology. And you could you
could already think that there's
going to be a lot of challenges,
right? That's a two, not
necessarily two different
worlds. But you know, you know,
kind of different environments
kind of have to mesh together.
And I praise John Deere, for
giving us the ability to kind of
keep our autonomy as far as
developing the technology and
going as fast as we can to
continue to develop it and grow
it and, and make changes as we
need. But keep us kind of, you
know, I would call it. What do
you call that leadership and
management? You know, John Deere
has this division, right? This
is where this thing needs to get
funneled into. You guys have the
ability to do whatever you think
needs to be able needs to be
done in order to accomplish
this, this goal here and we're
trying to accomplish and the
goal is big enough and broad
enough, right? That it
encompasses all the things that
they're doing, right? It
compasses, not just the sprayer
part, which is just as one part
that we're working on. And
probably the first thing that
will roll out, just because
we're Were Blue River was the
most mature in the area. Yeah,
but but we could, but we're
already developing other areas.
And so And so John Deere just
has a great vision has the great
wherewithal. And I think because
they have acquired companies
that just have all the
experience, are they the
company's been around for years,
they know, you know, the ability
and the way that they they went
about the acquisition after it
happened, and the way that
they're slowly bringing a sense
of their, into their
environment, and so their world,
but still allowing us to be Blue
River, I think is great. And I
think it says kudos to them.
Because they could have totally
just came in and say, Hey, boom,
we bought everything we own
everything you got, they're
gonna do his like how he said,
and they didn't do that. They,
they, they, they said, hey, they
appreciate you guys have
something special here going on.
We don't want to affect that.
Want to allow you guys to
continue to do that. But we want
you to do it in this direction.
Yeah, in any directions aligned,
which I think is another, you
know, smart thing on them. And I
think what Blue River as well,
to reason why we got acquired by
John Deere is because the
directions aligned very well. So
and so it was like, Yeah, this
is gonna work. Right. This is
gonna work, you know, kudos to
our CEO, for you know, navigate
that because Yeah, absolutely.
Absolutely. You know, making
those making those things
happen. And then he's still
around, right, like our CEO
still here or is still doing
job. You're still managing he
still going? You know, very
important things for us. Yeah.
And, yeah, we can say that this
is working out pretty pretty
nicely. I
Audrow Nash: Hell yeah, so what
was the timeline? So founding of
Blue River acquired by John
Deere...
Unknown: We got founded 10 years
ago, that's, what this is 21, so
2011. Yeah. So and then. And
then, we got acquired by Deere
in 2017. So that's what six
years after the founding, they
got acquired by dear God. Yeah.
And so here we are 2021, four
years after acquisition. Still,
still going well, and probably
going to bring the first product
to market. Two years from now.
Audrow Nash: Two years? Can you
talk a bit about that? Or is
that a secret?
Unknown: I can say that it's
coming. That's about it. I mean,
not any details, but it's, yeah,
the first, the first product
will be is coming soon.
Audrow Nash: Nice. That'll be
exciting. So then, can you tell
me a bit about your experience?
So you, you Quality Manager,
Quality Assurance Manager? Can
you tell me a bit about what
that means? And I mean, I've
been in academia most of my
time, so we don't really have
this, would you tell me a bit
about your job as a quality
manager?
Unknown: Absolutely. So, so
Quality Manager is, you know,
this is an essential part of the
business is to make sure that
the customer receives, you know,
value in that product, and that
the product that they get is
what they expect, not only what
they expect, hopefully it sees
expectations, but But you know,
first and fundamentally is what
they expect. And, and so it's
making sure you know, I think
about it this way, you can have
the startup mind frame, you
know, and just really just gone,
you read this, move fast and
break things with us break
things, you put something out
there, but there's all kinds of
bugs with it. And depending on
your market, and depending on
the customer, you think you
think about your, you think
about these phones, you know, 20
years ago, and they and they had
all kinds of bugs and issues
with them. But the customer you
were dealing with was okay with
that right? There early adapters
are okay, yeah, I can I can I oh
yeah, I gotta do this thing, or
I got to press it two times this
way and do this in that way. And
then it finally works. Right?
You know, so that that was fine
for that environment. But for
our particular customer, you
know, agriculture customer, they
want to bring in John Deere, you
know, name recognition. You
know, it just works. John Deere
has the reputation in the in
the, you know, the cloud that
when I get a bite when I buy a
John Deere, it works out of the
box, I turn the key, it does
what I wanted to do. And if
anything is wrong, they fix it
Johnny on the spot, no big deal.
High quality high, you know, I
pay a premium, because it is the
high quality product. It's the
best, right? It's one of its, I
would say it's the best, right?
It's the best that you're going
to get. And so how do we
maintain that right? How do you
know John Deere has maintained
that over years, over centuries?
How do we maintain that and so
my job is to allow blu rays For
developers, the ability to
continue to grow to continually
to develop this product and
continue to iterate and make it
better, you know, the Bay Area
Silicon Valley, quickly area
area can fail. But when we
release something out, or
release something out to the to
the, to the customer, it is it
has that John Deere quality it
has that this is going to work,
it is robust, it is going to do
what you guys told me it was
going to do. So I'm the kind of
the gatekeeper. I'm like, yeah,
go develop all that cool stuff,
go get in the lab, go write your
code. Let's get out here in the
field. Let's go test it. Let's
go. Let's come up with all the
cool things that we can. But
this is what we can release.
This is what we can, this is
what we can give out. Because
it's ready. If it ain't ready
yet, you know, hey, it's not
ready yet, guys, we gotta go
back rehash. We, you know,
reiterate. You know, and so and
so I want to allow those guys
the ability to continue to
reiterate and continue to
develop product, you know,
features and things, but only
allow John Deere quality
features got ready to go. And so
that's, that's my that's my
cool, cool. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: So does it what
does it look like in a little
more detail? Is it like when I
think of quality assurance
engineers, I mean, I'm at open
robotics, and we have a lot of
software. So quality assurance
for us means like, writing
software tests, or making sure
we have certain amount of code
coverage with our tests or
whatever, these kinds of things,
it sounds like your work is a
good bit more applied as in
like, go in the field. Can you
just tell me a bit more about
what it involves?
Tobias Holmes: It's that right?
Is that and but But you said you
said exactly. It's definitely
you know, unit test, you know,
code coverage of things in the
software stack, right. But it's
not just a software piece of
equipment, it's a robotic piece
of equipment. Yeah, and so and
so it has to actually perform
out in the field. So there's
more things than just does the
algorithm behave the way we
expect, but just the mechanical
devices to behave the way we
expect, can can the cameras and
the wires and the things hold up
to the environment that we're
going to throw them in. And then
again, I said earlier about, we
gave the customer the ability to
use a platform that they were
already used to using. And
they're already used to use it
in a certain way. So they
already used to have in this
sprayer that I parked out on the
corner over here, and it rains
on it, and it it snows on it, if
depending on what part of the
country you're in, you got it
that the environment you're
paying to it, but I can turn
that key next season. And it
goes and it does its job. So
making sure that all of the
pieces and all the all of the
parts come together the
integration, in a way in a way
that that when that customer is
actually my North Star is
customer turns, the key thing
does what it's supposed to do,
or at least tells you hey, you
need to go do something, you
need to go do something right,
you know, your camera cables,
have fried over this past
season, go replace them, you
know, and so making sure that
all of those things are there,
the quality is there in and of
itself. And when it isn't there,
it is very obvious to the
customer, what it is they need
to go through to fix it. And so
it's it's you know, it's unit
testing, it's called coverage,
like a software company that has
those features. But it's more
customer focused, it's more,
it's more customer focused. So
we definitely have to go out and
test it on the machine and give
it real machine time. Yes, see,
to see what the customer is
going to experience and give
them the best experience we can
get.
Audrow Nash: Okay, I'm curious
about the hardware side of this.
How do you deal with software,
if I write tests to constrain my
code to make sure that it's
working, the tests fail if the
code is not working? And then I
just run these frequently. And I
can tell if my code is working
over time. What do you do? So
that that, to me is clear for
software? How do you test
hardware to make sure that or
even like hardware and software
and their integration together?
How do you guys do this? Yeah,
no, I'm sure. I've seen like
with Boston Dynamics, or some
robotics company, they'll just
have their robot do the paces.
So they'll have it run and move
continuously for a week or
something like this. But can you
speak a little bit about this?
How do you...
Tobias Holmes: I mean, I think
it's essentially the same
similar things. I mean, I won't
get into the details of exactly
how, but it is something along
those lines, right, we run we
run that system through the
paces, if you will, I can't give
you all the details, because
that is it is essentially the
John Deere name, their
reliability and The and the you
know, the the the confidence you
get from saying that I bought a
John Deere and I know this thing
is gonna work. This is part of
their secret sauce as part of
their, you know, this is how we
this is how we got to be who we
are. And the I would say I will
say this, the nice thing about
being acquired by them is that
we were able to be brought in.
And so that process of how they
ensure reliability and quality
to the customer. And we could
add that in and that and I think
they you know, a lot of
startups, not every startup, you
know, there's always gonna be
great startups, they're always
gonna, you know, hurry up and
fail, and then figure out the
quality. To do that, and they're
gonna raise it, yeah, they're
gonna do it, right, they're
gonna figure out oh, that didn't
work, change it up real quick.
That works now change it up. And
depending on the customer base,
you have a lot of units, you
have a lot of room to do that,
especially if it's new
technology that's never been,
you know, out there, and your
customer base is like open to
it. You know, our customer base
isn't so much open to things
that don't work, it has to work.
And so John Deere is very, you
know, keen on that. And, and so
all the 50 did a good job of
bringing us in allowing a
startup to see how did you
change transform from making
this cool technology that works?
You know, at first, you know, we
talked about you could talk
about when you develop
something, you know, is that 95%
edge cases are the maker
breakers, right? You can make
something that works 80 85% of
the time, the 9095, you know,
the 9798, those ones are your
problems that take the most
time, right. So those edge
cases, and John Deere has a has
a method for that. And so and so
we and so we work, right, we
continue to work, and we
continue to develop the product.
I can't get into any of the
details other than that, like
you said very clearly is that
you continue to test that system
and method, you have a method of
doing it. So that you know that
when the time you release it. It
is ready. It's ready for the
customer is ready to accept it
is not is a perfect? No. It's
that there's no perfect no no
perfection. Oh, of course. Yeah.
But you have all you have all
you have all the big things out.
And then the rest of it is
there's a system to have the
rest.
Audrow Nash: So is there. So it
sounds to me, like a lot of your
job might involve figure making
decisions about what can and
cannot be included? Can you talk
a little bit to this, I'm sure
it has something to do with the
John Deere process. But also,
it's a value judgment. On your
side, I imagine where you're
going, we need it to be good for
this temperature range, or
whatever it is.
Unknown: That's right, that, you
know, it's essential, right?
Like, there's specifications,
and there's, there's certain
things that are, you know, go
no, go, I try to be very clear
on that. And then, and the other
part of my job is when that is
included, define some things are
just clear. This is good enough,
and this isn't. And then there's
some things that are like, Okay,
this is a gray area, you know,
we don't have a really clearly
defined.
Audrow Nash: Can you give me an
example?
Unknown: So, so, let's think
about the technology, right?
Think about artificial
intelligence, artificial
intelligence, you know, it's
probability, you know, so you
have these, like, you know,
these algorithms and these
metrics that say, okay, hey,
we're about this percentage,
good, on on our detection of...
Audrow Nash: So maybe like, I'm
95% confident that this is a
tomato plant.
Unknown: There you go. 95%, is
95 going to be good enough? Do
we really need to be 97 or is
that is that, where was that
number? And that's hard to say?
And you think about the world,
right? This these machines can
be anywhere in the world, that
various changes depending on
where you are. So you're over
here and this part of the
country or this part of the
world, that's good enough and
other parts of the country of
the world or particular actually
even a particular actual grower,
that's not good enough, I need
this thing to be this well, or
otherwise, I'll just go I'll
just go by the other thing.
Audrow Nash: So work. So I'm
thinking like, okay, considering
you guys are in like all over
the world, you have machines all
over the world. I'm imagining
knowing that if you're using
some sort of like probabilistic
machine learning AI thing for
identifying plants or weeds,
there's probably a good amount
of variation in We there's a
good amount of variation in the
type of lighting you're get
during the day, there's a good
variation in the amount, or like
the color of the soil, or the
makeup of the soil, or anything
like this. And this would
probably make it depending on
the method you're using. A good
bit more difficult to come up
with metrics, I guess, yeah,
this would be a good gray area
examples, right?
Unknown: That's exactly why I
brought it up. Because, okay, it
depends, right? It depends on,
like, all those things you said,
right. And probably oil more
than environment, the lighting
condition and what condition
you're in. And in, I think the
moisture important, the
important piece that I talked
about what quality is, is under
letting the customer know, how,
what quality you're getting.
Right. And so being able to
communicate that, I think that's
an key, I think that will be key
in the future of robotics, as
well, as we continue to develop
the technology. There will be
situations where there's an
expectation, and now we cannot
guarantee you what you'd expect.
And so you know, we tell you,
Hey, you're in a situation now
that we're using fuzzy
probability mathematics. And
yeah, your numbers are are
starting to below come below a
threshold, yet. So now it is up
to you as the union user to say,
Can I keep going this way? Or?
No? I think that is, I think
that's I think that's going to
be I think that's going to
always be the case, for a long
time in robotics. And so we can
get all the edge cases out of
out of a particular application.
And well, how many robotic
applications do we actually have
in the world? There's not a lot
of. And so as we develop these
new novel ones, though, they'll
need time...
Audrow Nash: ...to mature even
more and become more reliable.
Okay, does it mean, you go and
test the robot system in a
similar environment to what the
customer is, and then measure
how effective it is, and then
report that to the customer? I
assume it's not like a real
time, this is how well, we're
doing. system when you're
talking about telling the
customers quality information.
Unknown: So it's both it's,
it's, it's actually some there's
some real time to it right?
There has to be there has to be
in particular, it's a robotic
system, you have to let the
customer know, like, as real
time as you can, that we're not
getting like you're not
behaving, you're not behaving
the way that you want to behave.
Yeah, so you got to be able to
give them that you have to be
able to give them that.
Audrow Nash: Okay, I guess I'm a
little confused, because I'm
imagining like, a robotic system
going and spraying plants. And
maybe it says, we hit 80% of the
weeds. But the thing is, at the
time, it thought every one of
which it sprayed was a weed. So
20% might have been the cash
crop or something like this.
Unknown: So the secret sauce, I
can't give you but but what I
can tell you is that you have to
be able to allow the customer to
know that your system isn't
behaving the way you expect it
to.
Audrow Nash: Oh, right. Maybe
it's just being aware of how
confident you are about the
things you're doing and
reporting that.
Tobias Holmes: Exactly. So So
yeah, exactly. Right. Like,
Audrow Nash: So it's confidence
based, not outcome, you don't
have any real labels for what
you're doing. Gotcha.
Unknown: Well, so so. So it's,
it's so yeah, so it depends,
right? It's a combination, I
can't get into all the details
yet. But there is a I will put
it like this, there's both
components, there is a real
world component, that is real
time. And there's also a a
introspected after the fact, you
know, but you know that you can
go back and look at and you can
and then you can combined.
Right? So so I'll put it to you
like this, if you ran over a
field once, if you've already
kind of been through an area
once. And then you go back
through it again, you know that
that provides you ability to
make different kinds of
decisions.
Audrow Nash: You get to see if
the weeds were all killed, or if
there's a bunch of them still
or...
Unknown: Where the weeds are?
What, what's the density of
them, you know, how the machines
behaving at the time when you go
through that part of the field?
There's lots of different
things.
Audrow Nash: Cool, okay, I
didn't consider that kind of
temporal part of this.
Unknown: There's lots of
different things that we
definitely do both. I would say
we do both something real time
because you want to allow the
customer to know right away that
hey, you're not in a great
situation. And but then there's
also like, what is the situation
exactly in that area? What is
actually going on? Why isn't
that a great situation? And then
how do we correct for it? How do
we make it better? How do we
improve upon it? And so yeah,
providing the customer with the
ability to do that. And so those
are two, I would say, those are
two things that I constantly
have to make sure that we're
doing. And you know, it's cool,
because we're developing both,
right, we're developing both of
those infrastructures. Now real
time, like, you know, and so
when that product gets released,
you don't present the customer
ability to do both, he can say,
hey, right now, this is what's
going on, what do I do? He can
make a decision, or she can make
a decision on what do I want to
do now? After the fact that can
come back and say, hey, that's
what happened at that time? How
do the next time we go through
that situation again, time
better, gotten better prepared
and better to make a better
decision? You know, what new
information? And then and then
you know, that, that turns on
another, you know, opportunity
or ability in ways to, to tackle
it, you know, versus the real
time real time you're making a
decision right now. You know,
planning ahead of time is always
better, right? If you can plan
ahead for that's always better.
Audrow Nash: Now, would you talk
a little bit about doing work in
the field for this kind of
thing, or like, getting out in
the field and testing your
systems? Just I think that's a
very interesting part of what it
sounds like your job involves?
Tobias Holmes: Yeah, absolutely.
So we had to get out in the
field. And I got a team of
people, you know, and also in
coordination, not with just my
QA team, but the the, the field
team, that's always out on the
machine is always out there. And
being able to, to understand how
the machine actually behaves in
the field. And so, you know,
that it's not the same thing as,
like an iPhone, or, you know, a
piece of software that's
presented in a web server, it's
an actual piece of equipment
that's put in the field, and
another customer uses it, you
know, puts their hands on it,
and, and actually gets out there
and use Google ads. So it's very
valuable to me to get the
customer's input the customer's
point of view, the novel use
cases. So putting out something
in the field with a customer,
you know, you have in your mind
as an engineer and the
engineering team, this is how we
think you should be using our
product. And the customer will
just say, Oh, I can do this,
this and this, and totally
something you didn't even think
about. You don't even think oh,
wow, well, I didn't know that
you're going to go through this.
Because, you know, we didn't
design it for that. But it can
totally be done in that way.
And, and so that's always cool
to get their their point of view
to get their use cases, because
then we can start to think
about, oh, wow, this could be
used this way. We didn't even
think about that. But let's make
sure that way works. Let's make
sure that that way works,
because now we know, right? They
want to use it that way. Yeah,
they want to use it that way.
I'm putting it out in as many I
think any company wants to put
their product and all the as
many environments and use cases
as they can to get the 97 98%.
Because you don't know, right?
Somebody is using it this way.
You have your describe where you
want to use it. And you don't
know, you know what those edge
cases are in your software
stack, your mechanicals that,
you know, of what's what what
did we break down at? Were we
not good enough that, you know,
and, and so if you don't get out
there, and you don't give
yourself the ability to to, to
do it in as many different
environments as you can, you're
going to find an environment
that you didn't prepare for that
you're not capable of handling.
And you just have to figure that
out later. So we're, we're keen
on, you know, and the nice thing
about being acquired by John
Deere is we can go a lot of
places across the country and
across the world to make sure
we're getting the big slots of
use cases.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Cool. Let's
see, blowing up a little bit. Or
going up a few levels. What do
you think? Where do you think
robotics and agriculture is
headed?
Tobias Holmes: I think you know,
you know, robotics in general is
the future of all industries.
Agriculture is going to totally,
you know, 20 years from now it's
going to dominate. There's going
to there's going to be you know,
these machines will be
automated, and, and, you know,
self sufficient, you know, 2030
years from now, or a girl will
be able to say, hey, I want this
to happen on my land, and it
will happen and it will be very
little human input. You know,
there'll be there'll be some
spots for human input. But you
know, unless someone from
Congress or somebody, you know,
artificially removes the stress
that is going to grow. I mean,
it's the only way for these
things to grow, right? Like
there's, there's ton of machines
as Thailand, we have to feed in
a growing population, bunch of
people. Yeah, we have to do that
efficiently as we possibly can.
We have to take in as much
information as we can about the
ground, what's going on on that
ground? What do we need to do?
How do we get the most out of
it, and then get it ready,
again, season after season, year
after year, and we've been doing
that as humans, but a lot of
human input. And I mean, that
works. But in the future, that's
gonna, it's gonna be less human
input is going to be a systems
input, because we're finding
that the system, you know,
systems can can remove that
human input into a better and
more efficient. And so FFI
anything, you know, fair history
of history says anything, when
we find more efficient and more
effective ways to do something
we do with that way.
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah, for sure.
We're, I'm curious to where you
get the number of 20 to 30
years?
Unknown: It's just the
technology growth? Right. Like,
it's the, you know, that could
be off, right. I'm giving myself
buffer there.
Audrow Nash: For sure, I'm just
curious about order of
magnitude.
Unknown: It's the technology?
It's the ability, you know, so
AI is very, you know, I won't
say it's infant. But applying it
into real world problems is
still fairly new. Yeah, there's
some there's some areas, but
we're talking about agriculture,
agriculture, I think it's still
fairly new, like we were, I
think we're at the cutting edge.
I think blueberries probably
ought to be right, right at
right at front, right. And so
and so what and where does it
go? And what are the new things
that we're going to learn? And
how are we going to apply the AI
and the machine learning to this
environment? You know, along
with, you know, the cameras that
can can withstand the rush the
harsh environment, but still
give you all the information?
Yet all the like you talked
about a little bit earlier, the
cloud changing the lighting
changes the all the things?
Yeah, all the things so much
variance, so much variance. So
you, you put your dino, you
know, it's nice, very controlled
environment, you're in this very
real world natural environment.
How, you know, cameras, just one
thing, you could do this, all
these other things, right, it's
all the other sensors, and then
the machine and the machinery
and what you're trying to
actually do with that machine.
Can those you know, the human
hand, right is a, you know, a
very complex, very dynamic piece
of machine, that we still have a
very hard time. robota sizing?
Yeah, awesome. Dynamics is
pretty cool. Right? I think they
got some pretty nice dynamics,
but I don't think they have a
nice hand.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Focusing more
on local notion, the local most
universal robots or right hand
robotics or some of these other
gripping, I don't know.
Tobias Holmes: Those gripping
technologies, right. In the
garden. It's been, yeah, it's
really simple. It's for it's for
the application, right? It's for
the application, right? It's
like, okay, if I want to grab a
thing I can do I just need a
thing that does this. So that
that mimics some parts of the
hand. Yeah, but the hand can do
so many different things. And
so, you know, just, you know,
how do we do you know, so that's
the mechanical, more complex,
the categorical,
Audrow Nash: More sophisticated
in the mechanical part? Because
yeah, you're right, right now we
have very, it's like most very
fine manipulation. With, in an
environment where you're, like,
in a highly unstructured
environment doesn't seem to be a
thing yet.
Unknown: There's lots of there's
lots of dynamics right? And when
you get when you get out to the
real world talk about
agriculture, you know, that this
this this harvesting companies
now I think they got robotic,
like, they got he's got suction
things, but he's still suck to
suck the thing with a vacuum.
Right? And so that I can kind of
work in if you can manipulate
it, you know, and you suck it...
Audrow Nash: Little things for
picking strawberries. These
kinds of things. I think I saw
this at the Queensland
University of Technology in
Australia.
Unknown: You can get in there,
and you can kind of grab it, you
know, and that works in those
environments. But you know,
there's so many diverse
environments.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it's hard and
not very general. Yeah. At this
point, I believe I mean, I don't
really much.
Unknown: I think I think
initially there's going to be
people who are I got a
strawberry grabber, I got an
apple grabber, and then somebody
is going to make the universal
So I grab stuff, yeah, whatever
it is, whatever it is, you want
me to go grab, I go grab it,
right? So the mechanics have to
get to that point where I can
just grab anything, you know,
and the human hand can do that.
So I would imagine this, because
how our brain thinks that we
make stuff that is, you know,
but then again, with AI, they
might say, Oh, no, your hand is
not the most optimal grabbing
device, that's other device that
you can grab, it's completely
different than everything else.
So that's the other cool thing
that AI brings is the ability to
rethink about our own, you know,
designs, we come up with these
designs, and it's like, oh,
that's not the most optimal way
to build the structure. If you
build the structure with these
very like, to us, they're not
submitted, we typically build
symmetrically and you know, the
forces are very nicely applied
across these symmetrical, you
know, trusses, good things. And
AI can say, oh, no, if you put
this really long one here, and
this one here, it has all the
same constraints set as your Is
there a symmetrical thing that
you've been developing for for
hundreds of years? Are you
Audrow Nash: Are you familiar
with much work? I'm not? But are
you familiar with much work
where it's like design related
things that use some sort of
maybe an evolutionary strategy
or something in AI? Is this what
you're about?
Unknown: Yeah, we definitely. So
we do some we do some developing
Blue River, right? It's not?
It's not, it's not, you know,
across the board type of thing,
but we do some of our own of
that, right. And we do sort of
our own, how can AI affect the
design? That's what we do some
of that.
Audrow Nash: Something or, like,
the length of a part of it.
Unknown: No, I think I think it
is just like, you know, you
fundamentally give it a problem.
And, and let it do its thing.
It's actually like rocket
science. We got some of our guys
are like, you know, smartest
guys ever. And we got some super
smart guys here. Oh, my dad,
and, and, you know, some of
those guys just go out and say,
hey, I want to do this thing
here and give it a problem. I'm
gonna let the I'm gonna let AI
and the algorithms and the
techniques come up with fine.
Yeah, there you go. There you
go.
Audrow Nash: Hmm. I wonder, I
wonder if there's difficulties
there. Because of I assume,
well, I'm pretty sure you would
have to do it in simulation. And
in simulation physics doesn't
really match up perfectly with
our Oh, no, that. Yeah, yeah. So
like, the attack is very hard to
simulate.
Tobias Holmes: So you gotta you
got to get the you got to get
the test stuff up, right, you
got to build something, you got
to, you know, prototype it get a
texture rig up, see what you can
learn, you know, in river river.
And I think I think most
companies are all about that,
right? And every engineer would
love doing that. Right? Oh, hey,
there's this new thing. We got
to develop this new test rig
that that's saying, Yeah, let's
figure out how it works. And
totally, we, you know, that's,
that's part of the that's part
of the cool part of Blue River
is that, you know, depending on
what project you're working on,
there's still that goes on,
right? There's still that, hey,
I got an idea. I don't know
where this is gonna go yet. But
can I get a little bit of budget
to build a little something, and
let's see what we get. Cool. And
if, and if you get down, we
started to see promise. that'll
continue to get fans that will
continue to get like, Okay,
we'll keep developing. Keep keep
looking at that. Keep figuring
that out. Keep coming up with
that. And I think I think all
companies at some point, you
know, I think they do they have
to you have to do that. Right?
If you want to, if you want to,
you know how to have a John
Deere, you know, stick around as
long? Because we have to have
somebody out there. Yay. Yeah, I
want to figure out how to do
something that is totally no one
else is thinking about. Right.
Yeah. Totally put a little bit
of investment in that. And, my
God, what can come out with
we've come up with some cool
stuff is, you know, just
scratching the surface. I think
we got some of the right people,
you know, kind of like leading
the direction there to continue
us to grow there. Yeah, I think
I think yeah, I think that that,
and you talked a little bit
earlier about, you know, the
kids and the growing of the
population so that they are
capable of bringing those ideas
seed.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, actually,
that's that's kind of a good
segue into what I would like to
ask you about, which is I mean,
so you have kids, and you've
been encouraging them to program
would you tell me a bit about
this?
Unknown: Yes, so So I got I got
two daughters, my oldest, now
she's a nurse. And so she was a
little bit behind the power
curve when I, when I got into
engineering, but but but I did
explain to her that, you know,
robotics, you know, computing
and, you know, these actual
devices that she uses as a nurse
are going to converge, right,
and that device will do a lot of
things for you that you're doing
right now manually as a nurse,
and so that she should pay
attention to it. Right. And so
she, so she, you see has Riley
she's been, you know, keeping up
with, you know, a little bit of
the technology, magazines, you
know, around around the medical
field, and the new devices that
are coming and even like, you
know, I talked to her about
months ago, she was talking to a
doctor about these new these new
What do you call them, you know,
so you can a doctor, they put
that little thing on your your
finger in your policy and
system.
Tobias Holmes: Yeah, so she's
talking them about new ways that
you don't even have to put that
thing on there, you know, you
can just come in the room and in
the room has the environment,
when the patient comes in, it
just gives you like kind of the
patient's whole thing, right,
you can bring them in, and like
3d Walk around them, like they
just kind of stand there, you
can kind of walk around and
like, Okay, this is going on
here, your heart rates here, it
looks like we got some
distraction here on your phones.
And so technology is far away.
But, but it's getting there,
right. And then this is where
the future is going. And so our
doctors like, you know, paying
attention to it, you know, and
likes her because she's like,
interested in those things. My
youngest daughter is more of the
the one that I you know, I have
more of impact on she is she's
becoming a biomedical engineer
and actually go to school,
University of Florida. And she
was about when she was about, I
would say about 12. I had her
writing, writing small scripts
and Python, I used to do some,
some robotics work out in
University of Florida for Joel
teen, she used to come visit me.
And we'd sit there and and one
of the cool things about it was
that was Code Academy. For
Python, my daughter's super
smart. And the way Code Academy
is set up. It's just it gives
you a nice little introduction
into programming, and Python
syntax. And so you can start to
slowly learn how to program and
you can start to slowly
understand Python syntax, which
isn't so complicated. It's not
like C++, you know, it's a
little bit more, you know,
syntax see heavy Python, you
just like, you know, you make
these senses, you make these
things that is kind of make
sense, right? If this happens,
do this, that happens do that.
And there's not a whole lot of
syntax around it just kind of in
which I learned that in school
anyway. And she was able to, you
know, to start developing, you
know, smaller programs that
could do our homework and stuff
for you. And, yeah, and so now
she's like, Yeah, Dad, I want
to, I want to build robotic
arms. And I want to, you know,
build like these kind of like
robotic prosthetics for people,
right? Because she remembers
when I was in the military, she
and I got a buddy of mine who,
who lost his arm in the
military. And he's got a very,
you know, it works. But it's
really primitive, like a fork
kind of fork finger arm thing.
Yeah. And she wants to give them
hands, right? She wants to,
like, you know, hey, I want to
be able to make and take the
fork away and give him the
ability to grab things. Yeah.
And but, you know, what did she
get that desire from the wanting
to do that? And it was because
of the accessibility of
programming. And, and things
like Python and Ross, write
Python, being able to give you a
really high level language that
isn't overly complicated to
start writing a program. It's
very close to how you just kind
of think and write things down
when you're writing stories and
things. And then Ross Ross gives
you the ability to say okay,
hey, I got a I got this module
that does this, I got the
camera, the camera takes in
images. And I can get a process
image. I've got the sensor that
tells me what the height is up
and down. And I can break that
down into numbers. Essentially,
you break all of those things
down into numbers. And if you
understand enough mathematics,
you can now take camera images,
you can take sensors, you can
take lasers, you can take all
these crazy things, you know
that are you know, no one knows
how, how that how the camera
works, like how does it take the
image? electronically? Yeah,
exactly. That that's Oh my God,
how long it will take you to
understand, you know, yeah, it's
like an undergraduate degree.
Yeah, the sign What's behind
that, but but if you can tell me
hey, I can give you the you
know, I can give you an array,
you know, a vector of pixels and
what those pixel values are, and
those correlate to colors. And
then you can decide to project
that on to another screen that
just like displays numbers, you
can almost see the face that
you're taking a picture of, even
in ASCII, right, like we even
without it even would actually
give you the color values, I can
give you an ASCII
representation.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, or just use
OpenCV, and then have it do face
detection or some sort of thing,
some other existing library,
You learn OpenCV, and then you
become your, you become a guru,
right? Like you really get
OpenCV. You gotta learn the math
behind it, right? So you got to
learn the math behind it. But
you don't the tools, the tools
give you the accessibility is
the cool part. You make it
accessible, you make it easy for
these kids to get into it. And
so and so you get the the little
touches, I think I talked to you
about this offline, was I had a
kid, this this January, he was a
was Cristo Rey has a high school
program where they bring you
know, other representative high
school kids and merge them with
a mentor from a tech company, to
one talk this kid how to how to
cut his camera on from a
microphone, using Python, using
Code Academy, quickly learned
how to do let you know simple
programs and modular
programming, and bring in a
library, this is the library for
your camera. It's just how you
cut your camera on. There's all
these other API's in that
library that can like focus the
camera and go look at different
things. But I'm just gonna, I'm
just gonna show you how to cut
it on and off. Yeah, and hit
record for you. And then I'm
going to show you this other
library that takes your voice in
and you can teach it words, but
you know, teach it that camera
teacher that on and it loads it
from your voice, if I tell it
ain't gonna work, but from your
voice, it knows what cut means
and has a camera on and knows
what that means. And it sends
the signal to the camera to turn
on the camera API. And he's got
that working in the kids. It's
like, Oh, yes. Like, he was so
upset about it, right? It's
like, I love and see that. I
love to see that because that
kid's gonna grow, you know, I
don't know he's gonna do in his
life. I only mentored him for
for about four or five months.
But I showed him wonderful
though, what is cake, what he's
capable of doing? You know, and
it was over four or five months.
That was just, I just scratched
the surface. And I always
iterated. So this is just
scratching the surface, if you
actually want to be able to do
this for real, and get paid,
like I get paid to do it. You
need to go to school, you need
to learn you need to actually
understand the math behind it,
you need to understand the
details behind this so that you
do it the most efficient way the
way we did it was a way they
work, right. But this isn't the
most efficient, the most
effective way and ready for
sure. And if you really want to
get a job doing that, you can't
go get a job making this right
now because you're just a kid,
right? But if you get a
credential that says I know how
to write software, well, I know
how to develop cameras, and I
know how to develop, you know,
sound devices. And now you can
go get a to this. Yeah, how cool
is that? Right? How cool is it
to go get paid to make these
kinds of devices into make these
things that affect the world.
And he was totally, you know,
he's totally stoked about it.
And that that, to me is the key.
That's the key to get our kids
reback focused and, you know,
technology and doing smart
things. And I'm kind of bias.
I'm a little older. I'm 43. And
and I think like, you know,
there's a good chunk of our
kids. I think every generation
has this, we just want to be
like tick tock influences. And
they want to you know, they want
to do things that I like, Yeah,
that's cool, when that's fun,
but that isn't like, you know,
progressing society. Right?
Yeah, some way but you really
need to be studying, you really
need to be understanding, like
standing on the shoulders of the
guys that came before us, you
know, with this technology and
growing it. And it's not easy.
You know, learning that calculus
and learning that, you know, the
physics...
All the required skills.
Tobias Holmes: That stuff is not
easy. So how do you motivate
those kids to stick with it when
you know you got three
dimensional calculus? You got
integrals, and why am I doing
this? Yeah, I could go vo here
there was a tick tock dance.
Making my money that way. It's
like Nah, you get to actually
once you learn that stuff, and
what does that stuff apply to?
That's another thing I think
schools fail at is I agree
completely explaining to you why
is math important? Yeah, one
plus one is soup. Okay, that's
great. That's good for a simple
math. Why is it that I need to
know the integral of something
what what usefulness is that?
Yeah, this may give them
something that is actually
tangible.
Audrow Nash: Totally. This is
why I think it's such an
important thing that you're
mentoring people. It's like It's
hard to expect teachers to
understand, like K through 12
teachers to understand the
reasons that engineers use, say
sinusoids, or linear algebra or
whatever math related.
Unknown: Pythagorean theorem.
Yeah, for sure.
Audrow Nash: All the programming
concepts. But so like you who,
as someone who actually does,
it's very important for you to
go hang out with kids, I think.
And me too. Like, this is
something I hope to be able to
do in the near future, like, go
help help help high school
students or something like this.
As someone who's actually
applying these technologies, and
be like, Oh, this is why
sinusoids relevant, or whatever,
which is something my teachers
were not able to give me. When I
was learning them.
Unknown: You learn them, you get
the grade, you know? Yeah. I
don't know how you got into
engineering, but it wasn't
because you're learning sinusoid
like it wasn't your high school
math teacher.
Audrow Nash: Not robotic for
sure. I got into electrical
because my dad told me I should.
And then robotics was like, Oh,
this is awesome. And so that's
how I got into robotics.
Tobias Holmes: Robotics is
that's the cool thing about it
is like, it's it's really world
world, it's kind of hard
sometimes for computer science,
you know, to kind of explain,
okay, yeah, you make this
website. But in order to make
this website, you got to know
all these, like data structures,
and all this other stuff that is
not necessarily website base.
And then in the, you know, the
backend stuff is a little bit
more complicated, but you know,
being able to tie it to
something that's real world, and
I think robotics, is a very cool
thing, because there's just so
much, especially right now,
there's so much room for things
that are not there. You know,
when when kids are usually the
engineers, or the kids who are
like, I wish this could work
like this, we got this thing
already. But why couldn't they
work like this? Like who, you
know, I'm not the guy who made
it, but why did they make it
like that I would have made it
this way, I would have been
something like this, I don't
know how to do it. But if I
could, I would have made it this
way, I would have made my
camera, you know, fly around on
a drone and follow me around the
house, right? Like, and then I
don't have to just sit in my
chair, and have this video, I
could just go for a walk. And we
could have this video, right?
That'd be super cool. You know,
and we got it, we have that
technology now. Alright, but if
no one ever developed that and
thought of that up, that
wouldn't have happened. And, and
we got to give those kids the,
you know, I think early on the
early on is a photogram. Because
the technology is accessible.
Now, it's, it's not as
complicated. It's not like our
grandfathers and our fathers,
you know, entry level to get in.
It is now at a level where I can
teach my seven year old
daughter, you know, hey, this is
how you program a little math
equation in Python. Yes, how you
take variables. And this is how
you make these variables do this
map. And this is how you get a
result out.
Audrow Nash: Or even this is how
you talk to your camera. This is
how you run an optimization.
This is how you do these things.
Because these libraries exist.
So it's a lot of infrastructure
that you would have had to build
yourself.
Tobias Holmes: Oh my god,
optimization optimization. I
just learned about that like
grad school. Optimize this
thing? What does that for? When
you want to optimize? You know,
all of your resources in the
best way? So you're not wasting?
Yeah, if you don't, you know,
it's a very complex mathematical
thing. Yeah. But it's a very
intuitive concept. It's a very
intuitive concept. Because you
can totally teach a kid how to
use a library, this will
optimize your output. And that's
what you want to use. That is
what's going on totally right.
It's totally right. And then
they like, oh, I actually want
to I actually want to know what
optimization is. There's a class
for that. You could actually go
learn the math, right, you can
actually go learn to improve
optimization algorithms, because
there's, there's not just one,
there's multiple different ones
for different situations.
Audrow Nash: Yep. Yeah, concave.
It's like not, and ones that are
not concave. All these things.
Unknown: All these, and you
constantly gonna need to use
that, you know, going forward,
especially with robotics,
especially with all of these
different, you know, new
technologies that we're
developing with AI, all that
stuff. If you really want to get
in you want to make your own
robot that thinks for itself,
you know, Hey, these are the
ways to go. And every kid isn't
gonna want to do that. But I
think it's going to bring a lot
of kids, I think it will bring a
lot of kids you know,
Audrow Nash: Let's see. Wrapping
up because we are running out of
time. I would love to hear
advice that you would have for
someone say like teenager
someone just about to go to
college who might be interested
in robotics. Any any advice for
them?
Unknown: Um, high school or a
brand new college grad. You're
definitely doing the right
thing, this is the way to go. I
would say that, you know, the
most, you know, one of the most
important things about college
is determining what you're going
to do for your future, like,
what are you going to do, you
know, a good majority of the
rest of your life. And robotics
is the future, it is the way
that, you know, society is
going, you know, for better or
for worse, for the next, you
know, 50 to 100 years, you know,
you can go get a job, you know,
developing, you know, something
that is, I don't know, you can
go be a firefighter, or, or a
gas station mechanic, you can go
do something that is, you know,
not necessarily, you know,
cutting edge, or there's,
there's some work to be done in
it, you know, I don't want to
down up into crease. But there's
some people that you know, that
graduated college with degrees,
and are working at like CVS, or
someplace that is like, you
know, you went to college for
four years or more, and you're,
you're not even working in the
area that you want to go study
in. If you got to study
robotics, you're going to have a
job for the next for the rest of
your life. Kids nowadays, they
ain't going to school for to
learn software, mechanics,
robotics integration. There is
no end. There is no...
Audrow Nash: You mean that
there's lots of opportunity, no
end of opportunities.
Unknown: No end of
opportunities, right. And then
the the areas to go specialize
in, or just, you know, even more
broader, you know, what is it
about robotics that you are
interested in? You know, I would
like for us to develop a
robotics degree. And I think
some universities do have that.
It's probably not very well
defined. And they probably are
retired universities have well
defined one. But no, because
it's a lot of things, right?
It's program. Yep. It's a little
bit of electrical, it's a little
bit of mechanical, right. So
it's a little bit of the three
main disciplines, right, that we
think about electrical software,
mechanical, right, it's those
three things combined, to do
something real world. And so
there's the integration part.
And so if there's a, I would
say, a good defined robotics
program would have those three
things as classes, read a little
code, understand the basics of
circuits, understand how
mechanical devices work, and
then understand how to pull
these things together to dues
will work in the world. And then
allow the students to go and,
you know, and sensors, right,
bring it in sensors, utilizing
sensors, and then allow a
student to go, what are you?
What are you most interested in?
You know, what did you like the
most? What do you want sensors,
more, you want to write code,
you want to build robots, you
want to, you know, you want to
build the circuitry that powers
up the motors that powers up
the, you know, the devices, and,
you know, right solar solar
devices that that, you know,
bring the energy and that way,
you know, all sorts of things.
Yeah, the dried out, Oh, my God,
the areas of, of words are where
they're going to go to dive in
deep. They're endless. And so
it's the way to go, I would I
would even say, go develop, go
get a traditional degree,
undergrad, right, but get a
traditional, if you already know
if I know I want to write
program, or I know I want to
write circuits. Or I know I want
to, you know, I'm more
mechanically inclined, and I
want to do mechanics, do that.
But absolutely get your master's
in robotics, take that
knowledge, and then go into
robotics after that. Okay,
because that knowledge is going
to then that knowledge is then
going to allow you to build a
better robot. Right? I can, I
could probably as an undergrad,
undergrad is usually too broad,
you don't ever get enough. And
if you if you go too broad
across all those disciplines,
you will never know enough. But
if you're a mechanical, you got
a bachelor's in mechanical. And
then I show you robotics, you
now know how to apply your
mechanics to this robot
situation or you know how to
apply your software.
Audrow Nash: For the control
theory, or things you you learn
as a mechanical.
Unknown: There you go. So you
get the foundation, and then
apply that foundation to robots
and things. So think about what
robot and what about robot so we
should be introducing our kids
in high school to robots. It
should be as fundamental as
like, you know, they had those
old schools that were like,
where you had like ROTC and you
had Homeric and you had shop
class, you know where they show
the kids how to do so all the
stuff we should have a shop
robots class, all go in, all
kids get in it. You got to pass
it right like you got it. You
got to pay attention here
because this is gonna be part of
your life whether you like it
Not, but those kids who are
really into it, hey, what part
of it do you really like,
because this is where mechanical
engineers, they build it. This
is where the electrical is guys,
they do the circuits. This is
the control guys, they develop,
you know how it knows when they
go up or when they go down on
when to go this way or when they
go that way. This is computer
vision guys who really get into,
you know, open CV in a write
codes, you got to know how to
write software, in order to to
be able to utilize the camera
and utilize the sensors. So you
so you got to be a software
engineer. And so now those kids
know what they want to do. They
get out of high school, they
know what they want to go do.
Yeah. And if you don't want to
be a robot guy, then yeah, go
could be a banker or finance.
With those guys, we need those
guys suit. But that's really the
kids that are like us. I believe
we're all nerds. We're all those
kids who are like breaking apart
something that your mom had when
she was a kid. When you were a
kid, you have your mom's like
radio or something like that.
And you're like, oh, yeah,
that's that's us. Right? That's
our, our type of kids. And I
wish I wish I had a high school
teacher that showed showing
robotics when I was that age,
because in that age, I'm even
more I was even more fired up
about school and stuff then than
I am now. And I'm still fired up
about it. But man had I know,
then I would have already picked
my stuff. Like I went to the
military. I did a very long
around the way path...
Audrow Nash: To come to where
you are now working on the
future.
Unknown: Yeah, I would have
loved to have just been right
bing bing right on it. Because
this is this is it, man, this is
my passion. You know, creating
things in the world and
understanding how technology
works, and then being able to
leverage the technology to
create a new thing. That's
that's me. I think that's a lot
of I think that's just every
engineer. I think most of us,
you have to be like passionate
in order to get the capital. She
can't get through this though.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. All right.
So now finally wrapping up Is
there any like websites, blogs,
like your company blog, or your
any any contact info you'd like
to share with our listeners?
Unknown: So there's two things,
I don't have the websites of
topical head. But there's two
things...
Audrow Nash: I can include them
in the post. So Blue River one.
Tobias Holmes: So along the
lines of, of young kids getting
into technology, Crystal Ray
program, it's a high school
program, that, uh, that, you
know, I would, I would advertise
it to parents who have young
children who haven't went to
high school yet, who want to
give their kids a little bit of
an edge when it comes to high
school other than just going to
the top High School in the area,
which that's there too. But if
your kid doesn't have the
opportunity to get there to the
top High School in the area,
Cristo, Rey is particularly
structured towards kids who are
not going to get into the top
high schools in Cupertino for
the opportunity to work with
professionals in the robotics
field, or any professional
field.
Audrow Nash: Is it a common
model that other high schools
follow? I imagine listeners will
be all over not just in the Bay
Area, too.
Unknown: I'm not sure I'm not
even sure.
Audrow Nash: I heard about FIRST
Robotics is really good to get
high school students or maybe
even younger.
Unknown: So that was my second
one. That was actually my second
one. So I got a I got a we got
like, five or six first robotic
engineers, I got one of the guys
who's in FIRST Robotics on our
team, who is a He's like one of
the he's not only went through
from you know, from grade school
to high school and graduated and
went on he's like, a, an
administrator now in FIRST
Robotics. So he's, he's like,
he's a very like pivotal FIRST
Robotics person, and just the
whole organization. And we
probably got through his through
him. Another five people that
are from first robotics. And
these guys Oh, cool. These guys
are amazing. They're amazing.
Audrow Like, I can't even I
can't even put it into words,
man, these guys. They're young,
and they're on it. And so I
would say, first, robotics is
absolutely a a thing. A good
thing to get your kids involved
in. If you have it, right like
that. To me, those are the
things that I wish I had in high
school. I wish I had a high
school focus towards
professional development. And I
would I wish I had a high school
that that had the first robotics
program I would have told you
partake of it, and I wouldn't
kicked ass and because I because
it's you get because I get the
kids who are interested in that
Get the kids who like, I want to
do this, I want to make robots.
I think one of our guys, one or
two of our guys is in the battle
bots competition this year, they
just had they just filmed and so
they're in the battle bots
competition. A couple of our
guys were are there not even
full time employees out there
interning, working for NASA
helping them nasa develop some
of their software stuff in
robotic stuff. And, and just
this a great group of having
that great foundation, you know,
the right things. And it's very
targeted to robotics, which is a
tough thing to go find, like,
you know, a hiring manager and
robotics is you can find a
software engineer, I can find a
mechanical engineer, I can find,
I can find the individuals, I
need someone who understands how
we do this in the robotics
environment, the parts and how
they really is. And that is that
is a little bit more
challenging. When you get these
guys like this that have been
particularly focused on a
robotics environment that is so
much better. It's so it's so
great, because they already get
it. It's a real time system. It
has to work in all kinds of
environments, lots of variables.
Oh my god, that is the greatest.
So first, robotics is my second
one. So those are two things
that I that I think, I think
that I would point people to go
get more involved in crystal re
FIRST Robotics. There's another
one, but I can't think of the
name of the song won't bring it
up. But um, yeah, if I, if I
could start all over again, or
if I could, my kids are both a
high school now. But if they
could redo it.
Audrow Nash: They'd be doing
that. Doing that man,
Tobias Holmes: they'd be doing
that. That's not waste. It's not
waste our kids signs that the
future is going to be
ridiculously competitive. And so
that the better the Headstart
that we can give them the
better. And so crystal Ray gets
you in a professional mind High
School, at the high school
level, we should start thinking
about, you know, even some
people will say even before, I
feel like great school, I feel
like great schools, you should
give them some chocolate, right.
So serious, but high school is
sounding good, serious. Oh,
yeah. And from there, let's go.
Let's CCS kids. You know, let's
keep us competitive. You know,
and that's, and that's no
robotics, because, yeah, that
that that is the future man. The
other things, you know, you
know, outside of robotics areas,
they're going to still be there.
But they're, you know, they're
going to be using robotics to
man, the bankers and, and the,
you know, what else? What else?
Is there? The retailers, they're
going to be using robotics.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. All right.
Thank you.
Tobias Holmes: All right, man.
So, I hope you enjoy the
conversation. And I appreciate
talking with you, man. It was
great, great pleasure about talk
about you know, Blue River
robotics and, and what we do
here, man, you know, the
future's bright. So, you know,
let's continue to contribute to
that. That's for sure.
Audrow Nash: Thanks for
listening to this conversation
with Tobias Holmes. Thank you
again to our founding sponsor,
Open Robotics, and I hope to see
you next time