Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Tim Chung, who
is a program manager in the
Tactical Defense Office at the
Defense Advanced Research
Projects Agency, also known as
DARPA. We speak about the DARPA
subterranean challenge or SubT,
which is a robotics challenge
that aims to develop innovative
technologies to augment
operations underground. I was
excited about this interview, as
I have heard a lot about the sub
D challenge around the edges
here at open robotics. But it
wasn't one of the projects that
I'm working on. So I was happy
for this opportunity to learn
more. From the interviewer, it
seems like the SubT challenge
was a great success, and that
the challenge stimulated a lot
of great work. You'll hear more
from Tim during this interview.
I also found it fascinating to
talk about how DARPA picks their
robotics challenges, and very
importantly, how they scope the
difficulty of these challenges.
This is the sense think act
Podcast. I'm Audrow. Nash. Thank
you to our founding sponsor,
open robotics. And now, here is
my conversation with Tim Chung.
I Tim, would you introduce
yourself?
Tim Chung: Sure. Hi. My name is
Tim Chung. I'm a program manager
at the Defense Advanced Research
Projects Agency, or DARPA. And
I'm the program manager for a
couple of programs that involve
robotics and autonomy.
Audrow Nash: And so this
interview is mostly going to be
about the subterranean
challenge. Would you tell me a
bit about that?
Tim Chung: Sure. DARPA
subterranean challenge is all
about inspiring folks from all
around the world to discover
revolutionary technologies for
robotics, so that they can help
in diverse underground settings
for time critical missions.
Audrow Nash: And so this
competition has already
occurred, correct? Yeah, what is
right, what did it look like?
Like, what kind of challenges
were involved?
Tim Chung: Yeah, so I like to
describe the DARPA SubT
challenge, as we call it, as
kind of like this underground
scavenger hunt slash triathlon
for robots. So the general idea
here that we've heard time and
time again, from many of the
folks like those first
responders that need to go into
really challenging environments
is, you know, how come this one
piece of component technology
works in the, in the one tunnel
or the or the one parking garage
that I tested it in, but not in
all the others that I have to
take this equipment into? And so
the SubT challenge was about
how do we get robotic
technologies to work across many
different types of underground
settings. And that includes
human made tunnels like mines
for mine search and rescue,
urban underground. That's
everything from subway tunnels
to infrastructure, like storm
drains, to parking garages, and
even naturally occurring cave
network. So for the cave rescue
type settings. How would you get
robots to be the best
triathlete? Not just the best
runner cyclist, but you really
want that well rounded, robust,
capable set of teams or robots
that go do this. And the problem
that we posed in the safety
challenges, this underground
scavenger hunt, DARPA goes into
these environments, places,
objects of interest, and it's up
to these teams of robots to go
out and find them and report
them back to their human
teammates.
Audrow Nash: What would be an
object of interest? I could say,
what's an example?
Tim Chung: Yeah, so we really
intentionally set up a whole
array of artifacts, as we like
to call them. So you might
think, for example, we put a
survivor artifact. This is a
mannequin. So it looks like a
survivor. It has that visual
appearance, but it also was a
thermal mannequin. So it has a
thermal signature that's human
like, wow. And it even had a
voice box. So you could have
voice recordings or sound
recordings in there. And so
those robots going in to look
for the survivor artifacts. Of
course, most typically carry
cameras, that kind of makes
sense. But if you wanted to do a
little bit better, or use other
cues, maybe you're going to have
a thermal camera on board, or a
set of microphones. And that's
just one example of the 10 types
of artifacts that we placed in
these courses. We had a cell
phone in there that on the
camera, probably really hard to
find, but with its Wi Fi, in
Hotspot mode on cool and
Bluetooth and discoverable mode.
Now you can start listening for
RF signatures for signs of life.
We even had something we call
the gas artifacts. And this gas
artifact clearly has no visual
signature, but instead, in this
case, we're, of course being
saved. So we use co2 carbon
dioxide. But you can imagine
that, that these robots equipped
with co2 sensors, gas sensors
could be used to figure out
where there's good air versus
bad air or noxious chemicals
that might endanger those
responders going into these And
then environments. And so this
quite wide array of types of
artifacts meant that you can't
just send in one robot with one
type of sensor, but in fact,
likely benefit from teams or
robots carrying an array of
sensors to kind of cross cue and
help each other out much like we
do as humans, or you
Audrow Nash: could I mean, so I
could imagine one robot that has
like every sensor possible, but
maybe this isn't the best
strategy. So then you said,
teams of robots, what does a
team of robots look like?
Tim Chung: Yeah, well, one of
the things that we have
telegraphed early on in this
whole competition, and this is
the combination of multiple
years of teams coming together
to build and ultimately break
some of their robots. But we
said attrition is not only
possible, but likely in these
types of really challenging
environment, terrain and other
things. So for any team that
came with that one glorious
robot, loaded out with all of
its sensors, and that's really
putting all your eggs in one
basket. And so, you know,
thinking through what that means
for your strategy for your, your
competition, gameplay, if you
will, really led many of our
teams to think about
diversifying their robot
portfolio. And that not only
means two types of sensors that
go on different types of robots,
but how they even use them in
terms of like the positions on
the team or the roles on the
team. So all of that coming
together, you had all sorts of
robot types that can get into
crawl into different spaces,
maybe fly into high verticals or
other open areas, some had legs
that could walk upstairs or
downstairs or traverse. Adding
more rugged terrain, tracks,
wheels, you name it. That's what
the challenge is all about is to
go and highlight that the
problem is this, bring your best
and brightest solutions to
figure out what solves these
problems.
Audrow Nash: And I'd like to
just think about the kind of
make explicit to like, difficult
robotics challenges that are
involved in this competition. So
like, whether it was like, Can
you speak a bit about it, like I
mentioned, like mud and
reflective surfaces, and like
all sorts of other things. But
what were some of the challenges
that were especially difficult
for robots in this situation?
Tim Chung: Yeah, you name some
of them, for sure. I think
having been crawled through a
number of tunnels and urban
settings and caves myself, you
know, I can testify, I can
testify that these are the types
of challenge elements that made
it hard for humans, let alone
robots to navigate. So some of
those you already mentioned, the
types of surfaces, mud,
moisture, puddles, water, you
never know, we might be able to
see your tell if the puddle
depth is just an inch, and I'm
going to be able to step on
right through. But the
reflectivity of that and the
difficulty that robots might
have, that makes it a really
daunting kind of, you know,
survival question of whether or
not to step foot or roll into a
potential puddle, or, you know,
potential hole. Yeah, lighting,
lighting is a major issue. So
oftentimes he or only relying on
the lighting you bring yourself.
A lot of times there's dust or
fog, or certainly in emergency
settings, you can imagine things
like smoke, including many of
your sensors. So thinking
through what kind of paradigms
you would use to be able to
navigate when you really can't
see, again, in the context of
cameras, so DARPA used smoke
machines to go and learn from
sections of these environments,
so that we would intentionally
stress test some of that. And
then you start to learn, you
know, things like what types of
sensors are transparent to
certain types of dust or a if I
fly my multi rotors, my flying
vehicles, they're going to kick
up dust as they're flying
through. Yeah, as was the case
in these minds. And that can
hose your senses as well. So
self inflicted something
problems as well. So
verticality, I'll throw that one
out. So the three dimensional
nature's a really big player in
these underground settings,
because you're not just going
out, but you're also going down
or up. And so elevator shafts to
stairwells of varying types to
scrambling up older piles to
wow, other opportunities to look
in these wide open caverns that
you might find a real real, you
know, like a real diverse set of
those kinds of challenge
elements. And never knowing
what's around that next corner
is, is perhaps the most daunting
challenge for most of these
robots.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, sure. How did
you how were teams structured so
I know there was the hardware
and the software come or the
systems and simulation
components of this. But for the
hardware one, how did you say a
team can have some certain
number? How do you organize what
robots a team could have? And
was there standardization?
Tim Chung: Sure, well, as you
mentioned, there's the systems
competition and the virtual
competition. And there were our
our sister competitions, where
one could build and design and
break robots. And the other, you
would do all of that in the
cloud in a simulator. And so in
the context of the parameters,
which we defined the challenge,
it was, quite frankly, quite
loosely defined intentionally.
In some cases. It's the you
know, without constraining the
design or solution space,
sometimes that's where you find
those really creative or
solutions, innovative solutions,
right. And so this is
specifically for the hardware.
The system, yeah, version of the
competition now. Yeah, that's
right. And so we would specify
that the type of environment is
a coal mine, and highlight that
most robots, if you want to
reach all parts of the course
need to be able to fit through a
one by one meter area. So
something like a manhole cover,
if you elected to bring much
larger robots, then yeah, you
still might be able to access
parts of the course. But you're
probably going to be leaving
some points on the table, if you
can't access some other segments
of the course. And then beyond
that, quite frankly, DARPA, you
know, left it to the competitors
imaginations, to identify not
only what they might face, but
what robot types or technologies
would be advantageous for them
to bring two to conquer that
kind of an environment. So there
was no limit on the number of
robots, there was very little
limit on the style of robots.
There were some safety
considerations on maybe exotic
fuel types or what have you. But
other than that, teams were able
to use existing available
platforms, and then really just
keep on sensors or payloads,
radios, or what have you on top.
Or we did have teams that design
robots from scratch, really
thinking through the nuances of
these underground environments
in their build design power. So
yeah, what, you know, clean
sheet approach to trying to
solve a really hard technical
problem as a kind of a mechanism
here for identifying interesting
solutions that, you know,
frankly, we might not have seen
or thought about. And we too
narrowly defined the problem.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Was there
like a budget constraint for the
teams? Or was there was it like
open budget?
Tim Chung: You can kind of buy
by and bring whatever you will
for the systems competition?
Yeah, it really was kind of open
teams could and in fact, many
didn't seek out external
sponsorships or donated
hardware. One of our teams found
some repurpose some robots that
he found on Craigslist. Wow,
that's crazy, was able to turn
those into ground robotic suite.
Right. And so being really
creative with both the the the
resources that you have, and the
solutions you want to bring to
bear. Yeah, that's where a lot
of that creativity came.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Well, so
what was the what did some of
the teams look like? Like? How
would you describe some of the
robots maybe that show kind of
the diversity of teams of robots
that were entered?
Tim Chung: Yeah. Well, what was
really exciting from my
perspective about this empty
challenge is we had constructed
it in kind of a iterative
development manner. And so we
started off, for example, in a
coal mine, and we call it our
tunnel circuit. So, of course,
this human made tunnels,
thinking about the mine rescue
type scenarios, consulting with
mine, rescue responders, and so
forth. We went to a coal mine.
And then approximately six
months after that, we went to an
unfinished nuclear power plant,
and that was our urban circuit,
and then working and exploring
the possibility of kind of
transforming a cave into a test
course. But of course, we did
have to cancel that due to
COVID. But then, the final
events allowed us to bring
together all three of those
types of environments together.
And well, I'm sure we'll have a
chance to talk about that here
in a bit. But we fabricated this
course that allowed teams to
test their robots against all
three of these environment types
all in this magnificent course
that that DARPA fabricated. And
so, the reason I bring that up
is because you saw there was no
one form factor for a team,
there was this continuous growth
or evolution, if you will, who
will have both the individual
technologies, but also the team
compositions. And so we saw a
lot of robots that were wheeled,
and we tried to see some flying
robots in the tunnels circuit in
the coal mines. And I can say
that the wheeled robots did
well, and the flying robots did
not. And that was a great
learning point. Whereas we pivot
to the urban circuit. Now these
are expansive think everything
from warehouses to elevator
shafts to other things that
these drones really helped allow
robots in Canada teams to go and
explore places that just the
ground robotically would never
have been able to do. And then
also saw the showcasing of
legged robots, these quadruped
Ed robots, so that they could go
up and down stairs with a fair
bit more ease than some of their
wheeled counterparts. And so you
kind of see this progression of
both tailoring the fleets right
who's going to be in your
starting lineup might be a
little bit shaped by the type of
environment you're going to send
these fleets of robots into. But
by and large, that continued
learning process culminated in
the final event, where I'd say
you saw a pretty healthy mix of
air grounds, wheeled and legged.
We even had marsupial robots, so
ground robots carrying aerial
robots on their on their back,
piggybacking them, it's so cool
to other parts of the course.
And really, that, that
diversity, the fact that there's
not one and have common makeup
of a team, I think is a hallmark
of kind of the, you know, the
the what we're going for in a
challenge of being able to tease
out all these various ways to
attack this problem.
Audrow Nash: Now, how do you, I
guess, so you have these teams,
these teams all have the
hardware. They go and the
competition is about finding the
markers, or what we find them
the points that artifact
artifacts, artifacts, and also
it was about what total distance
covered or something like this
with this, these were the two
significant indicators of
performance,
Tim Chung: or Yeah, so work, we
yeah, we, you know, we kept it
as simple as you have a fixed
amount of time, you have an
hour. And you have to go and
find these artifacts. And what
we mean by that is you have to
be able to return the location
and the type of the artifact
that you found, you know, you
have to do that location
positioning to within five
meters. So the idea here is,
yeah, so you go into these
places, you have no GPS, I
should have, you know, maybe
stated that upfront. And so
you're moving through these
environments, and you know, it's
pretty easy to get twisted and
turned around and get lost. And
so being able to report out
where you found that survivor
artifact, for example, to within
five meters of global position.
So that if you had to send in
humans and would know, that
location, it'd be pinpointed
within, nominally within arm's
reach. That's the kind of
notional metrics for
firefighters, you want to get
them within arm's reach, because
it's going to be smoke filled,
and they need to be able to
reach out, touch the thing that
they got sent into to go find.
So within five meters, you have
to go find that out, and it's
not sufficient to have found it.
But you have to get to get that
information back out. Right? You
have to get it correct, of
course, what type it is, but
then you have to report it out.
And if you successfully report
out the physician to within that
five meters and the correct
time, then you get a point. And
so the aims that find the most
artifacts in that hour, are the
ones that take home. Yeah. It to
do the victory lap at
Audrow Nash: the prize. And it
was the prize was for the what
was the prize for the
competition?
Tim Chung: Yeah, so we had cash
prizes. This is one of the
hallmarks of these DARPA Grand
Challenges. And so for that
systems competition, building
the robots in such the top place
to come $2 million. Wow, to
their credit, that's awesome.
And Wow, very good. Like
publicity and everything to
which is wonderful. Yeah. All
right. It's the glory of winning
the challenge for DARPA.
Audrow Nash: So the robots going
back to finding the artifacts.
They would you're not providing
the robots a map of the minds or
of the environment beforehand.
They're building it while
they're going through it. Is
Tim Chung: that correct? Yeah,
that's absolutely correct. In
fact, that's one of the
hallmarks of how we constructed
the SubT challenge. Neither
robot nor human knew the man on
these competitor teams has set
foot inside this course and know
anything really about And so it
really is about exploring the
unknown environment and then
exploiting it to go and find
those artifacts quickly and
returning that
Audrow Nash: information.
Gotcha. So the robots are
building a map while they're
going in it. And this is why you
can get twisted up. So if the
robots building in an accurate
map, say it's like a crew
accumulating error as it's
building the man, yeah,
absolutely, then the map might
be inaccurate, inaccurate. And
then you could, you could say, I
found something, I found it
here. But because it found it,
and the map is distorted, the
location is wrong. And they
would get no points because of a
distorted map. Gotcha. That's
right. Now, one thing that I
imagined because it's or that
I've seen discussed in watching
some of the videos about SubT,
one of the major challenges was
networking. Can you talk a bit
about this?
Tim Chung: Yeah, sure. I think
this is probably one of the
understated types of problems,
when you go into these
underground environments, that
no amount of testing in a lab or
in even the basement of a
university building, will really
get you the feel of RF, the
radio frequency of underground
environments, because it's just
so tightly coupled to everything
from the thickness of the
concrete, whether they're steel
girders, or you know, rebar, if
there's, you know, metallic, you
know, metals in the in the soil,
you know, all of those, if it
rains that morning, it that
plays a role. And so because of
those dependencies Sue so hard
to really think about
communications in a robust way.
Now, that was one of the four
technology areas that the subsea
challenge was deeply interested
in. And so we did see teams
really get in some cases, both
surprised and confounded by how
they're calm solutions were
working under ground. So we saw
a lot of different approaches,
we had some teams come up with
tethered robots that they would
deploy from the outside, and
tethers long as they could to
maintain connectivity. And that
robot, imagine, yeah, it's a
long cable. I certainly twisted
it will get snagged it would be
a tangle hazard. And so there
are many, many good reasons why
not to use a tether, but some
were able to make good use of
that. There were others that
used breadcrumbs. So now I'm
carrying breadcrumb relay nodes
on on the robot. And as they
traverse either fixed amount of
distance, and to like console
and Gretel, they were at corner.
Drop. Yeah, that's right. So
they would drop.
Audrow Nash: Hansel and Gretel.
You're right.
Tim Chung: Yeah. breadcrumb
comms nodes. And that would
allow them to relay their
communications from robots robot
or robots a base station. And
then you had other models of
comms, which was, you know, I'm
gonna live without
communications, I'm gonna go,
I'm gonna go off the grid for a
little while do my searching,
scouting, mapping, finding. And
then after either a set amount
of time, or maybe I have really
good data that I don't want to
lose, I'm going to come back
into columns, and then try to
dump it, you know, to my
teammate, or, or to the base
station. So there are all sorts
of columns technologies, but
also come strategies that
emerged as a way to deal with
the difficulties of RF of
communicating underground, is
there.
Audrow Nash: So I guess there's
a lot of structural things that
make it really hard to do radio
frequencies in these like
tunnels and things like this,
like you turn a corner, and then
the signal kind of just doesn't
bounce down the hall back down
back through the corner, and so
you can't get it out. And so
that's why there were all these
difficult. This was this was
such a difficulty. Right?
Tim Chung: Yeah, yeah, exactly.
And that's a good rule of thumb.
You know, if you turn the
corner, your signal goes down
dramatically. Yep. And, you
know, if you've ever had those
kinds of problems, getting your
cell service, working in a
subway station, or, you know,
something like that, you know,
that RF just doesn't propagate
as well underground and through
the earth. And so that's
something that the teams really
had to wrestle with.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, I'm curious
about. So the motivation for
this competition. Part of it,
it's first responders and things
like this. Can you talk a bit
more about this? Sure.
Tim Chung: Well, I'd say it was
highly motivated at many of the
robotics technologies We have as
well as some of the component
technologies, whether it's
sensors or radios.
Audrow Nash: You still there?
Yep. Still, yeah, you're saying
so many of the robotics
technology seems to freeze.
Tim Chung: Yeah, there's so many
other robotics technologies that
we had, you know, four years
ago. You know, even the
component technologies at radios
or component sensors, they were,
you know, frankly, limited in
how robust they were how
resilient, they were to that
vast, very diverse set of
underground settings. And so
that's kind of know, from a
technology point of view, we
viewed this DARPA subterranean
challenge as a way to spotlight
and accelerate technology
development, not just of these
individual small component
technologies, but in fact, how
we think about integrating all
of them into resilient systems
of technologies. And I think
that's kind of the technology
motivation. But when we come
back to it operationally, you
know, if there is this period of
time where an emergency response
scenario is occurring, and the
incident commanders marshaling
our forces and trying to figure
out what resources he has
available, wouldn't it be great
in that kind of roughly one to,
say, four hour time period, you
know, that, that golden hour, if
you will, or she knows enough to
send in humans, you know, at the
at great risk, wouldn't it be
great to send it robots, if we
could do that, and pinpoint
where the survivors are located,
or trapped or otherwise, or even
if it's what kind of equipment
these first responders should be
carrying in with them. That was
kind of the key takeaway, if you
can tell me that I should be
bringing in shoring equipment,
because the ceiling might
collapse. And that will prolong
and reduce risk to the
responders that have to operate
in that environment. It'd be
great that the firefighter
didn't have to go in there
first, figure that out, come all
the way back out, and then carry
in all of that equipment. Same
with re breathing equipments,
and things of that nature. So
just being able to we like to
call it actionable situational
awareness. Yeah, it's it's not
just not just the map, which is
really helpful. And in fact, you
know, a lot of folks just kind
of would be grateful just to
even have a map. Yeah, but DARPA
likes to go well beyond what is
needed today, and anticipate
what would be really beneficial
in the future. And this notion
of actionable situational
awareness, is this idea of being
able to provide the incident
commander, who's about to send
in her teams of humans, the best
possible set of information like
hazards, where key objects of
interest are like those
survivors, where you know, where
blind corners might be, where
she might lose comms, all of
those points are very relevant.
And that's the kind of
information we really want it to
be able to develop the
technologies to be able to
provide or in the long run, so
that really served as the
motivating operational setting.
Yeah. And I think it's been
exciting to see how this
technology is mature to try to
meet that Mark,
Audrow Nash: for sure. To me, it
seems like the two hardest parts
of this competition for robotics
teams would be first, the
networking, and then also just
the mobility, getting around in
these environments, because I
think, like, you can find
different sensor pack, and maybe
I'm mistaken in this. But I
imagine you can find different
sensors that are good in
different environments. But they
may have big, they may be bulky,
they may have three power
requirements, whatever it might
be. But it seems like given the
constraint of these tunnels, or
these environments, where cons
aren't really good, it's like,
the big benefits of this
challenge would be testing
actual robot hardware in these
environments to see how well it
can do. And maybe like, what
approaches might be a bit more
robust. And then the second part
would be okay, now that we have
these robots moving around, how
do we get them communicating
their information out? Or
connecting? So I mean, like, you
could have kind of done robots
that aren't doing much of the
compute other than like, their
localization. And whatever
you're doing, they're sending
information all the way back
outside, for processing and kind
of keeping a global state of the
situation or whatever it would
be. It seems like kind of the
two areas that are pushed most
by this competition.
Tim Chung: So So you nailed
them. And so in fact, we had
four tech areas that we
predominantly focused on the
first. The first ones you've
already mentioned, it's the
networking. Mobility is the
second one. You got to be able
to get to these places, of
course, but the other two areas
that I'd also highlight are the
autonomy the decision making of
these robots in the face of
significant uncertainty. And
fourth and final was the
perception piece. So how do you
tie together? Not just like you
said, the sensors, but what you
do with that information? How do
you fuse different sensing
views, right? Those myriad
sensors that you might be
carrying? How do they provide
you with a common picture of
what is actually happening in
this environment? And so all for
autonomy, mobility, networking,
and perception, we kind of
really need to all come
together, for sure. And we found
the most successful teams were
the ones that really thought
about it holistically, and they
didn't, again, rely solely on an
autonomy solution to solve all
of their networking problems, or
didn't, you know, invest all of
their dollars in the best radios
and forego thinking about
sensors in perception? So?
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it's like
four dimensions, really? And
yeah, to be successful in this
company?
Tim Chung: I think that's a
twist. Yeah, that's a true
statement.
Audrow Nash: I think I need to
change the name of this podcast
to have something about
networking. Because something
thinking acting are kind of
They're analogous to three of
those. But then, yeah, working
systems, robots, and have fun.
Tim Chung: And, and that's kind
of another insight coming from
this competition has been the
role of teams, not just, you
know, we might think of robots
and humans as teammates, and you
have robots and robots as
teammates. And so just like you
said, the name of this podcast,
is this additional element
where, in addition to what
autonomy, perception and
mobility I might have, as an
individual player, how do I
leverage the team so that I can
cover all the bases
appropriately, so that maybe I
don't need, you know, it's like
the relay races, I don't need to
be the best cyclist. If I know,
I'm a good runner, and my
teammates are a good cyclist,
oh, they can help augment what I
might be deficient in. And so
that, that kind of level of
flexibility, kind of the, the
design choices that that just
explodes. The design space,
really. And, you know, I think
that's really one of the
fascinating pieces. And so
communication, communicating,
teaming is that additional
angle, additional perspective
that the teams really needed to
think about and not again, not
just on transmitting bits, over
wireless signals, but in fact,
what information to which
teammate when to send this
information, stuff like that.
And it turned out to be a really
interesting dynamic to the way
this research progressed.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. And it's
interesting, it kind of catches
my attention, because you were
saying triathlon earlier. And I
didn't quite understand. But now
it's like, there are mixed
events that each mode of robot
may be best at. And so it's
like, if one robot say a flying
robot is really good at going up
elevator shafts, which might be
a very important thing in this
competition, then that robot is
specialized for that, but it's
not going to be good for
exploring in general, because it
might kick up a bunch of dust.
And that could be prohibitive to
its sensors, so then it can't do
its job. Well, this kind of
thing. It's a triathlon, because
it has many events at which of
which different modes of robot
may do better. Yes, yeah.
Tim Chung: And yeah, exactly
right. And even calling it a
triathlon kind of glosses over
the fact that our urban
environments, when you think
urban, or your listeners are
thinking about urban, they might
have many different mental
pictures of what urban
underground might actually be.
Some might be thinking about the
sewer system, or others might be
thinking about the metro rail or
others are thinking about where
they park their car, in the, you
know, in the basement lot. And
so that, that even within a
single so called event, right,
like, like running, it's like
running in a very different very
courts and trying to figure out
how
Audrow Nash: best suited you're
running. You're running. Yeah, I
don't know, upstairs, you're
running. Like there's a ton of
different environments. Exactly.
It's like a Tough Mudder. In a
sense.
Tim Chung: That's not that
sounds like a future DARPA
program, right? Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. How did
you? How do you disseminate the
results of this? Because I
imagine a lot of teams came up
with clever solutions. There was
probably some push in terms of
algorithms or ways of doing
things. How do they results get
pushed and folded back into the
public.
Tim Chung: Yeah. So that's one
of the things I'm probably most
proud of from a kind of a
community sense is that the
subsea challenge competitors,
you know, they are competitors,
they're all vying for that top
prize. But in the end, they were
all wreck, you know, recognizing
that this is a an opportunity as
a community to leap ahead and
change that, you know, potential
trajectory of, of this research
in robotics. And so many of
these teams have gone to great
lengths to open source their
code, to share data extensively.
In fact, one of the limitations
of trying to, you know, with,
with our off the shelf, image
classifier, so object
recognition, you can get off the
shelf classifiers. But what do
you need, you need a lot of
training data, Well, turns out
finding training data in
underground environments and
various lighting out there for
that, that's just like, you
know, I left it Yeah. And so,
you know, finding that and
aggregating that, and even even
collecting such data is also
very intensive, and time and
labor. And so we found teams
actually sharing their datasets
by collecting so they had this
kind of pool of data that they
could train, and improve
collectively. And I think that
was kind of just one small
example of how communal and
collaborative that this
community ended up being. And so
all of that to say, even amidst
helping each other, you know,
whether it's lending, monitors,
and screwdrivers all the way to
sharing open source code and
data, I'd say all of the members
of the subsea community has
really embraced this idea of, of
sharing it, and, and helping
this community grow. So you can
go to their listing of
repositories they've shared, not
only in their publications, but
also in their online videos.
They've shared their research,
they've shared their code share
their data, many of the
researchers have gone on to work
on follow on projects that are
leveraging the technologies that
they developed in sub T's, in
some case, working with former
competitors, now, actual
collaborators on these projects.
And so a lot of that has kind of
kind of made it out to the wild.
And those are just the research
product projects. There's also a
pretty big effort amongst these
teams to kind of take these
pardons technologies, those that
have been tested in the crucible
of the darkness of T challenge,
and turn them into commercial
products. And so we've seen
startup companies spin out from
these competitor teams,
productization, of even some of
these components, technologies,
you can in fact, so go and buy
these sensor integrated sensor
packages, that you can slap on
the hood of your car, or carry
in your backpack, and get a
nominal kind of imaging, mapping
capabilities. That's now as a
product. And a lot of that
really came out from the SubT
challenge. And so again, being
able to make that impact, not
just the research community with
code, but in fact really turning
us around and impacting the, you
know, safety community in the
security community in the mining
industry, in the construction
site industry. And you know, all
those kinds of folks that can
really benefit from these, even
the component technologies have
already started to see that
impact from from getting the
research, but also the
technology out into the wild.
It's been awesome. For sure.
Yeah, that is super cool.
Audrow Nash: How did the so
another part of this that we
haven't really talked about? Is
the simulation or the virtual
competition? Would you tell me a
bit about this and how it
relates?
Tim Chung: Yeah, so we designed
the virtual competition of the
SubT challenge to be an
opportunity for us to kind of
explore some of these What if
cases, and that's one of the
incredible values of using
virtual environments to study
advanced technologies. And so
whereas in the system's
competitions, we might take over
a coal mine or an unfinished
nuclear power plant, you only
going to get one such course you
know, one such environment. And
despite having a lot of
variability within that, one
course, there might be a whole
lot of other things we might
want to study in the virtual
environment gave us those
opportunities to do that. To
give you an example, you know,
if you wanted to, you could use
in the virtual competition, we
enabled this ability to create
your own world, you could
procedurally generate your
tunnel like environments or
procedurally generate your own
cave like environment, specify
some parameters it would be Have
you long and narrow? Or, you
know, highly vertical? Or, you
know, kind of
Audrow Nash: parameterised?
Yeah.
Tim Chung: Yeah. And and that
gives teams on competing in the
virtual competition, this
opportunity to test against a
wide range of worlds far greater
than one would find yet a single
test site to kind of avoid
overfitting to the problem to
avoid studying to that one
specific test. And so this
virtual competition really kind
of embraced that we, instead of
testing against one virtual
world, in many cases, we're
testing against half a dozen
upwards of eight worlds, in some
cases to see how well a given
fixed solution would work
against a varying set of
environments. So the way this
works, we invested heavily in a
next gen simulation capability,
ignition, Zeebo, our SubT
simulator. And that's the
simulation
Audrow Nash: environment made by
open robotics where I'm working.
That's right.
Tim Chung: Yeah, that's right.
So open robotics, provided that
virtual environment capability
and advanced the state of
robotics simulation, I'd say.
And in that simulator, we're
able to run that in the cloud
using our cloud based simulation
infrastructure that we also
developed. And so now teams are
able to develop containerized
solutions. So bundle their
robotic software, if you will,
and upload it to the cloud and
run their software against our
simulation environments, not
knowing what the simulated world
would look like is, of course,
we are managing all that in the
cloud.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. You have your
tests, basically, which this is
how well does it do in the cloud
environment? Okay.
Tim Chung: Yeah. And so the
other fun part of this is we
constructed what we call the sub
t tech repo. Think of this as
like your, you know, your
storefront, your web based
storefront, you can go and add
robots to cart. And what I'm
doing here is I'll give each
competitor 1000 SubT credits.
Yep. And you go to this
storefront, this tech repo, and
each of these robots that we
have virtual models of cost you
some number of sub D credits,
yeah, up to that kind of salary
cap tees of, you know, NAC
league analogy here, you get to
build, mix and match the types
of robots that you want to add
to your team subject to this
budget of 1000s of t credits.
And these different robots are
all different sorts, they have
different sensor payloads, they
might have, again, wheeled or
flying or kind of all the
different different modalities
you might explore. And so it
boils down down to these teams,
thinking about where they want
to spend their 70 credits, and
the number of robots they want
to add to their team. And then
designing their autonomy and
perception solutions to best
match the virtual robot teams
that they're constructing. And
so in this way, you really get
to kind of explore what are the
best composition of teams? What
if, given this cost constraint?
He asked earlier? If they're,
you know, budget limitations for
Audrow Nash: that? Yeah, cuz I
heard about the virtual, the
budget. Yeah, the virtual one.
Yeah. So I was wondering if
there was something similar in
the hardware and how that would
work, because it's quite
complex, if they're building
hardware was my thing. Right,
Tim Chung: right. And so we
wanted to abstract away some of
the, you know, constraints of
having to embody some of the
software based side of things,
and free up that develop, you
know, the development to explore
some of these other scenarios.
The other really big difference
between the systems and the
virtual competition, was that in
the system's competition, these
robots have to report out where
these artifacts are located. And
they can coordinate with a human
supervisor, a single human, to
act as a teammate amongst a
fleet of robots. And that human
supervisor, is typically the one
that's forwarding the artifact
reports to DARPA to get scored.
And so you now have this
partnership, you can have the
human supervisor, kind of
interact with the teams of
robots and have the robots go
take a closer look at things or
maybe show a an image or review
and high man's like, go over
there probably or whatever.
That's right. Yeah. And they
did. And that was really great
partnership. But in the virtual
competition. These robots are
fully autonomous. You have
uploaded your software to the
cloud. It's one set of software
that has to get run against all
of these different types of
virtual environments. And
there's no human back and forth
and so really being able to
explore complete autonomy of The
solution where you don't get the
chance to, you know, back your
robot out manually, even if you
do it, you know, that gave us
again, studying what this what
if scenario in the future where
you didn't have the luxury of
having a human supervisor, or
the levels of autonomy got to
the point where you could deploy
these robots to good effect in
these really diverse
environments. So now we have,
you know, brackets, you have the
system competition, highlighting
where we are, we push the state
of the art in applied realized
technologies. And we also have
the the solution space of what
can be done in the completely
autonomous regime where it's
software only. And now we can
quantifiably say how far are we
from complete autonomy,
autonomous solutions, or we can
quantify it to some degree, the
value of the human teammate. And
so the virtual consecration is
benchmarking ability. Right now
we have comparative analysis
between systems and virtual. And
we did this all throughout the
whole competition, where we had
tunnel circuit in both systems,
virtual, urban in both systems
and virtual in cave, we couldn't
do the system's competition. But
man did the virtual competition
really shine through in the in
the face of the global lockdown,
where now we had teams flocking
to the virtual competition,
because they still were thirsty
to develop their technologies.
And so we had numerous systems,
competitors, crossover into the
virtual competition, in fact,
and carry that through to really
good effect. So it was a lot of
fun on the virtual side to kind
of help us imagine what future
technologies could be while also
being closely coupled to where
the current state of the art of
the technology was, as well.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, I find it to
me the most exciting part about
that, as you said, with the
benchmarking, it's that so like,
I'm thinking about, like the
advancement of technology and
say, like the computer image or
computer vision space, like we
established image net, and it's
a benchmark in a sense, so that
people can more fairly compare
what they're how their algorithm
performs. And so what you see is
people keep trying it, and then
the performance keeps going up.
And robotics, especially on like
a behavioral level, has not
really anything similar to my
knowledge, except for what
you're describing here, which is
really cool, where you can have
some sort of, so you have your
challenge. And you have a way
that people can try by basically
upload their algorithm to it.
And it runs it given their
robots and and all of this, to
see the performance, and you can
see the performance over time.
That's really, really
interesting and very exciting to
me.
Tim Chung: Yeah, totally with
you. I think this idea of being
able to set those benchmarks
allows for us as a community to
see how well we're doing right
and see that progress. And it's
exciting to see that progress.
And to be able to do that in
near real time with this side by
side systems and virtual
competition, I think, you know,
was really, really cool. And
I'll highlight two more things.
One is we took systems robots,
so robots from the system's
competition, and went ahead and
scan them, generate 3d models of
them. So controller code that
were contributed by the
competitor teams, and validated
it against their sensor spec
sheets and battery durations.
And you know, quite laboriously.
But now, in that SubT tech
repo, this is these virtual
robot models that are digital
twins of their systems, real
world robots. Now live in the
tech repo. And now virtual
competitors, they might not have
had the resources to build their
own robots, but they can
actually go and use a systems
embedded robot models in their
virtual fleet.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, and that's
very cool. If anyone had an
especially good idea for like,
how to, like a morphologie.
That's really, really good. And
now, I can play with that more
as a community. Right off. Yeah,
Tim Chung: exactly. Right. So
I'm going to pull the fantasy
league analogy. Again, you know,
if it's a virtual competition,
gave you the flexibility to mix
and match across the league.
With a systems competition was
kind of like the, you know, like
the NFL, right? You kind of have
to pick your roster at the
beginning of the season, you
kind of play the players that
are on your roster, because it
really is too difficult to go
back and do clean sheet design
after each one of these
competition events to start from
scratch, so you're kind of
trying to do that systems
thinking for the systems teams
holistically. But man in virtual
you get to mix and match. Play
around, see, if you want to be
an all ground team or an all air
team or, you know, beg and
borrow from different, try
different styles of robots, you
can do that. And many of the
competitors were able to do that
exploration. And there's still,
of course, significant
exploration left to do. And then
also highlight that there's a
virtual testbed, the SubT
virtual testbed, which
encompasses the simulator, and
the tech repo, all of that is
publicly available and open
source. And so, okay, yeah, you
can still go, despite the
competition being over, we know
that the value to the community
is so important that DARPA is
keeping up the testbed open for
a period to come, you can still
go to SubT challenge that world
and learn how to how to develop
a SubT solution and upload it
to the cloud and run it, you
know, and get free free reps in
for Yeah. For your simulate, you
know, your simulation solutions.
And so I think, yeah, the
availability is another
testament to, you know, how we
really cherish the the community
really are interested in
fostering the growth of the
community, because that's at the
end of the day, what's going to
turn around and develop those
technologies that are, you know,
first responders and warfighters
and others are going to be able
to make use of or precisely the
technologies that these people
that the community develops and
matures?
Audrow Nash: Yes, for sure. Do
you imagine that the the
framework that you guys have
developed which hosts this the
high level testing and
benchmarking of this challenge
to imagine that this can be
applied to other different like,
basically, the whole
infrastructure that you've
built? Do you think it can be
applied to other robotics
challenges, say robots like
moving around in hospital and be
inefficient or any, any rope,
any tasks that robots might be
very good for? To have this
provide like a standard
benchmark, so you can look at it
over time, and compare more
fairly, the algorithms and
approaches?
Tim Chung: Yeah, hands down. I'm
a, I'm a believer in this type
of a model of being able to not
only test at scale, but also
open up the innovation space, by
lowering the barriers to entry.
And simulation is a great way,
you know, to avoid having to lay
out capital expenses to build a
fleet of robot and oh, by the
way, have access to a hospital
or the underground mines or the
moon or wherever your setting
might be. So absolutely think
this back end infrastructure
absolutely critical, as a, as a
method as a set of tools to, to
help out. And in fact, I'm
pleased to say that, in fact, we
are seeing this precise
infrastructure being used in
other robotics development
settings already. So the impact
is already near and dear. And
stay tuned to see some of those
competition events making use of
this kind of infrastructure.
Audrow Nash: And is that
infrastructure? Is that in the
SubT tech repo that you've been
mentioning? Or is it Yeah,
somewhere
Tim Chung: else? Yeah. Yeah. So
the tech repo is the the source
code, if you will, of all, the
majority of everything we talked
about is already available, you
can go to get a, I believe,
under OSR. F, and see the SubT
project there. You know, nearly
everything that we've talked
about is already located there.
So there are a handful of
resources under github.com/sub T
challenge, and you'll be able to
find a number of resources there
as well.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. I didn't
know because I haven't. The sub
T has never been one of my
projects. So I'm not that aware
of what where everything lives
in this kind of thing. It's
awesome to hear that it already
is all online and people can
access it. And that people are
also using this infrastructure
to benchmark other tests in
simulation. I think that's
really, really exciting.
Tim Chung: Yeah, it's gonna be
great when kind of the impact to
not just the subterranean
robotics community, which
admittedly is just one sliver of
the community. But being able to
open this up, you suggested kind
of hospital environments or
maritime settings or other types
of environments where we really
want to explore more broadly, I
do think that, you know, this
investment will pay significant
dividends for many, many years
to come for the robot's
community.
Audrow Nash: Thank you, right.
Let's see. So we are running out
of time, and by that I mean,
like 20 more minutes or so and I
have a lot of things that I want
to talk About in this, but you
you mentioned the final events
and that we do you'd like to
talk about that and kind of how
you fabricated this big
environment? Would you tell me a
little bit more?
Tim Chung: Yeah. So, you know, I
think one of the visions for the
subsea challenge from the get go
was to have teams of robots,
that and, you know, unhindered
by the fact that you might face
all three of these environments.
Now, the challenge, and I've
crossed crisscross the country
to try to find a place that has
tunnels, urban caves, all next
to one another, all co located
all connected in a meaningful
way, if any of your listeners
have mine, please, please let us
know. So instead, as DARPA
intends to do is, you know,
because we are always seeking
those breakthroughs. We
transformed a limestone cavern
and built a one of a kind
course, kind of think, almost
like Hollywood set design with
the level of realism that, you
know, is, you know, very
compelling for both human and
robot, to the degree where we're
getting inspiration from caves
and mines and sites that we've
seen, we replicated New York
City metro station, all the way
to steam tunnels, and old rustic
abandoned mines to large caverns
that are either show caverns
that you might go to as a
tourist to the, you know, the
raw caverns or the untouched
ones that have a very different
feel as well. And so we were
able to take all of those
different sites that we had been
to or found to be really
compelling, and fabricated, we
built that we had warehouse
structures connected to a metro
station connected to a
featureless hallway. And that's
just a fraction of the urban
setting, we had small places
where you had to crawl on your
hands and knees often over the
different segments and places
where I'm certain many dozens of
times, if I hadn't had a helmet
on, if you walk away with a lot
of bumps and bruises, you know,
just trying to build a place
where we can test and push the
boundaries of autonomy,
mobility, networking, and
perception was a phenomenal
experience to, to do that. And
in having to build that course,
going back to where it all
started with all of our
stakeholders, all the end users
of people who this was going to
who we would have to have them
believe that these environments
were realistic enough, right? So
we did go back and say, Hey,
what are the pieces that you
need to see, to be able to say
that you believe this technology
is relevant to you. And we were
able to do that to good effect.
And whether and since we were
building it ourselves, we in
fact, had different segments of
the course take on different
personalities. And so in total,
even though we had three
subdomains, the tunnel urban
cave, we in fact had, like 60
different segments, kind of like
going on a on almost a Disney
ride through different parts of
the subterranean world, is what
we were able to pose to these
robots now facing all of that
difficulty, really, really,
really allowed for testing the
diversity. And we went to great
lengths, I'd say to hone that
realism. We talked earlier about
communications, and networking.
But I'll tell you, we went
through various types of RF
shielding and pains and other
things baked into the walls of,
of, of this course, to be able
to replicate the kind of the RF
propagation in underground
environments. And so I'm pleased
to say that I think we did a
good job of trying to replicate
not just the look and feel but
the RF, the radio frequency, the
wireless transmission all the
way to you know, the little
things like amount of water
moistures, slick surfaces,
Rubble, gravel, you know, all
that kind of stuff. Really,
really proud of this one of a
kind opportunity to, you know,
raise the bar for the robotics
community writ large, for sure.
Yeah, it
Audrow Nash: sounds like such a
great test environment that's so
funny that you like the
shielding and things so you
could get the RF properties you
wanted in the environment.
Amazing. So I assume that will
be used In future competitions
or how so actually How did it
go? In the finals? You use this
environment, correct? Yeah,
that's right. How did it go? How
was it?
Tim Chung: Yeah, I think I think
it was really great. I think,
you know, one of the benchmarks
for me as the DARPA Program
Manager here is, was it hard
enough, right? Does it push the
boundaries, it needs to be hard,
so that not everyone gets 100.
But we don't want it to be
impossibly hard, because then
we're not going to know where
the boundaries are, where the
envelope is. And so being able
to design this course, in a way
that had the level of difficulty
variants, that allowed some
pieces of technology to really
be showcased, and others, you
know, you found where their
limitations were, you know, that
was really great about the the
environment. I'll say, also,
from the kind of the
government's perspective, the
DARPA team, we are in the
command post, as you know, this
is not something that our
competitors get a really good
glimpse of, because you're all
behind the scenes. But in our
command post, we had
instrumented this course, with
everything from cameras, of
course, so we could see where
robots might be. But we had
things like motion detectors, we
had triggers, all of our
artifacts were instrumented so
we could make sure that they're
consistently Halloween house.
Yeah. Yeah, that's right. Yeah.
And so we could orchestrate kind
of like movie style, movies and
style, like, and so we had
dynamic obstacles. And so these
would be triggered when robots
entered a particular area, and
then section of the course would
collapse behind them now
blocking their way home, they
would need to find a new way
they would not be able to follow
their that's amazing, around the
home. And so that was built into
the course as well. actuated,
from, you know, from these types
of signals that we had
instrumented this course with,
and so does a Hollywood set up.
Yeah, in many ways it was. And
it was always done with a
technology objective in mind.
And that's the cool part about
it is and showing this collapse
was something that was very
relevant to many of our, for
example, mine rescue personnel,
because that's one of the hard
things is debris collapses, or
debris, integrity checks of the
environment. And so collapsing,
part of this was near and dear
to them. But for us, we are
interested in testing the
autonomy, the ability to
recognize that your map has
changed. And then your way home
is no longer viable, you got to
find another way home. And so
there was a really fun way, a
really tight way of coupling,
the operational kind of need and
insight with the technology that
we were trying to push in this
one, of course, was explicitly
designed, you know, from from
CAD drawing all the way to
graphic artists painting inside
the course. So to be able to
deliver that type of tight
coupling between operational and
technical objectives.
Audrow Nash: Gosh, that sounds
amazing. Do you have is there
like a YouTube of like a
walkthrough of this course? I
haven't seen it.
Tim Chung: Yeah, there are. So
you can go to DARPA TV, that's
the YouTube channel. And all of
our videos have been placed
there. There are walkthroughs of
every course that we DARPA has
transformed into a competition
course. So you can go and do a
walkthrough of Hardrock, like a
gold mine, coal mine, that
nuclear power plant, and then of
course, our grand finale, final
event course there multiple
walkthrough videos. And then
this might be a good opportunity
to share that DARPA also
collected very high resolution,
high accuracy datasets of these
environments, to the point where
we could dance, of course,
because we're also scoring the
artifact position reports. So we
were down at the, you know,
millimeter scale of accuracy.
And we've released that as a
public data set as well. So if
you were unable to test in the
final event course, well, you
can actually go to the SubT
tech repo on the virtual side
and get a mesh 3d rendering a 3d
version of the final event world
and, and see what it looks like
for your robots as well. And fun
fact here, one of the final
event, virtual competition
worlds was in fact, a 3d virtual
world of the system's
competition final event world.
So kind of bringing everything
full circle Now you get this
chance to test how the system's
competitors were testing in
this, again, unique one time
world. And at the same time,
we're running virtual
competitors do the same as that
course, having developed this 3d
model of the course, with all
the, all the pain, the same pain
points as the real robots had to
face, but not in a virtual
domain. And so all of that's
been publicly released, we can
see the video, but if you want
the point cloud, you can
download the Point Cloud
yourself and work with it, or
the mesh, 3d virtual mesh file
is available. So you can, you
know, do put in your own
simulators, if you wish, or
loaded up in the SubT simulator
and, and drive some robots
around.
Audrow Nash: So cool. What a
great public offering. That's so
it's so neat, that people have
access to all of this. Let's
see. So I have a few things that
I want to talk about. And we
have like, really 10 minutes
left or so would it be all
right? If we run a little longer
is it? Yeah, absolutely. Okay.
So one thing that's very
interesting to me, and I really,
really wanted to talk about
this. So I'm very happy. We can
run a little long. But can you
tell it's like one of the huge
challenges, I believe in setting
this whole thing up, which we
talked about before, is figuring
out how to scope these
challenges, because you want to
make it so it's not like like,
as you were just saying, you
don't want all the teams to
fail, because it's too hard. And
then it drives no innovation,
because no one can do anything.
But you don't want to make it
too easy. Also, can you just
talk a bit about scoping the
entire SubT challenge? Yeah.
Yeah, I think process of that.
Tim Chung: Yeah, you know, I
think it boils back down to the
really doing our homework and
kind of getting, I think that's
what DARPA is all about is not
only gauging where the current
state of technology is, and not
only kind of trying to
understand the trend lines of
where technology might be
gradually going, but
understanding the levers where
if we were to exercise, some,
you know, nudge here, hope
they're tested that, that we
would actually bend the curve of
the trajectory, and accelerate
where technology is gonna go. I
think that's what DARPA is, a
foundational mission is to try
to create a kind of
technological surprise. And so
by doing our homework, both on
terms of where the technology
is, but also what the end users
really needed, kind of doing
that, that you know, where we
want to be, right. And we want
to skate to that, to where the
puck is going to be, combined
with knowing where we were, you
know, I think it really was a
laborious process to tune and
tweak the evolution of the
challenge to be able to arrive,
as well as we have to this end
result of having advanced as
much as we had. And so I'll tell
a story here, at one of our very
early events, we transformed the
a gold mine into a test course,
and this was not for
competition, it was really just
a test. It was an integration
test, really. So we invited
competitors if they wanted to,
to come out and test and we had
done it up much like a
competition course. And this was
really to give teams a first
look at what DARPA had in store
for them. And so when we
conducted this, teams went in,
and you can safely say they got
their butts kicked, right, I
think they realize that, you
know, it's a little things that
we'll get to, in addition to the
big things that they were
worried about. And one of the
things that it became a
tradition afterwards. But we
took all of our competitors on a
walking tour of the entirety of
the course that we had laid out
that DARPA had laid out. And
whereas most teams maybe made
it, I'll be generous and say,
the best team made it 10% into
this first test course. Yeah.
When we went on the walking
tour, and showed them how far
and how expansive this course
really was. You could very
easily imagine that there are
those out there who would say,
Man, this is impossible. What is
DARPA thinking? They'll never,
you know, no one can ever
accomplish this. And yes, they
did say that to some degree,
like this is impossible, man.
But no, what really kind of
stuck with me is that the
prevailing sentiment after that
walk about two are in that very
first course, was not that this
can't be done, but that we
didn't do it. But man, somebody
believes in us that, you know,
DARPA must believe that this is
possible because otherwise why
would they have crawled up that
One ladder in the far reaches of
his mind, why would they have
kind of probably twisted ankles
to climb up to that location,
replace that cell phone company,
all the, you know, 80 pound man,
again, three kilometers into
this course, if they didn't
think that this was possible and
that spark, I think for them of
setting the bar really high, you
know, and saying yes, we think
that in due time you accelerate
the technology to get to this
point, you will be able to
conquer a good portion of this
course in the future. And that
trajectory, I think, has
continued to manifest throughout
the challenge. And so by the
time they got to their final
event, you have many teams on
record saying that you asked if
you ask them three years ago, or
four years ago, that they could
have conquered or handled any
part of this final event course
they'd say, Absolutely not. For
the fact that we're here, in
truth be told, by the way, you
know, I don't think we talked
about it. DARPA placed a fixed
number of artifacts in these
courses. And so for the final
event, we placed 40 artifacts in
nearly half a mile of
underground terrain that we had
built. And the highest scoring
teams scored 23 points, 23
artifacts. So you might say to
him, hey, that's kind of a
failing grade, right? That's
kind of like, well, 50% is just
over 50%. And you're saying you
did a great job? Well, yeah,
that's a phenomenal job, given
the difficulty level that we
know is where we want to be
right. And so again, it's really
been
showcasing that the technology
still has a lot of headroom to
grow. But to be able to quantify
the level of impacts, right,
we're able to cover this massive
environment in about an hour
with robots that, frankly, took
an order of magnitude, even two
orders of magnitude longer with
my human team to go gather that
high precision data, you know,
it took them a fair bit longer
to be able to go and do what
robots are doing in under an
hour under duress, never having
seen the courts before. That's a
market improvement that we can
point to and say, four years
ago, we might not have been able
to do it, if not, for this high
bar that DARPA sets. And I think
calibration process is a
iterative thing that we've fine
tuned, I think, here at DARPA,
Audrow Nash: I think it would be
more worrying if people got all
40 already. That would mean the
challenge was not hard enough
today, because it's a benchmark.
I mean, if you look at, again,
going back to like image net,
it'd be like 50% level when they
were starting, and then it's
like a free thing up 70% Now,
maybe, or 80, or whatever it is,
but it starts pretty low, and
then you have plenty of room to
improve, because you have a hard
challenge and getting all of it,
especially in that like limited
period of time. Right? Like
that's a real challenge. Yeah,
it's very interesting.
Tim Chung: Yeah, wholly agree.
And think that there's, you
know, really promising work to
get to be done and to be a
Audrow Nash: component, for
sure. And you were mentioning,
mentioning, DARPA has this very
iterative process for scoping,
like difficulty of these things.
Can you talk a bit about that,
because that's really
interesting to me.
Tim Chung: Sure. And so
specifically, for the sub D
challenge, we had designed it,
so that we would have those
opportunities to, to to learn as
we go. So by virtue of how we
constructed the SubT challenge,
we held that first event where
teams first saw what DARPA had
in store, but then, about six
months after there was the
tunnel circuit, where we
conducted our first event
focusing on tunnel environments,
in this case, a coal mine. And
then we broke that up into
again, six months after an urban
setting. And so the teams knew
that if they were going to be
competitive at the final event,
where they were anticipating
that all three of these
environments would all get
mashed together, then they
should be thinking about their
designs from the get go, that
can survive, quite frankly,
tunnel urban cave, all the way
to the very ends. And so we saw
teams to kind of internalize
this, this need for resilience
in their early kind of design
scoping. And so they went to the
tunnel and man, Were there a lot
of really hard lessons learned
at the tunnel a bit, but what
you saw was a learning not just
by team, but across teams. An
example is that a using a a
sensor on the outside to be able
to help correct as robots still
within line of sight of the
mouth of the tunnel. You know,
we had a team that was using
that and so they could extend
how far their accuracy was, you
know, subject to drift they
could they could extend And how
far they were by using this
total station sensor to, to
correct for any drift. And yeah,
that's, that's clever and so
even even at the tunnel circuit
he saw teams going out and
trying to find and they found a
local university and borrowed
one of these little stations and
tried to use it and by the Urban
circuit, you had more teams
using such a technology. Same
goes for legged robots say,
legged robots didn't do so well
at the tunnel circuit. But at
the Urban circuit where there
were stairs and curbs and other
things, man, those legged robots
really shine. And so at the
final event, you saw a lot of
legged robots coming to the
fore. And so that's what I mean,
by the iteration, there was
multiple opportunities for these
teams to come field go through
the the rigor of a competition
events, but that wasn't the end
of it, they would have to go
home, lick their wounds, and
then come back and do it again.
And then, of course, break some
more robots and learn what it
means to have to operate in the
cold, called nuclear power plant
or the human limestone cavern
or, you know, all of those kinds
of things. We baked in that
iteration and the kinds of
opportunity to learn quickly and
often into the stuff the
challenge. And I think, as a
roboticist, myself, I think
that's where you learn the most
by thinking and then doing right
thinking of doing breaking,
learning, and then thinking and
doing it again. And Field
Robotics, I think is, you know,
needs that and sometimes trying
to do robotics in the field,
especially at the scales that
the sub the challenge was
interested in really hard,
logistically, you know, it takes
a lot of time, a lot of people
power to get to transport robots
and get things set up. But, you
know, sub The challenge really
gave all these teams, not only
the excuse, but the incentive to
have to go and test in the wild.
And many of the teams,
especially the top performing
teams, really took that to heart
found, you know, and partner
with local caver clubs, local
gaming, clubs to go and gain
access to their caves and
practice, or, you know, all of
those kinds of opportunities, I
think, came about, with many,
many lessons learned a lot, a
lot of a lot of broken robots,
but a whole cadre of field
roboticists and the next
generation, I'd say, Field
Robotics is coming out, having
been battle tested in the subsea
challenge.
Audrow Nash: That's really cool.
So that makes me curious about
kind of the long term role of
DARPA in all of this. So you're,
you're mentioning like one
thing. Very interesting, as
you're mentioning, training the
next generation of Field
Robotics, roboticists, can you
just talk a bit more about the
role of DARPA? Yeah, as you see
kind of on a bigger picture?
Tim Chung: Sure. Well, you know,
at its heart, DARPA is always
going to be about bringing about
technological surprise, and
those breakthrough technologies
that will have broad impact
overall, and whether that's deep
investments that will lead to
breakthroughs when we need them.
And an example of that is that
mRNA vaccine approach that in
the time COVID, was investments
by DARPA early on to identify
that kind of methodology in the
time of need, where it would
arise. And so identifying, you
know, those opportunities where,
even if you don't need it today,
but you might need it in the
future. That's what DARPA is all
about. And I think, recognizing
that the state of the technology
for robotics Field Robotics
wasn't where we wanted it to be
in the future. That's what DARPA
was eager to inspire, and
incentivize, and then help shape
that future trajectory. As far
as building the community. I
really love the DARPA Challenge
model for innovation, where, you
know, we have a couple of
different ways that we seek out
revolutionary ideas. But the
challenge model is just one type
of those and, and I really love
it, because it also gives us an
opportunity to think about
solving a problem without having
defines the solution. When you
do that, and the community
hasn't yet informed around that
problem area, or the solution
space. The DARPA Challenge is
fantastic for being able to
plant the seed and nurture this
community that's now going to go
off and do great things right.
So the DARPA first started Grand
Challenge, self driving cars to
the desert or in the urban
environments, you know, had
planted the seed for a lot of
the of the self driving tech
investments today. And I imagine
that many of the types of
technologies that we've
discovered and invested in for
the SubT challenge will have
that long term impact. While
also, and I'm excited to say,
have a very near term impact for
many of our end users as well,
given how we structured this
this challenge to kind of think
about marrying, you know, what
the what the what the end user
needs tomorrow, not just many
years from now. So I think being
able to span that has been a
real hallmark of the DARPA
subterranean challenge of
understanding what the near
problem is, as well as
anticipating and planting the
seed for the communities to
address the fire problems as
well.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Let's see.
So I think I don't know how it
works. But what's next? Yeah,
like, what next with this SubT
challenge next with maybe
another, I suppose Grand
Challenges take a long time to
think about and I don't know,
things can be revealed. But
what's next? Yeah,
Tim Chung: well, I'll say that
the SubT challenge has
concluded. And while we have all
of those resources, all of the
Open Source Repositories, all
the things that we talked about,
available out there, it's my
wish that folks, you know, take
it and run with it, they can
reinvent or recreate or invent
the new, different types of
approaches to solving some of
these types of problems. And so
I think that what we see already
in the community is kind of
we've spun up the firewall, and
now it's operating on its own
momentum. And it's really
invigorating and inspiring to
see all these folks already out
there. You know, organizing
amongst themselves the the
ability to have this kind of an
impact. And being a resource. As
far as DARPA is concerned, I
think, you know, if any of your
listeners have ideas for Grand
Challenges, that's an
opportunity here, I think DARPA
is always on the lookout for
those types of problems, those
kind of technology questions
that are out there that don't
have or would benefit from not
having a pre defined solution,
kind of a direction to go, you
know that there's a breakthrough
waiting to happen. But you don't
quite have a finger on where
that breakthrough is going to
come from. And a challenge model
is great. And so DARPA, I am
certain that the DARPA Challenge
model is here to stay. It will,
as it at, like all things at
DARPA, continued to evolve and
tailor itself to the technology
of interest. But now, I'm
excited to say that, you know,
which DARPA Challenge model is
demonstrated, at least with sub
t, that it's a it's an exciting
way to both drive a community
and drive technology
development.
Audrow Nash: So wrapping up, do
you have any links, websites,
anything to share? I know the
SubT website. So I'll include
that in the post anything,
anything else to highlight?
Tim Chung: Yeah, I think, you
know, if you go to one of the
repositories, we mentioned
earlier that a GitHub repo slash
SubT challenge, there, you'll
see a project there, just called
simply SubT resources. But this
is where it's kind of the one
stop shop for all of the
references, links to software
that the competitors themselves
have now released. So you can
see that the datasets that both
DARPA have provided, as well as
many that SubT community has
developed and curated, are
there, links to papers and other
materials are there. So you
know, I encourage folks to go
check that out. And then of
course, the DARPA TV YouTube
channel has many, many videos
that you can go learn about the
sub D challenge, its impact and
why it matters, as well as learn
about all the teams as well. So
I think those are a great place
to start. And if you're
interested in learning more
about DARPA, I think darpa.mil
is a is a fantastic landing
point for any of your listeners.
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah. Okay,
thank you very much.
Tim Chung: Cool. It's been a
pleasure. Thank you so much.
Audrow Nash: Thanks for
listening to my conversation
with Tim Chung. Thank you again
to our founding sponsor, open
robotics. See you next time.