Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Dan O'Mara,
who is a founder and the COO of
Circuit Launch and Mechlabs,
Circuit Launches a space for
hardware entrepreneurs in
Oakland, California. And Mechlabs
is a project-based course
for robotics education. What
does a robotics education look
like to you? Dan jokes during
the interview that if you're at
a university that you need to
major in electrical engineering,
mechanical engineering and
computer science, to get a
robotics education, some
universities do have a dedicated
robotics program, but it's a big
commitment, both in terms of
time and money. And what if you
already have a degree, even an
engineering? Should you go back
to school? I have friends and
family considering this
question. And I feel like
there's a gap here, where a
group of would-be roboticists
don't know how to get started.
And this seems to be one of the
spots where mech lab fits well.
I also find it interesting that
Mechlabs basically does the
opposite of what universities do
on several levels, as you'll see
during this interview, and that
doing so has worked well for
them. They are, as Dan says,
during the interview, creating a
program that they wanted to
learn from. I'm Audrow Nash,
this is the Sense Think Act
Podcast. Thank you to our
founding sponsor Open Robotics.
And now, here's my conversation
with Dan O'Mara. Dan, would you
introduce yourself?
Dan O'Mara: Sure, I'm Dan
O'Mara, the COO of Circuit Launch
and Mechlabs, we are a
basically a community space for
robotics and hardware
engineering, with corking shared
labs, as well as a educational
program for mechatronics.
Audrow Nash: I don't want to
talk about both of those things.
Let's start with Circuit Launch,
would you tell me kind of the
story of Circuit Launch how it's
come to what it is?
Dan O'Mara: Sure, I think
Circuit Launch grew up in the
bay area here as a space coming
off the the tail end of like the
fall of tech shop, and the
understanding of like that,
there were all of these
entrepreneurs and people in this
area who are doing hardware,
electronics and robotics, and
like, this is the Bay Area, we
don't have space to do that,
where you can run a business
like this kind of in your garage
and a lot of other places. But
eventually, you do need some
type of space to build things in
a workshop and lab tools and all
of the that stuff. And we just
realized that there are all
these entrepreneurs who are
doing, you know, new companies,
like because of the start of
Kickstarter, and all of the
great robotics technologies that
are starting to become a lot
more available. And we need, you
know, they need space, they need
shirt labs, they need
facilities, they need that any
you know, I make a joke that you
know, we're not we work we don't
have you know, we don't provide
scented candles with your your
members. We're a little messy,
chic, we, you know, bow, you
know, one of the things that
really resonated on our
marketing language and website
is it's like, you know, do you
want to put a soldering iron on
your desk come work here, like
this is where we, you know, we
want you who are building stuff
making stuff. During that I
mean, we have we have one person
right now has a metal lathe that
he snuck onto his desk,
basically. And so in the
upstairs area, so like that, we
realized that there is such a
need for like a community and a
place where you can work and you
can share with other roboticists
and other electronics, hardware
specialists and, and everything
and build a business. And so
that's what we really focused
on. We said entrepreneurs who
are building hardware and
robotics businesses, we want to
have a space for them. And we
want to make this work. And so
that was the original side of
it. We partnered with our
building owner, which is also
another crucial part of our
business model, to be able to
provide that space and to be
able to make that so that we
weren't going to just grow big,
and then all of a sudden the
building owner, you know,
creates a lease situation where
we could. And it was it was a
wonderful match made in heaven.
We found an incredible business
building for about 32,000 square
feet. And we've started building
our community from just a few
people. And we used to let you
know any kind of company come in
and now we're over 95%
specifically, robotics not even
like, like we used to do like
oh, you know, if you're a lawyer
that works in the patent space,
you can come here if you're a
you know, you do some software,
somewhat something you could
come in like there, and now it's
just really our community has
become all about robotics, which
is great. And that's really what
we're, we're we're creating and
fostering and now people want to
build their companies from
marine robotics to you know, IoT
devices to Krub the we have a
company that just won the the
department energy E robot prize
From the robots, they're a
carpet cleaning robot. So it's
just all of these, these people
came. And, you know, we rebuilt
it. And they came. And that's
really the kind of the story.
And we've, we've been constantly
working with startups to be
like, give them what they need,
which is sometimes the ability
to have a desk, sometimes the
ability to expand into an
office. And then sometimes it's
the ability to go bankrupt and
have all of your employees start
new businesses and new companies
and go into little other places
and downsize things. So that
flexible space was what we
really knew that our community
needed. And then market tested
it. And now we have a really
flourishing awesome community
that we're leveraging to create
a, you know, an education
program on top of and get more
people, robotics experience and
projects and mentorship and
everything else.
Audrow Nash: It's awesome that
it's 95% occupancy.
Dan O'Mara: We're 100% occupied
just 95% Robotics 95% Robotics.
Where,
Audrow Nash: yeah, that's so
exciting. Yeah, cuz I was there
with Hello, buddy. Two, three
summers ago, as an intern for
them. And it was really
wonderful to be in the space.
Like, I loved all the robotics
that was going on around. And I
think I don't remember numbers,
but it was it didn't I don't
think we were, I don't think it
was 100% occupied two or three
years ago. Now. That's
wonderful. Gosh, and we just
went to the block party, or you
just had the block party, and it
was wonderful to see the turnout
for that
Dan O'Mara: robot, block party.
Barbecue, we do that every,
we're now that's our second one
in six months, their second one,
you know, in a year. So we've
done we're hope planning to do
those every six months, and it's
been now we had 40 Different
robotics companies and vendors
and demos all come out. And with
the job fair, and everything, it
was really
Audrow Nash: fun of it. Yeah. So
I mean, from my perspective, it
kind of seems like it's part co
working space. And then part
makerspace, with like laser
printers and CNC machines, and I
don't know all these things. And
then the focus on community.
Dan O'Mara: So that, like, from
our marketing side of point,
we're trying to, kind of, in
many ways, kill off those two
terms, coworker, and robot and
makerspace. And it's
interesting, because that,
that's really about where
really, so the the co working
side, obviously, we're shared
offices, you can read desks and
offices, that mean, it's co
working. Yeah, but, you know, co
working really kind of doesn't
explain the fact that you have
great labs and tools and 3d
printers and, you know, an
electronics bench and a
soldering bench and that you
can, you know, if you want to
put a 3d printer on your, your
dedicated desk, you know, you
can put a 3d printer on your
dedicated desk and run it all
night long, right? All of that.
And so that's really why we, you
know, co working is very much
this sense of, like, that's a
dead business because of we
work, right. And so we want
Audrow Nash: to I mean, there's
no more potential for a company
to start there. Because we were
kind of in applies that.
Dan O'Mara: Well, not even
monopolize, but just that, you
know, people aren't interested
in the like, coworking has a bad
rap because of it from an
investment profile and
everything else, right. And
we're so much more than that.
Like you, we don't want to be
pigeon holed into the idea of
just like, you know, you're
you're we're all working
together. And it's like, we have
a full lap and facilities and we
want to, you know, in a
community there, which is so
much more valuable than
Makerspace side of it. Another
business that is kind of doomed
to fail for most most people's
minds, right, especially after
Tech Shop. Right?
Audrow Nash: I don't know, Tech
Shop.
Dan O'Mara: Oh, okay. So, Tech
Shop was. And that's partly
because the space you're in fits
more with what we're doing. Like
we, we don't want to be a
makerspace we want to be an on a
shared Fab Lab, by intellect.
It's mainly the difference is
the level of entrepreneurs and
robotics companies, rather than
hobbyists and makers, right?
Yeah. And not to say that we
don't want makers and hobbyists,
we were happy to take them. But
we also realized that we want we
want people cutting edge
industry professionals in our
space and doing right. And so
Tech Shop was kind of the first
big Makerspace like, I mean,
make in magazine, they all kind
of evolved with tech shop to be
one of the largest, most well
known makerspaces, you know, in
the world, and Tech Shop, grew
on this very unsustainable
model. And then they made a lot
of mistakes. And obviously, we
don't want to go into that, but
they went bankrupt. And then all
of these makers and
professionals and entrepreneurs
who, who realized, hey, shared
laboratories and shared
resources is a it's a good thing
and an economically viable thing
for my business. And now I don't
have have that
Audrow Nash: anymore, right?
Totally. Yeah, so but
Dan O'Mara: so what we do, and
part of what tech shops issues,
whereas they didn't support
their entrepreneurs enough, they
supported their hobbies and
makers. But the problem with
that is that there is a limited
amount of money you can make off
of a hobbyist, because there are
always going to be, you know,
where an entrepreneur is
somebody who can be able to
support a community and be able
to invest in new tools, and have
all of those things in a
creates, and then build larger
office, you know, and be in
bigger offices and support a
space because that, you know,
having monthly memberships have
just a small amount and can't,
it can be hard to run an
industrial space with all of
these resources on whatever. So
having those those places for
entrepreneurs, and that's where
we realize it's like, if we
point ourselves towards the
helping entrepreneurs and
helping small businesses go from
like a small desk all the way up
to a larger office and help them
you know, introduce them into
networking and funding and all
of these things. Like I think
we're we're a little bit more
akin to an incubator than we are
a makerspace. Except we don't
take, we don't take that
percentage of equity from
anybody, we just want people to
pay for space and join our
community. And then that in
itself, has so many dividends.
Audrow Nash: Definitely. Very
interesting. Yeah, I've been. So
I've gone to a ton of
makerspaces. Because I find them
quite useful. I just trying to
be involved with hardware. And I
often see they're incredibly
underfunded, they're lacking,
like, kind of like, the really
knowledgeable people, like
they'll get burned out, because
they're helping everyone and
then they end up leaving. And
then often because of maybe the
weird funding situation, they're
very political often, which is
kind of like stepping into a
toxic environment, I just wanted
to use a 3d printer, this kind
of thing.
Dan O'Mara: Yeah, and it is
hard, we found that, you know,
we love our maker community,
don't get me wrong, I don't want
to say anything bad about the
makers, and the hobbyists who
come and use definitely is
wonderful. But entrepreneurs are
a lot more hands off. Like, I
don't have to teach the most
basic, like, everyone, when you
when we focus on entrepreneurs,
and robotics companies, everyone
is an expert in something,
right. And this will even come
back to when we are when we're
talking about education side of
things, right? Because it's very
much a pure we a pure learning
system as well. Yeah. And that
if everyone's coming as a an
expert in something, they've
learned how to learn, right. And
the same thing with a space
where if people are coming in,
they have a large expertise in
this one thing, they probably
they don't know how to do all
this other stuff. But the fact
that they can learn it and do
it, well is something that is is
very likely, and they don't you
don't do a lot of hand holding,
right? Where I find that with
some of the makerspaces
particularly tech shop, I found
that they they had the their
their staff were called Dream
coaches. Right. But they were
minimum wage, people who maybe
learned how to use the machines
a day before everyone else.
Right. And, and the amount of
help that ever all of the
members needed on all of the
machines and how to do things,
and all of that stuff that
wasn't part of their business
model that was just supplied as
your membership for free. And
they're understaffed. People,
right. So yeah, it becomes
really hard to run a space when
you are educating every single
person, the best makerspaces I
found are they do have ways like
where you say are very community
are very like, like politics
side, because the community has
to provide that. Yeah. Not, you
know, the tears and not the
makerspace variable. But you
have to create the community
that does that, in many ways.
We've, we've done that to a
large degree, because then that,
you know, but it's no longer how
to use the laser cutter, it's
how to get your batteries
certified for shipping, how to
get FCC certified for saying,
and that's where, you know, if
we had created a space that was
kind of like makerspaces for
that, you know, it's a lot to
leave handhold every single
person through, so that, you
know, I'm just continually
impressed by our community of
just how high level they are.
And then because of that, they
understand what it means to have
a shared facility and it doesn't
mean that we still don't get
messes and issues and politics
and all that
Audrow Nash: of course but yeah,
but
Dan O'Mara: you know, it's when
when a community is of a
community of experts and
everyone is kind of doing things
that and learning to level up
their businesses and their self
and then being in that community
of doing together the the the
ability to share that is
incredible. Right and where and
the best makerspaces do that
with the hobbyist level twos is
they get their their members to
Have other members and it's not
expected to be like management
teaches you everything.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Let's see. So
that I mean, it's a very
interesting, I really liked the
model. How did you? How did you
come to this model of like so
coworking has its perks, but
it's kind of saturated by
Upwork. Or it's, like hard to
improve upon that. And then
makerspaces have their kind of
business model level issues. How
did you come to this idea of
targeting people, not not
targeting people, but like
focusing on entrepreneurs? As
opposed? Like, how did you come
on the business model that we've
just kind of described?
Dan O'Mara: Well, that from the
very beginning, like we all saw
what tech shop was doing, and
knew that we wanted something
more, because they didn't, they
didn't serve the entrepreneurial
like makerspaces don't serve
entrepreneurs very well, right?
Because it's like, well, it's
got everybody's gotta have some
time on the tool. Well,
sometimes an entrepreneur needs
all the time 100 tools, right?
And you have to be able to
provide some of that, that
ability of ways to to work that
out. And so we, from the very
beginning, we were like, well,
you know, I'm involved in
hardware, one of our founders
were involved in hardware, and
like, this is, this is what we
do and what we need. And so we
were like, well, there are other
people who are there, this is
what a good space like, this
would be great, because we were
like, also, let's use the
resource of from the building
owner having the space. And so
we built this all out from the
carpets to the drop ceiling and
everything, and saying, like,
you need to have space, and you
need to be able to have that
customer group and find that
niche. And that's where we
really, we saw that this niche
was underserved. And, you know,
we took a big bet that this
would be that there would be
enough people here. And now you
know, it's like we have a
waiting list for most of our
wonderful tables. And we're
happy to hear that. It's
wonderful for for that and we
want to expand and we're you
know, we are currently looking
for for more funding for our
round as well. And we're looking
to put more Circuit Launchers
out there. And specifically, the
the tie in to education was is
that after we built this
community, people were like,
Well, how did everyone here
learn how to do robotics? Yeah,
right. I want to do this, how do
I do this? And we're like, go to
school.
Audrow Nash: Maybe? Yeah.
Dan O'Mara: And they're like,
well, but but that they're not
teaching robotics. They're just
there, you know, I what degree
do I get? I think well, you
should go get an A, you should
go get a computer science degree
in mechanical engineering degree
and an electrical engineering
degree. And all of
Audrow Nash: us learned
business, if you want to do a
stolen,
Dan O'Mara: you should learn
business, too. Yeah. And like,
maybe there's not enough time in
the world to be able to learn
all those things. So we we said,
we were like, Okay, we need a
mechatronics education program,
that immediately gets people
using the latest technology. And
the latest things in building
robots is the first step.
Audrow Nash: And from a very
pragmatic perspective to like,
this is one of the things about
having entrepreneurs and it like
they probably won't be wasting
your time, because they are,
they have skin in the game, and
their money is slowly depleting.
And this kind of thing, while
they're trying to get interest
and grow. Like Time is of the
essence for them. So they're
gonna do whatever is most
pragmatic for them. Well, that
that was actually
Dan O'Mara: the model that like,
led us to this type of learning,
right? But entrepreneurs are not
necessarily our target market
are the learning curves, for the
learning side of it was because
most of most entrepreneurs are
too. Like, there's a couple
things. They're too busy to do
the thing like they can only
focus on the thing that they
need the next step. Yeah, so
unless there's some type of
immediate coaching or whatever
that they need, then the
business model really is if you
need that type of doesn't like
good design services and
prototyping services, get them
connected with other people in
the network, right. But there's
a whole group, if you want to
work in robotics, and you don't
have a job and you're not
willing to like, be the
entrepreneur, like I want to
work for a company or I want to
build a robot, you know, or I
want to learn to get better in
my job, or upskill or do those
things. There's all of those
people, and that's kind of our
market for Mechlabs, which is
it's our education program.
Audrow Nash: Mechlabs. Yeah, it
sounds like so when you focus on
the entrepreneurs from the
perspective of Circuit Launch,
it seems like it's a it's a bit
of an exclusive community where
you come in and you're an
entrepreneur, and you are highly
skilled in at least one thing,
and you're good at learning and
you're pragmatic, and you can
pay the bills to occupy desk
space. And so that's a good
business model for circuit
launch, but being kind of
exclusionary. Now, it's like how
do we get the other people in a
position where they might go
into this and that's the
education program. You got it.
Gotcha. I really like that,
Dan O'Mara: that and then the
benefit is is that we are filled
in a community of mentors. All
of those entrepreneurs are, you
know, they're in the community,
they've done it they are,
they're on the bleeding edge of
technology and doing cool stuff,
right? So it's very easy to find
someone who has a lot of skill
and expertise to come in and
help people and become mentors
in a lot of the stuff and to be
able to get answers from too for
sure, if I have this very hard
problem. Now we've created this
community that that serves
everyone, and they've been
serving each other, and a lot.
And now it's being able to also
serve the, you know, the
students that want to come in
and be able to learn how to do
this as
Audrow Nash: well. Yeah. How do
you incentivize entrepreneurs to
be mentors? For this, because
you were saying they're very
busy. And I just imagine that's
a challenge. Or maybe you pay
them or maybe it's part of the
like, you get your desk at half
off, or something like this, if
you're a mentor, there's
Dan O'Mara: obviously incentives
to self to mentor. I think that
in general, you know, so yes, we
do pay our mentors that come in,
but we have a very different
model, like we're not looking
for instructors. That's the big
difference with our education
program. And Mechlabs is a
built to learn it program,
Audrow Nash: it is difficult to
you. Sure,
Dan O'Mara: so the Mechlabs is
the building to learn it
program. The idea is, is that
you come in and you build a
project, if you want to learn
ROS, you either pick a project
that has ROS in it, or you join
a team project that has ROS in
it, right. And then you build
it. And then as you go along,
you're you are either
individually or in a team
responsible for figuring out how
to implement ROS. And so
there's the side of that is that
then what happens when you get
stuck, right? That's why you
join a program, traditionally,
people just say, well, we're
just going to teach you
everything you could possibly
need to know in an A to Z way.
And we're going to start at A
and it doesn't matter if you're
on B or C and you need it, you
need D and other people need to
have like it doesn't matter,
you're just all going to sit
around and wait till you found
the information get taught to
you. And or in a book in this
process, right. And that's what
an instructor does, right? They
have a curriculum. So we say no
lectures, no textbooks, no
curriculum, we say, what will
happen is the way you're going
to learn this, you're on D,
someone else's on F. And then
this is where it remember when I
made the tie that everyone is an
expert in something, people all
people are that way, we are all
human beings, we are all experts
in something, we've all done
something cool and can share
that. So that's when you get the
peer learning. So then people
come into our program that when
they get stuck, they then have
an entire team of people who all
have a ton of expertise in a lot
of things that are in the
program and can share their
expertise. And, and we have, you
know, for people who are like
for really deep problems, this
is where we can go to like our
community of like, of experts
that are working on really
cutting edge technology and much
more deeper technical stuff that
is there. And then we ask them,
then when they mentor, we're not
asking them to build a
curriculum. No, they don't need
a PowerPoint presentation. They
don't need they just come and
help. Yep, right? Come for a few
hours look where to go and be
like, Oh, this is the wrong
thing. Exactly. And so they meet
zero preparation, their effort
and their time commitment
becomes a lot more useful.
Right? And the and then of
course, mentors are what they
really like when you're
mentoring, especially in Silicon
Valley. That word means like
giving back because of all the
all the mentors and all the
platoons. Yeah, right. It's not
to say we don't pay our mentors
for that. But it is a you know,
it's it's expected that this is
a community we're all giving
back. And then the best part is,
you get to work with really
bright, upcoming roboticists
that you can hire for.
Right? And that's a really cool
thing when you can say, Oh, wow,
this guy is, you know, he's a
Python genius, but he's never
done an embedded software.
Right. I bet I could help him a
little bit along and then jump
in, and he could help my car.
Right? Yeah. Right. So that's
where this that when you're all
thinking about the ecosystem is
what we're building. We're
building an ecosystem of
entrepreneurs, and the way to
become entrepreneurs, the way to
become employees of companies
that are good and and to
accelerate your career and close
that loop. Because what we've
seen, you know, one of our
companies that are here is
Silicon Valley robotics. They're
an industry organization and BP
probably know, the Andhra and
all of that. And they, they're
amazing. And they've been
talking to a lot of the all of
the companies that are in
robotics, which unfortunately,
all kind of are very siloed when
they're not in a community. So
it can be very hard to know what
they need. And it can be hard
for them to say, Well, what they
need for from employees. Right?
Yeah. And what what they're
finding is, is that most of
their, their applicants are
mechanical engineers, right? But
what they really need is some as
more and they keep hiring,
computer science degrees, their
computer, they're, they're doing
hiring programmers who have
somewhere along the way, figured
out hardware, right. And so
there's, there's a real
disconnect of what you can learn
in school, and how you can
prepare for a job in robotics
and actually get the experience
and the portfolio and the hands
on of all of that. I mean,
that's, that's been a real
change. And what we've seen in,
in people looking in robotics,
to accelerate their skills and
to get jobs and to be able to
learn these things is that
there's a disconnect from what
industry needs and what
traditional education is
teaching. And we want to bridge
that gap. We want people leaving
our programs being like, Hey, I
built the the, you know, I
integrated the robotics SDK for
these servos into a ROS node.
And now this whole robot is made
with ROS Yeah. And that's my
portfolio and so you apply to a
job that's like, you know, needs
ROS experience, right?
Everybody says, I need ROS
experience that's on every
little thing. But how do you get
ROS experience what is out
there building a robot, and not
just a, you know, a turtle bot,
right? We need you need to, to
get deeper into some of this
ROS language and, and on
different things to be able to
really be useful on that. And so
that's where there's really,
like, there are some great
programs out there, but the
hands on component is what's
missing. And so we want people
leaving with literally the like,
this is what I built. Here's a
tutorial that I wrote, here's my
GitHub that shows what the code
that I did. And there's me
instead of just a resume that
says, I know some ROS right,
and then no one knows what that
is. And that that provides
people who are looking for jobs,
killer way to get into the the
industry.
Audrow Nash: Definitely. Yeah, I
can think so I've done some
hiring while at open robotics.
And it is funny, because it's
like the first thing that I go
to, it's not like I couldn't
care less about the resume. And
this is just my approach to it.
But go right to the GitHub, and
then look at kind of what
they've done and try to sauce
out what their commits are, and
how much of it was just like,
like, what they understand from
how they're doing it. And that's
really nice to be training
people in very pragmatic ways on
an actual project. I really
liked that approach.
Dan O'Mara: And then they get to
learn, like, well, how to use
GitHub for for hardware. That's,
that's not an easy thing, right
there. And, and how are all of
those things? And then we, you
know, we asked people to like
one of the minimum requirements
every single week, everyone has
to write it tutorial. And so
they start learning, good
communication skills and
demonstration, documentation
skills, and all of that, that we
want to help them demonstrate.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Let's see.
That's really interesting. One
thing so this robot behind you,
I'd like to introduce that
robot. It was one Belcher in a
project by some students that
went through this correct.
Dan O'Mara: Yep. So this is
Ricci. It's based on an open
source robot robotics platform
that was developed by Paul and
robotics. They, they actually
sell the robot that but they've
completely open sourced the
designs. So we were the first
group outside of the developers
to actually build a fully
working robot, or off of
reaching, right. So we
originally, so the, there's a
lot of, it's kind of grown as
we've gone, but we started with
the torso and the head, and one
arm, and in 12 weeks, we went
from not knowing anything about
this robot to fully functional
working robot, which was
amazing, like, and these are
students this is not like, you
know, some of them had very
little robotics experience, and
some of them had a little bit
more so in 12 weeks to build
something that was incredible.
Our second session with with
Ricci, everyone wanted to work
on the software side is the
platform. I had, of course I
bought all the motors for the
extra arm, and everybody wasn't
interested in doing the arm that
okay, which is fine. That's our
program. If you don't like you
get to work on the things that
you want to work on. It's a
match Not the things you it's
not a, it's not like that
horrible group project you got
in school where you're like,
Okay, this is the thing you got
to do. There's one person who's
good at it, let's just make him
do it. Right. Yeah, like, that's
not what our program is ours
very much like, you might be a
Python, you know, a whiz. But
you want to work on motor
control systems in the power,
you know, in power delivery and
3d printing and CAD, well,
that's great. You provide your,
your expertise to the rest of
the students wanting to learn
Python. And then the other
people who have a lot more
experienced the MES that are
just graduated, they have a lot
more experience in some of the,
you know, the CAD and all of
that. So that's how, how that
gets trained. But so our second
session, I built the arm because
nobody wanted to do it.
And so, but everybody else they
did, they created, they put it
on ROS, they it was on this
thing called loops, which was
kind of a semi open source, not
like it was an odd thing. Never
heard of the pollen head choice.
Yeah, it's it's a, like a
distributed microcontroller
system that, you know, has a lot
of potential, but because no one
in the world could get the
microcontrollers. But, Paul, and
we were like, well, let's, you
know, let's put this on ROS.
And like, use the Dynamixel
control system. Like, that's
great. That seems like to be a
good thing. And so we put them
over that, put them on a mobile
base, and then he became a
concierge robot. And he actually
walked around told jokes and
gave tours and told told people
in the pandemic, if they weren't
wearing masks, that they want to
put a mask on. Oh, funny. So
that was the second the third
session we did again, Ricci as
the platform became a very deep
object orientation and grasping
techniques like work, so they
they rewrote a lot of the
control systems for for the the
motors, integrated all through
ROS worked with April tags, and
you know, criminal, you know,
creating a computer vision and
learning how to be able to grab
a block and we set it up so
that, you know, if you picked up
the block, the robot grabbed it
and put it back where it was
cool. And so that's kind of
their their session is that was
a smaller session of, of team.
Yeah, there's a lot of became an
amazing platform. That's
awesome. I like and it's all
open source, we publish all of
our stuff, and all of the thing
and so people who are interested
in doing it, and that's a really
important component that we
found out for our program was
the open source part, the open
source part. So we first
started, as you know, we're
growing and building this as we
go and figuring out what we
wanted our very first pilot was
to bill to take a already
existing coffee robot that was
working, it's a little bit
you've seen our coffee robot,
definitely. But it's basically
the three axis palletizing, two
arms that grab cups and things
and then put it up to a big
super automatic espresso machine
and then delivers the cup,
right. And it's all done on
ROS. But it was done developed
by a couple of Crazy Russian
developers that are awesome.
They were there interesting. It
but it it needed a lot of work
for for design. And so the
person who owned it wanted us to
upgrade it, and they're there.
And we found that trying to get
students to one manage client
expectations, too much being in
a little like an understanding
what they really needed and all
of that and ended up becoming
really too. And then reverse
engineering something is often
much harder than just building
it the first time. Oh, I'm sure
right. And so that's something
that I think we've all learned
as you go along. But in the
beginning, it can be very, like
enticing to be like, Well, I
have this thing, I can just
improve it right? Sometimes it's
really just better to kind of
Audrow Nash: go back to the
start over. Yes, yeah.
Dan O'Mara: And so that was our
very first session, we found
that having an and having a
closed, like we couldn't publish
any of our work. And so ever
since then we were like No, no
open source right away. Like all
of our projects, all of the
things need to be like
publishable because then you can
manage, like you benefit from a
community of people most of the
time that are working on the
open source group. You know,
documentation is always hit or
miss with all projects, but
particularly open source at
least, at least they have more
information out there than
something that's totally was
right. Yeah. And so you're gonna
look at the code doing as much
reverse engineering, you can
look at the code, you can
download examples, you can work
on that. And then you you have a
place to be able to say like,
you know, that something, at
least somebody has done
something, it's worked,
Audrow Nash: right. And you can
get an idea of the community
around it, too. So you can see
if it's supported or not, or
like will other people who did
Dan O'Mara: this with no
community, like Yeah, he had
zero community at first. And so
now we get tons of requests all
the time, be like, Hey, how did
you do this? Or here's, you
know, we want to make this too.
And so we can then cut Pretty to
the community. And then the
benefit for that is, is then all
of the students learn to, you
know, to better documentation
and how to better, you know,
support an open source and how
to work in a community of people
and how to do project management
and all of the soft skills and
kind of important things that
you need to know, for running
and being a roboticist company,
right? Sure, all of that is
available in the, you know, the
in between building
Audrow Nash: stuff. And also, I
mean, it's all like, the skills
are also just very valuable, in
general, if you want to do
anything. So teaching them how
to do that, like, I mean, I use
Git every day. And so like
learning how to work with people
on that, and get feedback and
implement the feedback and this
kind of thing, very valuable. So
that's so cool, that you're
exposing them to all of that.
Let's see. So you mentioned that
they do tutorials for this, or
actually, before that, how do
you how do you scope a project?
Like how do you decide Ricci
making it so Ricci grab looks at
a fiducial marker, grabs a block
moves it somewhere? Like how do
you pick a scope? How do you
make it not too hard? Or not too
easy? Given the students that
you're working with?
Dan O'Mara: Yeah, I mean, that's
kind of been the interesting
thing was, when we had a really,
like, scoped out project, we
found that we often had more
trouble with that and reaching
those goals and figuring out
what what could be happening,
what couldn't happen, then we do
in our current system. So
currently, what we try to do an
overarching project idea whether
you know, some of the things on
the blocks right now is like,
we'd like to do one of the
millions or, or improve on the
millions of open source Quadra
pets out there, we'd like to,
that's one of our ideas, we'd
like to do some more. You know,
like, autonomous driving, cars
and tracks, and like the RC car
kind of thing, like, those are
some of the ones we like to do.
We'd like to, we have a Boston
Dynamics spot, we'd like to put
him on ROS. That's another one.
But so there's a perfect example
of, you know, we'd like to do
the ROS but we'd actually like
to, you know, we need to choose
a project that one will appeal
to a bunch of people who are,
are there. So you have like, we
have to make it fun and
interesting and exciting, right?
So it's like if if our courses
are, you know, learn inverse
kinematics, we will get a small
percentage of people, right.
However, if we can be like, you
know, build your own juggling
robot, right. Yeah. But you
know, sometimes, you know, you
put that out there today. And
then as you so let's take that,
as example. Like, we're gonna do
a juggling robot, right. Okay.
So we have to one make sure that
we have the budget know what,
you know, what kind of actuators
we're going to need, what kind
of things to be able to even
capable do that. And then we put
like, maybe that's where we
start, right? And say, Okay,
we're going to build a juggling
robot. And then like, all robots
and all companies and everything
that you do, you have to say,
Okay, well, we're going to have
to learn a ton along the way.
And then we're going to change
the scope as where we go based
on what we have and where we
need to be. So maybe that robot
in the end is only throwing the
ball up and catching it, right.
And then, you know, maybe we get
two hands to do that or there,
but it's the beginnings of like,
it's juggling, you know, we're,
maybe the next session picks it
up where we left off. Yeah,
right. And then says, Okay, now
we want to balls, and then we
need to be able to have a vision
system for tracking. And we need
to be able to do that. And then
you implement that. So the the
project becomes, you know, make
a juggling robot several
sessions, and you make broad
progress on that. And then part
of it is, is to like, we don't,
you know, unlike a business
where you say, Okay, I'm gonna
go hire the most capable people
I can find to do these very
particular jobs. We have the
opposite problem. We want the
most capable people in different
things, not doing what they're
good at. Yeah. Because unless
they want to do that, like if
people really, they're like,
they're really good at this, and
they just want to get better at
it. Great that we have you too
perfect. Yeah, but, and we get a
bunch of that. But in general,
like we want, if you're really
good at something, you know,
diversity, probably needing to
know some other things and
wanting to learn those things.
So let's get you focused on
that. You can help the other
people who are not as good at
these things with their Python,
if you're a Python coder, or you
know if you're a mechanical
engineer, they're your cat.
Like, there's such traits Yeah.
And so the scope really happens
based on like, who needs who
needs to do what. And if we lock
ourselves to the like, while we
must get this end product done,
right, then it isn't as
efficient for for everybody,
like, we want to hit our goals,
but we're not afraid of also
changing where that scope is to
say, you know, so that it is
achievable. And that you can
then learn the things you learn,
which is way more important than
getting the end result. Yeah,
but and so we do sometimes re
scope a project.
Audrow Nash: Like that is a
great example. Yeah, yeah,
Dan O'Mara: juggling robot
would, you know, maybe it's not
a three ball juggling robot
that's doing this. But you know,
we've developed, you know, one
ball and develop the beginnings
of a vision system that can
track those balls and catch it
on another side, and then the
next and then it gets bigger and
better. As you go along. It's,
it's more interesting that way,
too.
Audrow Nash: Definitely. And
also really nice for people
learning. And also seeing what's
possible in this kind of thing.
Like, you say, juggling robot,
and it's like, oh, that sounds
incredibly difficult. But it's
like throwing a ball up and
down. Just one still difficult,
but not like incredibly
infeasible. And then like, maybe
you go from one arm to the
other, and this kind of thing,
maybe it's
Dan O'Mara: like air actuated
tubes that are on a Trump rail
system, right? Some way. Like,
you can scope that in different
ways, you know, trying to get
Ricci to do juggling would be
servos are just not, they're not
going to that. Yeah, and so you
do have to, and part of that, I
think is where the scoping of
things is actually a really
interesting problem. Because you
don't, you don't know how to get
to the end of the thing you want
to try to say this is the thing
I want to go do this is you
know, what I might need along
the way, that's the one thing
that you can't do on your own
easily, right. That's why you
need to join over with mentors,
because a mentor will say, hey,
you know, don't waste your time
using these servos for juggling
robot, and then you've just
wasted six months of your life
trying to get this robot to
juggle. Yeah. And so that's why,
you know, our programs are like,
you know, we have mentors, and
we have advisors to say, Hey,
this is feasible. This is, you
know, why don't we start here?
Why don't we scope this in this
way? You know, because people
come to us for our
individualized program, saying,
hey, I want to make you know, we
had another person come in and
be like, I want a trash
collecting robot, you know, is
what I'd like to make. It's
like, I'd like it to be a robot
on wheels with an arm that picks
up trash, and puts in there, and
this is their first project that
they had never done robotics
before. Yeah. Right. And to have
an expert to like say, Well,
okay, you need a full base that
can put around at least 25
pounds, right of like weight
plus the weight of its own
robot. And then if you're going
to build some type of an
extension arm system, you have
to be it has to be able to deal
with the mechanical torsion and
the the reach and the
counterbalance. And then you
have to be able to carry all of
that, like, that is not a it's
not a first Prime first robot.
Yeah, for sure. And so you say,
Okay, well, that what could we
start off first? Maybe we could
put a trash can on a mobile
base, and put a speaker and ask
people to help
Audrow Nash: like that. Yeah,
right. But there's a trash can
Dan O'Mara: robot that's like,
can you put a little mobile
base, and then we can buy really
cheap cheap powders and cheap
things and, and that little
speaker, and then it'd be like,
Hey, can you help me pick this
up? You've just created, right,
it's like, so being creative
with that scoping also allows
people to choose the project
that is right for them. And
that's the first thing you do if
you're not joining a team
program with the project is kind
of already scoped out. Our
individualized program is you
come and you talk to our
advisor, and then we help choose
a project for you that will
achieve your learning goals.
Yep. So if you're Where do you
want to learn? ROS? Do you
wanna learn motor control? Do
you want to learn? You know,
what are the parts of the
robotics you want to learn
first? Right, yeah. And then we
kind of scope that project for
where people are at and to their
budgets to, you know, it's like,
it's like, yes, I want to build
an autonomous car, like, Okay,
can you do you have a car?
That's our sensors? And like, do
we need to buy that? Yeah. So I
mean, all of those things come
into account. It's why robotics
is so challenging, but in the
community of program where we
can support those components,
and they expenses, like on a
team project where you know,
reaches was $6,000 worth of
parts, right? Yeah. So, you
know, then that becomes
amortized, and everyone to work
on and make something really
cool.
Audrow Nash: So one thing that
strikes me with this, it seems
like so it seems absolutely
wonderful, like what are what an
absolutely great way for people
to learn. I'm wondering, I'm
thinking about how it would
scale ill, because one thing
that it strikes me about, or it
strikes me about it is that you
really need a knowledgeable,
engaged instructor or mentor, I
suppose, like someone to
facilitate this whole process.
What do you call them? Because
they're not they're not exactly
maybe their mentor.
Dan O'Mara: So, you know,
advisor is an easy advisor do
that. But we actually created as
we create a system so that the
mentors and advisors can help
run this help run the sessions.
Yeah, right. And those sessions
are lead. They're very
structured in like the what what
you do, you know, you have, like
our team session, we have a
project management, like, you
know, Monday, we do our project
management, we talked about all
the things that were done, we
follow kind of a scrum
platforms, we've divided we
choose our sprint, we get all of
the things together. And someone
kind of runs that. And we've
played around with actually
different people running that
each time. Oh, I like that,
which is also really helpful.
And some things or students
Yeah. Oh, so the students often
run the sessions, right. And
then we have collaborative work
sessions where everybody's
working together. And then we
have like a show and tell day,
where people are actually, they
show what their work is, they
get feedback from in person, all
of that kind of stuff. And, you
know, what's often what's
amazing is is though that, like
it's with mentorship, everyone
thinks like, Oh, I gotta have
that really, really highly. It
is accessible person or
intelligent person to run all of
those meetings, and all of that
stuff. And the structure helps
with a lot of that. And then
peers, because a lot of the
expertise comes from mostly from
their peers, because again,
everyone's an expert in
something. And the mentors spend
less time. And they also don't
teach like mentors don't
lecture. There's no one anyone
lecture. So we train our mentors
to simply say, to help them find
the thing that they need the
next step, right? Because in a
world where you can learn
anything on the internet
streaming thing, it's not, you
know, where will you get the
information from? I must have
the person in the information in
their head, it's how you find
that information becomes the
real challenge, right? Yeah. And
mentors become less than the
purveyors of information and
more the guidance along your own
path for you finding the
information. Yes, like, you
know, I think of my exploration
of, you know, I've been building
an espresso machine on my
bicycle. I'm in middle, like,
I'm in the middle robotics area,
like I'm an advisor and the
technical mentors, but I'm also
loved, I have a passion about
it, as well. And I'm not an
expert in any one thing, right?
So I was learning some basic,
like, learning to do certain
basic electronics, really, I've
done a cabinet on maker stuff,
but I've never really done basic
electronics stuff. And so I was
learning, the the beginnings of
putting a whole bunch of sensors
in my espresso machine, because
I'm also a coffee nerd. And I
was working on learning how to
build a PCB and, and how to wire
this all together. And I was
like, well, so then I ran across
this problem that like
microcontrollers. Take, have
logic, voltage and power
supplies aren't often different
than that about and so like, but
I was like, so do I need a step
down converter? How do I get the
signal from my sensor to the
voltage and still keep the
signal going? And I just had, I
was like, how do you search for
that? If you don't even know
what you're searching for?
Right? Yeah, obviously, we had
somebody with more electronics
experience, like know what you
need to look, it's explore
voltage divider, and then a bi
directional voltage divider. And
that's that circuit that was
like, Oh, great. They gave me
the jargon, that I could go
Google to find. And then I can
learn it myself. Right? They
didn't need to sit there and
explain Voltage dividers for me.
I don't need that. And so what
it does is it puts less like
previously, when you talked
about how do you incentivize
other entrepreneurs to be
mentors, is if you take this
impetus that they have to
explain everything, and do
everything for the students that
instead all they really have to
be available. This is like, Hey,
have you explored the concept of
a voltage divider? Have you
explored the concept of, you
know, the Ohms law like what is
this is kind of the thing you
need next, and then the student
goes, looks it up, implements
it, and they have a problem with
that. And so that's where the
change in things and in fact,
our mentors, we're not looking
for people who are experts in
everything. What I'd much rather
have in mentors and teach
students how to do is to be to
learn how to learn.
Our best mentors are people who
probably could learn the thing
that you The students were doing
the day before. Right? Like, oh,
you're you're, you know, we
don't get experts in everything.
There's no expert in everything
with robotics, right? So
instead, I'd much rather have
somebody who can look up and
say, like, well, I've got the
basics of ROS down, I've done a
little bit with machine learning
and computer vision. But I bet
you, we could probably figure
out how to integrate a point
cloud and be able to get a depth
map and be able to create that
kind of a thing. Right, you
don't have to have someone is
that the but a mentor will be
able to help lead the students
and then they do it with them.
And then they all learn
together. And that's kind of
where I feel like I'm, I guess
I'd be considered a mentor,
also, because I'm also often in
my groups, and learning that,
you know, but that's the real
change in it. And it takes a a
thought change a paradigm shift
in this, like, I'm gonna sit
here and wait till someone
teaches me exactly what I need.
Right? That's where what
education has taught us, like
original education is taught.
Yeah, we just have to take the
class to get the thing that we
eventually someone's telling us
what we need. Yeah, it's
Audrow Nash: very instead, in a
sense, yeah. Instead,
Dan O'Mara: it's active. You
say, this is the project I'm
making? What do I need? Oh, it's
run, you know, it's computer
language. It's got a, you know,
it's running Linux. And Oh,
guess what I can control with
Python. I guess I should go take
a weekend course in Python Crash
Course and then write a ROS
node. Right? Yeah. And that,
that's kind of and then I mean,
that's kind of how I learned
Python was like, hey, this robot
was cool. It ran on Python. I
guess I should learn that. But I
had not been incentivized to
learn it in my entire life.
Because I was like, Well, why I
don't like websites, I don't
want to run a write another
website, I've got HTML, that's
fine. I don't want to write
back. Like, oh, he does cool
things, I want to learn Python.
And it's the same kind of thing
with Project learning where
we've been, you know, I'm sure
everyone who's listening to this
has done this in their life is
like it worked on a project,
they haven't known something, so
they had to go learn it. And if
you have that project, like if
you're working with robot arms,
you know, the linear algebra
with for inverse kinematics and
all of that stuff, that's a
thing you need to kind of know,
a lot of times. And so that was
something that, you know, all of
a sudden, we had everybody like
looking up and learning doing
doing like linear 100 projects
on the side, because they wanted
to, to learn those things. That
you know, so we believe that
instead of going, starting from
A to Z, and trying to start with
all the foundational you've ever
you ever need, and then you will
immediately forget and have to
relearn anyway, no total, we
just say, hey, when you get to
the point that you need this,
you will be incentivized to
learn. And then all of the
foundational knowledge that you
need, will start coming in and
you'll be incentivized when
you're actually using. It's a
different way people are, you
know, they're not, they're not
these experts in fields, they're
people who got a little bit of
everything can probably figure
it out along the way.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, I really like
that. It's, it's kind of it's a
flip in the hole thinking about
how to learn and how to
structure groups to do things,
which I really like. It's like,
you put people to work where
they're motivated, because they
think it's interesting. And you
have them in this group, where
they can ask questions, and they
can contribute where they want.
Yeah. And so because of that,
the mentor is really just the
person that gets them unstuck.
Yeah, occasionally, and that's
really low overhead for the
mentor, you just need someone
who's like, good at thinking, to
be the mentor. I really like
that. It seems like a great
structure. It's like a stable
structure for a team to do a
productive, dude, do something
and learn a lot. That sounds
great to me.
Dan O'Mara: Yeah. And it creates
a real interesting thing with
like, you know, everybody hated
group projects. I know I did in,
in school, right? And it was
because the whole power
structure in the way that you
were doing things were was
really flawed. You know, it was
like, Okay, you guys all don't
want to do this thing. And I'm
gonna make you do this thing.
And I'm gonna put you to a bunch
of people also, who don't want
to do this thing. And what's the
easiest way out is you give the
person you think that will know,
like, who won't say no. And who
doesn't want a bad grade on it,
you force them to do all the
work. Right? It's it's horrible,
like social experiment, that bad
incentive structure for sure
incentive structure, right?
Where instead our group's people
that come in, and it's like,
well, you get to work on the
thing you actually want to
learn, which is great. And then
you become motivated, motivated,
you do a lot of work. And if if
there's literally no one that
wants to work on something,
right? That we figure it out,
either, you know, everybody gets
together and they do this one
thing or that thing to get over
the hump. Right. Yeah. And we
all agree to it. or, you know,
use free scope it like, Why does
a robot have to have two arms?
Yeah, it doesn't. We just bought
all the parts. And so I was
like, Well, fine. If you guys,
you guys don't need a second
arm, but I, well, I bought all
the parts, so I'll build it for
you and make it happen. And they
were more interested in the
software and the, you know, the
control systems rather than the
actual hardware at that point.
So they weren't forced to do it.
And that's really a crucial part
is there is no like, it can be
flexible, a project is flexible,
and it can be developed in a way
that everybody's efforts are
working towards the thing that
is awesome. And then then the
things that aren't as awesome,
you at least are motivated to do
them because you understand why
they're important.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, I think I was
thinking about it just now. And
it's, I was wondering about like
the unsexy tasks, in a sense,
like, as you're saying, and what
it seems to me is that so say
there's this one critic because
often the unsexy tasks might be
very important. But people don't
want to do that. Maybe it's like
developer ops kind of thing. And
so what I see or what I'm
thinking is that with this
structure, what happens is
everyone learns basic skill, or
everyone learns skills in what
they're interested in. And then
they get to a point where
they're fairly good at what
they're like they've learned a
good bit, they're fairly
invested in the idea of
continuing and then on their
own, maybe, then they can go and
they can learn some required
infrastructure or best practices
or whatever it might be. But
this has kind of prepared them
by giving them enough skill to
get somewhere interesting. So
that they might eventually go
over the unsexy task, go and
complete that one.
Dan O'Mara: And because it's a
project, right, you know, it's
like if the, if the unsexy task
is like, you know, a power
control system like, well,
nothing is gonna run unless you
have so that everybody gets
pretty motivated, even for the
unsexy tasks to battle notion
when it's a bottleneck and that
they won't get there. And then
and then you're all working
collaboratively to split up the
tasks that no one wants to do.
Right. And, and that people
volunteer and actually help out
with that. And so And there's
usually somebody who, who is
excited about learning, like, it
is robotics it is, and somebody
understands why, you know, or at
worst, there's someone who's
really good at it, who can
hammer it out way quicker than
anyone else, then everyone else.
Yeah. And then they help other
people do that really quick, you
know, so all of those things are
your tools to be able to create
a great group and actually
succeed in a project. And, and
learn a whole bunch on the way.
But the whole point is, is
unlike business, where it's you,
everybody has their silos, well,
what's really created. And
that's a bit of a disservice in
the robotics industry, what we
see is, is a lot of our students
are coming that are, you know,
automation, engineers, QA, it's
all sorts of like, deep company,
like people in larger robotic
civic roles. Yeah. But they want
to learn one's role something
else, because they don't have
any of opportunity to do that at
their work. Because, like, the
way companies are set up is like
you don't give thought, you
know, tasks to somebody who's
not good at them, you give them
to this person who's really good
at them. And then that's all
they do. Right? But I mean, you
know, it's it, as a business
side of things in my brain, I'm
always looking for something
that somebody might excel at,
that they don't currently do.
Right? Because then you get
happier, better employees that
are learning more things, rather
than giving only the things that
are to the people who are good
at, like, we get excited about
learning, we want to grow by
employees doing new things, and
what what else might they be
good at that they're not doing
right now, then they grow into
new positions and stuff. And
it's the same thing, you know,
with with this group, but it but
when you have a lot of people
coming from some of these other
other companies that aren't
doing that they're hungry to
learn all the new stuff, and we
want to we want to give them
that opportunity to to learn the
things that they're not good at.
Audrow Nash: What do you think
would happen? If so I understand
from a company's perspective,
that desire to specialize people
and have them do the thing
because they're going to be
really good at it. And also, you
can kind of pit pay them like
the minimum amount because the
majority of their time is on the
most specialized, highest value
added thing. Whereas if you pay
them to learn about something
that's irrelevant to whatever it
is that they're most specialize
on. You could think of it as
last time, but as you're saying,
maybe it's they're pivoting into
a thing that they're really
really good at but they're very
happy to do. But I just What
would you think if companies
were to adopt this approach
where maybe like, I don't know,
there's some things where it's
like 20% of your time is your
own for side projects or
something, but what what would a
company look like that did this?
And what do you think the
outcome would be?
Dan O'Mara: Well, I think that,
you know, as a side thing, like,
we have a whole enterprise side
that we would love to be able to
do and have people doing that.
And it's like, that's a really
easy way that they can provide
that for their students, or for
their employees be like, Hey,
you guys want to learn to get
trained on a whole bunch of
other stuff that has nothing to
do with it? Like, let's put you
through Mechlabs, and then not
only you're going to gain a lot
of experience, be able to help,
and really pull this back to
your teams and new a new way of
thinking. So that is something
we want to provide for companies
and enterprise as as well. But I
didn't realize that business
model. Yeah, I mean, but I do
think that that's like companies
getting someone very specialized
is it's important for for speed
and effectiveness, right.
Because obviously, if you want
to build something and get it to
market, you need to be really
fast. And and the fastest way to
do that is to get a whole bunch
of people already know how to do
it. But no one truly knows how
to do it. If we're actually
working on good technology,
right? It's all new. No one's
done it before, if it's
exciting, cool stuff. And so
what we want to do is we want to
foster the, the AI and we want
to foster companies who realize
that it's not what the skills
that people know, that will make
them successful, it's how well
that they they can learn. Right?
And that's like that metric is
something that, you know, we
really have to train our
companies to look for. And we
have to train our people to be
able to demonstrate. And that's
one metric
Audrow Nash: explicitly,
Dan O'Mara: how how, how easily,
like how quickly you can learn
to learn?
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah,
definitely. I think it's so
valuable, right? For sure. And
it's something that by keeping
that muscle strong, it seems so
valuable.
Dan O'Mara: Absolutely. Because
you want somebody who can figure
things out and learn how to
learn a new skill yet, if you
put them doing the same thing
all the time, that just that
they're good at, and they aren't
as good at learning. You know,
you get your job done, but you
don't, like succeed if that job
changes.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. And I think
also over time, if people are
not engaged in their work, they
start slowly falling behind,
because they were really
specialized ones. But the jobs
responsibilities are a moving
target, and they're moving away
from their core competences.
Yeah. So
Dan O'Mara: you have to if I'm
not learning something new, or
like, growing in something that
I'm doing in some way, I get
really bored. Right, yeah,
that's why I've been, you know,
I've been a weird employee to
hire in many ways, because I
went through so many things that
are so many has, like my resume,
bizarre looking, right. I have a
degree in ethnobotany. And I do
robot interest now. You know,
it's, like, what, but I know,
it's bad. And so basically, I
just created a, like an
education program that can
justify the way that I like to
learn. That's really what we've
done. I just feel like, you
know, I'm good at learning
things. And I can get to that,
like, 80% of competency really
quickly, pretty quick, you know,
and so I wanted to be able to
help people who are interested
in not only that, like learning
that last top 20%, but also the
people who want to get up to
that at that first 80% quickly.
And, you know, realizing
robotics is something that's
changing so quick. And like the
the last five years, the
availability of hardware, that
at a low price point that you
can start building at has just
exploded, right. Yeah, think of
all of the like, you know, it's
like, right now we're getting
little, the, like the Itsy Bitsy
and the feathers and the you
know, all of the cool stuff from
Adafruit, the microcontrollers
that not only now use, you know,
Arduino and see but they also
you could do circuit Python. And
so basically, you can take a
weekend workshop to learn
Python, you can you can take a
microcontroller with and use
that Python on it, you know, and
then in a very short time, you
can be writing, we're doing
robotics code, and bad code, and
making sensors work and building
this stuff for you know, so
cool. You know, so much less
than what we used to have to pay
to get into robotics, right? You
don't have to have a platform
like Ricci to understand
robotics anymore. Like you could
there's so much more remember
when bait like if you'd wanted
to make a robot, just a simple
base with a couple of wheels,
and they hundreds of dollars,
you know, and now you can, you
know, obviously you get what you
pay for it but you can You can
buy a $30 kit on Amazon and have
a base of a robot that you can
put the Asbury pie on, and put
ROS on and then beat then put a
camera on and you know, under
$150, you could actually be
having a full like ROS
implemented computer vision
robot.
Audrow Nash: Oh, totally. Yeah,
no. I just, I just spoke with
our friends from Meg Dang, who
does the spot mini looking robot
mini buffer. And like, that's a
quadra pet for $500 that has
pretty sophisticated sensors and
a Raspberry Pi. Like, that's so
cool. That's totally new, like
buying a quadra pet at an
affordable price. Exactly. Like,
unbelievable. Yeah, and you're
right, yeah, the explosion of
hardware, it's
Dan O'Mara: moving so fast.
Right. And right now is the time
to get deeper in robotics or
learn other things in robotics,
because it's so much like the
availability of learn this stuff
is finally to anyone, you don't
have to be, you know, a
researcher, you know, when
million dollar lab to learn, you
know, inverse kinematics with a
with arms, you know, 3d printed
with a few few stepper motors,
and, you know, you could be
learning it for less than than
$100.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it's not
going back to thinking about
corporations or like larger
businesses and having them do
something similar to your
courses. One, one thing, one
challenge that I could imagine
is that if the people don't want
to be there, because you have,
it's sort of a biased group that
comes to you for these courses,
where they're all really engaged
and very excited to do it for
themselves, like they're
literally paying their own money
to spend their time learning and
working with you on some
projects. How do you imagine it?
Would I just What do you think
about the idea of people having
their company send them to this
kind of time? Where they would
work on something in line with
the projects we've been
discussing?
Dan O'Mara: Yeah, absolutely. I
mean, the part of it is, is
that, you know, as we have to
make it fun, we have to make it
interesting. That's kind of the
point is, is that and that's
scoping those projects, right?
Yep. So 14 projects, you know,
we do have to make a fun and
interesting project that people
are going to be excited about,
right? If someone really doesn't
want to be there. Like, we can
also think can just sit the
corner and read their phone if
they want, like, I'm talking.
Like, if they want to
contribute, they can. And the
way our programs are, is there's
no one's relying on like the
fifth person who's breathing his
phone to get the job done.
Right. You know, and so we did a
program just yesterday for a
Brazilian Innovation Tour
Company that that brought in
about 3030 students all have
different corporate backgrounds,
who had not no robotics
experience, per se. And we
brought them in, set them down
on a little platform, which is a
I don't know if you've seen
their polo zumo bots, they are.
Audrow Nash: Yep, use them as
like a sumo thing. Yeah. Robots,
Dan O'Mara: but they have an IMU
they have proximity sensors,
they have line following they
have, they have all of these
things, and an example library.
And so we basically set them up,
I made a quick tutorial on the,
you know, on our wiki, and I
said, you know, this is, you
guys are going to figure this
out. So you're going to learn
how to connect the robot, you're
gonna learn how to install your
IDE, you're gonna learn how to,
to load it up and understand
that all the things that you
want to pull your hair out with
Arduinos. And like, I don't like
it, the Comm port, where do I
find the library. And so we made
some of the tutorials to make
that easier, but we put them
through the paces, and then let
them explore all the examples.
And we said, hey, there might be
a fighting robot example, in
there somewhere, see if you can
figure it out. And they all did.
And then we let them decorate
the robots. And then and then we
had a big tournament of a
battling, you know, bots. And so
these, you know, and they got a
chance, if they wanted to get
into the code and learn a little
bit of coding, they could do
that if they wanted to play
around, you know, with the
hardware, like they could do
that. And so that that's really
the thing is, is to like, you
know, aim it at wherever, you
know, we're not going to get
them into the you know, the deep
math and deep coding of stuff if
it's if that's not where, where
they need to be. But having a
cool product like if you are
Bible is the project, you build
it to learn it. If you get a
good project, there will be
something there that will
interest most people and if it
really doesn't interest them at
all. It doesn't hurt them to be
on their phone over there to
help in any way that they do.
Like we often we occasionally
have students that that fall off
the, you know, fall off the
beaten path a little bit and so
that we have to pull them back
in, or they don't contribute as
much. But the way it works is
they get what they need and what
they put in.
Audrow Nash: Oh, definitely.
Let's see. So you were speaking
about tutorials over earlier?
Can you tell me a bit about
having students? Because it
sounds like it's one of the
like, few things that you're
taking more of an active stance
and encouraging students to do
in the program? Would you tell
me a bit about that?
Dan O'Mara: Sure. So a lot of it
is is like understanding the
process of accountability,
right? With a project based
program? The big question is
like, Well, why don't I just do
it myself? Right. And rightly,
so if that's like, we want you
to learn it yourself. And we
want you to grow those things
like that. And a lot of people
can. But we also want to offer
the points for like, a, when you
get stuck, you have mentors, and
you have people who can help
you, right. And that's what you
don't have doing your product on
your own. And we all get stuck,
right? The other side of it is
is the, you need some kind of
structure of accountability,
right? We all know that we were,
there's no way that we're going
to continue going to the gym, if
we, if it were a pay by the day
kind of thing. Right? The fact
that we've paid for them on and
we have to go to the gym, that's
the only way that really gets us
to go to the gym sometimes,
right? And so you have to create
some levels of structures of
accountability. And so
documentation is one of those
things that we just found. You
know, I'd like to say everybody,
but there I have some people
that like I love documentation
that like good to help us with,
right? Because most people don't
do well with writing
documentation. Right? They're
great on building stuff, but
they don't want to document it.
And so part of the, the learning
process for, you know, the
classic thing is, is the, you
know, show and demonstrate and
then involve the other person
into learning, like, that's the
classic way of teaching
something, right? Yeah, well, in
this situation where, you know,
it's a little bit flipped,
right, you're learning it along
with them. It's like the, the
demonstrate and the teach
someone else, what you're
learning is part of that
documentation process. All of
those put together creates
accountability, it creates a
ability for people to ingrain
what they've learned, because
they have to explain it. And
then it's documented so that
when other people need that
information, it can be there, as
well as when we need that
information. You know, they say
documentation is a love letter
to your future self. Yeah,
definitely. It is. And so it's
super important. And so we
that's, that's one of those
unsexy things that we, you know,
we require people to do. And so
that that's just one really
important thing we found that
really helps on so many levels,
that we want to make sure that
it's it's part of every single
person's like, kind of
requirements to that.
Audrow Nash: Are there any other
requirements that you have? Or
is that really like? I mean, you
show up at certain times, and
you have like, these are the
hours we'll be all together. But
other than that, is there any
real hard structure in the whole
program?
Dan O'Mara: Well, there's a lot
of structure, but requirements,
like, don't have any other
requirements. We don't have any,
like, you know, school is filled
with prerequisites, right? You
can't take this unless you've
taken this and you can't take
this. And, you know, I don't
know about you, but I opened
right up to the back page of the
manual. But I want to take all
of that, like I really, four or
500 classes. That's what I want
Audrow Nash: to take those
interesting ones. Yeah. Why do I
have
Dan O'Mara: to take Intro to
Computers? Like, really? Like,
I've been using computers, thank
you. And like, so we realize,
like, there are no prerequisites
we do for our team programs, we
do choose people that have a we
need to have one skill in strong
the team that not have been
strong, but you need to have a
bear like your competence, you
have to have some competency in
one of the fields that is needed
to complete this project. And
so, and again, you don't even
have to do those things. But we
do want to piece in your
resource for the group. And so
we try to match people in that
and if there's really truly a
spot that has no competency in
that area, that's where we'll
bring a mentor and to be able to
help sense that there. And so
for our team levels, it's the
our one requirement is that you
have some competency and some
level of that and we can be
pretty loose with that if you're
a maker and you've done a lot of
CAD to be 3d print But you've
never done anything
professionally or you've never
done a bunch of other things
with it, that's still really
valuable. Because we find that
you've learned that thing. It's
that like, what did you get
expert T said, we just want you
to have some expertise in
something, so that we know that
you, you can can do that. And
that helps with the team project
for the individualized project,
there are no requirements, you
can come in as green as you
could possibly be. And, and it's
really amazing, because you do
see, you know, it's not just the
people who are, you know,
experts getting other be like,
there's so many things that this
person, for example, that person
who's really green in robotics,
has really good business sense.
And this other person who is an
electrical engineer, is now
learning about basic marketing
for the very first time, you can
contribute to their basic
marketing, right, like, yeah,
and that ends up being still
really valuable because of this
community thing. So we, we just
kind of say, forget the
prerequisites. You know, most
people have some level of
something there, and then they
can join us, or we can help put
them into a group, maybe you're
not jumping into the deep object
orientation and grasping class,
you're working on the mini, you
know, DIY pup, you know, mini
pumper where you're, you know,
just working with Raspberry Pi,
that some of those things. So,
you know, it's, it's about
scoping the people for the prior
matching the people for the
project to those that we don't,
other requirements is just you
need to show up at sessions. But
we also have a really cool way
of doing an asynchronous thanks.
So we have even talked about how
this whole like you actually
asked earlier, how do you scale
this, and I don't think we got
to that right.
Audrow Nash: Now I definitely
want to talk about it, you can
do the
Dan O'Mara: scaling is that this
is all a hybrid model. Not only
can you be in person, but you
can do this completely remote.
Right, that's all. So that's how
we scale a lot of this group.
And we found so it can be
literally double the amount of
students because we can do half
in person and half out of, you
know, being completely virtual.
And then even so our facility
wise of this, even our students
who are in person, they don't
need to be here doing things all
the time. If we're at a meeting,
like we're having a Zoom
meeting, there's no point in us
all being in in one room. And,
and so they can all be home and
like, you know, in their
bathrobe, doing it doing a
project planning project. And
some people might come into the
lab. And so that's how we really
scale this is that you create a
hands on experience, even if you
don't have an experience now and
I'd like to tell this quick
story about Noelle who is one of
our Argentinian students. He
lived in Argentina. And he was
an automation engineer, but he
had never done cat never done
any type of cat design. And, you
know, just like, like, this is
something I want to learn. But I
just again, he's like, Well, do
I go back to school for this? Do
I take a course to learn how to
use basics, I've never had
anything fun to make. Right. And
so now we're like, hey, so the
the neck piece of this was
originally scoped with the Paul
on robotics as this really
fascinating but very intricate
mechanism where it was a three
degree of freedom system that
was called the orbiter, it was
really cool. It was a little
outside of what we were going to
build and recreate. So we just
put a pan tilt servo in there.
But all of this had been
designed. And so we needed to
actually design the mounting of
those servos into the program.
So we needed somebody to Cat up
the whole structural mechanism
to hold that. And so he was
like, Oh, I'd love to learn CAD.
So I literally went on a, you
know, a call with him spent 20
minutes to be like here, this is
how you set up your components
and your you know, your your
components and your parts in
Fusion 360 so that you can be
successful, here's how you turn
on your device, you know, your,
your actual changes history so
that you can get back to things.
And here's like two other tips.
Here are the models for the
servos that you could put in and
this is how you put them in. And
now I want you to build this.
Right yeah. And it gave him kind
of the specs of what what we
want to hear the measurements.
There's that he you know, he
went home and by the very next
night had built something. And
so he put it on our 3d printers
over the air. And so it was
literally printing out in the
morning when I came in. I come
in, I hand it to the team, they
assemble it for him, they give
him notes. He goes back and re
revive designs it and it's like
he's hands on calving and 3d
printing. He's just not
necessarily touching the thing.
Which is incredible. So he
basically learned to CAD better
than most of us in two weeks.
That's awesome. Right and manage
managed to do all the things
that we needed. So that's kind
of the process is like, you
know, you have something cool
that you need somebody who wants
to learn it. And even if they're
completely virtual, you know,
they can buy, you know, a
cheaper robot, a servo and a
control module and then start
working on the code to control
that and understanding it, even
hands on at their desk, that
then that code can go and be
uploaded into our project and
work in a much bigger system. So
yeah, you kind of on a micro
level do quite a bit hands on,
even if you're not in our lab,
then in most of our programming,
like a lot of our programmers,
that we're mostly interested in
just doing the code for the
robot, they didn't even come
into the lab, they were working
with everybody, but we'd have
them up on the big screen and
talking to them. And they would
be uploading code and
controlling the robot from their
home. That's so cool, right? And
being able to test this, while
we're all working on this, you
know, it becomes like, we aren't
limited anymore to in, in, in
classroom, you know, experience,
the pandemic is taught like this
was developed during our
pandemic, because we were like,
well, we can't wait, we need to
create this amazing program for
people now. And the pandemic
shows just how well we can be
able to do that and what the
limitations are, as well. But
yeah, allows us to create a
system where we can scale this.
And the actual in you can be
hands on without necessarily
having to be in a school, nine
to five every single day.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, definitely.
Yeah, it's so interesting. To
me, it seems like the whole
approach that you're taking in
this, how do you call it again,
Mechi, or with labs, Mechlabs,
the whole approach you're taking
in the Mechlabs, course, or
program? It seems like, I'm
comparing it in my head to like
universities, or these kinds of
things, where it seems like they
go against a lot. So for
example, people have to take
courses they're not motivated to
do, you have to learn things
that are kind of abstract, and
not directly applicable to what
you're working on, or what
you're even interested in. But
it's like a to z learning, as
you were saying. They have a
rigorous measures in place for
accountability, like all the
exams, and things like this, and
the like hierarchy that forms
from all of that. Whereas you
guys, and also then they have
they have the high paid lectures
relatively. They have the
intricate infrastructure around
like TAs and graders, and all of
this kind of thing,
Dan O'Mara: multimillion dollar
labs that very few people can
access that money. Yeah,
Audrow Nash: that's totally
true, too. And so you guys kind
of took everything and you
flipped it on its head. And so
it's like, people are motivated
to do whatever it is, you need
very little of an expert's time.
Those are your advisors and
mentors. The people it's like,
if they want to disengage,
that's totally fine. But for the
most part, they're doing it
because they're totally
interested in it. Yep. It's very
interesting. And then the
accountability with
documentation, providing it so
that it's good for them in the
future, it's good for you to
build off of their work. And
it's helping them kind of skill
up in how they communicate, and
also in their own understanding,
by leveraging the idea that they
teach, to learn because they are
writing documentation, teaching
it to their future selves, or
whoever their reader may be.
readers may be, it feels very
clever to me. With all this,
it's like you're working with
the grain of human nature very
well, as opposed to other
structures is how I'm thinking
of it now.
Dan O'Mara: Well, it's like, we
we develop something that we
wanted to learn from, and how
we've kind of learned these
things, right. And so it's,
that's been modeled on that. And
then, you know, we put it to
test we got groups of people,
we, we built this stuff, and
said, Hey, this is where we
refined over time, and we
refined it with all of this is a
giant experiment as well. And
we're going to continue to grow.
One of the things we hope to do
is micro credentialing with like
NFT badges where if you were
actually you own your
certificate, and you can
demonstrate value along with,
you know, we can say, hey, you
know, you want to get a badge in
motor control theory, right,
your project is right in there,
all you have to do is is maybe
hit a few of these other kinds
of things and demonstrate that
in your project, and you will
earn this badge, and then you
can put that on your LinkedIn
and your resume and everything
else. Right. Yeah. Other stuff
that we hope is is that we'd
like to create even a reward
structure structure based around
a crypto coin, where you can be
able to somewhat like a miles
program, you know, you're in a
in a program and you're you're
actually learning and you get
rewarded by a crypto token. And
then as you go through there,
you're actually being able to
find like, earn your way through
your program and, and you know,
if it ever becomes successful,
and we're something maybe that
crypto pays for your entire
education itself just by you
learning, right? That would be
super cool, throw everything up
into the air and say, Hey, we've
just run radicalized all of this
education system by, you know,
that and if it's worth nothing,
at least you get an education.
So, yeah.
Audrow Nash: And you guys had
fun making a cryptocurrency?
Yeah,
Dan O'Mara: exactly. So like
there's, there's a lot of really
interesting things that we hope
will come down the pipeline as
we as we build this and and
experiment with it. And we're
excited to have people who come
and be part of this journey with
us.
Audrow Nash: What do you think
is the role of typical? Like, I
mean, I guess K through 12
education, but then university
education? And like, how does
all that relate to this? Can it
supplemented? Is it meant to be
torn down by this is like, Where
does it all fit?
Dan O'Mara: I think it can fit
both. I mean, you know, right
now, I would say that it's a
great supplement, to, you know,
an engineering degree to get
actual hands on experience and
portfolio projects. Electronics
degree, I mean, any of those
degrees, you can you will gain
by joining a program like this,
we, you know, we have
aspirations in 10 years to maybe
make actual universities just
not as relevant, you know,
relevant. I mean, who knows,
maybe we can do it. Like we'd
like to, that's what we're
shooting for. I mean, you know,
how we see a problem. And we
think that our solution can do a
lot for things. And it doesn't
mean that we're also just
because I say, that doesn't mean
that we're not open to like,
hey, you know, you're we can
partnership with universities,
we have partnership with
programs and boot camps. And,
you know, you're learning and
embedded embedded programming
bootcamp, right, we can be able
to provide the hardware and the
projects that you could actually
cut your teeth on even virtually
right. And so that, you know,
all of those things can be
possible. And so the, there's a
lot of opportunity for us to
create good partnerships and
work with organizations as per,
you know, we're focused mostly
on, you know, 16, to 18 year
olds, and up, we're looking for
kind of, you know, post high
school graduate, we get a lot of
people who are already
graduated. And we keep seeing
this like this. The sad part is,
we also see a lot of people who
are experts, so called experts,
we get the literally on paper,
and we see like, wow, why are
they even taking this course?
It's like, they don't know why
paper, they're great. But you
know, time after time, I can't
tell you how many masters of
mechanical engineering degree,
you know, people that we've come
in, and they can't cap their way
out of a paperback. Yep. Right.
Like, there are some really
basic skills that are not being
taught by these programs, then,
that we need, right? And what
they need the most out of
anything, regardless of what
whether they're good academy or
not. They need practical
projects to learn from you need,
like you have to do the thing.
It like we live in a world where
you can learn to be an expert
woodworker on YouTube. Yeah,
it's not but unless you actually
do the woodworking he won't give
it. So you can learn to be an
expert, you can know all the
things you can collect all the
knowledge. Yeah, but you have to
do it. And that's that
everything. It's the builder to
learn it approach is what we we
think, is the way of the future.
Audrow Nash: Definitely. Yeah, I
had a professor, at some point
that we used to say something
like I can watch all the golf on
TV, but it doesn't make me any
better at golf, this kind of
thing. Same with watching all
the woodworking videos,
Dan O'Mara: and all the college
courses and all this to all of
the lectures in the world of all
the things but it's not going to
make you an expert in those
things. The only way you get to
be good at these things is
actually just doing and yeah, in
failing out of it been learning.
Oh, totally. You know, all of
that part of the process?
Audrow Nash: Yeah, I think it's
really important to me to try to
build something and then by
trying to build it, you see the
limitations, you see where it's
difficult, you see why you can't
do the first thing you wanted to
do immediately. And then you
start to think creatively and
learn the skills to keep
growing. It's a wonderful check
on reality or on yourself with
reality. So just cutting their
teeth on actual projects. It
sounds like a wonderful thing
for your students. Were so you
mentioned expansion, like
looking at different areas. Can
you tell me a bit about your
expansion plans.
Dan O'Mara: So right now we are
looking to expand more circuit
launch locations, expand more
labs for Mechlabs, kind of
we've the we're in the middle of
a funding round that will allow
us to to be able to do that. Of
course a lot of because we are
dealing with space, there's a
lot of like kind of long term
planning that has to happen when
you open spaces and everything
else. So we are exploring a lot
of things from working with
governments to be able to
provide economic centers of
innovation. And a lot of you
know, we're looking at the
venture model, we're looking at
a lot of different stuff to to
go. And so there will be, you
know, big things in the future
that we're having, but we're not
quite sure. And so right now, if
you are interested in being part
of that future, we'd love to
talk to you as an investor or
student or an entrepreneur or
roboticist. But at the at the
moment, we, you know, it's, it's
a giant experiment, even to us,
we got to figure out what will
work and where we can, can
provide value and create the
change that we want to want to
make.
Audrow Nash: Let's see. So if
people are interested, how
should they follow up? Or what
would the what would the good
approach be?
Dan O'Mara: Yeah, if you're
interested in becoming like an
entrepreneur in our in our bay
area, Oakland facility, circuit
launch.com, as we open up other
facilities, hopefully that will
be, you know, that will also be
the website until we have them.
Right now. It's just the Oakland
facility. And if you are
interested in learning, learning
robotics, or you know, building
some of these cool things, mech
labs.ai is the best way to come
and, and find us and get in
contact, see what what projects
are there and, and build. We've
got some some really fun stuff
up on the on the horizon.
Audrow Nash: All right. Well,
that's all we have time for.
Thank you, Dan. Thank you. All
right. Hi, everyone. Thanks for
listening to this conversation
with Dan O'Meara. Thank you
again to our founding sponsor,
open robotics. See you next
time.