Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Helen Greiner,
who is the CEO of Tertill. Tertill
makes a solar powered robot
wieder for home vegetable
gardens. And you see this Tertill
robot, you might think of the
robot vacuum cleaner the Roomba
by iRobot. This comparison makes
sense. And funny enough, they
were both made by some of the
same people, Helen included.
What I think is beautiful about
the Roomba, and this robot the
Tertill is that it is so
relatively simple, yet provides
real value. Vacuuming under the
bed is a pain. And I don't have
much experience with weeding,
but weeding sounds awful. And
both of these products are for
the consumer market, meaning
that they have to be inexpensive
enough that many people can
afford them. The iRobot Roomba
was one of the first successful
consumer robots, and it grew the
consumer robotics space, which
benefited all of us in robotics,
from making investment easier to
come by to parts being cheaper
to showing people that robots
aren't all Terminator robots. As
Helen says before this
interview, and has been said
before on this podcast, a rising
tide lifts all boats. I look
forward to seeing how the Tertill
does in the future. And if I
start a garden, I'll probably
get one. I'm Audrow Nash. This
is the sense think act podcast.
If you like this interview,
please consider subscribing. A
big thank you to our founding
sponsor open robotics. And now,
here's my interview with Helen
Greiner. Would you introduce
yourself? Hi, I'm
Helen Greiner: Helen gainer. And
I'm a robot enthusiast.
Audrow Nash: Now, we're gonna be
talking mostly about Tertill. But
I'd love to start, like for
context to talk about your whole
path in robotics.
Helen Greiner: Oh, that's a long
way. A long time.
Audrow Nash: You want to just
tell me like, I mean, maybe at a
high level from grad school, and
then you were involved with
iRobot?
Helen Greiner: Well, it started
back when I was 11. And I saw
Star Wars and fell in love with
auto detail and odd to think,
you know, he wasn't just a
machine, right? He was a
character. He had an agenda. He
saved the universe. He had a
personality, a lot of expression
with his bleeps and bloops. And,
you know, since that time, I've
always wanted to make things
that are more than machines. And
so I went to MIT to learn how.
And it turns out, I learned a
lot of great engineering there,
but they didn't really know how
to build robots for the real
world. And so right after grad
school, I was in grad school at
MIT, in computer science,
although my undergraduates
mechanical and accepted to the
Ph. D. program, but instead
decided to cofound iRobot
corporation with vide books and
Cullen angle.
Audrow Nash: And then, so you
will What did you do at iRobot?
So you were designing the robot
I believe. Original vacuum
cleaner robots.
Helen Greiner: Now, way back
when way back when, when the
company first found it. All of
us myself lied and con, we're
actually designing the robots
and building them and
fabricating them and everything
about the robots. But though,
you know, we started iRobot in
1990. It wasn't until, like, 98,
we started seriously working on
the Roomba and not until 2002.
We put it on the market. So
there's a lot of history before
that. Oh, we are, you know, the
longest overnight success.
People hadn't heard about us
until the bomba. But you know,
there's a whole lot of robots
that we were building. Before
eventually military
Audrow Nash: in nature. It was
like we did we did
Helen Greiner: robots for so
many different industries. We
did a robot for oil and gas
industry doing downhole
inspections, plug patch
perforate stuff. We had robots
that large cleaning robots, we
had robots that were in a museum
that was robots that we sold to
research labs. We get a toy
robot, a baby doll robot with
Hasbro. Just so many different
robots. But it wasn't until we
put robots on the market under
our brand that we were you know
that we had any success.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. So it
was was it kind of like you were
contracts Acting around like
people would want robots or
you'd see it opportunities.
Helen Greiner: Yeah, it was it
was kind of like any robot for
money usually would get the
large company to bring the
dollars. And you know, we, I, we
believe the marketing and the
the market savvy, and we were
doing the technology and the
creativity and the innovation
and the robots. And you know, it
sounds good on paper. But what
usually happened was the
industries work at glacial
paces. And the person who was
advocate either move to another
position or another company, and
then you almost had to start the
sales pitch, again, from the or
from the beginning. Yeah. So I
don't think we had enough top
level buy in at the companies to
make it successful. And in some
cases, the robot technology was
competing with the status quo of
how the the existing product
lines. So you know, a larger
company wouldn't have that much
incentive to, you know, push it
forward.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. And
then how did it how did you go
towards the Roomba with us
Helen Greiner: like? Well, let's
see, our first employee at
iRobot was Joe Jones, Joe had
been thinking about some of the
things while he was at MIT, and
that Maxwell was wide Brooks's
behavioral control algorithms,
because, you know, we really
didn't have a lot of resources
to put on these smaller robots.
So we couldn't have, you know,
the kinds of processing and the
kinds of capabilities that some
of the robots have today, even
the Roomba. So, Joe wrote a
white paper in I think, you
know, maybe 9097, or 98, saying,
you know, hey, we're building
these large cleaning lots, we're
building all these larger
robots. But really, we should do
the simplest possible thing
first, and he spelled out,
small, low bought five point
about $200. Needs to be fully
automated use the simplest
possible senses rather than, you
know, the most capable senses.
And, you know, get something out
there pretty quickly. And we,
you know, it sounded like a good
idea to everybody. So it was
funded with very small amounts
of money, because we didn't have
a lot of money. And, you know,
it kept building prototypes of
it, Joe and the team, and they,
you know, got, you know, we
could never see a reason why it
wouldn't work. And we fully
expected when we started it to
see a reason why there's one
component missing, like, it's
not a product. Yep. There was
another robot vacuum. On the
market. We didn't know that much
about it at the time, I left on
that Sandborn, but it was many
1000s of dollars. Us, it doesn't
sound very high tech today, but
use Sona technology, but it made
it very expensive. And I think
that when a new concept is new,
it has to be reasonably
inexpensive for people to take
that jump. So Moonves might sell
sometimes for, you know, $1,000
today, but when you're a new
company, with a new band in a
very new area, it's important
that it's, you know, it's a kind
of product, you can take your
wallet out and say, Oh, I'll
take a risk on that.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, definitely.
And there's a lot of people that
are willing to do that, because
maybe they're way less that are
willing to take the risk and
like $1,000, robot vacuum
cleaner versus a $200. One.
Okay, and then where
Helen Greiner: we got, we got
the robot on the market, the,
the Roomba, we still doing the
robots for the military. And
that actually, we got them both
on the market in 2002. The
robots in the military got moved
up because of the war efforts
and Operation Enduring Freedom
in Afghanistan, and then soon
after evac, they probably would
have stayed as military research
for a while. But there was this
Driving driving need for bomb
disposal robots, and we were
like, they're with the
capability that they needed. And
at the same time, we put the
limbo on the market and you
know, starting to get some
consumer success. And so these
companies never would have had
these two disparate areas if one
had happened first, right,
because all the resources would
have been thrown at that one,
just because they were
successful together. And you
know, it really helped us
because I can tell you a lot of
the investors didn't believe in
the consumer robot market until
we had it on the market. And it
was successful.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So that the
investors were or was it like
you were funding the efforts
with the military robots. And
that allowed you to bootstrap
the concern?
Helen Greiner: We were we were
paying for infrastructure with
the military contracts, because
we have large contracts as
research contracts as well as
having built up, you know, so
the infrastructure was being
paid for, like, you know, the
offices and that we had people
on staff to a very capable
roboticist because we had the
ability to pay for them. But we
didn't really raise investment
capital until eight years in in
1998. That's when we started.
And by 2005, when we took it
public, it you know, we'd raised
a total of 38 million, which is
peanuts today, that's like
seeing these, you know, a OB
today.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Okay. And
then you raise the capital, and
then that lets you scale so you
could grow the consumer market
for the room, or the consumer
side of the business for the
room.
Helen Greiner: At the same time,
though, you know, after we went
public, the military side was
going strong too. But
eventually, after I left in
2008, they did spend the
military stuff out into a
company called andeavor, which
was purchased by FLIR for like
over $300 million. And then,
that was purchased actually was
all purchased by Teledyne. So
the technology still exists, the
robots don't exist, a lot of the
same people are working on them,
but it's no longer a robot.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. What is
your so between 1998 and 2008?
Or so when you left? iRobot?
What were you primarily involved
Helen Greiner: in? Everything I
was, you know, going on time, I
was president chairman, and, you
know, everything from sales to
media to taking it public and
investment. Acquisitions as you
know, everything.
Audrow Nash: Mm hmm. And then
how did you decide to go to sci
fi work? So that was the next
step? Right.
Helen Greiner: Yeah. Well, I was
looking at what next? And, you
know, being chairman of a
company is kind of the best job
actually, what it really is,
because it's a gotcha what I was
at Iowa, but because you have,
you know, you get to do a lot of
interesting things. But you're
not, you know, you don't have
all that operational
responsibility. But it's not the
best job when you're 40 years
old, which is what I was. So I
think that I really, when I
looked at what I really liked, I
liked it when the Roomba and
pack bought the military robots,
were first being developed the
innovation side when you're
getting something the likes of
which people haven't seen
before, after. And so that's why
I want to do it again. And I saw
that the drone space was the
place to do it. And
Audrow Nash: how did you see it
was the space to do it? And what
made
Helen Greiner: it was an
untapped market. You know, when
I look at drones, it's like, a
magic technology that solves a
lot of the problem. You know, I
think it will guild guild fat
who was adopted now at Toyota
research, I think he he's the
one who first said, The problem
with ground robots is to ground
all this stuff on the ground,
right? Especially when you take
it out outdoors, and even
indoors with the Roomba. You
know, there's a lot of pollen
you have to face and a lot of
recognition, you know, a lot of
knowing what it is and getting
around it. And negotiation was a
drone, you could just fly right
over it. Right? And you know,
free space is actually easy.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Okay, so you
saw that there was potential
here because it solves a lot of
existing robotics challenges. So
you could probably do new and
interesting things. But then how
sci fi works? And actually,
would you kind of speak to the
premise of the company?
Helen Greiner: Well, the Sci Fi
works. The idea we had
originally was at the time, a
little less so now, but at the
time, the battery technology
wasn't there. So the drones
would only run a short amount of
time and not enough any real
types of military missions or
law enforcement missions. So or
even, you know, long term
communication missions. So we
had some technology to make a
tethered drone. And we were, you
know, the first ones out there
with a drone that you could stay
stays up in the air for, you
know, weeks at a time. So you
put it up on a tether, and you
put it up to you know, put it up
to 300 feet in the air and it
just flies all the time. And
then you have that station where
you can get eyes on something or
you can do communications
Audrow Nash: So the idea Well, I
Helen Greiner: never I never
envisioned that the only thing
that company would do, but I
wanted some differentiated
technology to go in because
there were some drugs on the
market already.
Audrow Nash: So the idea was,
you'd have a cable that goes to
the drone, and that cable would
send power. And you could also
probably do things like maybe
some of the control, like the
brains of it, maybe I don't
know, if you want that on
Helen Greiner: putting the veins
oil on the robot, so you send it
up, and it just stays the or,
you know, autonomously. And you
know, what, that's a little bit
turnkey today. But at the time,
we were doing it, it wasn't so
much. We are, uh, you know, that
wasn't the the only tightness of
company it was a starting point.
And so we want some good
military, you know, multimillion
dollar contracts about that. We
were working on getting it into
an acquisition program. And I
can tell you, there are many
companies building tele drones
today. So it was sci fi wasn't
successful, but the concept was
successful. And it's in pretty
hot demand for the familiarity
application applications because
of the capabilities to do both
surveillance. You know, I
getting eyes on 24/7. And also,
communications videos work a lot
better when you put them up
high. The effects of terrible on
the transmissions,
Audrow Nash: yeah, but it seems
to me like a really good way to
bootstrap infrastructure. Like
if you need to set up quickly,
it's like, oh, we have a
security camera that's deployed
there through a drone, it's kind
of thing or boost your radio up
and put it real high. Like
that's very nice. Very clever.
Okay. And so you said, so a few
things were interesting there
that you said. So first, you had
preparing it for acquisition?
Does it mean you kind of created
the company with the intent of
it being bought?
Helen Greiner: Oh, no, I am
sorry, I meant in that context,
I meant military acquisitions,
making sure that you're in the
palm cycle in the military
budgeting cycle. So that money
exists when you're ready with
the technology and prototype.
Yeah, and at the same time,
getting to a point where we got
it deployed, we did get it
deployed with a Rapid Equipping
Force and will then be used in
Syria and Iraq, very
successfully by a special
forces.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. I mean,
that feels really good to
positively impact our troops and
it both iRobot and and sci fi
works. It's like you were
contributing to some of the
difficult situations,
Helen Greiner: it doesn't
matter. Some sci fi, someone
came up for Special Forces.
Perfect came up at a conference
and said, Hey, I heard that
thing is out there saving saving
lives. So you couldn't tell us
much about the missions, of
course, but actually, they did
tell us I was having great
effect. And the same thing that
I wrote about once. You know,
once I was speaking at the War
College, and I was between two,
you know, three star general, my
vide and a four star general on
my left, and I assumed everyone
would want to go speak to them
after the conference, but a lot
of the soldiers came up to me
and one guy, remember, he shook
my hand and said, I want to give
you my coin because this pack
bought saved 11 Guys on one
mission, and you know, that was
really rewarding can be the
Pentagon actually did a study
and the pack blood should have
been credited at that time, even
more today. But at that time,
they've been credited with
saving the lives of hundreds of
soldiers and 1000s of civilians.
Audrow Nash: Wow, that's
absolutely nuts. It feels like
it's kind of like, it's amazing.
And it's probably hard to wrap
your head around, like the
abstract notion of saving lives
for this kind of thing. But I
it's just wonderful. Like, what
a crazy thing.
Helen Greiner: Now, it is
wonderful.
Audrow Nash: And then so you
said that sci fi works wasn't
successful, in your opinion, or
this kind of thing. Oh, we I,
Helen Greiner: I live in the we
had a difference of opinion with
the investors that I bought on
in the direction. And at that
time, I decided, you know, the
person who first deployed the
PAC bots over in Afghanistan, he
asked me to come in and join, he
became the acquisition
executive, that's the person who
runs the, you know, the, you
know, multi billion dollar
acquisition flows on all of them
for the OMA and he wanted me to
come on and be his special robot
advisor. So I decided to take
that opportunity. Because I
didn't agree with the direction
of cycline.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, that must be
frustrating. I've heard many,
many people that I've talked to
that I started robotics
companies where the investors
wanted to go one way and the
founders want to go what another
way? It's a very frustrating
spot. Right? Right. Uh huh.
Helen Greiner: But at some
point, you got to say, you know,
they have that opinion. They're
gonna pick on that The people
and if those people make it
happen, the company's gonna be
successful. If they don't, it
won't. And I can tell you this
one was really well set up to be
successful because there's a
really hot demand for the
technology.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, and then so
but it just wasn't where you
were personally interested in
taking it. And then this other
opportunity popped up to advise
on government purchases of
robots, right?
Helen Greiner: The government
research and development of
robots AI and machine machine
learning.
Audrow Nash: That's super cool.
So that was, so I got to
Helen Greiner: work in the
Pentagon for two years. Which
was great. I mean, I, you know,
I stayed in Boston, where I
reside, but we went down,
though, every few weeks to spend
days down there. And, you know,
my office was the Pentagon?
Audrow Nash: That's so crazy.
Yeah. How was that? Like? I
don't I don't know much about
it, or what would be involved?
Like, what? I don't know, how
was it?
Helen Greiner: Well, after
selling, you know, over a
billion dollars worth of stuff
to military, right, it was
interesting to be on the other
side of the table, and see some
of the, you know, constraints
they're under, right? I mean,
there's a lot of hard working,
patriotic, very, very good
people, and you say, why can't
they just do this? And, you
know, sometimes there's a lot of
reasons that they just can't do
that, you know, mostly, you
know, it's against the law.
Audrow Nash: So, you know, give
me a specific example.
Helen Greiner: Well, you know,
even if they want the
technology, it has to go out for
competitive bid, and you have to
have the evaluation criteria,
and you have to, you know, go
through the process, because
someone will complain like that,
Congressman, and then there'll
be a bit dispute, and it's
better, especially when you're
dealing with billions of dollars
to get the program right from
the beginning. So you don't have
to, you know, lose it, you know,
later on, because the, the, the
soldiers need this equipment,
right. So, sometimes, you know,
even if it's a really, really
good product, and you know, it's
going to be the winner, you
really have to go through the,
you know, the process.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. either.
Yeah. So that's interesting,
it's interesting to do that,
that's very different than like
how startups might operate, or
this kind of thing, because you
don't have the implications.
Like the voters and all of this,
if it goes badly, you just like,
do something and fail and try
and whatever. It's interesting
to be on the other perspective.
Did you? I don't know, like,
any. Like, I was very impressed.
So I talked to a previous
episode, Tim Chang, from DARPA,
about the sub D challenge. And I
was really impressed with that.
The like, it seems like a very
pragmatic approach in robotics,
to these hard challenges, and
I'm trying to start these
communities around around this
area, I should
Helen Greiner: say, DARPA does
have a little more leeway,
because of the way it's set up
to be able to work with
universities, and, you know, get
those great new ideas into the
military. But when you get to a,
you know, a knowledge
acquisition program, it has to
be, you know, go through a
process.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, so were you
kind of responsible for advising
these large purchases, or I
wasn't funding a process or
Helen Greiner: I was brought in
to give an honest opinion on the
state of the robot technology.
And I didn't take a role in any
particular acquisition program.
But I think people kind of
thought of me as a trusted
adviser, and I can't talk too
much about it. But I think I
really did have a great impact
and getting some of the, the
drone and the ground vehicle
programs in the right direction.
Audrow Nash: And how did how did
that end? So was it just the end
of the term? You have a two year
term? Or how does it
Helen Greiner: Yes, I I actually
went until my first appointment
and out and they would have had
me come back, but especially
with COVID. Like, I couldn't
even fly down to the Pentagon
anymore. And, you know, I, I was
at the point where I felt that
I'm doing something else to push
the robot field further would be
what I most want to do. I see.
Audrow Nash: Okay, and so now
this comes to Tertill, right.
That's the next jump. Okay, now,
tell me a bit about Tertill. Just
the set up in the premise and
everything.
Helen Greiner: Okay, so Tertill
is a company that builds a
weeding robot. It was invented
by the gentleman that I
mentioned, Joe Jones, who was
invented the Roomba when he was
I know but and he, him and Lloyd
McKee, again, he they were out
of they came out of harvest
automation, which was an
agricultural company. And once
they had finished with that,
they decided that they wanted to
be back in the consumer game.
And, you know, Joe, we're
thinking about all the different
applications that have robot
potential and weeding, you know,
is really at the top of a lot of
people's lists those jobs that
are just tedious and hard, and,
you know, you're in the hot sun.
And it's a job that, you know,
you do once in a while, you
know, find somebody who likes
it, right? Just like you're
fine. Believe it or not, you
find people that do like
vacuuming. There's always people
like that. But, you know, it's,
you know, a lot of people like
it, but they like it on their
schedule, like not when it has
to be done. So Joe, thinking
about the problem, he looked for
a robotic solution, because, you
know, we believe a Tertill that
an AI robot that you don't have
to do things exactly like a
human does. In fact, to be more
powerful, you don't really want
to do things exactly like a
human, you want to do them. You
want to set up the past, so a
robot can succeed. So an example
is, you know, maybe Roomba can't
do everything that an upright
vacuum does. But it should does
well going on to the beds.
Something that an upright vacuum
doesn't do well, doing under the
couches and the robotic
applications, it doesn't matter
how long it's on the you know,
covering the whole space, and
now with the latest technology
generations, ensuring that the
space is covered. So you know,
when you think about it in robot
terms, instead of in human
terms. So one way to do the
weeding to get back to total,
one way to do the weeding would
be you know, you have a fully
dexterous manipulator and you,
you know, you use your AI vision
system with lots of machine
intelligence, and you say that's
a weed, and then you come down
and you, you know, you have your
dexterity to go down and grab
the wheat and pull it up. And
then you have to grab it and
pull up the, you know, the
roots. Or you use events, lasers
or something like pesticides.
And in thinking about that,
that's a long way, right?
Because that plant has already
sunk nutrients out of the soil,
you have a disposal problem with
the plant. And you know, quite
frankly, powerful lasers are
expensive and pesticides.
Audrow Nash: Lasers. Yeah,
Helen Greiner: we always
consider lasers, because you
know, having a robot with
lasers, it's just inherently
cool. But may not be the most
practical approach. So what was
built instead was a robot that
prevents weeds from ever
growing. So with a scrubbing,
scrubbing wheels, it keeps seeds
from germinating. And with a
spinning weedwacker. If one does
pop its head up, off with it.
And original Loomba navigation
strategy, it negotiates through
the garden and covers the entire
area using local intelligence.
But it's got some inventions on
it. It's got capacitive senses
that sense the plants, and it's
got a very innovative pump
sensor that uses the
accelerometers.
Audrow Nash: So it actually,
would you just for our listeners
who are only listening, would
you describe it? Describe Tertill
a bit.
Helen Greiner: This is a small,
round green robot, it's about
eight and a quarter inches wide
and about maybe four inches
tall. And it's it's got wheels
that have cleats on them. Four
wheels that are a camford with
cleats on them that makes a
very,
Audrow Nash: you know, just at
an angle that 45 degrees. Yeah,
tilted so that they kind of like
scrape the Earth. Yes. And in
Helen Greiner: fact, we build a
not very good die system because
we want to be scraping the earth
when we turn rather than lightly
travel. Like many robot
applications.
Audrow Nash: That's so funny. So
you turn all the wheels
Helen Greiner: I think they skid
steer it's really the it's
really the combination effects
of scrubbing and then the weed
whacker that makes it do such a
good job.
Audrow Nash: So then in the
middle of the robot, so you have
the wheels and then in the
inside of the wheels in the
center of the robot there's a
little tiny spinning thing that
has like a wire like a weed
whacker.
Helen Greiner: Yes. It's not
just like a weed whacker. It is.
Yeah. This is the only thing
Part of the robot that that you
have to change, so maybe three
times a year, you have to pull
it out, within a, just do it
like that and you push it a new
one because it does wear out
when it hits locks and other
things in the garden. It does
have a little USB port here that
whoops, does have a little USB
port here that if you take this
off, you can see a little mini
den, I think it is where you can
plug it in and charger. But the
great thing about this robot is
you never have to, because it's
got a solar cell on the top. So
you're putting your garden at
the beginning of the growing
season, and you leave it there
and every day when the sun comes
out, it charges up when it gets
down to you know, when it was
when it goes out and weeds when
it gets down to something like
70% battery, and these all
changeable numbers, but 70%
battery, it stops weeding, and
it charges again, and then when
it gets to a certain number,
it'll come back out and do the
do the weeding and then when it
gets down. And that way, we
really use the batteries really
lightly. So it lasts for years.
You know you're using them so,
so nicely. And it makes it run
throughout the day. So if it's,
you know, if it's cloudy in the
in the morning light, it'll, you
know, keep running in the
afternoon, it also has some very
intelligent algorithms. So I'll
go sit at the sunlight, rather
than under a tomato bush. So
it's really a very intelligent
little robot that lives in your
garden runs on sunshine, and
does the weeding so you don't
have to
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So it
drives you basically set it in
your garden, and just leave it
and then what it's going to do
is charge period charge with the
sun and go knock out some weeds
when it drives around for a
small period of time each day,
Helen Greiner: individually
throughout the day, so it
doesn't just come out once it
comes out a few times every day
and does the job.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And so how
much ground can this little
robot cover?
Helen Greiner: About 200 square
feet of a garden. So that's
about you know, an average size
in ground garden. Some people
have smaller ones these days
with a you know a vase bed but
you know, if you're putting in a
garden you you know you have to
so it covers a reasonable sized
garden.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And it
detects the weeds to kill
because they're small enough to
drive over.
Helen Greiner: Well, it doesn't
really detect the weeds or kill
it prevents weeds from ever
growing. What we have to do is
protect the plants. Now, you
know, as I mentioned that
capacitive sensors are very good
and the accelerometer based bump
sensor is very good. But if
something's less than four
inches, it will consider it a
weed. So we do what all good
roboticists do to make robots
work and that's cheap. The way
we cheat is if you put a seed
in, yeah, well, I am what what
I'm holding is a thin wire
that's molded into a curved
shape that you can put a round
put around a seed that you
planted a small seedling that
you plant by just pushing it
into the ground. If you plant a
row of carrots, for example, we
have a row God and you just push
this these along the row so the
robot can't get to your carrot
seedlings. And once the plants
four inches tall you you can
take these out or leave them in
and it's really your choice to
take them out. You could just be
used them.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Okay, so
when it's driving around, does
that mean that it's what weed
whacker is always going? So like
Does it smell plants? Or does
it?
Helen Greiner: It can sense the
plants, we've discovered that
having a duty cycle does
actually help the performance so
we can send so we can just have
a duty cycle just Yeah. And get
them all. Gotcha. It doesn't
take that much. Damage power,
especially when it's not hitting
anything.
Audrow Nash: Oh, you just keep
it spinning. Yeah.
Helen Greiner: We don't just
keep making it's got a duty
cycle.
Audrow Nash: What do you mean
exactly by the duty cycle? It's
on for a little bit.
Helen Greiner: It's gone for a
little bit. It goes off? Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Oh, is it? Okay, so
it's base. It's like almost like
it's full power than offer a
little bit than full power than
offer a little bit while it's
driving. So it's
Helen Greiner: yeah, you need to
have a weed whacker. You need to
have them spinning like a very
high speed weed whacker. Right.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And then,
so what what is what exactly is
it sensing in the environment?
So you mentioned that it can
move into the sun, if it's in
the shade.
Helen Greiner: That with its
solar power system light with a
solar panel, so
Audrow Nash: it's going to drive
on till it reaches some sun kind
of thing, or how does it work?
Helen Greiner: It? Yeah, it just
doesn't stop. If it's too shady,
it keeps going for a while and
it you know, it looks at the
average reading over time and
goes back to, you know, web it,
it looks a bit if you know,
wants to know, make sure there
is some sun before it starts
looking for sun. So yeah, if you
have an average eating and, you
know, none of these things, you
know, these things are tuneable.
So we've done the best job we
can, you know, tuning them that
we that, you know, that we could
do, but they are things that we
can vary if we need to at any
time.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Okay. So I am
imagining that this takes a lot
of lessons from the Roomba. So
like, one thing that was very
obvious to me as a like Roomba
tie back, is that you have the
one button. So like with the
Roomba, I have heard that it's
like you just have the one
button to start it. And this
Yeah, it has the one button as
well push it. And that just goes
and you don't have to worry
about
Helen Greiner: it didn't always
have one button, right? That was
a lesson learned. We had three
buttons, and they were labeled
S, M and L. So small, medium and
large. And we get questions all
the time. What's a small room?
What's a medium? What's a large
room, so then we started putting
numbers out there, then people
are really confused because they
don't know the area. And so it
was a little it'd be much better
to have one button. You know,
now they say clean on it. Right?
So that's what you want to do
you want to clean you press one
button. And the on off switch
the first ones we had on the
room, but were labeled zero and
one. So one is one is on and
zero is off. But you know,
people would say well, I put it
on. Oh, isn't that on? And it
was not obvious to most people.
40 year old
Audrow Nash: white men. That's
so funny.
Helen Greiner: Well, it's kind
of funny that we would do that.
Like, yes.
Audrow Nash: I mean as a
roboticist. Like, it's like, oh,
yeah, I got it. Like, yeah, I
know what you're going for. It's
like all you but it's not for
all of the other anyone who's a
general consumer, I see what
they mean with zero seems like
Oh, fraud. Like, it's totally
it's off to so.
Helen Greiner: Yeah. Yeah,
that's what the confusion was
like, why? Well, what about off?
Oh, so we designed it with one
button and the one button. You
know, it's, it's something that
people can understand, like, you
put it in the garden, you press
a button, and it stays there.
And it's on and it's running in
the garden for the rest of the,
for the growing season.
Audrow Nash: And then so, so the
operation of this as you just
put it there, you push a button,
and then you walk away until
winter, I suppose
Helen Greiner: that would be
ideal. That would be ideal. But
in reality, because we live in
reality. Mine and even though I
made my space pretty. I mean, I
am a little bit of a lazy
gardener. So my place isn't
really nice. And you know,
beautifully make do anything
like that,
Audrow Nash: but a good
roboticist would
Helen Greiner: if I had to free
it a few times during the year,
like it would get stuck, and I
would give it a kick. But that's
a few times as opposed to every
day, you never have to charge
it. You do have to replace the
weed whackers every, you know,
every few weeks, but apart from
that, you know you're good to go
for the season. So it really is,
I'd say one of the most if not
the most autonomous robot out
there because it's solar
powered. You don't have to
charge it. And it just stays
there and does the job for you.
Like a little creature living in
your garden? Like a Tertill?
Yeah, like a kettle?
Audrow Nash: Huh? Yeah, I see.
And so you mentioned that the
control style or the control
scheme is a bit like the
original Roomba. Does that mean
it's gonna just drive around
randomly? And then eventually,
like in the limit, it will have
covered the whole garden
Helen Greiner: space Yes,
although it's never been manned.
And the moon does whenever
random a us you know, local
intelligence based on the the,
you know, the local sense of
meetings, to negotiate along
walls about obstacles and to try
and cover you know, an area and
then move to the next area. So
neither you know, the original
room has went random and this
one's not random. We don't have
a full positioning system yet.
And you do have to put a
boundary around the area where
it's working like there was a
luxury in the house that the
walls originally that pretty
much we had a boundary because
of the walls. Turns out most
vegetable gardeners have a
boundary or they don't mind
putting one in. You can take a
piece of wood you can take the
VO Gods the pieces of metal that
it comes with you can buy at
stripping a metal one from From
Home Depot or Amazon, you know,
there's a lot of easy solutions
for it. But it is one of the
reasons why we don't advertise
it for landscape beds, because
it's a little tricky to explain
where it can and it can't work.
And, you know, you do have to
have a boundary of bounded and
some landscape bed, that's fine,
I've got one in a landscape bed
in the front of my house. And
it's wonderful, I don't have to
weed it. It's amazing. What I
didn't mind having, you know,
when you have, like, you know,
you know, some beautiful shrubs,
I have some bamboo in a, you
know, with a bamboo belly around
that most people can't stop
bamboo from growing, but my
bamboo isn't going so everything
else was going in that bed. So I
put, I put a barrier around the
where the bamboo Spedding farm
and I'm giving it a chance to go
in. I also put one on my gravel
last year, you know, got pea
gravel. And we can't advertise
for that either. Because at the
end of the season, I'd look
down, there'd be some little
portly plants growing that had
established a boot structure. So
that type of weeding we do to
venting, which doesn't quite
work. But where I didn't have
the Tertill weeds were like,
literally up to my shoulder,
like up to my shoulder. Like
it's crazy. What was how fast
the things could grow in a
growing season if you never take
care of it. So for me, you know,
it works great. If you don't
mind a few little leaves in your
in your gravel. But I you know,
advertising it for that would be
would be hard. But we have a lot
of users who use them on on
landscape beds, because they
figured it out for themselves
that I meet the criterion. And
so we can have it running. And
it's not a problem. You know,
you got to have your plan set of
space, at least about a foot
apart. You have to have not too
much. Exactly, yeah, yeah. So
the robot can go right between
them. You want to have not too,
not too much undulations a
barrier around it. And it
doesn't work on really chunky
mulch, like you know, a lot of
landscape beds are mowed. And
that prevents weeds. I put
motion fresh and even last year,
about a month later, I got weeds
all over. So it's really chunky
motion. It won't work. But I
have it working on both beds
that have final motion. It works
fine.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So what
have been some of the biggest
challenges with this robot it?
I'm imagining weatherproofing it
it's interesting to have the
small set of sensors. I don't
know.
Helen Greiner: Well, I actually
jumped into this. After they
kick started it, and I bought
one on the Kickstarter. So I can
do this. Because my vote because
you know, Joe started the
company and I knew him and some
of the other guys and of course,
I'm gonna support the
Kickstarter. I, they delivered
it. And I you know, I put it in
the garden. And I think, you
know, it worked for a little bit
then it stopped working. And I
didn't care because it was a
Kickstarter, right. And it's a
robot and I buy lots of robots
on Kickstarter. And quite
frankly, I like that. Oh, yeah.
Yeah, anyone could tell me a
robot on Kickstarter. Because I
want robots to exist. I want
more robots to exist. Yeah. So
everyone should always support
the small robot companies just
you know, get the robots try
them out like that. So many
people said that to me about
Roomba. Like I got one of the
early ones and look at the
generation they have. It's like,
no, no, that's 10 years in. You
need to get to these companies
when the first kick started when
they're, you know, just have it
on the market for a few years.
But I was anyway, I got the
robot on the Kickstarter, but it
stopped working. And I didn't
really care. So but they
actually came over, took a look
at it and replaced it. And I
then I put it in my vegetable
gardens. And I was actually
amazed that it worked. It was
like night and day, right? It
was like instead of going to my
garden, and it was a weedy mess,
because I you know I'm not one
of those people who does it
every week, you know, on time.
Instead of going there with my
daughter and you know, I get
distracted because I don't like
the weeds in it, you know,
instead we can go and garden
together right? Instead of you
know, instead of it being a
chore it's like a more fun
experience about growing your
own food. So I really loved it
and they I was looking around of
what to do after the you know,
after the military appointment
and you know, I called them up
because I you know my mind I was
thinking about outdoor robotics
because you know, I'm not going
to go into us right because we
will visit inside I was
thinking, Hey, I see the robot
lawnmowers taking off, you know,
I've got a Tertill meeting my
goal. And that might be another
space that you don't they've
maybe thought about that and not
pursuing and I could take that
and learn from them. And
instead, they invited me to come
on and be CEO.
Audrow Nash: Wow. Gotcha.
Awesome. And so how long? How
long have you been with them now
as CEO?
Helen Greiner: Um, it's been
probably, it's been over a year
now.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. What? So
were actually like a little bit
about the company. How large are
you guys?
Helen Greiner: Well, we don't
really disclose that because,
you know, we, you kind of keep
it to yourself until it's
something to really brag about.
But we're a small team. We're
very agile. We have the robot on
the market on our Shopify site,
we have it on at Amazon, we've
just released a new product did
make also makes gardening
easier. It's not a robot, but it
does. You know, it is it shares
the app with the the Tertill.
Okay, you know, so this is the
space that I love when a small
team can get stuff going quickly
and get, you know, get it out on
the market.
Audrow Nash: It does seem like
the most fun part. To me
anyways, the whole growing
everything. Very fun. So then
you guys are what kind of things
have you been? So since you've
been CEO? What kinds of things
have you been helping the
direction of the company move
towards?
Helen Greiner: Oh, well, I'm
just switching from, you know, a
technology band to a more
lifestyle brand. Getting the
word out more. You know, we got
on This Old House last last year
in USA Today. Wall Street
Journal. actually practicing
filming for an HSN slot will be
on Metro Bay on the 16th. So
there's a close $4 million
funding round last year. So
just, you know, trying to take
it from where it was, which was
great to
Audrow Nash: have more consumer
facing. Yeah, more
Helen Greiner: consumer facing
and more. Welfare.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, that's an
awesome thing. I mean, it just
seems like from my perspective,
like, the idea of pulling weeds
in a garden is like, I don't
know, because you're right,
like, like, I'm not going to be
diligent about it every week or
whatever. So this kind of thing,
it seems like a really nice use
of a simple robotics solution.
Like it can just drive around
mow down the big weeds, you can
like garden around your plants,
maybe if they go really close to
your existing plants, but it's I
don't know just makes the work.
It does like 80% of the work
kind of thing,
Helen Greiner: right? Yeah, I
mean, I still had some weeds
around the very edge of my going
like I could have ignored them
you know, sometimes I choose to
pull them out but it's a choice
like not not something you have
to go and spend a lot of time
doing.
Audrow Nash: And you don't have
like this giant like I don't
know field or bush of garden
that like you can't get to
anything and this kind of thing
because this is getting to all
those plants that grow super
fast, very early, and then you
don't have to deal with them.
Helen Greiner: Right? And it
goes to our you know you know,
our mission is to make gardening
easier for people but why do we
want to do that? So more people
take it up a lot of people took
it up in the pandemic by the way
people you know, studies say
like 17 million more people took
up gardening so great timing for
it.
Audrow Nash: But
Helen Greiner: you know, we'd
like to encourage even more like
because what's more healthy for
the planet shipping it in, you
know, sometimes from another
country or, you know, wasting
all that transportation all that
pollution. Big Ag has a lot of
pesticides used out goods for
pollinators, not good for the
environment, not good for you
yourself. So having an organic
garden at home, if you can go
into a CSA that's organic in
your area.
CSA is I don't actually know
what it stands for. But you
know, it's when you have a farm
that allocates all their produce
that they make to a set of
customers and they deliver it or
you go pick it up every every
week. So it's kind of like a
shell in a farmers you know,
harvest August. Yeah. Wonderful,
very good thing to do. By the
way, we're not against that. We
totally promote that. I've done
it many times when I've not been
going my own stuff. I didn't go
on my own stuff when I was doing
iRobot. Because I knew that I
didn't have time. But I knew
that it would be too much time
and effort and I go on a
business trip, I wouldn't be
able to meet the goal. And so
something that I really love to
do is go and I couldn't do it
because of the weeding issue.
So, you know, what I love about
this company is we're solving of
this real problem that people
have, and it's good for the
earth because the the most
nutritious delicious food you
can get is actually from your
diet. I don't know if you have a
garden, or if you've ever grown
vegetables,
Audrow Nash: I I've grown
vegetables. I'm in San Francisco
and a little apartment, but I'm
likely moving to Texas in the
near future. Oh, so one of one
of the things we are most
excited about my fiance and I
are getting chickens and having
a garden. So we're right on the
same thing with you.
Helen Greiner: Okay, cool. Cool.
Well, I'm, I hope you all have a
Tertill in the garden. Yeah. So
you know, because of the
nutritious delicious food
organic, being able to, you
know, save on that trend, you
know, transportation, pollution,
the fertilizer, the pesticides,
but also, you know, people take,
you know, to, you know, a bunch
of carrots and put them in a
plastic bag, right, and then you
have plastic waste, or anything
else. And so, you know, if you
need something, you know, food
waste is a big problem, too,
right? I've read studies that,
you know, between a third and a
half of the food is wasted
between when you pick it, and
when it gets to your table and
what you know what you don't
eat, right? There's a lot. It's
crazy numbers. But if you have
it in your garden, if you need
it, you just go get it for that
night. And it's better than a
refrigerator to have it, you
know, on the vine.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Mm hmm. I
really liked that perspective,
where it's clever, and I wasn't
thinking of it until you brought
it up right now that this kind
of has a lot of like, you can
produce your own healthy food,
which is really, really nice.
And then it requires less of the
whole infrastructure required
for buying going and buying food
because the plastic that it's
coming in the shipping, the
pesticides and things that are
when the thing is being grown
from a huge agricultural
company. So it's really
benefiting the individual. And
Helen Greiner: so really like,
farm to table when you go to a
CSA, and we go a step further
and backyard to table. Yeah, but
we do, we don't call it CSAs.
Right, if you don't have the
opportunity to grow your own
vegetables. You know, a CSA is a
wonderful way to support a local
farmer.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, like I'm a
big fan of the regenerative
agriculture approaches where
they put a lot of effort into
the soil and have like a smaller
number of animals. And it sounds
very similar to the CSI and
probably how they structure
things. Interesting. It's so
it's so interesting to me that
it's a small robot with kind of
like big ambitions of helping
people and helping the planet in
this kind of thing. Do I did
you? In you figuring like
joining this company? Did you
have those ideas about this? Or
is this something that's kind of
come along? Since you've been
with the company or? I don't
know, like, how did you come to
that?
Helen Greiner: I did see it as a
way to encourage people to grow
nutritious and delicious food,
but I don't think I'd really
studied too much on how big ag
and the pesticides and the
transportation from other
countries. You know, just what
it takes to get food on the on
the table. I you know, I
honestly just love going I love
to see, go ahead and come to
life and produce, you know,
hundreds of pounds of food.
Audrow Nash: So I don't know
because I mean, I've grown food
a little bit but not never
really much. Can you like so if
I if I have a yard that is say,
Say say I have one turtles worth
of garden space? So I have 200
square feet? That was correct,
right? For one Tertill. Yeah. Of
garden space. How much food can
I make from that? If I'm gonna
do a good harvest?
Helen Greiner: If I had to guess
it would be a few 100 pounds. If
you if you wonder if you really
go well and you use fertilizer.
We actually just put out a
another product. There's not a
robot but I'll just briefly
describe it. It's a fertilizer
product. So a lot of folks who
beginning gardening don't know
that they they need fertilizer.
A lot of folks don't get that
soil tested and then you know
they come in they say I've just
got it Like thumb, it's like no,
you don't have a black thumb
you've got. Yeah. So we put out
a fertilizer plan. And the trick
that we're doing is we're going
to ship it with a soil test. And
when you get the results of the
soil test, it goes right to the
Tertill app, and we send you the
fertilizer that you need. So
instead of having to, you know,
get a PhD in soil chemistry, and
figure out whether you, you
know, whether you need
potassium, or magnesium or
whatever, all the
micronutrients, like, you know,
there's 26 of them or something
like that, we'll close that loop
and ship you exactly what you
need.
Audrow Nash: That's super cool,
because I've heard of like a
similar idea for like exercise
related things, or people with
their nutrients, where it's
like, you take a nutrient test,
or say, your goals or whatever
it might be, and then they send
you the appropriate supplements.
It's so cool to do that for
garden, where you go, and you
try the soil actually needs
these things. So I caught
Helen Greiner: the nutrient
thing is true or not, but I know
the soil test works, or every
land grant university had been
doing soil tests, and a lot of
them are at the point now where
they split it out. You know,
develop new nutrient
recommendations based on the
soil tested, tested for many,
many years. We're working with
Cornell University, where we,
you know, get these initial
recommendations, and then we
augment them. So this is
something that has been studied,
and it is science. It's not. You
know, when I hear something
about nutrition, I worry that
it's a it's, you know, like fad
pseudoscience. Yeah. Soil
Science is not pseudoscience.
Horticulture is not
pseudoscience. This is real
stuff.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Yeah, it
really drastically improves the
yield of the plants, you're
saying, if you consider the
nutrients that the plant
Helen Greiner: don't even go by
some people, they get some, you
know, they get, you know, a few
little tomatoes on the tomato
plant, and they're perfectly
happy because they don't know
any better. And they don't know,
you can have this lush green
garden, if you fertilize plants,
and they're really heavy eaters,
right? Because there's so much,
you know, vegetables that, that
producing that if you don't do
it, your soil just gets worse
every day. Yes, yes.
Audrow Nash: Shocking nutrients,
right? Yes.
Helen Greiner: Suck the
nutrients out of the soil. So
even if you start out and you've
got great soil, those vegetables
are going to suck it out over
time. And every university that
you know, the whole cultural
universities, they all recommend
fertilizing and doing a soil
test every three years. So
that's the that's why we
actually got the parameters of
the program that we put out.
Audrow Nash: That's so cool.
Would you think about like
supplementing with chickens or
something that are going to make
Helen Greiner: even better, even
better? I've had you know, fans
who do that, even composting
yourself, you could do that too.
But for people that don't have
the space, don't have the time
don't want to do that, you know,
because of the environment that
they may they may. Yeah, you
could just do it with
fertilizer, but we're not ever
going to say don't do that. If
you want to do that. That's what
you should be doing.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, and plus all
the bugs and stuff that you can
see with this kind of thing.
Helen Greiner: Not everyone
could get chickens either.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it's true. I
think maybe it's like state. My
complaint don't get roosters.
Yes, yeah. In San Antonio, where
I'm looking the you're not
allowed to get roosters. But you
can have as many better known
hens as you are this kind of
thing. I'm so excited about it.
Helen Greiner: It's wonderful.
And you can get the eggs and
yeah, go with chickens. And
everything. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: So it seems to me
just kind of bigger picture
even. It seems to me that you
think that we have like there's
a lot of problems in the world
and with agriculture and
everything. And it seems like
your approach is kind of like a
bottom up approach. So it's like
get the people doing things,
make it easier for the people to
structure things so that they
don't have to rely on these big
systems quite as much can eat
healthier. Also, one of the
benefits we didn't bring up is
having people get outside to go
garden and this kind of thing.
It's a huge, like physical
activity for that kind of thing
seems really nice. Yeah.
Helen Greiner: Yeah, lots of
features. Studies show that
gardening is good for your
health. Less scientific, it is
good for your soul. It is good.
You know, it's just really,
really good for you. So you
know, it is something that we
do, we do want to promote.
Audrow Nash: You know,
selfishly. One thing I would
love if it was like I don't know
if you guys will be doing
additional products but if you
made like an automatic chicken
house
Helen Greiner: you don't have to
take it right to your garden but
me decided you got the chicken
scratching around them and they
poop it all. But you know, if
you're gonna get the chicken
poop, I would actually you know,
composted was something. That's
okay.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So let's
see, the robots, the Tertill
robot sounds awesome. We have a
bit more time, I would love to
talk more about your path and
your opinions on robotics and
this kind of thing. So starting
with all that, you've made a lot
of transitions, it seems like
you've been on top of all these
really cool areas in robotics.
What? Like,
Helen Greiner: I guess I use
that I made a lot of
transitions. But I've been doing
this since 1990. Right. So I was
I did I have about 18 years and
you know, took it public. So
chairman for three more years.
So you know, I don't think of
myself that moves around too
quickly. I really jump into
something. But yes, I've been
able to see the growth of the
industry and I every robot
success I consider a success of
the entire industry of rising
tide truly does float all boats.
Audrow Nash: Definitely. Yeah.
And I was meaning transition and
more like, problem domains, or
this kind of thing, because it
was military. And then it was
home, and then it was drones.
And now then it was figuring out
how government works. Same thing
for military. So it's a little
more military. But now it's a
home robot for agriculture or
gardens.
Helen Greiner: Right? It all
comes together, like because I
knew a lot about home robots.
But now the areas that I'm
learning about with a great
advisory board is, you know,
the, I've been a gardener like,
but I'm not a horticulture best.
So I haven't studied that. But,
you know, we've got great
advisors who are amazing
multiculturalists. That, you
know, have shown us. You know
the science behind it.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. How do you?
So I guess one thing that's
really interesting to me is it
feels like with iRobot. And with
sci fi, and with Tertill, you're
picking very pragmatic robotics
applications, like given where
the technology is at the time
you pick something,
Helen Greiner: and also it also
in the Pentagon as well, but I
can't talk as much about that.
Well, yesterday, I was waiting
for the very practical
applications, and that's push
them fully.
Audrow Nash: If you ever can
talk about that. I would love to
do another interview on that.
Because that would be very, very
interesting. I don't know if it
like has a time way of whatever.
Helen Greiner: I don't think I
would ever come to pad not
because they were particularly
secret because some vendors win
and some vendors lose. And this
is not my story. It's a story.
Audrow Nash: Yes. Can you tell
me a little bit about that
perspective of like, just how
you've kind of honed in on these
spots where you can make a
simple robot that has a few
parts that something that
consumers can buy. And then it
provides a lot of value, like
Roombas helping people so they
don't have to vacuum especially
under the bed Tertill so that
it's like, it makes having a
garden a lot more feasible for
lazy people like me, where it's
like, no, I can do that I can
not do 80% of my weeding.
Helen Greiner: Um, yeah, we we
had some amazing experiences at
the first part of it well, but
for those eight years before we
were doing the Uber, we won, we
did get some military contracts.
So we went to developing the
pack bots. You know, but all
those other areas that I spoke
about oil and gas, commercial
cleaning, toys and games. You
know, we did some SpaceX
formation. And you know, we
really felt like we honestly
felt that these areas weren't
wrong. We just didn't have all
the pieces in place and we
didn't you know, you're turned
out on the downhole Well, the
price of batteries went went up
at the time and then on the
commercial cleaning it you know,
the you know, the company felt
that it would obsolete the
products that they're that they
were building and it so we had
all these, like all these areas
and our heads that we knew that
the could be successful robots
like I really think that
commercial cleaning is a great
place for robots. Although a lot
of companies just buy a Roomba
now because you can get them
Good, yeah, it's kind of like
the cell phone, right? You don't
say I'm going to build a cell
phone for industry, although
that was, you know, big with
blackberry and stuff, but you
just buy a consumer cell phone
and use it. But I really think
that there are a lot of
industries that need still did
great business opportunity even
today. And we were there, but we
couldn't make it happen. But you
know, the timing was was wrong.
And I do honestly believe that a
lot of times, it's just matching
the technology to the market.
And it's not, you know, a lot of
times, we were ahead of our
time, I see some space robot
companies starting out and I, I
want them to be very successful.
You're the first business model
that I will buy had was to do
the first robot steps on the
moon, like, wow, coming out of
university, that's what we
thought would get you I'll get
some big sponsors. And they'll
be sure that, you know, help us
do that. And we actually got
further than you would imagine,
even in, you know, 1992, we had
a flight test at Edwards Air
Force Base for the people who
make Brilliant Pebbles. And we
did some, you know, you know,
not not yet we didn't get the
space, right, but we were doing
it and they lost their launch.
You know, they lost their launch
vehicle, and now they're on
launch vehicles commercially.
Right. So I think the companies
today have a better shot. And I
wouldn't say we were wrong, we
would just, you know, early 30
years ahead. So we have aliens
market timing as well. Yeah. I
mean, you can see what's going
on in logistics and the number
of companies that have been very
successful and fulfillment
centers. And I mean, because the
time for that market has really
come on the market needed that
if we had tried that in the 90s,
I mean, it was before E
commerce, right? It wouldn't
have was
Audrow Nash: how don't wait, so
go ahead. Oh, I'm just
Helen Greiner: gonna say it
really is picking them lock it
and the timing as well.
Audrow Nash: How do you pick the
market and the timing? Like any
any thoughts or heuristics on
thinking about that?
Helen Greiner: Well, I for sure,
yeah. Yeah. I think what was
well son who said Why Why do you
go Why do you rob banks is
because that's where the money
is, you kind of look when the
money's flowing. And you can see
money today and logistics you
can see money today don't love
banks. In you know, the E
commerce incredible books, so I
don't I obviously I don't think
it's capped out, right. I keep I
keep like buying stuff MBA
online. Underwater Robotics,
right. You know, there's just
so, you know, people are looking
at, you know, how to service the
wells how to produce geothermal
wells, right, there's, you know,
so many with the wind farms that
are offshore, there's so many
applications for underwater, you
know, being able to go out and
do something, and then there's
you know, all the vehicle
robotics, right, even the switch
to electric power, which is
happening now. I mean, that
helps, uh, you know, I think
promote the robots. Nobody, you
know, robot inside. I, you know,
I can honestly say, you know,
what I Robot, you know, as we
had all the sticky notes on the,
on the wall, all the different
industry, we had autonomous cars
up there, like we were watching
the grand challenges, and we
even entered one, right. But we
decided that the market timing
wasn't there, and we didn't see
how we would ever get insurance.
And so we put it on the table.
And it really took a company
like Google to jump in and get
those regulations change. So I
think we would like not to go
there. But, you know, you see,
you know, companies like coups
Rive and Zooks, you know, all
these companies. Yeah, so
pushing on it. And of course,
Tesla and I know isn't Yeah.
Audrow Nash: That is very
interesting. All those areas.
Where do you where do you go to
get information for these things
so you can look where the money
flows? Do you have any advice on
how someone would see where the
money is
Helen Greiner: flowing? I think
you have to become an expert in
the industry that you're
entering. I don't say that
lightly. Right. Because at
iRobot we didn't at first we
thought we would be the
technology guys. And it wasn't
until we became industry experts
that we had success. So
sometimes the best way is to
hire someone who's been in the
industry. You're trying to
disrupt it, you don't want to
take everything they say, right?
Because you're not going to
disrupt it if you do the status
quo, but people who know the
economics of it, you know, the
multocida, Kima, like he had
done. Part, I think it was, you
know, he was involved in one of
the other, you know, ecommerce
delivery things and didn't get
it to work. And then he had so
much experience with it. So he
knew the field. And, you know,
figuring out what would work?
Audrow Nash: Yeah, so that's
kind of a nice pair, you have
someone who really understands
the industry, and then maybe
some people that understand that
technology very well. And if you
can kind of marry the two. And
that seems like a good way.
Helen Greiner: Yeah, well bang
people on learn about it. You
know, I think a lot of Abbas's
have usually, you know, a little
bit of jack of all trades if
you're a roboticist. So you're
probably pretty good at picking
up new things. So you know, it
is possible to learn about
there's plenty of information on
the web, there's plenty of
people who are willing to talk
to you, there's, you know,
there's all these companies that
just put out market research for
a living like this. There's so
much information out there,
thanks to Google and others,
right, that it's not like it was
in the 90s. Where, you know, you
go to the library, right?
Audrow Nash: Yeah, gosh, now
everything is just a Google OA.
It's a crazy time. Okay, um,
what do you think? So, if
someone wanted to start a
company now, in robotics, what
advice would you give them?
Helen Greiner: Um, be ready for
ups and downs. There are a few,
you know, get on the lucky ship,
so to speak, Locus robotics
seems to be on a good
trajectory. And even then, my,
they were incubated quite
logistics for quite a few years
before they spun out. So they
had that opportunity to get the
technology ready before, you
know, before the, you know,
going for that, you know,
economic blockade show.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So,
Helen Greiner: yeah, a lot of
times you can find, you know,
find something that's like a
long time to trace things back.
It's not that people just got
together and built something,
but there's something that was
late it was working, or it
failed somewhere else, and
you're taking it in or, because,
you know, the reason that didn't
work or at a university
gestating topic when you know,
something, maybe a challenge
funded it, there's so many ways
it could come from a large
company that doesn't want to
take it forward, spin out or
spin out a company from it. But
just getting it to the point and
getting all the capital
together, just you know, a
straight shot, I think is
reasonably difficult. You can do
some alternative funding, like
government contracts, like not
just SBIR. But there's many
different programs in the
government to try and get the
innovative people to get the
technology, though.
Audrow Nash: So SBIR, that's
Small Business Innovation
Research, right? Yeah. How do
you. So if you want to pursue
the path of an alternate source
of funding, so you can kind of
bootstrap a startup and doing
the market research, you can
find a good fit? How does one
learn about these government
research grants or government
grants that way they could do
well,
Helen Greiner: you can learn
about the process by meeting it
right. It's an easy, SBIR
program does a great job of
putting everything out there.
But in reality, you should be
talking to people that have a
need for your idea. Because if
you're not you're I mean, it's a
real statistic statistics are
there for you not to get
something if you haven't been
talking to people about your
technology about the way you see
the problem, your innovation,
because I you know, it's hard to
get things from a proposal Lily,
it's not that you cannot win
right. But you know, it does
help to Yeah, but I will also
look at other types of programs
that the government runs in, in
in innovation that some contests
the incubators are amazing these
days. My challenge I mean, NASA
robotics you know, my head
Audrow Nash: specifically
Helen Greiner: not NASA Onyx is
I think it's a little more
national. Now. They have
companies that uh, you know, not
just in in Massachusetts, the
actual physical mass robotics is
in Massachusetts, but I've heard
of companies that have
participated that are from
around the country. We're
actually doing a total we're
doing a massive robotics
accelerator right now with
Amazon Web Services. That's been
a very, very good learning
experience.
Audrow Nash: So it means you're
using you're using, you're doing
an accelerator to get your stuff
using Amazon Web Services, or
Helen Greiner: they're coming in
and they're giving, you know,
classes on what technologies
Amazon Web Services about Robo
maker about, you know, the
infrastructure behind it, which
you know, so well. I know, and
also, panels on raising venture
capital panels on, you know,
exiting panels on all the things
and you might say, Hey, you
don't need that hell away, you
taking up this face? You can
always learn more like it's a
different funding environment
from you know what I did with
iRobot? Like, we were one of the
first write comments on venture
capitals, like, oh, they don't
make investment in this space.
That's to science fiction, I
thought this would kill me. But
I persevered, right. And I found
some very, very good, forward
looking venture capitalists to
get to come in. I forgot where I
was going. But you know, this.
Audrow Nash: Go ahead. So it?
Yeah, you found these forward
looking venture capitalists and
it helped you find it basically
let you proceed, even though the
times weren't quite there. So
now we're at a different time.
Yeah. In the investment
community. And these incubators
seem to be really nice. Onyx and
all the talks and all the
education they're providing
sounds wonderful,
Helen Greiner: right? And then
Okay, so one of the reasons for
participating is we, you know,
the data infrastructure that
Amazon Web Services has, of
course, is great for storing the
data that we're collecting.
Audrow Nash: Mm hmm. Yeah. So
are you using like their IoT
service? I think it works well
with I don't have experience
hands on with Amazon Web
Services been robomaker. And
these kinds of things other than
like some basic s3 stuff, or
whatever it is, but are using
like their Greengrass platform,
which is for Internet of Things?
Helen Greiner: We are actually
not we are on a much lower
powered process, but we're
learning about it to see if we
can make use of future you know,
micro loss, for example, you
know, the, the simulation
environment, that bubble maker,
which is built on Zeebo, because
Eva, like, that's what I was
gonna say, um, you know, so, we
make, can we make use of that,
to augment our, you know, common
simulations, which are probably
not as high fidelity as Amazon
has been able to, to put
together and then you know, the
changes in the environment and
stuff, so you can always learn
more, and I was saying the
funding environment, right, the,
you know, with AI robot times,
right? You know, they didn't
have this, you know, convertible
notes as much, and suddenly,
safes hadn't been invented. And
now, if someone was starting a
robot company, I'd recommend
start a safe, which is, it's a
investment. You know, like, like
a convertible note, but it's not
a debt instrument, it is, it
basically just converts to
equity, or when another funder
puts a price on it later. So you
basically sign up, you get a
discount on the, you know, on
the bound, and some people don't
even have a discount on the
bound, no interest, and it lets
people come in and fund your
company. You know, it turns out
there's a lot of high net worth
individuals out there now who
are willing to, you know, fun
robot companies. So you can go
out, start a safe and start
getting that traction with
investors and maybe, you know,
maybe it's 25,000 100,000
quarter million at a time, but
it's easier for them to make
that decision. Like, you know,
we've had to make that decision,
you know, kind of on the spot
rather than the process you have
to go through to get a lead VC.
So you can get get that funding
going. And then when you go to a
lead VC, you have that traction
already and so you know,
hopefully some good names, you
know, names people have, you
know, people have Yeah,
respected in the industry,
funding the company, and also it
gives you advocates for the
company and people you can call
for help and you Want to push to
the next level? So, so like my
only point is not safe. So not
there's a lot of different
mechanisms to get funded. But
the environment does change. And
you have to keep up with that
environment. So no matter how
much experience you have joining
something like an incubator can
be helpful.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, so you guys
are doing the incubator now,
which is so cool. You're doing
the AWS one that is?
Helen Greiner: Yeah, it had a
criterion. You know, you can't
do you know, over a few million
dollars of business. So we still
we still made the cuts.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Gotcha. No,
that's really cool. Let's see if
there was Do you think so? The
whole con. So with? I guess,
actually, when you are creating,
so one thing that's different
with robotics versus other
industries, I feel like so if
you're doing like, a software as
a service thing, so it's going
to be some web app that people
use, investors look a lot at,
are you already getting users?
Are you already showing that
you're profitable? Or whatever?
With robotics, there's a big
investment in capital. And you,
I don't know, the model is
different, because you have to
build your robots, and you have
to building up the supply chain
and manufacturing. Yeah, go
ahead.
Helen Greiner: No, I think
that's true. But it's less true
now than before, because you
could get a prototype together.
Much easier. Like because of the
open source robot Foundation,
because of open robotics, I
should say, because of the
simulation, because of what
happens on Web Services is
doing. You know, because of the
global infrastructure, because
of what the video is doing, you
can actually get a prototype,
you can buy a robot on to test
out your idea. So I think a lot
of people aren't building
everything from scratch, you
know, a lot of the code to get
things, you know, tried is, you
know, is out there already, we
have to modify it like, but it's
a whole different modifying it
than creating the whole robot
infrastructure yourself, which
is what we did at iRobot. So
you, you know, and in some
applications that put together
commercial pieces can actually
be a product. And then as the
product gets more more
successful, you might fine tune
it. In the till application,
that's not true, because it
really has the cost is king for
consumers, you really do have to
design it from the ground up to
get the costing that you need to
get for consumer products. But I
see people going into the
industry now with these
commercial, you know, available
infrastructure and getting stuff
together so much quicker than we
could have ever dreamed of doing
it in the past. So I see.
Audrow Nash: And so one thing
that's interesting to me with
this is, it seems like a lot of
the robotics prototypes, kind
of, as you've been saying, with
this, it's a lot of business to
business transactions. But you
guys are going business to
consumer and you were saying
that for consumer products, you
need to really design so that
you can keep the cost as low as
possible. i There's a lot of
business to business potential.
I think in robotics, like if
you're selling things to help
stock shelves, or do security
guards or whatever it might be,
but business to consumer is
something that's been kind of
hard for robotics to break into.
And there's the Roomba, and
maybe the Tertill will we'll see
in the near future, but it seems
like you might be connected to
two of the most successful ones.
Right.
Helen Greiner: But I would also
put the DJI and the audio tones
in that mix. Right. But I, you
know, I there's been a few that
are more, you know, either a,
kind of bordering on a toy and a
game and I feel that those don't
usually come out over over time,
I really think it has to be a
practical application that
people have this real need for
and then you know, that the
Moomba is cute and bleeps and
bloops. And the Tertill has, you
know, patent you know, found as
it takes off and stuff. I mean,
I think that helps. But it's not
the primary reason why people
buy it.
Audrow Nash: It's not the value
offer. Yeah, for sure. Like it
really does something useful.
Yeah, rather than the cosmetic
beeps and boops Yeah, and the
whole value of the product.
Yeah, I wonder Do you think the
robotics consumer space will
grow in this like the will keep
finding ways of having less
betting on it.
Helen Greiner: I'm certainly
betting on it. Because once you
have, you know a robot, cleaning
your floors, mopping your
floors, doing your pool, doing
your lawn, doing your weeding,
right, I think people, you know,
look at it. It's like, why don't
I have a vote but to do these
other things? Yeah, I told him
it's robots in unstructured
environments are an actual
challenge. Right? Yeah. And so,
you know, so again, I do suggest
cheating, like we do with the
kernel. You know? Because making
it so it's a robot, um, you
know, that you do the jobs
robotically, like like the
Roomba going under beds and
couches makes it so they do
something that you couldn't
really do any other way.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Let's see. Do
you getting big picture again?
Where do you see robotics going?
In the next like, say, five
years or so five to 10 years?
What do you better life looks
like and how are robots around?
Or what's the robotics industry
look like? Oh,
Helen Greiner: I mean, it's such
a great time. But I think it's,
you know, it's a little like
you know, some pet kind of like
computers like that is a
computer Mandal see? Certainly,
and, you know, I'm using one to
communicate today. But there's
computers in everything, right.
And I think that's going to be
MOBOTIX in everything is almost
not a field, I can think of a
physical field that you wouldn't
want to have a robot adjusting
in the future. So I'm, I'm
bullish on robots, obviously.
You know, but all the jobs that
people don't like doing, I mean,
I constantly get requests, and
nobody's cracked it yet. But I
have seen prototypes. And you
know, that's one company I
invested in. I tend to buy it
that's collecting tennis balls,
you know, if you're, you know,
doing serving practice, it just
goes out and collects henna
balls. And that's, you know,
some of that technology, you
think, Well, that could have
been done in the 90s, right?
Because we had a little green
ball chasing robot running
around the company for a long
time, but we didn't make any
friends of ours did. And it was
great fun made it just like you
put a ball on and zoom and
everyone's like, I want that.
It's like, why. And now they're
making it to collect tennis
balls. And you know, I've seen
people try to do folding the
laundry. I haven't invested in
that one. But I mean, a lot.
Yeah, it's hard. But there's so
many people who say to me, I
would buy it in a minute, like,
oh, you know, ironing, right?
Um, you know, if you can come up
with a robotic solution to some
of the things that people we
help people have to do every
day. And, you know, that's what
I think with with a Tertill, you
know, weeding is like mowing. I
love the robot lawnmowers.
Right? But you can have someone
come in and mow your lawn. But
weeding it's actually hard to
get someone to come in and wait
for you because it's a job.
Nobody really wants, right. It's
it's fiddly. It's out in the hot
side. If there's no machine to
do it really. It really is
something that a lot of kind of,
like elbow grease right.
Audrow Nash: is required. Yeah,
for sure. Okay, now, wrapping
up, you mentioned you're bullish
in robotics. How do you see
robotics as like, important in a
bigger picture sense? Like why
are you bullish in robotics?
Helen Greiner: Because I just
see all the applications that
robots can lend a hand to you
know, it's important because I
think that you know, like, like
anything else, you know, people
worry about robots, people
worried about computers. But I
think they they just add such I
mean, computers have added so
much people couldn't have even
predicted at the time that in
communications to doing the
school virtually by in the
information were able to access
and robots I think we don't even
know what great things they're
going to be able to accomplish
yet. And keeping the environment
safe, safer. Getting rid of the
pesticide usage. You know,
helping with you know, getting
geo FOMO thermal and wind farms.
going, you know, I, I would
imagine if we do get fusion
reactors like there'll be robots
servicing them. And like, I
could just see that they have an
infrastructure that most
everything's going to depend on
to, you know, just to make it
work.
Audrow Nash: Right. Awesome.
Thank you. Yeah, thank you. It's
Helen Greiner: great fun.
Audrow Nash: Thanks for
listening to this conversation
with Helen Greiner. If you
enjoyed it, consider subscribing
wherever you get your podcasts
or on YouTube. Thank you again
to our founding sponsor, open
robotics. See you next time.