Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Dan Mantz, who
is the CEO of The Robotics
Education at Competition
Foundation, also known as the
REC Foundation, which is a
nonprofit that works with VEX
robotics to build interest in
STEM related career
opportunities. In this
interview, Dan reveals that he
sees a problem. We have a large
labor shortage for technical
positions. This includes
engineers, but also more
vocational roles like
technicians, and this shortage
might get worse. So Dan and the
REC Foundation are working to
expose students to stem through
robotics competitions. These
competitions balance difficulty,
how much they appeal to
students, how easy they are to
facilitate for the schools, and
the cost of the equipment so
that they can be as widely
available as possible. It was
great talking to Dan and I
learned how he and his team are
trying to pragmatically solve
the labor shortage through
education. And I think their
mission is important. Also, it
was surprising to me to learn
how their program really helped
students to learn soft skills,
such as working on a team and
problem solving, almost as a
byproduct of the students
participating. Yet Dan says
that those soft skills are one
of the most valuable things for
students to learn in their
careers, whether they stay in
robotics or do something
different. I'm Audrow Nash.
This is the Sense Think Act
Podcast. Thank you to our
founding sponsor, Open Robotics.
And now here's my conversation
with Dan Mantz. Will you
introduce yourself?
Dan Mantz: Hi, first, thanks for
having me on today. But my name
is Dan Mantz. I am the CEO of
The Robotics Education and
Competition Foundation. You'll
hear me say REC Foundation,
throughout the course of the
discussion. And we're based here
in Greenville, Texas, about 45
miles east of Dallas. So you'll
hear me just say we're in the
Dallas area. And we're one of
the largest not for profits for
STEM education, with a
specialist on robotics and
drones and workforce
development.
Audrow Nash: Can you give me an
idea of some of your
competitions that you guys host?
Dan Mantz: Absolutely. So our
largest competition, what we're
most known for is the VEX
Robotics Competition. And that
was launched over 15 years ago
now or 15 years into the VEX
Robotics continuum. It started
basically as a high school
middle school program, but it's
evolved into so much more. So we
call the high school program
with the metal parts and the
larger motors that's VRC. We
also have a very, very popular
Middle School and mid elementary
program called VEX IQ. That's
our fastest growing program.
It's even larger now than our
VEX Robotics Competition, our
VRC program, interesting for
early elementary, we have FX go,
which is a fantastic, really
great program that we developed
and released during the
pandemic, for students to really
start learning how to build
things in programming. There's
Vex 123 4k through two. And then
unlike so many other robotics
competitions out there, we
actually have a university
program called FX u. And that
draws students from across the
across the world of both two
year and four year colleges.
Also, another competition we
launched last year is Vex AI for
artificial intelligence
competition, and that's where
the robots use cameras and GPS
sensors, and they do everything
without manual driving. Outside
of our VEX robotics
competitions, we run the
robotics competitions for
SkillsUSA. And for TSA. We also
run Bell VRC, which stands for
vertical robotics competition.
So Bell Helicopter, based here
in Texas, we run their
competitions, we have some rad
competitions. We call it rad C,
which stands for REC Foundation,
aerial drones competition. And
then one of my favorite programs
that we run is our factory
automation competition. And
that's for students, build
conveyors and robots that
simulates a distribution center.
So we do the full spectrum of
mobile robotics. That's the Vex
platform, aerial, which is the
Bell Helicopter, and then our
drones as well as workforce
development with our factory
automation competition.
Audrow Nash: That's quite a lot.
How so how large are you guys?
Dan Mantz: Yeah, it's
interesting, somewhat, a lot of
people haven't heard the REC
foundation or they just think
VEX robotics, but we're actually
in 80 countries. We're in all 50
states. Pre pandemic, we had
30,000 teams just in our FX
program since often and between
our on in education and our
coding programs, we reach over a
million students. And you know,
the pandemic didn't really slow
us down. It caused us to look at
things a little bit differently.
But we put a lot more emphasis
on virtual and remote. But we do
believe building robots and
building drones is a key to what
we do. So we actually still
continued to the pandemic, we
had real competitions, but we
developed a technology called
live remote competition, live
remote tournament, and students
still built their robots. And we
connected students from
different places across the
world. And they still competed.
Of course, we had to modify the
game. But we persevered through
the pandemic, and we continue to
grow. So I have a staff of 50 in
the United States, full time
employees, we have another 30
part time employees that help us
run competitions. And then
internationally, we have a team
of six regional support managers
based in different countries
that support our international
competitions.
Audrow Nash: How do you? How do
you get funding? So like it's a
lot of people to?
Dan Mantz: Yes, it is. We're an
interesting model. It's a it's a
kind of like a what I call a
museum model, right. So we have
multiple revenue sources, which
is really good for us. So our
largest revenue is actually from
our registration fees. So VEX
robotics team will pay $150 for
the first team. And then if they
have multiple teams in the
organization, it's $100. All so
if you're talking 30,000 teams,
you can do the math, we also get
a lot of corporate sponsorship.
Now, Northrop Grumman Foundation
is our presenting sponsor, but
so many of the names that you
know, are big supporters of our
program, Google, Dell, Texas
Instruments, NAFSA, Tesla, all
those organizations, and many,
many others, give us funding to
keep our programs going and to
grow our programs. And then
we're also get government
funding to through grants. So
for example, that we were the
recipient of advanced robotics
and manufacturing grant on ARM
grant out of Pittsburgh, that
helped us develop our factory
work cell competition, we get
money from the Department of
Defense for growing programs.
For example, in Hawaii, we have
a grant right now to grow
programs in Hawaii. And we get a
lot of state funding. So for
example, in Texas, we're
recipients of the Texas
Workforce Commission that helps
us grow competitions and teams
in Texas. So it's not quite a
third, third, third, but it's
definitely three different
revenue sources, marine
government grants, corporate
funding, and team registrations,
Audrow Nash: Team registrations
and team registrations. Are the
like student teams registering
to compete in the challenges,
right? Or they're absolutely
Dan Mantz: yeah, so we keep our
price entry really, really low
compared to some other programs
out there. Again, it's $150 for
that first team, and probably
about 70% of our teams compete,
their extracurricular. Over half
of them are tied to schools. But
we also have teams that are tied
to Girl Scouts, for example, a
great partnership with the Girl
Scouts. So we have Girl Scout
teams, and we have private club
teams, we even have homeschool
teams. And then the another
growing trend in this industry
is robotics is becoming more and
more integrated into classrooms,
science and engineering
programs. So a lot of times we
see this in Nevada, for example,
they don't meet extracurricular,
they actually have their
robotics team as part of their
classroom. Oh, I love that. And,
and so but to compete in our
program, you do have to register
that covers the overhead of
running the programs. But we
actually don't charge for the
events that we run, we actually
have a network of volunteers
called Event partners, and they
run the events on our behalf.
You know, we're the overseeing
organization, think about Little
League. And our event partners
will charge a token amount
anywhere from 35 to $100 to run
an event, and then they keep the
revenue. So over the course of a
year, we'll have 3000 robotics
competitions, we'll have
hundreds of drones competitions,
and then with like our Vex go
program will have many, many in
class challenges and
competitions. Yeah. Wow.
Audrow Nash: That's not how does
it work with countries. Other so
you mentioned a lot of countries
are doing this as well. And you
mentioned most of the sponsors,
maybe it's just the ones you
mentioned mentioned are US based
or US government and this kind
of thing. How does it How does
it work with other countries
outside of the US?
Dan Mantz: Sure, absolutely. So
we still as the REC Foundation,
we still have the same rules for
the challengers in games and
stuff like that, but we use our
support outside and they will
collect registrations if they're
a federal Lau for example, in
China, we have 4000 teams in
China. And they actually don't
pay a registration fee. It's
covered by the government, for
example. But at the end of the
day, the teams still register
and they still play the same
game. And then our competition
model is it's you start locally,
and a lot of local competitions
and then you'll go to a regional
level and a national level,
we're under playing with the
same rules, the same game, the
same game elements. And that's
what's so popular is it
culminates in our world
championship, which is actually
being held in Dallas in May.
It's the VEX robotics world
championship, where 3000 of the
top teams from across the world
come together, we have four
different competitions, and each
competition will crown a world
champion. That's awesome. But it
the funding to you do bring up a
really good point, as we talk
about a lot of times we talk
about our global sponsors, but
each country, each state, even
every town will have a sponsor.
And here's a good example,
Honda. So Honda is technically
not a sponsor of the REC
foundation. But Honda does so
much for VEX robotics programs
in Ohio. And so they give to
local chapters, and they sponsor
teams, a TVA, Tennessee Valley
Authority, while they are sort
of sponsor the REC Foundation,
they do an incredible job of
giving funding, giving equipment
to teams in the Tennessee Valley
area. And internationally, for
example, shell Exxon Mobil,
those companies will sponsor
teams and programs. Matter of
fact, of pre pandemic I was even
in China have sponsored by
Alibaba. So if you don't know
Alibaba is like the Google of
China, for example, or excuse
me, Amazon of China, and they
actually fund the national
championship there, they brought
me over. So it's and then but we
shouldn't even forget about the
mom and pop stores to the subway
shops, the pizza shops, the
local gas station, they all fund
teams and stuff like that. So
it's a huge ecosystem of how
teams get funded. And it's
emerging to I mean, right now,
it's not just private, its
schools are really investing in
these type of programs, and
putting more and more of their
budget into in class and
extracurricular robotics
competitions.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Gotcha. It's
amazing to me your reach with
this, how far it's going and
with a staff of only 50 people,
and then 30 that are part time
in this kind of thing. And then
you have the volunteers. How
does it? So from your
perspective of actually running
this and setting this up and
having this big reach? What do
you guys do? Is it like you're
setting the standards? Or you're
creating the curriculum? Or how
does it work?
Dan Mantz: All of the above. And
it's interesting, because I'm
glad you appreciate what we're
able to accomplish lost a small
staff, it's, it's not a fact,
sometimes I think I've stretched
our staff too much. But it's the
model that we chose. And the
model is to rely on volunteers
and partners that aren't on the
payroll, right. And but what we
do you know, a lot of teams say,
hey, what do I get for my $150?
Right? What do I get for my $100
registration fee. So primarily,
one of the most visible things
we do is we work for example,
with the VEX Robotics on
designing the games every year.
So the IQ program has the VEX IQ
challenge to go Mexico program
has their little competition,
and then the VRC competition. So
a lot of our staff are spending
their time to develop that game
and develop the resources, it
comes with manuals, it comes
with videos, you have to support
it. So that's a you know, one of
the things that we do, we also
work with our event partners to
help them run good events. And
that's where a lot of our part
time employees come in. So we
have a series of team engagement
managers and of engagement
managers that support
competitions in the United
States. And then we have
regional support managers
internationally. And they work
very, very closely with our
volunteers to make sure that
they run events that meet our
standards. So again, I think
good models, if you think about
Little League, you know, the
Little League Association sets
the rules, but each local level
runs their own baseball camps,
right? So we kind of do the same
thing, but we're very important.
And one of the things that
distinguishes us from other
programs is we really believe in
student centered. So we're not a
program that encourages the
parents or coaches to do the
work. Matter of fact, in our
program, our code of conduct and
our students centered policies
is about the students doing the
work. It's not about building
the world's best robot. It's
about learning, engineering and
problem solving and
communication skills through the
students doing hands on work. So
a lot of my staff are team
engagement managers or event
engagement managers, they're
working with the coaches and the
event partners to make sure that
we follow the ecosystem. And
like any organization of course,
we have accounting. We have
marketing, we have to
development we have those
infrastructure to it's I pay my
staff, we try to pay
competitively. And we give our
staff free health care, for
example. wonderlands. So we have
an HR department. So we have all
those types of things that are
standard business as to
Audrow Nash: how does it work?
Can you tell me a little bit
about being a nonprofit with
that?
Dan Mantz: Sure. So I personally
come from the for profit world,
my entire career was for profit,
I joined the REC foundation
board over five years ago, and
ultimately ended up as the CEO
here. But I didn't have a lot of
experience. So I'm learning to
but you know, I'm not for profit
still has to pay their bills,
definitely, we still have to
generate revenue, provide value
and pay our bills for being a
not for profit, what allows us
to do is get those foundation
donations, for example, the
Northrop Grumman Foundation are
our largest presenting sponsor,
and allows us to get those
government funds, but we have to
do due diligence, we have to
show the funders of our
organization, whether it's the
government or private, that
we're good stewards of their
money. So again, we have
probably spend, you know, 4000
hours a year between audits and
reporting and stuff like that.
So like anybody familiar with
any business out there, we get
revenue, and we have expenses.
And at the end of the year, the
board that I report to expects
me to bring in more money than
I've spent. But then we have to
account for that money to the
people that fund us.
Audrow Nash: How do you think of
profit versus nonprofit in this?
Dan Mantz: Well, I think that's
a great question. And actually
one that I've never really been
asked before. But I think I
think the challenges of a not
for profit, is there's an
expectation that you can do
things cheaper. So there's an
expectation, you can hire people
cheaper and something like that.
And that's not true. If we want
to be the best STEM education
and robotics not for profit out
there, we still have to pay
competitively. But because we
have, we don't have just a
customer buying our product that
basically tells us whether we're
successful or not. We have so
many different customers in our
program. I mean, primarily for
us, the teak the students, and
the educators are our primary
customer, our programs are for
them. So that's who I'm trying
to please first. But we also
have to make sure that if we get
federal money, that they're
satisfied with how we're
spending the money, if we're
getting corporate sponsorship,
we're doing the things they
expect us to do. And I think
that's the big difference. So I
was president of a company
called rack solutions. We made
infrastructure products for data
centers, primarily sheet metal
products. And if I came out with
a new product, if rock solutions
came out with a new product, and
it's sold, we knew it was
successful. That was our answer.
And if it didn't sell, then we
made a bad engineering or sales
decision for a not for profit,
it's not so black and white,
right? So I can have a program
that the students love. But if
the coaches and the teachers
don't like it, it's not a
success, I can have a program
that the funders think is
excellent. But if nobody wants
to do it in their schools or
extracurricular, it's not so the
city's argue your customer? I'm
sorry, can you have to satisfy
all of the parties in it? And
that's the challenge. And it's
people ask me, Is it easier to
run a not for profit, you don't
have this pressure of like
having a return on investment
for? You know, like a
stockholder? I'm like, no, it's
actually for me much more
difficult to run a not for
profit.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. I mean, so
I've been involved with like,
when I was very involved with
Robo hub, which is a robotics
news organization, we were a
nonprofit. So I, I feel like
I've been through some of the
like pain of being in a
nonprofit. But I think you can
do a lot of good work and not be
accountable to not necessarily
have the economics drive the
mission of the thing. But can
you tell me kind of like, why
not go for profit, or this kind
of thing?
Dan Mantz: Well, I think the
biggest reason is, we don't want
to become a for profit is
because I want to be able to
just breakeven for one sec for
the year, I don't want to have
to have a return to
shareholders. So that really
allows us to keep the prices as
low as possible and maximize
value for our customers. So
that's one good reason. So we
had the difficult decision of
raising our registration fee.
After five years, we've gone
five years without raising
registration fees. But if you're
reading the news, you know how
bad inflation is right now. And
that affects us to insurance
costs are up the gasoline
everything. So we had to raise
our registration fees for the
first time in five years, but
because I am just trying to
break even, it wouldn't have
been as large as maybe if I was
trying to maximize revenue for
shareholders. But then again,
also being a not for profit.
There's great companies out
there. Google, for example, that
really invest deeply into our,
our programs for the underserved
community for Title One
students, women in STEM, etc.
And that's another reason to
stay as a not for profit,
because these corporate sponsors
will really invest in you if
you're doing something that they
feel is going to help them out
the long term to our corporate
sponsors are amazing when NASA
invests in us because they want
that next generation of people
developing the Mars Rover
mission. For example, when Tesla
invests in us, it's because they
want that next generation of
workers for their new truck
factory in Austin, and for the
Gigafactory, outside of Reno,
Nevada, right. So they're about
us developing the workforce. And
you know, NASA is about
developing the engineers and ti
tech system, it's about the next
generation of computer
scientists. And that allows us
as a not for profit to better
serve those funders of our
programs.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. How does
it? So how do the different
competitions compare? So when
you have the young elementary
school students or you have the
middle school or high school?
How do these different
university as well? How do these
different programs and different
challenges compare?
Dan Mantz: Yeah, that's a great
question. And in a sense,
they're a progression, a word
that I like to use as they
progress. So if you're doing Vex
go, you still have a challenge,
and you're still building cars
that the first thing I have, is
our first competition. So as you
know, third, and fourth graders
is the priority,
Audrow Nash: low IQ, RC, and I
don't remember what the
university wants. So
Dan Mantz: what technically have
123 That's an entry level
programming K through two, but
we don't have a competition for
that we have in class
activities, then we have Vex go,
which is third and fourth
graders. Again, it's simpler,
build simpler programming,
understand the concepts, then
you get up to IQ. And that's not
a competition where two teams
are facing each other, they're
actually collaborating. When
things I love about IQ, as the
students work together, the two
teams work together to get the
most points. And now you get to
VRC and NBRC. Now, it's a two v
two competition, right, so now
you're playing defense, and
you're strategizing with a
partner, and how to beat an
opposing Alliance and, and the
power of the motors is bigger,
and the programming, all of our
competition and VRC starts with
a 15 second autonomous mode,
right? So the first 15 seconds
are robots moving to score
points and win the odd time
bonus. And then you get to vex
you, which now it's the same way
bigger motors, but now you're 3d
printing your parts, and there's
a lot more customization. And
then you get to the AI
competition. And now it's
advanced programming. And now
you're using GPS sensors. And
you're using high end cameras to
do data exchanges between robots
to solve it. So. But the nice
thing about our program is if
you start with, you know, 123,
and you start coding, all that
coding just grows and grows and
grows, and the concepts of how
you build, and the soft skills,
which are so important to these
programs, how you troubleshoot.
I'm an engineer, by background,
I worked 21 years at FANUC,
robotics and core to the REC
foundation programs is our
design process. So wherever you
start in our programs, the
design process of identifying
your challenge and how you're
going to solve the challenge and
score points, and then the
process of iteration design,
right. So trying something
designing something, building it
failing, and then persevering
that permeates through our
entire program, whether you're
at the very beginning, or you're
doing facts you and AI.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha, I really
like that. I feel like failing
is so important. Because if you
don't ever fail, you don't it's
like you you learn limitations.
And you have to work with those
limitations. And you can't
really make anything interesting
unless you're failing, most
likely. So I like that it's
baked into the
Dan Mantz: curriculum. Yeah.
When I became CEO, we stepped
back and we looked at our
mission and vision and we just
tweaked our mission. mean, our
mission is to increase student
interest in STEM by engaging
students and hands on affordable
and sustainable Robotics
Engineering Programs. Right. So
we made it less worried that if
that stayed the same, but what
we really changed was our
vision. Because for me, I wanted
people to know that we want
students to innovate and
experience failure and
persevere, right. So we
literally set our vision is
where students design and
innovate as part of a team and
they actually fail and in our
program, because we're a year
round program, students fail a
lot, but that's not a bad thing.
I mean, they learn from that and
they persevere and then they
become much more confident and
they work the world better
place, right. And these skills,
whether they go into robotics,
or they go into medicine, or or
they work in marketing, or
they're working, you know, as a
technician, those skills by
failing and persevering are
lifelong skills.
Audrow Nash: What do you So you
mentioned mission and the
mission is to increase
engagement and your mission
vision, how do those how to
mission and vision relate to
you?
Dan Mantz: I think, you know,
first of all, one of the things
we talk, if we circle back to
working for a not for profit,
one of the things I really try
to do is make sure that the
decisions we make in this
organization are missing driven,
we have so many opportunities to
go into the next great thing.
But that mission of increasing
student interest in STEM
through, you know, hands on
affordable robotics programs, is
the core of what we do. And so
we have our mission, we're
developing these robotics and
engineering programs for our
students. And it's evolving,
that's also workforce
development programs, too. And
then the vision is, is more
captured of what we want to see
these students do in the future.
And that's, you know, persevere,
become lifelong learners.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. How do you
so when you are developing these
curriculum, or these
competitions? How do you
balance, like, all of the
different factors, so there, you
could make it too difficult? You
could make it to like, really,
really appealing to the
students, but it's like a video
game, and they're not actually
learning anything? Or, like,
there's all these different
things. How do you think about
actually designing these
competitions to make them and
gauging for students?
Dan Mantz: That's a great
question. And it's a really hard
process. When I joined the REC
foundation, I would have never
guessed help difficult game
designers. And that's what we
call it, we call it game design.
And so there is a game design
committee. It's a collaboration
between VEX robotics and the REC
foundation for the Vex programs.
It's a collaboration with NASA
for the win, and REC Foundation
staff for our our drones,
competition, and then Bell and
many Bell suppliers in the REC
foundation for our bell VRC
program. So first of all, all
three programs that have
competitions, it starts as a
collaboration. And then you're
really trying to define what
your outcome for that season is
going to be. But our program has
a bell curve, right. And on the
competition side, especially the
top teams, which are the top
10%, they care about winning
more than anything, right. But
from my perspective as CEO for
the REC Foundation, that's not
what we're trying to do, we're
looking at the entire bell
curve, and making sure that they
can, you know, get something
that matches our mission out of
this. So we will literally
design a game with an easy
scoring component, right?
Something that every team can
do. And then we have more
complex. And we want to make
sure that we wait it. So what
are the challenges even after
you brainstorm games, and you
get it down on paper. And of
course, you have to design your
field elements and your game
elements. So you have mechanical
engineers, and electrical
engineers that are designing
this, you have to hit a cost
target, right, we can develop
some of the world's best games.
But if it costs $5,000, for each
team to buy game elements, it
can't do it. So we have very
strong cost elements. So you do
all that. But then you start
designing how you're going to
play the game, and the REC
foundation and VEX robotics for
our Vex competitions, we
actually release a couple of
robots for different levels so
that everybody that plays the
game can achieve at least some
of the game objectives. And
that's the key, right? Like,
I'll admit, we've made games
that people have figured out in
the first month, and they've
maxed the score, and we've had
to tweak the rules. And we've
made our games that were maybe
just a little more complex than
we expected to at the beginning.
But it's a team of engineers and
non engineers that are looking
everything. And also, you know,
the other thing, people don't
realize this, so we have to
think about transportation.
Because we're running 3000
competitions a year, somebody's
got to go set this game up at
the library or the school or the
gym, you know, different places.
So we have to make sure that the
game can be torn down and
assembled easily too. So that
all goes into it. So when people
ask like you did earlier, you
know, where's that registration
fee goes to the game design
committee is 12 people. We're
all in different roles. And
there's a lot of engineering
behind that. And it's expensive
to develop one of these games
and we release new games every
single year for both IQ and for
VRC. And our drones programs to
we have new games every year for
drones to
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So you
mentioned you said you have
different robots for it. So it's
like people will register their
team that happens each year I
suppose. And then you have like
different key basically how to
teams get their parts and I
think you were saying something
about like different levels of
robot that they can have for the
competition or something.
Dan Mantz: Yeah, so every one of
the things about our program is
we want it to be affordable and
accessible and sustainable.
Right. So once you've bought for
them talking next program here,
but once you bought a Vex kit,
you can reuse that those parts
year after year, now there's
some wear and tear over time,
you're probably going to buy a
replacement motor to etcetera,
but use those parts. But you
know, you can build with a with
a basic robotics kit, you can
build a claw bot, right and a
call bot can do a couple basic
functions, what Vex engineering
does every year, they also
design a hero bot. And so a hero
bot can play the game at a
little bit higher level, right.
So they're not going to be a
state champion or world
champion, but at least allows
you to execute and be successful
at more of the game challenges.
And then, you know, we work with
other people, and people will
develop an even more advanced
version of the robot for that
game. But ultimately, we're not
going to release a design. For
the world's best robot, we want
the teams and the students to do
that. But it's really important
to understand there's a lot of
clubs out there and a lot of
classrooms that they're just
going to compete one or two
times, and they don't care about
winning, they want the the fun
of going to a competition and
seeing how they do. And so we
want them to be successful. So
that's why we released some,
some designs the hero bot so
that they can at least achieve
success at certain parts of the
game.
Audrow Nash: Definitely, how do
you find your price point for
that? So if you, you're going to
make a robot kit and that robot
kit? You want it accessible to
the majority of schools? How do
you? How do you figure out what
they can afford? And what you
can include and what you can do
with that? Well, that's
Dan Mantz: always the debate,
right? What can what can people
afford? So if we're talking
about the game elements, that's
probably an easier one, right?
So every year, we want teams to
be able to if you're in IQ, you
spend $100, so you can get that
game element. So it's a little
bit more expensive for the VRC
program. So basically, that is a
limiting factor, to be honest.
So anyway, any engineers
listening to this will tell you
that if you have tooling costs
for these parts, there's a real
cost to make these parts, you
got to cover shipping. So it's a
really limiting factor. Here's a
good example. So this year is
game, you could shoot balls,
right? And they were more like
hacky sack balls, this is in the
IQ. And I forget how many we
have on the field, shame on me,
but say there was 24 Maybe the
game would have been harder to
max out if we would have had 28.
But you know, for $100, we can
only afford to design tool,
manufacturing chips. So that's a
like a limiting factor. Or maybe
everybody in the community
always wants a water game,
right? Everybody always want to
have a water game. Could we do a
water game? Yes. Will we do a
water game someday to the
community out there? You never
say never. But the price point
to now have waterproof motors
and sensors and stuff like that
just doesn't make it realistic.
I mean, we these are high
schools and in junior High's and
middle schools and elementary
schools that are primarily
buying this. So we can't have
very expensive products out
there.
Audrow Nash: And what are the
kids look like? Like I've seen
some images and things. It's
like a little similar to Lego in
terms of how you make it. But
like, how would you describe the
kids? Yeah, so
Dan Mantz: let's talk about VRC.
First, so VRC is metal parts.
I've always described it as,
yeah, this is for high school.
And you know, a lot of eighth
grade seventh and eighth grade
teams that have been doing Vex
for a long time. They'll they'll
also do VRC. So those are metal
parts with bigger motors. And I
think I described them as an
erector set. So I think as its
generations get older, it's
maybe people know what Erector
sets, but those are metal pieces
that they can be cut in and bent
and stuff like that. The Middle
School in late elementary the
Audrow Nash: IQ is like a
modular design where you'll have
a piece and it has a bunch of
holes in it. And then you can
insert something in and then you
can exactly anything to that. So
from
Dan Mantz: the metal pieces
you're using fasteners for for
IQ and Mexico you're using pins,
and the pins index go that's the
third fourth grade, the pins are
larger and easier to take in and
out. So IQ. Um, there's a lot
more parts, but that's exactly
what they are. There are parts
that you can put pins in,
there's different sizes. I don't
think, you know, some people say
like Lego, but the connection is
so much different. And the IQ
parts honestly stay together a
lot better, right, you can
actually build so if you do
Lego, you know, you're not
really running into stuff and
stuff like that you're more it's
more like a programming
challenge versus IQ. These
robots need to be a lot more
robust, so and the motors are
more stronger. There's a lot
more mechanisms. One of the
things I always ask subjects to
do every six months is release
new sensors. So as someone who's
come from industrial robotics
sensors are everything to me.
And that's the other beauty of
all of our programs they can Um,
with sensors, cameras, color
sensors, potentiometers, etc. So
it's, you know, you have to make
sure that your electronics are
robust enough to do the sensors
and stuff like that. But that's
the best way to teach coding to
is when you include sensors, and
you make sure that your game you
can win, you can play the game
without having sensors, but
you'll do better if you
integrate sensors. And that's
really, really important to me.
Is that, that students that are
learning this Learn sensors,
too.
Audrow Nash: So how do they so
if a student has a robot,
they've put it together? It has
motors, and it has a whole suite
of sensors that it can access?
How do they program it?
Dan Mantz: Well, one of the
things that Vex has done an
amazing job is they have Vex
code, and you get Vex code for
free. And I do want to say
there's third party programs out
there, like pros and stuff like
that, that you can use to but
for the simplicity, we'll just
talk about flex code. So a lot
of our students start with
blocks. And then they transition
into text based programming, you
know, it's looks very much like
C or you know, or something like
that. So, you know, it's, but
most of the most time students
will start with block coding,
and when they're comfortable,
they switch to text coding. And
it's, and then you have lots of
libraries that you can bring in.
And with the advanced
programming and our programs are
amazing. And same with with cat
two, even though teams start
with a kit of parts, our high
school teams, over 75% of our
high school teams CAD up their
robot and cat the parts too. So
you start at the very basic
level and early elementary
school. And it's a continuum,
you just continue to progress.
It's awesome.
Audrow Nash: For the coding. So
we have the block language that
kind of looks like Scratch, I
think.
Dan Mantz: Yeah, I think I think
that's safe to say that it's it
looks like Scratch, right? And
then as you move on from blocks,
then it looks like Python and c
plus plus.
Audrow Nash: Okay. I imagine
like a little subset of it
because C++ can be quite
complex.
Dan Mantz: Yeah, I can. It's
it's a simpler version of C++.
But as someone who used to be a
professional programmer, I think
that it's a good subset, you can
do some really good subset, I
feel very comfortable that
students that are programming
are robots with the C Plus Plus
and Python will be able to
transition that skill set
outside of robotics.
Audrow Nash: How do you so for
both of these, these are kind of
both your custom things? How do
you? How do you decide to make
it? I mean, so you're a team of
50 people with 30 additional
people as part time, how do you
decide to go make your own
programming languages as opposed
to like using Scratch, or using
Arduino or using something that
exists out there
Dan Mantz: the difference
between us as the not for profit
and then Vex as a product
company? So okay, so VEX
Robotics is one of the leading
education, STEM education
companies in the world, right?
So we just take their, their
products that they develop,
right, so we collaborate with
them, we explain what we see the
needs, but but Vex themselves
has an incredible resource of
mechanical electrical engineers
and programmers so so it's Vex
that actually develops the
hardware, develops the motors
and develops all the coding
resources. So Vax has a division
Vex education in Pittsburgh, and
they provide some of the best
products are as for example, I
would highly encourage the
people listening today or
watching today to look at Vex
code, and virtual robots VR,
there's free resources out there
that are absolutely incredible.
And again, they're free
resources. And these are
designed to for the education
market, right? So Vex is there
in classrooms across the world.
And so we're focused on the
competition piece. So again, I
always remind people index does
the same thing. They're a
product company. Their goal is
to make money and sell products.
And we're a not for profit that
runs competition, and camps and
education activities. And we
have the same thing at our
drones too. So we have partners
for our drones, competition,
that design and make drones. And
then we take the drone partners
and we integrate them into a
competition and education
curriculum. Gotcha. When
Audrow Nash: you're making a
competition and you are
selecting the robots to use how
closely do you work with Vex to
kind of get the parts prepared
and get the kids
Dan Mantz: question and we
actually on the game design
committee. It's actually half
Vex half REC foundation. So it's
100% cooperation, right? So we
go in there from the perspective
of our event partners, our
coaches, our students, what they
need, what parents need, with
the rules, and more importantly,
Are we going to be able to
support the competition? So
that's, that's what are our big
contribution on the Vex side?
You know, they have the
engineers and the programmers,
and that's what they contribute.
So it's a truly collaborative
effort. And we always design our
games two years ahead of time,
right. So the game that we're
going to reveal in March, and
May, has been designed already
for a year, and it's been
totaled up and the parks are in
the warehouse, and we already
have the game ready for 2023.
Right? So we'll start working on
the 2024 game very, very soon.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So being
two years ahead, does that mean
you do like small groups of
students that are approximately
the age you're looking for? And
you like, run it by them? And
have them try it? Or, like early
feedback? Or
Dan Mantz: what do you guys we
don't, they're glad that the
students from our programs that
were listening would say, Man,
please do that, please do it. At
this point, security is very,
very key. Because when we
announce our new game, and may,
you know, competitions will
start happening, you know, a
month later, and Singapore and
Australia, etc. But we have to
be very, very sensitive about
keeping the game private,
because it is a competition. And
so we actually keep the circle
pretty small, that's aware of
the game. So some some people
from the RSAF will, will play
it, you know, simulate it. Same
with some of the Vex engineers,
but we actually don't do any pre
testing. We also try to be
flexible, just like we want our
students to be flexible. So for
example, last year's game, the
IQ game where one month into the
season, basically, we you have
you can lift yourself up at the
end, it's called the end game,
you can lift yourself up for
points, and we didn't have a
possession limit. And so teams
just filled up and then they
lifted and dumped. And they were
maxing out the game one month
into the season. So that's where
we evolve and stuff like that.
We're like, Okay, if you're in
the air, you can only possess X
amount of product, right? So,
but for the most part, we try to
do all our scenarios, the person
who leads the GDC, the game
design committee, he's very
meticulous, and looking at all
the what if scenarios, and for
the most part, we get it right.
And if we make a mistake, we
acknowledge it, we make a rule
and we give, we send out rule
updates, at least every couple
months throughout the season for
clarification. A lot of times we
do that, for the benefit of our
referees, the referees have a
very difficult job, especially
at the high school level, right?
So we're always evolving to make
sure that we're clear on our
rules.
Audrow Nash: By at the high
school level, is it especially
difficult,
Dan Mantz: I believe that it's
just more competitive, I think
teams, the bell curve I talked
to there's more students at the
high school that are motivated
to win, you know, so I think you
know, the earlier like, you
know, these kids that are at
second and third, they're
playing, and they're just having
fun, and they're learning stem,
and they're learning soft
skills, and they don't care
about winning or losing. But the
older you get, the more
important winning and losing is.
So I think our our, our high
school students are a little
more crafty about finding the
loopholes in our roles. So and I
mean, that affectionally to you
students out there, but they're
definitely better at identifying
and the loopholes and taking
advantage of
Audrow Nash: those. That's so
funny. Okay, and you mentioned,
you mentioned a couple of times
drones and the whole set of
drone competitions. How does
that fit? Or how does that fit
with everything? Yeah,
Dan Mantz: so you know, a few
years ago, I love mobile
robotics. And we'll talk about
my background a little bit
later, but I come from from
robotics, industrial robotics.
But when I joined the REC
Foundation, when the board asked
me to join as the CEO, there's a
couple things that I asked for.
I said, I'll take the position,
but I want to be able to move
outside of just stem, I want us
to focus on workforce
development. And I think there's
a large set of students that
aren't doing mobile robotics for
different reasons. And I want to
try to reach those students too.
And when you look about a drone
technology is everywhere. I'm a
country boy, myself, and you
know, drones are used in
agriculture for identifying, you
know, fields that have bug
infestations, or need more
watering or need less watering.
And drones are fun, and a lot of
people love flying them. So we
dipped our toe into drones about
three and a half years ago. And
I think a lot of people honestly
were skeptical. They weren't
sure that I was making a good
decision there. But I just felt
that mobile robotics aren't for
everybody. And by mobile
Audrow Nash: robotics, you mean
ground robots? Yes. Drive
around.
Dan Mantz: Exactly. The ones
with wheels are true thank
tread, etc. And so there's a
whole group of students that
maybe weren't going to do STEM.
They weren't going to analysis
because it's fun to fly a drone.
So now they start programming a
drone and they add sensors to
the trunk. Under, they build the
drone. And they're getting that
same skill set that you get in
the ground based robotics. And
so that's why we did it. And,
and then for our our V five
workcell, our factory automation
competition, same thing,
students out there, they're not
going into engineering, they may
not have the financial, you
know, ability to do it, they may
not have the background, and
they want or they just may not
like, you know, school, right,
so, but they need good, good
jobs, too. And robotics is the
fastest growing industry, right?
There's robotics everywhere. So
we didn't know develop, we
developed a program where
students, they build a robot
that looks a lot like a factory
automation, an industrial robot,
they build conveyor systems, and
they figure out how to make the
robots work and how to
collaboratively stack cargo and
by color, sort by color and
stuff like that. So we felt it
was really important to reach
all the students that we need so
desperately for our workforce.
Audrow Nash: Why do you? So I
mean, I know that there's labor
shortages, and I know that we
have an aging population. And
there's a lot of other things.
But why do you? Why do you say
that the last statement?
Dan Mantz: Well, I mean, just
even Department of Defense and
Department of Workforce studies.
Now we have a gap. You know,
even a couple years ago, there
was 2 million more STEM jobs
being created every year than we
had people to fill them. And
when I say stem, I'm not talking
engineers and scientists, I'm
talking robot technicians,
people that are doing technical
jobs in the workforce, because
even in retail, now, there are
technical jobs, you know, you go
into WalMart, you see the robots
that are doing inventory and
stocking and you need people to
maintain those. So technology is
permeating themselves in all
industries right now. So those
jobs are growing much faster
than non technical jobs. I mean,
they're growing 30% faster. And
there's a huge gap of people
that have the talents to use
these to do these jobs. And
that's the challenge that we're
trying to face. Of course, we
want the next generation of
scientists and engineers and
technicians, I don't want to
minimize that. But we also have
so many students that didn't,
the good paying jobs out there
are maintaining the robot on the
factory floor are tweaking the
inventory robots at a retail
store, they are the ones setting
up the cameras, so that, you
know they can do better
scanning, and those don't
necessarily have to have college
degrees to do these jobs. But
you do need to have a technical
aptitude. So that's a gap that
the US government has
identified, it's that gap exists
everywhere in the world is that
tech jobs are growing so much
faster than non tech jobs. And
we need our students to have
those skills to fill these jobs.
Audrow Nash: So it's from I
guess, this is kind of a big
picture perspective, where
you're trying to think of where
the world will be in the future,
and you're trying to make it so
that this knee that keeps
growing, that we can kind of
match it by exposing more people
to robotics, getting them
interested, even if it's at a
much even if it's not like PhD
in robotics, or like a leak
researcher or robotics engineer,
but
Dan Mantz: I think your your
audience has probably heard of,
you know, the industry 4.0 the
fourth industrial revolution,
right, that it's, yeah, it's
rapid technology and stuff like
that. And that's where we are
right now. And, you know, I like
to think at the Rec Foundation,
we were slightly ahead of the
curve as far as developing
programs for the fourth
industrial revolution, right for
industry 4.0. But it's not in
the future anymore. It's here
now smack smart factories are
here. Now, artificial
intelligence is here. Now, you
know, data learning is here.
Now, all those things are here,
there when you when you type in
something in your search bar,
and all sudden it does a profile
on you. Those are technology
jobs, that is the industry 4.0.
And, you know, and so we need to
make sure that we're not
preparing students for the
future jobs, we're preparing
them for the jobs that are here
now. And it's just going to tend
to continue to grow. And again,
it's not just factories, it's
just not manufacturing. It's
agriculture. For example, I
mean, if you've ever gone into a
dairy farm, and I've been to
many, many dairy farms growing
up in rural Pennsylvania, they
have some of the most advanced
technology and it's been there
forever. I mean, they would, you
know, or the cows are being fed,
right, you know, or how's the
quality of the milk and stuff
like that? And of course,
military, right. That's the
military's high tech now, and
we're very, very proud that the
junior JROTC army JROTC chose
the REC foundation to be one of
their partners. And it's not
about people joining charity
See, as engineers, it's about
these students building our
robots programming our robots,
building our job, drones, flying
our drones, they're just giving
them the basic skill set. So
when these students enlist in
the military, they have the
skill sets to use the modern
tanks and, and to do all that
type of stuff. It's we're here
now industry 4.0 is here now.
And we're just one of many
organizations out there that are
trying to make sure that our
students are ready. And I think
that, because of our model, we
keep prices affordable and
accessible. And I think we have
a really, really good model,
which is why we're growing so
quickly.
Audrow Nash: What what
explicitly in terms of skills
and like, how explicitly do you
see the REC program,
contributing to preparing people
for the jobs you were
mentioning, like maybe setting
up a camera or whatever it might
be.
Dan Mantz: So I do think in our
program, you learned some hands
on tech skills. I do, I think,
you know, you'd learn
programming, you learn, you
know, without even know you're
learning math, you're learning
about gear ratios, and torque
and some of those things. So
you're learning some, some
technical skills, but what our
program really, really does, in
my opinion, and many programs
like ours is we're really
teaching the soft skills. And
you hear more and more people
talking about the soft skills,
but our data shows that students
coming out of the program to the
soft skills. So let me step back
and say what that is. So
students that are in our
program, really learn how to
communicate, to be successful in
our programming, you have to
communicate with your teammates,
you have to communicate to your
coach and you have to
communicate with the teams
you're playing against a force.
So you learn communication, you
learn problem solving, and
troubleshooting. I mean, that's
a skill set. No matter what you
do. In our program, you are
learning how to troubleshoot and
to solve problems. And I think
that's really, really clear. And
you're and you're learning the
perseverance, and you're
learning patience. So all these
skills aren't necessarily
technical skills, but they're
what employers really, really
want. I myself, I used to hire
lots of engineers, I didn't
always hire the engineer that
had the highest GPA. I hired
engineers that were good
communicators and good problem
solvers, because I could teach
them the tech skills, right? I
could teach them that. But I
really had a harder time
teaching people how to
communicate and troubleshoot and
stuff like that. So I feel with
with very strong confidence, and
the data shows that the the
universities that study our
students, the data shows that
students in our programs come
out with advanced soft skills,
they really are good
troubleshooters, good
communicators good problem
solvers.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it's funny to
me, it's almost ironic, in a
sense that it's the whole, the
mission is to increase stem
engagement. And then the big
outcome is increasing soft
skills, which is not exactly
stem to me, but very, very
important.
Dan Mantz: Yeah, that's actually
very insightful. And four and a
half years of doing these,
you're the first person that's
pointed those out, and
internally, my own staff has
actually stepped back and, and I
do think you'll see us tweak
our, our mission and vision to
emphasize that more. And there's
a lot of other robotics
organizations out there. You
know, I joke that we're the
largest, but we're not the best
known. But I would say that all
the other robotics organizations
out there would all say that the
STEM skills is what the students
get most from our program. I
mean, literally, the data is in
the 90%. You know, you talk to
coaches, you talk to parents,
you talk to employers, and, you
know, 90% of our students have
good communication skills, you
know, 97% demonstrate problem
solving. It's the data is
remarkable. And we can teach a
lot of the skills, but we giving
them that infrastructure, that
foundation of the good problem
solving and communication skills
are so important. And again, I
don't want to hand wave. You
know, I joke how many students
in our program, learn about four
bar link systems and gear ratios
and torque, they do learn
technical stuff, too. And, you
know, and then if you do drones,
if you're in any one of our
drones, programs, you're
learning a lot about physics and
aerodynamics, and lift and stuff
like that, too. So
Audrow Nash: yeah, definitely.
Not too. Well, kind of to play
devil's devil's advocate, but
not to, I don't know, just just
out of curiosity, is robotics
the best way to teach these soft
skills? Or why is it well suited
for this? That's kind of like
one of the big underlying value
adds of this kind of structure?
Dan Mantz: Yeah, you know, and I
have been asked that question
before. And, first of all,
you'll never hear me say
robotics is the only way to do
it. I mean, if I would have felt
that way, we wouldn't have
started drones programs, and we
wouldn't started our factory
automation competition, right.
So there are other programs, but
I think the reason that robotics
is so effective, and the reason
that there's other robotics
programs out there, is because
you Start with a concept. You
have a challenge that you're
trying to meet, and you start
with a concept. So then you
design and you build. But then
you start competing. And whether
you're competing with somebody
to score points, or whether
you're competing against
somebody to truly win and lose,
the big brings up the fun part.
And I think sometimes we don't
talk about the fun part. And
that's why robotics is so it's
so effective at doing this,
because it's a lot of fun. If
you go to a robotics
competition, kids are dancing
and laughing and making friends
and stuff like that. So. So
that's why I think robotics is
is one of the great platforms to
teach these skills. It's not the
only one out there, though, I
think people that tells you that
it is aren't being genuine. But
I do think it's one of the good
ones. And honestly, with the REC
Foundation, our price models
good too. And we offer all the
educator resources for free. If
you go to our website, and you
want to know how to teach gear
ratios, we have stem labs
available for the teachers to
learn this. And really night.
And so that's really, really
important is to make sure that
the entry level I mean, we have
what we call educator training.
And it's not to teach the
teachers to become roboticist.
Right? It's to help them get
over the intimidation factor. So
the not afraid of it, right. So,
you know, in our program, the
teachers really just need to be
facilitators, because the
students will embrace the
technology and, and students are
a genius, right? They go on to
YouTube. So if there's an early
season competition in China, or
Singapore and Australia, and
when school starts in the US in
mid August or early September,
these students have already
scoped out some of the good
robots from other countries. And
And honestly, people say, well,
don't you have a convergence of
design. And some of our games we
do to get convergence of design,
right, at the end of the year, a
lot of the robots look the same.
But that's real world, too. You
know, I've spent 21 years at
FANUC robotics and a six axis
robot that does palletizing, or
does welding or something like
that, they kind of look the
same. I mean, they look a little
bit different here and there.
It's what's behind the scenes.
It's the kinematics, and it's
the sensors and the speed that
really make the difference. So I
don't really care that much that
the robots start looking the
same after a year, it's real
life. But those students that
have figured out how to program
better and how to utilize their
sensors better, they're gonna
probably have the top performing
robots.
Audrow Nash: That's very
interesting. Yeah. How do you so
can you tell me a bit about the
pandemic, and like how you use
simulation, and all of this?
Yeah, so
Dan Mantz: so we made a decision
during the pandemic, that we
weren't just going to become
virtual. Now Vex did an
incredible job, developing
virtual resources, their Vex
code, and teaching kids how to
program and their virtual
robotics that they gave to the
community, we're free, we're
amazing. That was for so many
teachers for, you know, hundreds
of 1000s of teachers out there.
And for the millions of students
that learn how to program during
the pandemic, because the
virtual, that was a lifesaver.
But at the Rec Foundation, we
firmly believe that hands on as
part of our program, it's not
just virtual. And there's a lot
of companies out there that have
transitioned or like you can
virtually build a robot or a
drone, and compete virtually,
but we actually believe the
design process, which includes
building a robot and includes
using the tools, using your
hands, putting things together
things breaking is vital. So
while we offered virtual
programs, we really went for a
remote strategy. And since so
many, you know, we when you have
a program as large as we do,
there's Vex parts all over the
world, right? So teachers found
a way to get the parts to their
students, and they built robots,
and we connected them, you know,
you did have to have a field.
But we also made it very simple
Do It Yourself field that you
could build with plywood, you
know, and, and then you needed a
camera. But most laptops have a
camera and we basically develop
the infrastructure to connect
these. So one of my favorite
things in my entire career.
Definitely one of my favorite
parts about 2021 was we had live
remote Vex worlds. So we're
still at the point of the
pandemic where people couldn't
get together and large. So we
had a lot of in person state
championships even during the
pandemic, but we couldn't have
effects worlds with 1000s and
1000s of teams and 10s of 1000s
of students, right. So we did
this live remote technology. And
one of my favorite days is I was
watching a match. And we have
this big screen setup and we had
six divisions and in the
divisions we had like I think it
was 16 Different countries
represented. So you saw a team
in China playing a team in Texas
and a team from Japan, a team
from the UK, and where the
fields were set up was amazing.
We had field setup in bedrooms,
we had field setup and empty
libraries. We had field setup
and Hall Ways we had a field set
up in the outside tent, New
England where they weren't
allowed to have indoor events in
basements and garages and in
some traditional schools, too,
right? So, and here we are all
these teams were still playing
with and against each other
because we decided to do it
remotely and not virtually.
Audrow Nash: That's so cool.
What do you so
Dan Mantz: I agree with you, but
Audrow Nash: why hands on? Like,
what's the, what's the big
reason for that?
Dan Mantz: I, you know, that's,
I probably need to get some data
behind this too, although I know
we have. And I just don't have
it handy right here. But I think
the hands on reinforces the
learning. So it's easy to say,
Okay, I'm going to put two
different gears together for
speed or torque or power, and
you do it in software, or you do
it in CAD and stuff like that.
And you see it that way, versus
when you actually do it on a
real robot and you put them
together, and then you change a
gear, and it goes faster or
slower, it's stronger. So I
think it demonstrates what
you're learning in the
classroom. I don't think, you
know, project based learning is
fundamentally what I believe on
hands on learning, because you
can learn it in the classroom.
And then when you do, it
reinforces what you learn.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, I totally
agree. I think from from my
perspective, like one of the
reasons I really liked
programming is because I can try
things very quickly. And I can
immediately see where my idea is
not complete. But I think that
that took a while of learning
how to program. But if you're
playing with gears and things,
or you're trying different
things, you can immediately see
if the results are working. Like
if it's doing what you expect,
and if not, it's a great
opportunity for learning. So
intuitively, it seems to me that
hands on is probably the best
way for learning and probably
the best way for getting
everyone involved. Because the
results kind of speak for
themselves. And it's not that
you have to follow an abstract
programming language that is
hard to understand for people
who are beginning. So physical
makes sense to me.
Dan Mantz: Yeah, I absolutely
agree with you. And, and, you
know, coding is a great way
because I actually started my
career as a controls engineer.
So I've done a lot of
programming myself. And in our
program, we have the autonomous
so even in our, our elementary
programs, we don't start the
matches with autonomous but we
have a programming factor like
so one minute, it's 100%
programming based, but what a
great way to learn programming,
you build your robot and say,
You need to go, you know, shoot
some balls without driving it,
right. So you learn a sensor,
you scoop up the ball, and you
shoot it right. And the fact of
a developing your mechanism is
the mechanical spa. And the
electrical is the sensor, but
the programming is is how you
make it all work together. And
whether you just say, go forward
for this distance or go forward
at this or whether you actually
use the sensors. It's an
iterative programming, and I
think the programming skill set
from our students is the one
area I've seen the most
advancement, that the skill set
of programming from four years
ago when I first joined the REC
Foundation, that's the biggest
area of increase I've seen.
Audrow Nash: That's so
interesting. Yeah. So one thing
that I haven't heard much in the
whole program is any, like open
source related things or use
have, you mentioned that you
have libraries involved with the
coding, but I imagine that
they're developed buybacks, or
it's kind of like a closed
source kind of.
Dan Mantz: And so you know, our
program tends to be a little bit
more closed source. But that
doesn't mean we don't have open
source libraries is a good
example, the community will,
will develop libraries and share
them. And that's a good example,
open source on CAD designs, for
example, and some things like
that, but we're not giving out
the the designs of the motor so
that you can design your own
motor, for example. And we do
that for very practical reasons.
One is level playing field. And
so many stem competitions, the
more money you have, the better
you're going to do. And by
everybody starting with the same
parts, it does level the playing
field. Now I'm not naive, if you
have more funds, you can buy
more motors, more sensors, build
more iterative designs and stuff
like that. And you're probably
going to, at the end of the
season, maybe have a better
robot, but the concept of using
one manufacturer's product
really does level. The other
thing is it keeps the cost. It
really, really keeps the costs
down because we're talking
volume here, right? So if every
robot out there is using eight
of the same motor, and we have
30,000 teams, you're mass
producing those motors if it's
open source, you know it's true,
you might have somebody comes up
with a lower cost motor for one
application, but overall, it's
going to be a more expensive
product by the end of the season
and there's a lot A lot of
robotics competitions out there,
they're, they're open source,
and they say it's cheaper. But
when you talk to the teams, they
ultimately spend way more money
in the
Audrow Nash: interesting. I
would wonder also, just, and
maybe this is the students being
a little too young for this kind
of thing, but I feel free to
really get a lot done, it's very
useful to understand how to work
in kind of, in the open source
software world, where you can go
and grab this one thing, learn
about it quickly, and then
integrate it into what you're
doing, and then grow, but grab
this other thing, and you can
see the value of testing and all
of the my Siri going off all of
the, it's just there's a lot
that is very useful to learn
there. That's very practical, I
think. And I wonder if that
would be something that'd be
useful to fold into the
education for the students.
Dan Mantz: And I think we have
that with libraries already.
Right. So, you know, a lot of
times the people that are
providing libraries are just
providing a compiled version,
and maybe not the open source,
build on what to do, right. But
at the end of the day, you know,
with Vex code, you can develop
in blocks, and then you can
switch it, you can actually
switch it over to text and see
how the code works. And to me,
there's no better way to learn
programming, I wish I would have
had that in the 90s when I got
started, right? So back then it
was pseudo code, right? You did
pseudo code, and then you wrote
code behind it? Well, you can
pull in a library. And if the
source code is available, that
you can see how it works. And so
yes, there's a practical reason
to use the Vex code, but you're
still learning C plus, plus,
you're still learning the
languages out there. Again, this
goes back to because I have
these discussions a lot. And I
do understand both sides of the
argument. But for our program,
it's the bell curve. And I
remind educators, I remind my
staff all over again, it's like
we're not appealing to the top
10%, we're trying to appeal to
the entire bell curve, and
authority. I think the way the
model of our program is actually
the most approachable and
sustainable model for most
students. And, you know, my kids
did robotics, I have four
children, three of the four did
robotics. Two of them did Vex
and, and two of them did other
programs, two that were had more
machining involved, for example,
and stuff like that. And they
have the resources at their
schools to do it. But they also
had much, much larger budgets.
They had engineering mentors,
computer science mentors, our
program is so that the teacher,
the classroom educator, or the
parent can be the coach, and the
resources are free. So by having
everybody start from the same
level playing field that really
works better for reaching more
students, but I don't pretend
that our program, you know, for
some of those very advanced
competitions out there, that
we're offering that same level
of engineering, I've never, you
know, pretend that we do again,
but when you look at the 1
million students in our program,
I think, reaching more students,
Audrow Nash: definitely, yeah,
it makes sense. Because you're
trying to basically supply the
most it's your it's your
mission. You're trying to get
the most people interested in
STEM, correct?
Dan Mantz: Yeah, you just said
it for me. Thank you so much.
Exactly. So it
Audrow Nash: makes sense. Your
approach makes complete sense,
given that mission, and it's
nice to see you guys be very
mission driven. That that
informs a lot of your decisions.
Yeah. So now, tell me a bit
about your background.
Dan Mantz: Okay. Well, so I have
a lot of passion for world and
underserved communities, because
I grew up in rural Pennsylvania.
You know, I was, you know,
definitely solid middle class,
but I grew up we had 30 acres,
you know, a lot of my neighbors
had 10 Out 1520 acres, but I was
a country boy, my school was,
you know, 18 miles away. I was
in a graduating class of 180.
But I was really good at math
and science. So I had a teacher
that said, you should look at
going into engineering. I'm from
other parts of Pennsylvania,
where Lee Iacocca and maybe much
of your audience will know who
he was, but he ran Chrysler, he
was at Ford and he went to
Chrysler, and he turned around
Chrysler from bankruptcy. And,
and, but a lot of my friends
that I grew up with that we
built dirt bikes, and tree forts
and stuff like that. I went into
skilled trades, right? They
went, they became machine tool
operators. They became HVAC
technicians, they became diesel
mechanics, and I was the only
one that really went to college.
So, at that point, I never felt
that to have a successful
career, you had to have a four
year degree. It just was I had
the aptitude and you know, my
parents were able to help me out
some and so I went to college in
Michigan, I went to at the time,
it was called GMI. It's now
called Kettering University.
It's in Flint, Michigan, but it
was a co op school and to this
day, it's the only full time Co
Op university in the United what
does that mean? So it means that
you would go to school for three
months and then you would work
for or your sponsor, which in my
case was General Motors. You
worked for three months. So you
did that for five years. So as a
five year program, three months
of school, three months of work,
it was year round. We used to
get a week off for Christmas and
a week off in the summer. And so
yeah, I've been working, working
in industry since I was before I
was 18 years old. But with the
Co Op program, your freshman
year, right out of school, you
don't have a lot of skills, but
you're already working with very
professional engineers. And, and
you're with I worked for General
Motors, CPC, Chevrolet, Pontiac,
the candidate division for my
entire Co Op career, and I was
doing very advanced projects by
the time I was a junior, and so
my junior senior and my thesis
year, I was really, really
working on that stuff. So when I
graduated GMI Kettering
graduates tend to get really
good starting salaries because
we have so much work experience.
And so but I was at GM and a
friend of mine was at FANUC. And
he says fanic needs controls
engineers. I'm like, well,
that's not my background, you
know? And he's like, Yeah, but
you were like, the best coder in
our fraternity right? here that
what everybody answered it. So
I'm like, Yeah, controls is a
lot of coding. So I went to
FANUC. As a controls engineer, I
traveled the world. I went to
factories and dozens of
countries and learn control
systems. And, you know, you do
that for seven years, we started
raising a family and my wife
says, It's time to be home more.
I went into project and program
management and started
developing the next generation
of robotics. And I, you know, I
was fortunate enough to be on a
couple of patterns. My, my
expertise was pneumatics,
believe it or not, that was kind
of where I really thrive,
controls and pneumatics. But I
did that for five years. And
then I started doing the
management training. And so by
the by 20th, year at FANUC, I
had been Director of Product
Development for five years. So I
had mechanical engineers, and
electrical engineers, they all
worked for me application
engineers, and we're developing
great, great things. And we were
doing AI and we were learning
about collaborative robots. And
but I was getting really tired.
You know, I did a lot of
traveling, I've been to a lot of
factories, and a friend of mine
was down in Texas. He said that
they were looking for a
president of a company called
rack solutions. He said he
thought it'd be a good fit. I
traveled to Texas, I got the
job. And I went from high tech,
very advanced robotics, to sheet
metal design and manufacturing.
But it was one of the best
things that could have ever
happened to me. Because I
realized how important
manufacturing, I mean, we always
hear that impact, you know,
manufacturing is important and
FANUC had initiative called Save
Our factory, that, you know, by
using robots, you're actually
keeping the factories
competitive, so that we can
compete against the, you know,
the rest of the world. Well,
here I was in a sheet metal
company competing against China
and Europe and stuff like that.
So it was a great experience for
me, I started learning the
business side, you know, p&l and
stuff like that. And I started
coaching robotics. And
so I started coaching robotics.
And my good friend was the
president of VEX robotics. And
because people knew that we were
friends, they started saying,
hey, go tell Paul, this, go tell
Tony, this, go tell Bob this,
right. And so I kept going to
those guys. And I kept saying
that, hey, this is some of the
feedback we're getting from the
community. And finally, there
were I think, I must have
frustrated, like, you need to
join our board. So I joined the
board of the robotics education
competition foundation, I dug in
really hard for six months,
because you know, I've been
hearing with the community
thought of it right. And I
thought we could do better. So
after a couple of months, like I
gave a report to the board on
things I thought we could do
better financially, and
organizationally and product
wise. And the board asked if I
would take over as CEO, and that
was five years ago, in June, so
the first week of June, five
years ago. And it's been
fantastic. And as I started the
conversation, I was happy to
take the job I had, you know, I
had my doubts because I'd never
been for not for profit. But I
said I wanted to have the
ability to work on workforce
development, not just be stem.
And I wanted the ability to to
branch outside of just ground
robots to and the board was kind
enough to say, Sure, go for it.
If you have time, go for it. I
think they thought it'd be so
busy with the VEX robotics
competitions. I wouldn't have
time. But we've built up a
really good staff here and we've
expanded so 21 years of
industrial robotics from from
the control side to product
development. And I've gone full
circle to now robotics,
education and competitions.
Audrow Nash: It's quite a path.
Yeah. How did so how do you? How
do you see programs like yours,
like REC, helping, or how does
it fit with the educational
program? In your mind?
Dan Mantz: Yeah, I think we're
really Be very complimentary, I
think, again, because of Vex,
and for the win and Dell, and so
many of our other partners, they
developed curriculum content.
But I firmly believe that to
reinforce what teachers are
teaching in the classroom,
especially technology, pre
engineering, physics, math, you
know, you can teach it in the
classroom, but like we talked
about earlier, when you can
demonstrate it and have hands
on, it reinforces it, and it
goes the same way. You can't
just start a robotics program
and just build robots. It's
complementary to your math
programs and stuff like that in
the classroom. So I think we
really, really work well. One of
the things we can do at the Rec
Foundation, one of the huge
values that we have is, when I
first started the REC
Foundation, we gave out grants,
but it was always equipment
grant, that was the only grant
that you got from the REC
Foundation was a robot kit,
right. But we've listened to the
teaching community, the
education community, and they
need more than that they need
resources. And the beauty of
this position is we've been able
to go to the north of Grumman
and the Googles and the Tesla's
and now we're able to get
funding for them for stipends.
And for other resources. So now
we can go back to the teachers
in the classroom. And we're
going to like, if you're going
to do a robotics team, we can
give you $1,000 or $2,000. And
we can give you other you know,
continuing tech training and
stuff like that. So we don't
just give kits anymore, we still
give a lot of robot kits out as
grants, but we give out so much
more. And that's where we
really, really complement each
other. Because let's face it in
the United States, football
coaches, basketball coaches,
they all get paid stipends to be
coaches, why not robotics
coaches, and I think other
organizations were really
challenging that. And there's
been a huge, huge increase in
our sponsors and government
grants, giving us money that we
can give stipends to robotics
teachers.
Audrow Nash: That's really
awesome. I like that idea a lot.
It's, I mean, it definitely
makes sense. Like, it's crazy,
if it's basketball coaches, and
football coaches getting
stipends. And then the robotics
team, I mean, especially if
you're bringing in someone who's
having to learn these things,
and be very involved or, like,
it's very nice if they can get a
stipend to to just kind of help
out with it. Because it might be
at the expense of other areas in
their
Dan Mantz: life. Educators
getting rich on their on their
stipend, right. But the thing
is, we don't want them to cost
them money, right. So I'm sure
most of our stipends just cover
the gas and pizza and the spare
parts that they buy. And
nobody's actually increasing
their net worth because of the
stipends. But at least it's not
costing them more money. And
again, it just doesn't as the
United States for us to continue
to evolve. And of course, we're
a global foundation. So all the
worlds but particularly in the
United States, you see a
difference. People ask me
geographically, what's different
about teams in the Northeast or
the south of the Pacific
Northwest? Well, you know,
there's a lot of programs in the
Northeast that have been paying
their robotics coaches and
teachers for a long time, right.
And they're very, very stable,
and they have excellent
students. And then you have
emerging areas in the United
States that never thought about
paying a robotics coach, they
never even thought about having
a robotics team. In Alabama is a
great example. When I joined the
REC Foundation, there was
probably 100 teams in Alabama.
And it's almost at 1000. Now
because our staff really did a
great job of working with
teachers and educators. And then
the detail Alabama Department of
Education started investing
money. The first year was
250,000, this past year 850,000.
and other organizations in
Alabama started, you know,
Hyundai, again, not a sponsor to
the REC foundation directly. But
Hyundai is making sure that
every elementary middle and high
school in Montgomery, Alabama
has a robotics team and you have
score is making sure these
teachers are getting their
training and the Department of
Education is giving stipends. So
they all build together. And now
Alabama, has got an incredible
robotics program. And guess
what, there's a lot of factories
in Alabama, a lot of automotive
and other factories, and they
need the students. So some
places have been committed to
doing this for a lot longer. You
know, and you know, Michigan is
an example of a state that's had
robotics programs for 25 years,
and you have other parts of the
country that are just starting
to get into it.
Audrow Nash: What do you So you
mentioned that there were a few
schools that were adding this
into the main curriculum, not
just as an as an
extracurricular. Can you tell me
a bit about that?
Dan Mantz: Yeah, sure that I
would say that pendulum is
really increasing, you know,
maybe five years ago 10%. And
that's at least 30%. Now, I'm
not talking condition panels
you're at if schools or schools
are actually whether they call
it in manufacturing, or whether
they call it engineering, or
technology. I mean, I've heard
all All right, so uh, technology
clicking, but I was at a
competition this past weekend,
and the top teams there. If they
start as freshmen, they can take
technology. And then they take
technology to then engineering
one, and engineering two. And
they meet every single day just
like you do for History or
English or whatever. But they
have their technology class, and
they use Vex and, and they start
by building simple mechanisms.
And then they learn about
motors. And then next thing you
know, you're a sophomore, and
you're building more complex
stuff, because they do it every
single day for an hour a day. By
the time they're senior, these
kids are really, really good.
And most of them are actually
going and getting engineering
degrees. But I have one student
that has a job at John Deere
lined up, he's going right to
John Deere out of high school,
right? He's going to get his
industry certification and go
and Tesla has similar programs,
right? Where some of these
students, why go into debt,
right? Why go work for Tesla and
John Deere and no pay for you to
take classes at your community
college or your four year
university. So they're paying
for you. They're paying you a
salary to do the job, and
they're paying you to get your
certifications and your degree.
And next thing you know, you
have a two or four year degree
but back to your original
question. Schools themselves
know that we need to do a better
job for the students and make
sure they're prepared for the
workforce. So more and more
students, more and more schools
are investing in technology.
It's kind of full circle. You
know, when I was in high school,
we had vocational programs, the
HVAC, the machine shop, etc. And
then we got away and then we
said everybody needs to go to
college. And now we're kind of
going back and saying, Man, all
these people that repaired our
air conditioners, or did diesel
mechanics, they're all getting
ready to retire. We have nobody
coming behind them. So these
schools, the government's
they're reinvesting in these
programs. But now it's not just
HVAC and diesel mechanics. Now
it's robot technician, etcetera.
Hmm, that's really what we at
the RSC Foundation, we just work
really, really closely with
these educators so that they
have the tools so that they can
bring these programs to their
classes.
Audrow Nash: What do you think
the so you think the future of
education is, or a future of
universities will be that fewer
people go to actually get like a
Bachelors of Science and
something and maybe more people,
it'll it would be more like,
say, somewhere is some places in
Europe that have more vocational
schools and this kind of thing,
you think that education will
start to lean that way? Yeah, I
Dan Mantz: think I think the
data is trending that way, I'm
going to be really careful here,
because we have a lot of
university partners, right. A
lot of great universities we
partner with, but I think we're
already seeing declining
enrollment in so many schools.
And it's not a secret that they
expect a lot of colleges and
universities to fail in the
future. Because it's just gotten
so expensive, you know, for
students to go. So I do think
you're going to see these
alternative career paths instead
of, again, the internship, the
externship program that Tesla
did is a great model where the
graduates start, you start the
program, when you're in high
school, and you get experience
working on the factory floor,
you're working in the shops, you
get paid. And then again, if you
want to go get an interesting
certification, they pay for
that, then you start taking
classes at a two year school, I
think you're going to see more
and more organizations do that.
And I think you're just going to
see people make financial
decisions that make sense. And I
think you're gonna there is
going to be some type of
consolidation. And I think our
universities will step up, and I
think our community colleges are
fantastic in this country. It's
really one of those gems that we
have, that the rest of the world
doesn't, you know, because maybe
we don't have tech programs in
high school like they do in
Europe. But we do have these
community colleges, and we have
a lot of programs, you know,
that are supported in community
colleges. And that's a good way
for students to get the skill
set.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. I know
very little about the community
colleges and what kind of things
they offer. But it you're saying
it helps people get vocational
skills or Yeah,
Dan Mantz: I mean, you get you
get your you know, and some pass
you get your baseline to go to a
four year university gets your
your general classes out of the
way you get your, your math,
your sciences, your history, and
like in Texas, if you go to what
a accredited community college
in Texas, the four year
universities have to take those
credits, right. And there's a
lot of states that have similar
programs. But so many community
colleges that we work with now
have industrial automation are
our technology programs where
they're literally teaching the
skills and after two years, the
students earn certifications and
then they go get the jobs.
Right. So community colleges are
really the government you know,
Department of Defense is
investing in community ecologist
because they know that's a
really good way for us to train
our workforce.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. Yeah,
it makes complete sense. What do
you so we're beginning to wrap
up? What do you think, for kind
of the future of education and
programs like wreck? Do you
think it'll be enough? For all
of the help? Like, will we be
able to provide a good number of
workers for the shortages? Or
just how do you think of things
going forward?
Dan Mantz: Well, we're gonna
make a debt, if nothing else,
right, we're gonna make, we're
gonna help and the REC
foundation, you know, we have a
lot of great programs, there's
other great not for profits out
there, too. And you have, like,
you know, Apple is investing in
their own education programs.
And there's other companies that
do it. So I think if
collectively, we all work
together, we are going to
address the issue, but it's
gonna take some time, it's gonna
take some time to, to retrain
our teachers, you know, so that
they have the skill sets to
teach this, it's going to take
time for our industries to adapt
to a different type of model,
how they, how they employ their
employees. Now, I don't want to
get too philosophical here, but
you know, students in this
country, know prefer playing
sports and prefer doing video
games and stuff like that, you
know, and, and I've traveled,
I've been fortunate, I've
traveled across the world, and
then over 50 countries, and
there's other cultures where
they emphasize academics, and
especially tech, and we're not
there in this country yet. So
it's going to be an entire
cultural shift between education
between the government, between
private companies, public
companies, and not for profits,
we're all going to have to work
together. And there's great,
great organizations out there,
like, you know, the REC
foundation belongs to arm out of
Pittsburgh, advanced robotics
and manufacturing. And they do a
great job of bringing government
private industry for year to
year and not for profits
together to tackle this problem.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. What do
you have anything to share for
people that are interested in
either getting involved as like
students or interested in
getting involved, as someone who
facilitates it or just learning
more? Any resources?
Dan Mantz: I mean, the best, the
easiest thing to do is I always
ask people go to our website,
it's robotics, education.org,
again, robotics education.org.
And on the landing page, it's
like, Are you new to robotics,
and they need you just navigate
the website, you know, VEX
robotics, they also have a
great, great website for
educators. I mean, they just
have so many amazing resources
that are free. So go to VEX
robotics, or go to robotics,
education.org. Those are always
good things. You can always
Google, you know, how do I how
do I start a robotics team, and
our website has those responses.
And that's the best way to do
it. On our website, we have a
map of the world. And literally,
when you click the country, it
tells you who the REC foundation
person for that country is or if
you click the state that tells
you who the event site is and
who the team site is. And then
we have things like online
challenges, too. So maybe this
year one, you don't want to jump
into starting a robotics team.
But you can do online
challenges. And some of them are
like CAD based, some of them are
about diversity and inclusion
programs like girl powered, but
there's different ways to do it
there. And then there's also
grants, you know, we know that
cost is a barrier of entry. So
we have an entire page on
grants. And then for the
students out there, you know,
the Ric foundation gets close to
60 million. Well, we don't give
it directly, but our university
partners give $60 million in
scholarships for students. So
all those resources available by
the website. So if you're an
educator, come to our site or go
to the web site, if you're
really wanting to learn about
starting a team and how we can
help you in the classroom, go to
our website.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Alright,
it's been a pleasure speaking
with you.
Dan Mantz: I've enjoyed it so
much. And, again, if anybody
here wants to reach out to me
directly, my email was, Dan
underscore man's robotics.
education.com. And I take I
always respond, sometimes they
don't get to it in the first day
or even the first couple of
days. But I'm always, always,
always happy to reach out. I'll
see if I can share this on the
camera real quick. I give this
back and it's backwards, but
it's robotics education.org I
just realized I said calm. So
Dan, underscore man's at
robotics. education.org. And me
or someone from my team will be
happy to help you navigate,
which I can at times can be
terrifying. But I guarantee you
it's rewarding. If you talk to
the people that are involved in
our program, they'll tell you,
we're really making a difference
and it's really rewarding for
them.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Thank you,
Dan. And everyone thank you for
having me thanks for listening
to this conversation with Dan
Mance thank you again to our
founding sponsor open robotics
See you next time