Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Jason
Richards. Jason is the CEO of
Daxbot, which makes a
charismatic robot for food
delivery. We talk about deck
spots delivery robot, their
crowdfunding campaign, that spot
revenue model, how Jason works
with lawmakers to have robots on
the sidewalks. And Jason teases
their real time operating
system. DaxOS. This is the Sense
Think Act podcast. And thank you
to our founding sponsor, Open
Robotics. Now, here's my
conversation with Jason
Richards. Would you introduce
yourself?
Jason Richards: Sure, you bet.
My name is Jason Richards. And I
am the CEO of Daxbot.
Audrow Nash: Would you tell me a
bit about Daxbot?
Jason Richards: Sure, yeah. So
Daxbot is a robotics company
that started out at a research
and development lab back 2015,
the founder, started a couple
other companies, pretty
successful guy, and decided that
he wanted to create a research
and development lab to, you
know, what is the next wave of
technology that we can get in
front of, you know, and so, in
2015, one of the thoughts was,
okay, well, we need robots to be
able to do things. And there's
plenty of plenty of robots in
the, you know, in the workforce,
you know, more in factories and
things like that. But how do we
bridge the gap into the next
generation of robotics, where
you have robots that are on the
streets, similar to, you know,
iRobot? Before the robots go bad
kind of thing? It's like the
movie being able to say, yeah,
like,
Audrow Nash: not the company
backs the back. Yeah.
Jason Richards: Not No, no, not
that company. No, yeah, the
movie, right. So you can tell a
robot, Hey, pick up that, and go
watch that window. And robots
are smart enough to go and do it
in human space. So that was the
idea. And looking at what things
could be most helpful out of the
chute, is the delivery seemed
like a natural first thing that
a robot could do that would be
pretty simple, you know, simple
tasks that would be helpful to
humans. So so that's where the
idea came from. And so as of
recently, we just got through
restructuring companies now
we're dexpot, Inc. and now we're
able to go after and
commercialize and, and have
robots now being deployed to
different states around the
country where you before? Yeah,
so before is Nova dynamics. So
Nova dynamics was the research
and development incubator. And
they've got several projects,
Dax as the robot was kind of the
big one. And so with that
platform, we knew that at some
point, it has to move out of the
r&d Lab and into its own entity
that can be commercialized and
become something Gotcha. So. So
that was the next step. So as of
last year, when you know, all
the research and development
last year, when COVID hit, it
was a great opportunity to start
getting robots out in the field,
in our local hometown, because
restaurants, people aren't
coming to, you know, restaurants
are closing their doors. But
people aren't wanting to see
people. So it seemed like a
great space. And it was, you
know, for that beta test, being
able to take robots that we have
go to the restaurants, pick up
food, and then ticket to
people's houses, you know, all
without seeing a human was
really highlighted the need for
this type of technology. And it
is well received. And it was a
great, great beta test for us.
So January of this year
realizing okay, we've got a
product that is ready to go
awesome. So commercialized and
Audrow Nash: here we go. Hell
yeah. Tell me can you describe
what Dex looks like?
Jason Richards: Yeah, so Dax is
a robot? It's about right. Yeah,
yeah, if you're, if you're
watching the video, you can see
the one behind and it's about
three foot tall, and white and
black, kind of a reverse tuxedo
type situation. And so you see,
you see, Dax has got a fully
articulated neck so that he's
able to look all around and look
up and down also has LED panel
eyes. So the eyes are able to be
expressive, you know, whether it
is being able to be hearts or
you know, I love you going to
sleep blinking, so that it has
some sort of emotional response
from another human. So that is
and then the, the cargo that's
the thing that everybody asks,
well, if it's the delivery
robot, where's the cargo bay,
and it's actually inside the
stomach. So what you think of
the stomach of this little
creature, for people that
haven't seen DAX before, I'd
encourage you to go, you could
check out DAX spot.com. You can
see pictures of him and that
kind of thing, but, but inside
the drawer, which is where his
stomach is, is where the payload
goes. And then inside that is,
you know, heating elements.
We've got to design for a
refrigerator so that we can do
that's cool pharmaceutical
delivery. Yeah, things that need
it, which is pretty. That was a
pretty astounding thing from the
engineers perspective to be able
to build a refrigerator Inside
the robot, obviously, it takes
up a lot of space with a
compressor and, and heat
exchange, especially in that
type of area. But fascinating,
and we did a lot of cool testing
with that one. But so that is is
Dax.
Audrow Nash: And so, to me, Dax,
I was gonna say refrigerator,
like a little like college dorm
freezer kind of thing. Right?
It's kind of looks like one of
those. And then it has this
articulated kind of like
hexagonal head that has the LED
lights on it. And that head is
on a neck that seems to have a
few degrees of freedom, which
I'm sure we'll talk more about
that later. And we can't see it
in the video now because of how
the cameras positioned. But DAX
is on tank treads, right? Yep,
gotcha. Correct. And to me, Dax
looks a lot like Wally without
arms. And like, you say, like,
the belly is where you store the
payload. So whatever you're
delivering, like in Wally Wally
was designed to have that trash
compactor there and its belly.
So it seems kind of similar to
me. Right. And the tank treads.
Yeah, these kinds of things.
Yeah, we,
Jason Richards: we joke about
the fact that Dax kind of looks
like Wally and Eve had a baby.
And that baby.
Audrow Nash: That is right,
because of the coloring. Yeah.
And the sleek design color in
the scheme. Yep. Yeah, yeah,
exactly.
Okay. Tell me a bit about the
neck. Or the head, I guess.
Yeah. Yeah.
Jason Richards: So the getting
the biggest piece that we wanted
to solve was, you know, the
human robot interaction piece.
There other than delivery
robots. There's a lot of people
that will ask about that, you
know, why? Essentially another
delivery robot. And it's it's
kind of funny because, you know,
Dax was built people are
familiar with starship, Dax and
starship started almost the
exact same time not familiar
with starship as far as what a
starship? Oh, yeah. So start.
Yeah, so starship is a delivery
robot on some college campuses.
And if you look up delivery
robots, if you just Google it,
you'll find you know, kiwi, bot,
and starship. And there's some
others. And essentially the
same, the design is exactly the
same. It's about it looks
essentially like a cooler with a
couple of wheels on it. And so
it has a payload and it's, it's
useful in some applications. But
with the the neck and the eyes,
it was more of, you know, how do
you create something that is
going to be accepted in human
pedestrian spaces. So so that's
where the idea of, you know,
articulating neck head, not
putting sensors all over the
place, and the founder, you
know, dexpot really wanted to
make sure that it wasn't creepy.
You know, there's, there's
plenty of really cool, like,
mechanically amazing feats that
people are coming up with, you
know, as far as like mechanics
of robots, you know, bipeds,
those types of things. But if
if, for example, you just saw,
you know, two legs, two robotic
legs running you down the
street, you'd think that
Armageddon was happening, I
mean, that that would be a
creepy thing. So wanting to make
something that would be accepted
in human space. So there's a lot
of work that went into that, of
how do we make a robot that
people want to have around? So
So delivery robots, most of them
have that design of a cooler on
wheels, and about two feet off
the ground. And it becomes an
annoyance for a lot of people,
because it's it's in the way,
similarly, people don't really,
people don't even want bicycles
on sidewalks, right? And it's a
human on that bicycle, but it's
annoying and pedestrian space.
And so they make bicycles
Audrow Nash: that cars have. And
so I don't know if it's quite
the same thing. I get that
they're also annoying, but
perhaps it's like, they go fast.
And there's the potential to
like, get hit by a bike
bicyclist or something like this
or them for to come out of
nowhere. Yeah. Whereas I don't
know that small tub robot would
be quite the same thing. Or what
do you think?
Jason Richards: No. Yeah, the
biggest piece had to do with
with visibility is not being you
know, not being able to see it.
If it's it knee height, it's
different than if it's it, you
know, waist height, or, you
know, shoulder catches.
Audrow Nash: So it's like a
mobile piece of furniture to
trip over if it's short, and
that could irritating. Okay.
Jason Richards: Yeah. Yeah. And
same way. I mean, you know,
people don't like skateboarders
on on sidewalk. Yeah. Again,
moving fast, though. Remote
Control often, yeah, some of it
could be moving fast. And it's
in a way it's becomes a tripping
hazard, that kind of thing. And
so the interesting thing with
Dax is that with all the testing
we've done on the HRIS side of
it, is you know, especially kids
love Dax, it's about the same
height and so they can give it a
hug, and it's looking them like
almost either with very cute and
with and with the neck itself.
And the reason that we didn't
want to creepy with sensors all
over the place, people ask,
well, it has 360 degree cameras
in it, for example. You know,
it's kind of an assumption a lot
of engineers have, it's like,
No, there's not 360 degree
cameras in it. And people always
want to know why it's like,
well, you don't have 360 degree
cameras and you know, you can
kind of hear that their stuff
behind you. And so you can, you
know, you have some sense and
awareness of what's around you.
But you're not a spider, right?
You don't have this spidey sense
where you can you know that
something's behind you. So in
the same way, that's where the
articulating that came from, you
know, you could have something
that that knows everything
around it in a 360 degree view,
or you have something that
actually is more like, you know,
more like a dog or a human,
where you actually have to turn
your neck around to see what is
actually going on. But yeah, and
so even those those pieces, it
gives it a feeling that it is
actually alive, instead of just
being a machine, which why not?
It actually is machine.
Audrow Nash: So I mean, I'm
thinking of this thing, where
it's like airplanes don't flap
their wings kind of thing. So I
mean, we can draw some
inspiration from biology. But
where do we end Drawing
inspiration? From biology?
Absolutely. And I wonder, I
would think it would be possible
to use cleverly hidden sensors
and to have the articulating
neck, but have the articulating
neck not necessarily tied to a
vision system. Why Why limit it
to having the vision system on
the articulating neck instead of
just having hidden sensors and
this kind of thing?
Jason Richards: Yeah, that's a
good question. I don't know,
the, the founder when he went
through all of this, there was a
lot of there was a lot of, you
know, reasoning and things like
that. And again, making it more
a phrase that we use around here
is anamorphic. You know, it's
not anamorphic. It's not an ad.
Cannon morphic. I don't know who
doesn't like thrupp amorphic are
more like a like a dog. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah, it seems more like
it's a pet than it is a machine.
Audrow Nash: So anamorphic. So
it's like anthropomorphic
animal. So when we assume but
with cane, but for things like
dogs, or whatever it might be,
okay, so it's a creature and has
some sort of intent when it
moves around the world or
whatever it might be. Right.
Jason Richards: Yeah, exactly.
And so one of the things, for
example, is, I believe one of
the stories I heard is that if
Dax you know, robot goes into a
situation and needs to go
backwards. You know, we as we as
humans, don't walk backwards,
right? We don't just like walk
backwards into into us, yes, we
will turn and say, Oh, here's
where we're going to go. And
then, you know, if we need to
have some field division in
front of us, we'll be looking
back and forth. So in the same
way, wanting to train, train the
robot, right train the neural
net, so that it's not just doing
things automatically. So it
actually is showing intent, that
oh, here's where I'm going. One
of the things that we've heard,
we actually, we live close to a
university, Oregon State
University. And one of in
starship, one of those
competitors is up there. And I
haven't heard, I haven't talked
to anybody around that really
likes them on campus. And the
reason for that is because it
has to do with intent. So the
device will drive up to a street
corner, and then stop. And then
all the other traffic, the cars
are like, What are you doing?
Yeah, what do I do? Yeah, is it
gonna cross? Am I gonna cross
there's no clarity? No, there's
no law about right of way. Yeah,
exactly. So there's sensors, no
signaling, there's, there's no
idea, you know, are you going to
go am I going to go and so it's,
you know, some of these devices
have been hit one guy hit by a
train that's been hit by a
truck, one's one into a train.
And so it's, you know, and it
has has plenty of sensors
onboard. You know, that's, you
know, with that one
specifically, it's, that's not
the problem. But because people
don't know what it's gonna do,
they don't have any, any idea
versus Dax will get to the
street corner, and like a human,
it will look at you, and it will
watch you and follow your
vehicle as it drives past. So
you know, oh, this thing sits
somewhere. And it's aware of
what's going on. And it cannot
its head, like, yes, you can go
Go ahead, or, you know, shake
its head so that people know,
Oh, you want me to go? Versus
you're gonna go right. And so
there was a lot of there was a
lot of thought and
intentionality into the neck.
Yeah, isn't just necessary for
the neck sake, but it's more for
communication, it looks one of
the design,
Audrow Nash: it looks to me. So
thinking of like the founders
perspective, and this kind of
thing, perhaps it had something
to do with making it so that so
I mean, if you have sensors
everywhere, and you can get a
really good rendering of the
world and this kind of thing.
You can design behavior that
uses that understanding of the
world. But in this case, you're
kind of constraining the
behavior of the robot to be
something that seems more
natural. In like, it has to go
and look behind it. There's
something if it's going to go
and back up or if it wants to,
like look both ways for the
street, you have to do that with
the head. And it almost so it
basically constrains the
developers to like, I don't know
program more lifelike behavior
in it so that it operates in the
world. I could see that being a
clever way of doing that kind of
thing.
Jason Richards: And for for
engineers, specifically,
mechanical engineers, they would
much prefer to have the device
to be a cooler, right? Just
right. Yeah, that's it, that's a
much simpler thing than a fully
articulating neck was dual pitch
motors. Right?
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Or just a
sensor information would be
probably more valuable.
Absolutely. The who cares if it
looks like a cooler, but I get
your meaning that for like,
sensors everywhere and full 3d
map of the whole environment
that it's in and this kind of
thing?
Jason Richards: Yeah. Yeah,
absolutely. And we, you know,
obviously, we got, you know,
that technology to be able to do
that, so that Dax is able to
learn in 3d space, and you know,
instead but, again, more similar
to, you know, a human if I'm
walking down the street, and
I've been down that street
before, I have an idea of what
to expect, right? I know,
there's a curb there. I know.
There's a telephone pole. I see.
Oh, there's a box there. I've
never seen that box before.
Okay. New information might not
be there tomorrow. Right? So
it's not something that that
really comes in. But because
everything is changing in such a
rapid space, again, on a factory
floor,
Audrow Nash: you mean in the
environment? Like walking
around?
Jason Richards: Right, yeah. And
environment or walking? Right.
If you're walking downtown, you
know, in a metropolitan area has
a lot of moving parts. It's
changing all the time. Yeah,
exactly. So so being able to
have something that is more
lifelike to be able to adapt in
that environment. And it seems
more natural in that
environment. Actually, pretty
interesting.
Audrow Nash: So what sensors are
on this robot on the Dax robot?
Jason Richards: Yeah, so despair
division is is one of the two it
has
Audrow Nash: a stereo that has
two cameras beneath the kind of
chin. Yes, something right below
the display. Right. And
Jason Richards: yeah, so yeah,
where you see the display of the
eyes is where that
Audrow Nash: just been, you
know, just beneath it. Yeah. Cuz
I think I see that a little
circles from the cameras that it
has. So you have the two
cameras. And from that, you can
infer some 3d information about
what's in front of the robot.
Okay. Yeah. Anything else? I
mean, I imagine there's encoders
and things on the wheels, or the
track. Oh, yeah. What, uh, and
then all the motors have sensors
and things. But what else for
perception?
Jason Richards: Is it just those
cameras? Maybe microphones?
Yeah. Yeah. So it's got, yeah,
it's got stereo microphones.
See, so you can hear what's
going on. Again, kind of that
sense. If you're, if you're a
human, you can hear somebody
coming up behind you, right? You
don't have eyes in the back of
your head, but you can hear that
something is happening. And
you're more aware of your
environment that way. So, so
yeah, those those. It's fun.
When I when I talk to people
about sensors, a lot of times
they're thinking very
unilaterally, and they're
thinking about, like Lidar and
Audrow Nash: things.
Jason Richards: Yeah, exactly.
Yeah. Like LiDAR, ultrasonic. I
Audrow Nash: mean, I'm honestly
surprised. You don't have like a
plane or lighter or anything in
there. But if you can do
everything with vision, that's
great.
Jason Richards: Yeah, yeah,
it's, it's pretty fascinating,
obviously, yeah, the tracks have
sensors, things like that, you
know, when we're going into, you
know, autonomy, things like
that. Being able to have tracks
to be able to know, even if you
lose, you know, GPS signal and
that kind of thing, you're able
to know, within, you know,
centimeter to where you're at in
your thing.
Audrow Nash: The tracks are very
accurate for encoding it. And
that's probably because they
don't slip as much as wheels
might.
Jason Richards: Correct. Yep.
Yeah, exactly.
Audrow Nash: So Gotcha. Okay, so
going back to the neck, you have
these two cameras, and those are
that's the majority of the bed
that is the big perception
sensor, the two cameras, and
then you have stereo
microphones, or whatever it's
called, so that you can tell
directionality of the sound,
right? Yeah. Great. That's
that's pretty much it for
perception. Other than like,
actually, I forget what it's
called now, like dead reckoning
your position for from the
tracks and this kind of thing.
Jason Richards: Yeah. But that's
it. Yep. Yeah,
Audrow Nash: that's it you've
like, are there like capacitive
sensors? So it can tell if it's
being pat or hugged or anything
like this? Or how do you detect
like, a person is your buyer
interact? I guess the cameras
would do that. But do anything
for a person touching it or
anything?
Jason Richards: No, no, not.
We've, you know, talked about
that a little bit. It's not, we
don't know, how helpful that
would be at this point. You
know, everything, everything has
to have, you know, some lead
time and stuff like
Audrow Nash: that. What do you
mean meantime,
Jason Richards: you know, just
which I like to do is that just
takes time. Gotcha. Yeah, yeah.
Just development time. You know,
and so what you know, weighing
priorities, which is the most
important thing totally, but
yeah, with with you know, the
vision for example, you know, if
if somebody sneaks up behind me
and touches me, yeah, I would
know that and maybe the robot
doesn't at this point might
being able to hear this. Yeah,
exactly. Somebody is coming up
behind me. I can look back and
be like, Oh, hey, what's going
on? And then you know, we can
have a conversation so no, no
perceptions. As far as that's
gotcha
Audrow Nash: is just curious
with like interacting with
little kids and stuff with like
the little kid with patted on
the head and would know with
being pat on the head. Oh, yeah.
But
Jason Richards: people people
are hugging it all the time.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Okay, so the
neck. Tell me about the neck. So
it how many degrees of freedom
does it have? What kind of
things gonna do? Yeah.
Jason Richards: So not wanting
again, not wanting to be super
creepy. So we've limited the
range.
Audrow Nash: So we can't go
around like, a hole or
something.
Jason Richards: Yeah, we don't
want this. It's Halloween. Yeah.
Yeah, robot, right. Yeah,
exactly. So it's a limited a
limited range view, just just
like a human would be. So it
doesn't it will go back,
probably a little farther than a
human would by itself. Turn my
neck, I can get about 90
degrees. But it doesn't go much
further than that. So we have we
also do a full 180 either. And
so it's about it's about 150
degrees. So that's pretty harsh.
And, you know, basically looking
over your shoulder, right, you
can look back and see what's
going on. Yeah. And then And
then, you know, down basically
similar to a human right, you
can sit down touch your head.
And then the other problem is,
you know, looking, looking up,
you've got the back of the the
head,
Audrow Nash: right, the Yeah,
because the cameras are just
underneath the chin, in a sense.
So it really does like to look
up. Yeah, to clear the chin.
Right. Yep. Yeah, exactly. So,
Jason Richards: yeah. So that's
it fully, fully articulating in
all of the directions.
Audrow Nash: That's two degrees
of freedom. Can it turn
sideways? I think it probably
can. Right?
Jason Richards: Yeah. Yeah.
Being able to kind of, yeah,
tilt the head, like, one of our
Yeah, and that's one of the one
of the most favorite ones that
we have, you know, especially
when we're interacting with
kids, or they want to play with
the robot. And so the robot
kinda like a dog, like, you
know, caulk its head and look at
you funny. So that's one of the
one of the things that we love
doing with people. Yeah. Like,
and then, and then a couple
sounds that we put into the
robot. So for them, they sound
in some of the videos, which is
interesting. I mean, Pixar did a
wonderful job. So
Audrow Nash: we'll leverage a
lot of their things.
Jason Richards: Yeah,
absolutely. Yeah. But it's, it's
pretty fun. One of the in its,
you know, with the sounds,
people ask, you know, if it can
talk in, in some language, you
know, English or whatever? And
the answer is, well, yeah, tech,
technologically, that's pretty
simple to do. Yeah, but we've
made a decision to not and
again, the reason for that is
when you don't expect a dog to
talk back to you, you know, in
in a language, but it will bark
and you can you can understand
with with nonverbal
communication, what is going on.
And so in the same way, as we,
you know, work with different
robots in urban spaces, and they
would talk to you in English, it
doesn't matter how nice the
robot is trying to say something
in English. It comes across
route, you know, you don't
expect a device to be telling
you to get out of the way,
right. It's like, well, that's,
that's kind of, versus a robot
that is just making sounds, you
know, more RTD to ask, then,
than anything else, right? So
that you, you understand, like,
Oh, this is asking me to move. I
was actually just having lunch
today. It's at our local Mexican
restaurant, and we have a robot
down there that's doing
deliveries all the time. And the
robot had had come inside. And
then there was a cup in the way
where it's supposed to park. And
so it's looking down there
looking up looking around, you
know, its head like, hey, come
over here and putting sounds and
then just somebody that was at
the restaurant looked at it was
like, oh, it's trying to tell me
something went over, take the
cup, got it out of the way. And
then the robot was able to say
thank you turn around and back
into its spot. So one of your
robots you're saying? Yeah,
yeah, one of one of the ones
like this. Yeah. So So with
Yeah, so it a nonverbal
communication, and that human
robot interaction pieces, again,
a lot of stuff that we've we've
studied. So it's where we put a
lot of time and effort into
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it seems like
a thing of setting expectations.
Because I think if something
talks, we expect that it can
really talk. Right? And then
it's frustrating when it
immediately doesn't recognize
you, like you could say any
arbitrary complex thing, and it
would have no idea unless
there's someone behind the
scenes like this.
Jason Richards: Right? Yeah,
like a web chat. Yeah. You know,
mean, typing, and you're like,
No, this is definitely this
isn't a human
Audrow Nash: talking. Yeah, the
robot would be similar to that.
Otherwise, yeah, I've seen that
quite a bit from like different
human robot interaction research
where they want to set the
expectation low. So that they
can not over promise.
Jason Richards: Right. And
obviously, you know, other
companies have done a good job
of overcoming that barrier by
having an actual human you know,
via like a computer screen on
the other side. And then you're
talking face to face with a
human right? The robot just
happens to be, you know, the
carrier. It's the media of the
iPad, for sure. Yeah, exactly.
Audrow Nash: So do you. So how
much of the robots control? Is a
human in the loop? Like tele
operating the robot? And how
much is autonomous? At this
point?
Jason Richards: Yeah, at this
point, the, the autonomous piece
is almost strictly for
navigation. So now that part's
out of the way, one of the
things obviously, the the
software guys, they're really
excited about the HDRI
components automatically know
facial recognition, somebody
happy, sad, how do I some
emotion or act? Yeah, yeah,
putting them putting emotion.
But you know, while it's on the
job, if you will, you know,
especially with disparity
vision, and making sure that,
you know, collision detection
and avoidance and things like
that is all working, it's going
down a path to making sure it's
not going to run into something,
but at the same time, it comes
into an obstacle, you know, it
hits an obstacle, not hits an
obstacle, it sees an obstacle
stops, and then can look around.
And it's kind of like, you know,
looks like it's looking at
flowers or trees are cars that
are passing by. So that, so that
is more natural than, you know,
a robot that just drives you
know, gets to a point and then
just kind of sits there for
Yeah, so. So all of the the
human interaction pieces have
been with tele operating, you
know, having somebody on the
other end, being able to emote,
and it's been really fun to,
again, experiment in a pretty
tight loop. So you can see what
do people react to? And what do
they want? Like, what do they
want to see from this robot on a
emotional or interaction basis?
And then once they have that,
you know, now that we've had
that we have some really good
data now, just programming
right? This program, like, okay,
when this than this, yeah. And
then the robot can know what to
do in certain situations.
Audrow Nash: So when so the
robot will autonomously go from
point A to point B. It does it
uses GPS or how to do that.
Jason Richards: Yeah, GPS and,
and Dead Reckoning and dead
reckoning. So, right? Yeah. So
within the tracks itself, it, it
knows where it is less slippage,
like you'd say, you know, better
better than
Audrow Nash: does it use. Is it
doing? It's not generating? I
think, in us talking a little
bit before the actual recording
started. It doesn't do mapping,
right, you have to go map an
area before the robot goes into
that area. Is it correct?
Jason Richards: Yeah, for the
autonomous piece. Yeah. So when
we go into a new area, yeah, we
go into a new area, we have, you
know, an operator that's doing
that piece, you know, going
through finding out where the
the obstacles are stuff like
that. And so here's the road
crossings. Here's the dangerous
battle. Yeah, don't go here. You
know, kind of like kinda like
the Waze app, you know. So once
we have all that, all that set,
then we can say, Yeah, this is a
this is a free and clear
sidewalk, you can go, you know,
full speed. This is a danger
zone slowdown. This is a road
crossing. We don't, we aren't,
you know, there's a lot more
programming, we aren't letting
the robot cross streets fine. So
yeah,
Audrow Nash: that seems that
seems terrifying. For your
robot. Yeah. Yes. Yeah. So what
is it when someone is going to
create one of these maps for the
robot? What does it involve? Do
they just like a handheld stereo
camera to do it like? Or do you
just bring a lidar through it?
And it just maps everything? Or
what like, how do you how do you
create this initial map?
Jason Richards: Question, we
actually, we actually just do it
with a robot to drive the robot
relocating. Mm hmm. Which does
Audrow Nash: generate a big 3d
mouse that way, and then you
annotate it.
Jason Richards: Know where it's
a little more complex than that.
I won't, I won't try to butcher
it. Because I'm not one of the
engineers on the project. But
yeah, but being able to go
through. And then with that,
being able to process all the
data that we need, so we can
see, here's, here's what's going
on. And it also does a lot of
good stuff. When we're doing
bigger deployments. One of the
things that people really want
from our customer base is Dax is
really cool. It's a really cool
thing, right? It just happens to
be cute, and it delivers food.
So you know, what it does is
kind of an accessory. So when we
go to a new area, it brings a
lot of goodwill to the, you
know, to the people that are
getting in as well. You know,
we're driving a robot on every
path that we can think of, you
know, for delivery area, and
people are stopping us all the
time asking questions, this
robots like oh, we're partnering
with this person and and so and
then also gives us some good
information as well for the
other connectivity, you know,
LTE and stuff like that. So when
operators have to jump in, we
got to make sure that we have
what carrier do we need to use
for the different agencies? What
bands right Yeah, cuz
everywhere. Everyone's A bit
different. And so obviously,
what will work in here in Oregon
is not necessarily the best
carrier down in Coronado,
California, which is may not be
the best carrier in Atlanta,
Georgia.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Gotcha. Okay,
yeah. So you have a map of the
environment that you get from
driving the robot through it.
And then you have the robot
navigate autonomously, from
point A to point B using kind of
like, somewhat labeled map in
some way where someone says,
this is a crosswalk, this is a
sidewalk, these kinds of things,
then you get to your
destination, and the robot is
taken over by someone who's
controlling it with a
teleoperation setup to actually
do the delivery to it. Correct?
Jason Richards: Correct. Yeah.
So that at this point, knowing
that, you know, that's the
interaction. It's not just the
delivery service, right. It's,
it's the experience of having a
robot that is being nice to you.
Yeah, so that's exactly that's
where a human takes over and is
able to be interactive. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: And so for that
part, what does it look like,
for from the humans perspective?
Are they sitting on some sort
of, like, video call kind of
thing that sees what the robot
sees? And they have a bunch of
buttons in front of them? Where
they can say nod head like this,
make this noise? Like this kind
of thing for picking the
behaviors? Or how does it work?
Jason Richards: Yeah, a little
more simple than that. A couple
joysticks, you know, that have,
you know, a lot of lot of pre
programs into the joysticks, you
know, kind of your over your
overview map, you can kind of
see where the robots were at,
you know, you can monitor
several robots at a time. You
know, making sure they're
staying on path. And then if one
needs help, you know, the
operator is able to go look into
it and see what they need to do
navigate around or end of
destination, right. Being able
to, to contact the person. Let
them know that they're their
personal copy that's funny for
the delivery, like Uber Eats or
DoorDash or something. Yeah,
when you have to call them and
be like, where
Audrow Nash: are you at? Yeah.
Yep. That's funny. So, okay.
Let's see. So then, so they're
using a simple interface to
control the robot while they're
doing that interaction. You were
saying that eventually, maybe
you could automate this kind of
thing? Or you or at least part
of the interaction now that
you're generating data? How and
then do you have the customer
like rate how enjoyable it was?
Or different metrics of it. So
you can see how the interaction
was and what parts of it they
liked and disliked and whatever?
Jason Richards: Yeah, good
question. So we, so there's not
like a Dax app? For example,
people aren't ordering food
through
Audrow Nash: us to get not Yeah,
actually.
Jason Richards: Yeah. Well,
it's, it's, it's an interesting
paradigm. We work with the
restaurant and so we'd rather do
integration with people so that
it's their brand. We just happen
to be the Korea robot that's
delivered. Yep. Yeah, kinda
like, you know, I lived in
Seattle and Boeing, obviously
the a great company. But, you
know, a Boeing airplane could
have Alaska Airlines on the
side, or it could have delta or
United or whomever, right. So.
So when I go to get on my plane,
I'm not saying hey, I'm on a but
am I on a Boeing? I'm no, I'm,
I'm with delta this time, or
Alaska or whomever? Right? So
yeah, it's kind of the same, you
know, kind of feel. But, but
with that, yeah, so especially
here in our local town, it's a
small town. And so being able
to, you know, we've got their
phone number, and then we can
ask, you know, direct
conversations, and see what
people like and don't like we we
did a test at a retirement
community as well. I mean, the
assumptions that we had were
kids, we know kids like robots,
which I think back to when I was
a little kid, and I've got a
I've got a eight year old and a
two year old, and to them
growing up. Oh, yeah. Robots
around the street. Like it's
just kind of a normal thing,
right? Yeah. But so I'd imagine
kids probably are good with it.
And they do they love Dax,
people, our age are, are a lot
more amenable to Dax as well,
because it's cool technology. So
we didn't know how it was going
to be received with people in
their 90s and, shockingly, Dax
were all for overseas. Yeah. Oh,
yeah. Again, because it's not
it's not a machine to them. It's
it's an entity. Right? So when
you watch Star Wars, for
example, are 2d to into machine.
He is but you don't perceive
him? Yeah, you see, you perceive
him as an as an entity, you
know, somebody that you are
having conversation with, not
just, you know, directing to do
a thing so so in the same way
when people see Dax, you know,
and it's funny, I do the same
thing. I know what's behind you
know, I know you know, all the
inner workings of the robot, but
I'll see him on the street while
I'm, you know, going to get a
taco. And I'm like, Hey, Dad,
I'll say hi. And it's so funny.
And obviously I know you know,
it, doesn't it You know, I'm
saying but it's, it's definitely
an experience until somebody
experiences or sees the
difference between, you know,
just you know, a cart that can
deliver something to you versus
having an interaction with a
beam. That is a machine. It's
starkly different.
Audrow Nash: Now. So you guys
are deploying in your, in your
town. So you're in Portland,
right? I haven't been to No,
Jason Richards: not poor. Oh,
where are you? Yeah, not
Portland. We're. So Oregon State
University Corvallis, which is
about an hour and a half south.
And we actually are in a small
suburb of that in a little town
called fellowmen. But yeah, so
not Portland. Not Not a huge
Metro.
Audrow Nash: But yeah, small
town. How many people to the
town? Oh, about 5000. Wow. So
Jason Richards: small. It's
crazy. Small town. Yeah. Small
town. I moved down here from
Seattle. It's a big change. It
was it was good. Yeah. Yeah. I
grew up in it. I grew up in
Montana personally. So it wasn't
changed to go back. Yeah. Back
to a small town. Right. Yeah,
we've got robots now that are in
Coronado, doing food delivery.
Down there. That's been fun. We
got some robots that are
shipping out to Georgia. Cool.
We next week Expo Hell yeah. So
we're getting packaged up and
shipped to Georgia. And then
different deployments. I think
Long Beach. We've got some
robots in Long Beach right now.
Yeah. Deliver stuff. And then.
Yeah, and more people are
contacting us all the time. Oh,
yeah. Yeah,
Audrow Nash: how many? How many
robots are deployed? Right now?
Would you estimate?
Jason Richards: What really, I
could probably do the math in my
head. It's not a lot. So we've
got the deployment in Coronado,
Long Beach,
Audrow Nash: we definitely use
it on the order. Georgia, or is
it on the order of like,
Jason Richards: yeah, that's
about it's about, we've got, you
know, got more robots in that
that are coming off the
production line, but we've got
actually in the field working.
We've got about
Audrow Nash: about 10 Yeah, 910.
Gotcha. They're doing stuff.
Okay. Interesting. How large are
you guys as a company? Like how
many people are involved?
Jason Richards: Yeah, so we've
got there's a 18 of us, Hey,
we've got the manufacturing. So
we got the manufacturing side.
That is, you know, getting
robots, you know, off the line,
then obviously, the operation
side and servicing, you know,
like, getting data on that, you
know, how long do you have to
run a robot before the tread
needs to get replaced? Yeah. How
many miles on their tires, you
Audrow Nash: know, imagine where
you were out fairly fast, too,
which is interesting,
Jason Richards: surprisingly,
not really, actually have lasted
a long time, we finally we
finally got one that we're like,
Hey, this looks like it's
certain to how many were out. We
should swap this out. I don't
actually this actually just
happened. I think it was either
earlier this week or late last
week. And so I asked her
Operations Manager, like figure
out how many hours we put on
this. Yeah, we can put that in
our service manual. But yeah.
And then obviously, they the
engineering team, you know,
mechanical and electrical and
software and firmware, and yeah,
so Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Cool. And
how are you guys funded? For
this kind of thing? Have you
been accepting investment? Or
like, what kind of where are you
at in terms of funding?
Jason Richards: It's good
question. So um, so in 2002,
brothers, I'll tell you the
story of the founder. So two
brothers, they started an
internet an ISP. dead broke. I
mean, they, they were volunteer
firefighters lived at the fire
station and paid themselves $50
A week, a month kind of thing,
you know, crazy. barely getting
by got it got it up and running.
And then in 2011, or so kind of
limping along there. Since they
were firefighters. One of the
brothers had this idea because
they went to a fire call, they
got to the fire station. And the
fire trucks were coming back
from the call, by the time they
got there. He's like, this is
stupid. Like, we have the
iPhone. I'm gonna build, I'm
gonna build an app. And so he
built this app called active
911. And last I heard it's about
40% of firefighters in North
America use this app called
active. Wow. So it's done very,
very well. And by his that
Joseph and Joseph goal was
always to have this r&d lab that
I talked about. So in 2015, they
started Novo dynamics. And then
Dax was kind of the first big
project that they said, Okay,
five years from now, I think
robots doing delivery is going
to be a thing. So let's start
working towards that end, and
more importantly, working
towards the future that people
want to see, you know, when, you
know, again, when people are
thinking the future of electric
cars, electric cars have been
around, you know, since the 80s.
Yeah, you know, long people have
tried to do electric cars. But
it wasn't until Tesla before
now, it's something that people
want, right? People are like,
Oh, that's the vision of the
future that we want to see not
these weird box things that are
glorified golf carts. Yeah,
right. So in the same way, you
know, with the robot is solving
that, you know, what kind of
thing do we want in pedestrian
spaces? That isn't going to be
creepy, that people are going to
want to attack themselves to
they can do helpful things for
people. So that was that was the
idea. So the r&d portion is all
been self funded, you know,
because these other two
companies that have done well,
it's been self funded up until
about a month ago. And so about
a month ago, I was actually, you
know, January when we said, we
need to, we need to
commercialize this thing, what
do we need to do we need to get
investment. Because, you know,
building you know, 20 robots is
one thing, building a fleet of
them. Hundreds is a totally
different ballgame. So. So it's
actually just about a month ago
that we opened up a crowd,
crowdfunding campaign through
start engine, which is the
intermediary, so so it's kicked
off. And this first time I've,
you know, I've been involved in
lots of companies started a
couple myself, but I've never
gone after investors. So it's a
whole new experience for me. You
mean crowdfunding specifically?
Or? Or even venture capital? You
know, filing with the SEC? Yeah.
Never. I've always been
bootstrapped. Yep. Right. We've
always bootstrapped company. So
this is the first time going
after investors. And it's really
interesting, because the the
majority of people that don't
know us, you know, they don't
know who we are. And they don't
understand that, that the two
brothers like, people that know
the two brothers, a lot of
people that know them have
invested quite a bit because
they paid another venture. Yeah.
Yeah. And yeah, and they, they
seen the robot, obviously, our
hometown, couldn't ask for a
better reception, you know, from
the investing standpoint,
because they're like, No, this
is our robot. This is our
hometown, and, you know,
friendly neighborhood robot that
we're investing in. But people
that don't know us, that have
invested. You know, we're saying
over $1,000, you know, $1,000 or
more, yeah, I've been reaching
out to those people. And
predominantly, they're
engineers, you know, it's people
that, that see what we're doing.
And they say, Oh, this is cool.
Like, this is a cool version or
vision of the future that you
guys have. And we want to be a
part of that. So yeah, so that's
where learning, you know, how do
we how do we get that message
out to more people? So not just
engineers, but everyone that's
it seems to be? It seems to be
interesting that that's the
community that is really liking
what we're doing.
Audrow Nash: So yeah, well,
they're interested. I don't
know, as an engineer, I'm
interested in robots. And I
imagine it's true for a lot of
other engineers.
Jason Richards: It's true
anyway. And it's not just you
know, robotics into you know,
every discipline you can imagine
civil engineers are like, wow,
this is. So it's kind of cool.
Audrow Nash: So, how was the
crowdfunding? What are your
thoughts on crowdfunding after?
So is it still alive? Or yeah,
it's still alive. So at the time
of this interview, it is how
long will it stay live until?
Because it may be I said, it'll
be like three weeks before this
is published. So
Jason Richards: yeah, so the
the, the raise is going through
either you hit the the first
goal that, you know, we can hit
with what we filed with the SEC.
So we're looking for a million
dollars by the end of the year
is kind of the the goal and the
target that we have, we're about
a third of the way there, you
know, after been going for about
a month, so it will either will
either hit that that mark, and
the fund will shut off, or I
believe it goes until I think
it's a six month campaign. So it
would go until until April of
next year.
Audrow Nash: Oh, hell yeah.
Okay, good. So this episode will
air while it is still going if
it goes to the six month time.
Awesome. Yeah. What have you
thought of crowdfunding? It's an
interesting model. Does each
person get some equity? Or
they're just supporting you? Or
they like get a tax robot? Or
how does it work?
Jason Richards: Yeah, so there,
yeah, there are different ways
of crowdfunding? Yes. You know,
we're a nonprofit or something,
it's not equity, what we're
doing is actually is actually
equity. So you're actually
getting stuck in the company,
which is, is kind of cool. So
I've heard horror stories of
that,
Audrow Nash: where you have
funding crowdfunding, where you
give them equity, because like,
you'll have to go and get
permission from everyone for all
the decisions and eventually,
just like veure bureaucracy
weighs down the company no
longer gets anywhere. That I
guess you have clear about their
terms kind of thing, if you
guess.
Jason Richards: Yeah, and
everybody so yeah, start engine
is the platform that we're
using. And part of it is that
yes, you do get common, you
know, common stock, you know,
which is you have shares in the
company. But you also are
essentially signing over your
vote to the CEO, which is me.
So, so when anybody says yes,
you know, I'm going to put
$1,000 into Dax and get, you
know, however many shares
they're also saying that that,
okay, I know that you run
minority shareholder, yep.
Right. So I am your
representative. So I am the vote
for the shareholder. So
obviously, if people want to
talk to me, obviously and let
their voice be heard, you know,
kind of like a representative
government, you know, cool and
Okay, I like that a good way
better talk to me. Yeah. And
then same thing where it's
exactly cuz otherwise, you know,
your shareholders meetings.
Everybody's there by proxy, and
I'm the proxy and I'm the boat
so, so it doesn't really bog us
down administrate If that makes
sense, yes, the cap table is, is
big. And usually people that
don't understand technology very
well and the liberalization,
Audrow Nash: which is where the
monopolization goes, right? Like
or who owns what? That's
typically correct,
Jason Richards: right, right.
Yeah. Who owns what? Yeah. So if
you buy, you know, 50 shares in
index bought, your name goes on
the list of like, okay, you are
an investor. So Oh, yeah.
Audrow Nash: Okay. That's crazy.
Yeah, that's, I will at least we
have like, you can automate
everything. So you don't really
have to do too much. Probably.
Jason Richards: No, that's,
that's all gonna say, yeah,
there's not and and people that
don't know technology very well,
they have in their mind that
you're looking, you know, that
many stamps, you know,
envelopes, as you're sending out
like, requests, you know, to
shareholders and things like
that, like, No, you put it in a
CSV file, and boom, everybody
gets a mailer.
Audrow Nash: So how, how much?
How much? So you said, your goal
is a million, you're a third of
the way there, it's been a
month, you have five more months
or so? How many, so in that
third of a million dollars,
which you've collected? How many
people are involved in that?
Jason Richards: A little A
little over 200. So,
Audrow Nash: okay, so it's
mostly like at least investing,
at least investing like 1500 per
person, on average kind of
thing.
Jason Richards: That's, that's
the average. And we had to, we
had to have a minimum that was
above 100. And so what we wanted
to do, and back back to the
large cap table, right, the
number of people that would be
on this, this list of investors,
people were saying, you know,
don't make it too big, but at
the same time, we have a lot of
fans. We call it the DAX fam.
You know, and we wanted, we
wanted people to be a part. And
so we said, Okay, we need to
have a minimum, that minimum
entries 170 bucks, so that
people can be, you know, an
owner of DAX but why
Audrow Nash: is that arbitrary?
Jason Richards: Weaver?
Audrow Nash: Why $170?
Jason Richards: Yeah, so we I
like round numbers personally.
And so our, it's 169 50. And so
our with our current valuation
and what the stock price is, and
ends up being 50 shares, we have
to we had to have a number over
$100. Okay, and so we said,
Okay, well, then 50 shares, so
50 shares is 169 5339 shares.
Oh, I see. Okay, so that's how
it works out simple. Yeah. So I
just made it that was it was
arbitrary, but it was a, okay, I
have 50 shares of dexpot. Right,
that became kind of the lowest
investment that you could do,
and then up to to answer your
question. So up to $50,000 is,
is, you know, 50,000. and above,
if somebody wants to invest at
that level, we said, yeah, we'll
fly back to your location, and
we'll have them deliver
something to you. Cool. So we
have nobody's, nobody's taking
us up on the 50,000 yet, but
we've had had a few investments
that invested down, you know,
several $1,000. And the average
is about 1500. But I think
there's a lot of investors, the
majority of the investors, if
you will, are about $1,000,
guys, so it's been a good
reception. And because it's I
don't know if I know this
correctly, but this is my
impression, and you can correct
me, because it's relatively
small amounts of money that
people are investing. They don't
have to meet the bar, the people
investing don't have to meet the
bar for
Audrow Nash: being like an angel
investor or something, which I
think is like a million in
assets or assets or something,
and over some amount per year.
So anyone can invest in this
kind of thing.
Jason Richards: Yep, exactly.
And, and that was a law. And I
might get it wrong. But it was,
you know, fairly recently, I
think, when 10 years or maybe 15
years when the law came out.
Before that. You're right.
Everything was an accredited
investor, which, like you said,
massive amounts of either high
income, high disposable income
or huge net worth that is in
your house. Yeah. And so it's
very, very rare air to be an
angel. Yeah, exactly. And so, so
with that, they said, okay,
there are some rules around it.
So for example, if you go to
start engine, and you say I want
to be an investor, they will ask
you some questions about your
income and things like to
confirm because there are
limits. Okay. Yeah. And to make
sure that, that if you don't
have a lot of disposable income,
you're not doing it going to
hurt yourself. Right. That's
good. Exactly. So yeah, and
there are certain limits and
things again, depending on
income and assets and things
like that, so it doesn't hurt
anybody, but at the same time
people can invest in in cool
startups like this totally. And
it's kind of
Audrow Nash: early to, yeah,
yeah,
Jason Richards: absolutely. So
they can say oh, you know,
people a lot of people like I
don't want to put my people that
are okay putting money into
crypto are usually okay putting
money into, into into startups,
right? They you know, it's not
people they just want bonds,
right? Yeah, I don't want bonds
and put it in that row massively
and I want to be something cool.
So exactly. I get it more risk.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So and again,
it's not you know, for a lot of
people you know, $1,000 is not
like a it's Yeah, doesn't
exactly doesn't break the bank
but if it if it goes big like
that, pool. And again, it's
again more a part of a, you
know, I've met people that
invested in Microsoft when it
was nothing, you know, kind of
thing. And it's like, yeah, wow,
you're probably enjoying that.
Audrow Nash: So, so one thing
that I would be curious about if
I was to invest in this is about
future rounds of funding,
because it might be possible
that they get diluted through
additional funding. How does
that look for like, yeah, just
talk about that, because I don't
know too much about it.
Jason Richards: Absolutely.
Yeah. I didn't either, you know,
till a few months ago, when I
really had to learn a lot. So
the way that it works is that
the goal when you go to each
investment round is to the value
of the company wants to go up,
right? That's, that's the goal.
So if the value of the company
goes up, so does the amount of
dollars you know, easy math, if
you invested $5, and then the
company, the value of the
company doubles, then your $5
turns into $10. Right? Just, you
know, hypothetically, yeah.
Okay, value goes up. But then
right, then you say, Okay, we're
gonna go after other investors.
So we're gonna add more shares
to this. Yeah, well, exactly.
It's just gonna dilute your
shares, right. So your your
share was $5. Now, it's $10.
Because we doubled it, but now
we've put more shares in the
mix. So now my shares are worth
eight. But it allows it allows
more fuel for more growth, if
that makes sense. Yeah. And the
hope is that it grows again. So
then that eight turns into 16.
And the company doubled again,
right? So that's, that's
essentially how that works. And
that's a very simple, very, very
soon. Yeah, but
Audrow Nash: the dynamic, is
there. Yeah. And you just hope
that it's not diluted to such an
extent that you make quite a bit
at the end. If a company does
have some sort of liquidation
event?
Jason Richards: Yep. Yep. And
that's the goal. And I've, you
know, talking to venture
capitalists and angels, and just
kind of getting a sense for what
what are you looking for, you
know, what is what does an angel
investor or a venture capitalist
looking for?
Audrow Nash: What do they think?
Jason Richards: Most? Yeah. Most
of
Audrow Nash: them
Jason Richards: have no
experience with at least the
ones that I know. I've talked to
most of them have no experience
with it, because they haven't
had to write they they're that
rare air of angel investors
accredited investors. So are
they don't need to have an
investment firm or something.
Exactly. This kind of Yep.
throwing around the money. A lot
of people. Yeah. And since
again, because it's a fairly new
concept in the scope of, you
know, the history of the world,
it's a fairly new thing that you
can get into these crowdfunding
rounds. They don't have a whole
lot of experience with it, but a
lot of them, it seems that the
tides are turning a little bit.
I'll give an example. So there's
a, an angel group are called the
Oregon rain. And it's more for
small, small, small startups.
You know, like, you know, I need
$30,000 to get this, this idea
off the ground. Yeah. And so
because they're angels, and
trying to figure out how they're
going to do it, they actually
partnered with another
intermediary, I can't remember,
but basically who it was, but
essentially, this other
intermediary, like start engine
was going to give them a white
label version of what does it
mean, programmable? That
version? I don't know. Yeah. So
yeah, so a white label version
would be. So for example, if I
have a software, let's call it
Microsoft Office or Microsoft
Word, right? So a total a white
liberal version amendment.
Audrow Nash: Yeah.
Jason Richards: Okay, so I can't
just I can't just say, hey, it's
Microsoft Word. Yeah. But if I
had a white label version, if
you came to me and said, I'm
going to give you you know, $300
billion. So I have a white
labeled version. It's not
Microsoft Word anymore. It's now
dexpot word, right? And so I the
label, or you buy, essentially,
okay, you buy it, you buy the
rights of the software, but they
put your name on it. And so
that's so a white middle version
of startengine would be, you
know, Oregon rain.com/investors.
But the actual software was not
written by Oh, yes. Investors,
okay, by another company. Yeah,
that makes sense. So, so, so I,
it looks like it's becoming
more. There's more awareness
around crowd fund so that in
these angel groups seems like,
Audrow Nash: okay, that's what
you were. So I was a bit lost
for a sec. You were saying
basically, that's an example of
crowdfunding going into
something that is a bit larger.
Yes. With investors or
something?
Jason Richards: Right. Yeah. The
angels. They are they know of
it, but they haven't
participated. But it seems to be
just the research that I've been
doing, it seems to be that
they're more open and receptive
to it. Interesting, more,
because you have companies that
have gone through crowdfunding
rounds, and they've they've done
they've done it successfully,
meaning that they, they got the
money, and then they executed on
the goal correctly. They started
getting revenues. And now they
have revenue. So now they could
go into like an angel investment
group or venture capitalists and
say, here's our revenues. And
here's the funding that we got
before. Now, would you you know,
invest in this and there Now
seeing because they're seeing
this happening more often,
they're more privy to the fact
that, oh, we might want to look
into investing in crowdfunding
options ourselves.
Audrow Nash: Why would so why
would a company go into
crowdfunding as opposed to
seeking investment from, I don't
know, like a, like a pre seed or
some sort of company or some
sort of angel investor or
something like this, because I
understand that one of the
benefits of having investors
come together for your company
is that they can help you make
while they can connect you to
the right people, or they can
mentor you. So you avoid
potholes. Why would you choose
crowdfunding over a specific
like one larger investor? Kind
of thing?
Jason Richards: Yeah. Yeah, to
two main reasons. So January,
then back January of this year,
when we were looking at going
after investment, reached out to
some venture capitalists and
friends of friends that we have,
but no people. And essentially
all of them said, Okay, well,
what are your revenues? Zero.
Okay, so if your revenues are
zero, that's a pretty big
gamble. Right? You're for them.
That's the perception market
event
Audrow Nash: or these kinds of
things. So neurons,
Jason Richards: okay. Yeah.
Yeah. So I did at this point,
they would look at that and say,
Oh, it looks like it's still
like a research phase. It's
like, Yeah, but we want to go
from a research phase into a
commercialized phase. So in
order to make that jump, it's
going to require money. And so I
was talking to one, one venture
capitalist who he been on the
other side of the table to write
he had he had startups gone
after venture capital and had
some successful exits. And, and
he said, he said, what you're
going after right now is he
called it dumb money, for that
reason, right? Because when you
go after venture capitalists,
you're not only you're getting
their Rolodex, right, the old
Rolodex is where people had
contacts and things like that.
So you're going after their
Rolodex as much as you are on
the cash. And so that's kind of
the next step that I see.
Audrow Nash: And also just
advising to not just rollback,
but like they can really no,
because they could have could
have seen people go through
similar stages. And they can be
like, Ah, this Yep, like, at
this point, you should be
working on this. And at this
point, you do this, and this is
how we get to the next stage,
our Series A or whatever it
might be.
Jason Richards: Yep. So yeah. So
with with the, so as we talked
to different people,
essentially, it was, you know,
that was kind of the feedback we
got from several, the, you know,
get some revenue didn't come
back to us kind of thing. So we
looked at that and said, Okay,
well, then crowdfunding seems
like, a good option for a few
reasons. One was because we
everywhere DAX goes a celebrity.
You know, everybody, kind of
everybody, there's, about half
of the people will kind of walk
by like, oh, yeah, I see robots
trying to talk to me every day,
you know, like, and I might say,
I'm trying to
Audrow Nash: go, where is this?
I don't know. I feel like I
should be in the area with all
the robots. And you were
mentioning that it's not legal
for robots to drive on the
streets here. But I'm in I'm
supposed to be in the tech area.
And I so seldom see robots
anywhere doing anything. Work
From Home stuff, but yes. Okay.
Jason Richards: Right. And then
and then the other half of
people are, you know, getting
out of their cart. We haven't
caused any, you know, auto
accidents from people like
rubbernecking, but it is fun
being you know, walking. It's
fun walking behind dact. Yep.
And seeing people on the road
because people will look and
even if they're having a bad
day, it's funny watching the
people in the car because they
will, they will turn their head
look at the robot. And you know,
the look at DAX and then
everybody smiles. Where has this
look of like astonishment? Yeah,
what is that? Did I just see
that? But everybody smiles like,
well, that is that's cool. You
know, like, huh, I just saw
something special today. So
anywhere, the DAX goes. He's a
celebrity. Like I talked about,
you know, the hometown film, if
we wanted to be able to say,
hey, you can invest to for
crowdfunding. So yeah, like,
give you that opportunity. The
other piece of crowdfunding is
it's a lot of, it's a lot of
marketing. Right? Film is, is a,
it's a great little small town.
But it's a small town. Down here
for me. Yeah, versus Seattle.
And you got 4 million, you know,
not as big as you know, LA where
you're coming from but, but need
more eyeballs on DAX, right,
more the more eyeballs, the C
DAX, the more people that have
invested interest literally,
right? If somebody is in Texas,
and they put $1,000 into DAX,
they're probably also more privy
to be like, hey, I want DAX down
here, too, you know, or what
connections do you have any
larger sense? That makes sense?
So those were the two big
reasons that we said yeah, let's
let's go after crowdfunding and
make it work.
Audrow Nash: So what do you
think? So I coming from, so I
was in grad school doing human
robot interaction for a little
bit. Oh, yeah. And one of the
things that was very concerning
for the community was kind of
the this novelty effect. So like
someone can be, like really
excited about the robot, and
they'll like, do all the things
the robot wants and behave
really well around it. But then
over time, so as weeks go by,
and months go by any, like,
maybe the robot becomes less
influential on those people,
because they now are like, I
know what it does. I'm kind of
sick of it. This kind of thing.
Yeah. Any any thoughts on this?
Because the robot is currently a
celebrity. But I wonder, could
it be a novelty effect? Or is
it? How do you think of these
things?
Jason Richards: Yeah. So if if
all the DAX did was be novel? I
would agree with that. Right. So
differing things and so right.
So do you have to have a useful
function as well? Right. So if
he's, if it is, same with you
know, like, I would say that,
that if it's doing useful things
for people, whether it's, you
know, delivering you food or,
you know, patrolling grounds,
like a security robot or
something like that, right, if
it's doing something useful,
it's not only novel and cool.
You wouldn't get sick, because
it's actually helping. It's
justifying it feels way. Yeah,
exactly. Especially in the
delivery space, because
delivery. You know, if you look
back to the 1970s, when they
started tracking it, called the
labor force participation rate.
And so the US government
tracking, it was like, US
government. Yeah. Department of
Labor. Okay. Yeah. The
Department of Labor is looking
at how many people are working
compared to the population, and
that that number has been in
steady decline since the 70s.
COVID exasperated that. Yeah.
But you know, where was less
people working in at the same
time? If you look at just food
delivery service, in general,
that's been on an increased, you
know, exponential growth path
for the last several years.
COVID exasperated that as well.
So the restaurants and the
people that we talked to in the
delivery space, it's almost an
expectation. Now, you know,
where, what if you own a
restaurant delivery, you really
want a restaurant? Yeah,
exactly, exactly. You might not,
but Uber Eats or GrubHub or
DoorDash, or somebody is going
to deliver this food to me,
right? It's kind of the
expectation. Yep. And so that's,
maybe I don't want to say an
unrealistic expectation. But
when you don't have enough
people to fill those roles, it's
just not going to happen. So for
example, in Coronado, one of our
guys walked into one of the
restaurants in the back and they
said, do you see all those
orders, and there's like 20
delivery orders sitting there,
like they, they've been sitting
for hours, and there's nobody
going to come pick them up, like
very doubtful that somebody is
actually going to get on
UberEATS or GrubHub, or
wherever, and go and pick those
orders up and take them to the
people that want them. You know,
last delivery experience I had,
when I was on a trip to Montana,
is we had delivery set for 1130.
For lunch for there's only five
of us in the room. So okay,
lunch is gonna be here at 1130.
We we ordered it ahead of time,
make sure we got into delivery
schedule, and it didn't show up
till 2pm. And that's just
because of you know, there's not
enough people to fill those
types of roles. Is that
Audrow Nash: a thing that's more
particular to small towns, do
you think like basically, is the
whole like, say, middle of
America that would have smaller
towns? or basically any, because
I'm thinking of like, I'm in San
Francisco now. And generally, it
seems like the food delivery
services are quite quick. But
maybe this is so it hasn't been
in my experience, as you've
described, where there's like,
20 orders for this kind of
thing. Is this particular 20
locations, I guess, or any types
of sounds or types of towns?
Jason Richards: Yeah, that's a
good question. So Coronado,
California isn't isn't exactly
like, you know. Yeah, yeah. It's
right outside San Diego. But
it's right outside San Diego,
right, you got to go over the
bridge. So it's also very
wealthy zip code. And so if you
are living in Coronado, you're
probably not the person doing
the live delivery. So people
have to come in, and then do the
delivery within that, that area.
So, so that's kind of unique
thing. The other thing is that a
lot of people, you know, door
Dashers and people that do
GrubHub and UberEATS, and stuff
like that. A lot of them don't
want to do the short, the short
stuff. Yes. Similar to like,
your Uber driver wants to drive
you 30 miles away to an airport,
they don't want to drive you
three blocks, right? Because
they set
Audrow Nash: up for but in
general, some of them are trying
to generate trips and these
kinds of things.
Jason Richards: Right, yeah. But
in general, you know, you're
you're making more, if you will,
you know, the longer you have.
Yeah, you're doing the long
trips. So so same way you know,
for robot you know, this you
know, the DAX is not DAX is not
optimized to go 30 miles you
know, he's he's got a pretty
good like, one, one and a half
mile range. And those are that's
a good niche to fill.
Audrow Nash: Mm hmm. Okay, could
you Imagine pairing with
vehicles and things where this
are like kind of like the
package delivery idea where it'd
be an autonomous car that drives
the robot and the robot does the
last little bit of the delivery.
Could you imagine that being
used in that kind of thing?
Jason Richards: I could. It
would be it would definitely be
interesting. Obviously, there's
a lot of people that are working
towards those types of
solutions. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Even in the Oregon
area to thinking of agility
robotics, I believe. Yeah,
they're trying to do the
legendary
Jason Richards: robotics thing.
They're just up the road from
us. So Oh, cool. Yeah. Yeah.
Hello,
Audrow Nash: litres of package
delivery, or whatever? Is that?
Yeah.
Jason Richards: Yeah. And it's a
very interesting it, you know,
that, you know, last mile
delivery is always the most
expensive, you know, you look at
logistics in general. That's,
that's the hard stuff to figure
out. Yeah. So very potentially,
there's a lot of, obviously, a
lot more that has to go into the
logistics of that loading and
unloading a robot moving parts.
Audrow Nash: You need, like a
little lowering platform or
something to get the robot
Jason Richards: down there.
Yeah. And we've got a band that
we, you know, haul robots in.
And we have that, but it from
from a large scale, you know,
like if you're a big Logistics
Center, like Amazon, or UPS or
something like that, right. It's
a lot of moving parts there. And
so sure, eventually, I could see
something like that, like an
Amazon locker, you know, that
that drives to a town, but then
every locker opens up and
becomes a little robot and
drives to your doorstep. You
know, it'd be super cool. Yeah.
You know, there's, there's
probably something there. But
there's a lot of not just not
just, you know, technological
hurdles to overcome, but a lot
of like legislative hurdles to
overcome as well.
Audrow Nash: Which I do want to
talk about for sure. Yeah,
legislative things are very
interesting. But just before we
do talk about that, when so
you're not generating revenue
yet? I believe, right.
Jason Richards: We are we are
now you're just doing the
stages. Yep. Gotcha.
Audrow Nash: I'm just wondering,
What will your business model
be? Or what is it now? Yeah, for
generating revenue? And maybe
you'll flip it around a bit. But
Jason Richards: yeah, um, so
the, the thing that we have
right now is kind of twofold.
One is that we realize kind of a
back to the DAX as a celebrity
thing. We can talk about it now,
there's been a few events that
the DAX has been in. One was for
a TV show called the coma FD. So
there was a bunch of DAX robots
that they turned into
firefighters and and get a bunch
of promotion for a season or get
one with or under. Yeah,
exactly. Right. He was an avid
he's like, my two worlds
collided, this is amazing. And
then, and then one was for a
Jack, Jack Daniels. It was some
some beverage company. And we
did a delivery promotional event
at a golf course in Napa Valley.
Things like so. Yeah. So
different marketing agencies are
reaching out to us because it's
a unique, it's unique enough,
right. It's novelty enough at
this point, that it's a great
marketing engine for them. So so
being able to do appearances and
stuff has been fun. And
obviously, it gets our brand out
there as well. So that's fun.
That's that's been generating
some revenue. The the flash
entertainment robot, yeah,
right, exactly. But those are,
those are gig events, if you
will, right. It's not recurring
revenue. So but the the actual
business model is revolving
around that you have different
deployments in different states
that are, you know, renting
robots for, you know, 1000s of
dollars a month for robot, and
they're gonna do deliveries a
service for you, which also
keeps it so that we can take
care of service and those types
of things. And then those that's
the monthly recurring model that
we want to spin up. So Gotcha.
Audrow Nash: So it's been where
they buy the hardware, or where
they rent the hardware. They
Jason Richards: rent the
hardware, correct? Yeah, yeah.
They're renting the service of
delivery. And we happen instead
of us being humans there. We
have robots that do it for
Audrow Nash: us. Gotcha. So I
just recently, at the time of
recording this interviewed
cobalt robotics, and they're
doing something very similar for
security guard robots, where
they're having the robots
basically be the legs and then
they have someone controlling it
at a very high level. And so to
me, this is kind of similar to
what you guys are doing, where
it's you will have the robot be
autonomous on the navigation and
then you'll have a person
control the robot for the
interaction for the delivery. Is
that Is that what you imagine?
Yeah,
Jason Richards: that's yeah, I
imagine that that more and more
pieces of that puzzle will get
solved, you know, autonomously.
Yeah, again, like the facial
recognition pieces. Are you
happy sad how do we make your
day if you're a kid, what do we
do you know, you know, those
those types of things. But then
say what the delivery piece you
know, being able to get to an
end destination, and then
somebody comes out you realize
that There's a person now in
front of you, you can interact
with that person. And then open
your drawer if you know, you can
see the code is correct, you
know, those those types of
things can all be young
automatable. And that's the next
pieces.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So the goal
is full autonomy as much as
possible. I'm just wondering,
yeah, if you would have a, like,
I don't know. So in cobalt, they
have, like, half of the people
there are just watching over the
security guards. They're the
people that take over autonomy.
And I would wonder if at least
before all this stuff is
automated, would you have some
sort of similar model where
it's, you have a bunch of people
working to do the autonomy, or
do to supplement the autonomy.
So when it can get there?
Jason Richards: Yeah. In you're
exactly right. It's more of the
and that's what we tell people,
it's semi autonomy, because when
people think autonomy, they
think, full on this robot is our
duty to and it does exactly what
I want, whenever I want. But no,
the semi autonomy piece is being
able to increase the number of
you know, the ratio of operators
to actual robots that they
oversee. Right. And that's the
goal is to have greater and
greater autonomy, which requires
fewer and fewer operators, that
aren't necessarily interacting
with every single person that
they see. But making sure that
robots are, are generally
staying in line with what they
need to be doing. Yeah, you
know, or if they see something
that's completely, you know, a
tree falls in the middle of
their path. And now they have no
way around, because we're not
letting it go outside the bounds
of you know, it's on a sidewalk,
it's like, we can't go into the
road. You know, so not very nice
to take over and make a human
decision of okay, we're gonna
have to find another path,
right, turn the robot around,
but that kind of thing. So. So
there will always be an
overseer, you know, somebody
that's commanding, you know, a
crew of 20 or so robots. So
Audrow Nash: cool. And how did
you decide to do the
subscription model as opposed to
like, they buy the robot, and
they're on their own, or they
buy the robot and you like,
manage it somehow? Or they buy
it? And then they are a
subscription thing? Or like all
these permutations? How did you
pick the one?
Jason Richards: So the current
one, investors really like MRR
monthly recurring revenue, they
like seeing that this is going
to come in whether you, you
know, yeah, essentially all the
time. Right, versus fairly
predictable. Exactly. And that
that really rings true for a lot
of investors. So that's one. The
second is, is that when people
have asked us to buy the robot
outright, we've kind of played
with the idea. But at the same
time, we said, Okay, well, we're
gonna have to come up with some
sort of service contract on top
of this. Because, you know, you
could take a, it's not
ubiquitous enough, where you
could take a laptop to a
computer repair shop, and they
could probably figure out what
to do or diagnose it. You take a
robot that nobody's seen before,
to like, you know, yeah, a
computer repair shop, they're
not gonna know what to do. And
so at the same time, we said, it
wouldn't, it doesn't make a lot
of sense, because we did come up
with a model and said, Yeah,
well, you can buy the robot for,
I don't remember what the number
was, like 30 or $40,000. And
then it's still going to be a,
you know, a fiver $1,000 monthly
service contract to have that
robot. So we said, you know, if
we're, we have to go that model
anyway. And explaining that to
people, they understand that
they're like, oh, yeah, because
if a track falls off, or you
know, a tread wears out, or
whatever, you know, yeah, you
need to get to the restaurant to
repair that. Exactly. Yeah. And
so, so having a service model
made a lot more sense. Yeah. To,
to us, and to people that have
been talking to so
Audrow Nash: yeah. Let's see, I
have a few questions that I want
to ask all at the same time. But
what? So you're doing things
where it's like, they're in
Atlanta, they're in California,
they're in Oregon? Does it mean
you're going to have to set up
technicians at all these
locations so that they can do
these repairs? Or how the kind
of the logistics of that work?
Jason Richards: Yeah, so it's,
um, we actually what we do is we
actually find partners in those
areas, that we can then train on
some minor stuff, you know,
usually it's, you know, computer
repair shops, or people that are
in, you know, manufacturing,
robotics type hardware, maybe
not robotics itself, but you
know, something that they see a
circuit board and they don't
freak out, you know, they it's
not like taking into a bicycle
repair shop. Right? Yeah. So
somebody that has some
experience with technology, so
we partnered with them, and then
then become essentially our
point of contact for shipping,
you know, robots in and out of a
city. And then we also we keep a
hot spare that's readily
available inside swab. I see.
Correct. So if the robot has a
problem, something happens. That
yeah, we can we can within the
day, swap the robot out with a
new robot ready to go. If it's
simple enough that we can repair
with remote hands. We'll have
them do that on a surface
contact. If it's more complex
than that, you know, the one
that was there's a hot spare in
the crate. We saved throw this
one in the crate we got another
one coming your way we ship a
robot and they robots basically
meet, you know, somewhere in the
middle of America. So
Audrow Nash: somebody then The
next thing I don't know if I'm
correct on this, but I imagine
that food delivery is a fairly
low margin industry, which means
you need a lot of volume.
Because and I think this and I'm
not I don't have data and I'm
not really aware. But I don't
think that the like Uber Eats
drivers are paid that well, or
any of the any of the delivery
services. And so I think it's
more about like, How many can
you get? Does this and I'm
wondering basically, for how
long before the robot would like
pay off its existence, and start
being profitable to the
companies in this kind of thing?
If it is a low margin thing?
Because they have to make a lot
of deliveries? Probably, yeah.
This kind of thing? Yeah,
Jason Richards: it really
depends. So a good example of
this would be one of the people
that is getting the service down
in the Atlanta area in
Fayetteville, a company called
nourish and bloom, and they're a
kind of a cool new concept of a
grocery store that is
essentially fully autonomous
with people that can help
conserve eat it. Yeah, so Amazon
had one that was similar in
Seattle, where you walk in
facial recognition, here's why.
So it's
Audrow Nash: that kind of thing.
Jason Richards: No, it's not,
not quite that that degree, but
similar. And so people are
coming in, they can kind of self
self serve, they don't need to
get checked out. Right. It's,
it's, it's automated, you know,
okay, so they, they wanted
robots as well. But if, for
example, you know, the, the
payload is huge in a robot. So,
how do you how do you make that
valuable, and it'd be similar
to, you know, if you're going to
shop at Walmart, for example,
versus Whole Foods, you know,
the amount of money that you're
going to make per bag at Whole
Foods is, is a much higher
margin. Walmart, for example.
It's a totally different market.
So we're not It's not like a
luxury market that we're going
after. But it is more of a high
end market that we're that we're
Audrow Nash: targeting, ah, so
these things, evaluate your ad,
like heating and cooling, and
this kind of thing on your robot
so that the the food arrives and
is still tasty, not like, with
DoorDash, if it's slightly cold,
or something like this. So it's
the luxury market with
subsidized a bit too,
Jason Richards: you know, if
that makes sense, they're making
higher margins on products that
they're selling anyway, I mean,
you know, Whole Foods and
Walmart, they don't sell exactly
the same thing. But the margins
are definitely different. Right.
So, so that's part of it. And
then the other part is, is also
the, that becomes a unique, you
know, unique service that they
can provide that nobody else
does. So then drive more traffic
from a marketing perspective.
Yeah, oh, I can have a robot
deliver it to me, these people
can do that. And these people
can't. So I'm going to shop
here, even if it cost me a
little bit more.
Audrow Nash: I know that it's
cool for you guys. But I'm
looking forward to the day that
it's not uncommon for robots to
deliver things. I think that
would be sweet.
Jason Richards: Yeah, me too.
Actually.
Audrow Nash: That'd be nice.
Okay, now, complete non
sequitur. How does your robot
deal with stairs?
Jason Richards: It doesn't.
Audrow Nash: Yes, so what? So
I'm imagining, like in San
Francisco, it's not always the
case that there are nice curbs
to get around. So it may just be
like a sheer drop onto the
street kind of thing. Does this?
I don't know. i How do you guys
decide to not do stairs? With
the tracks? And it? Does that
affect? Where the rope? I'm sure
it affects where the robot can
go? And what cities you can
deploy in things like this?
Jason Richards: Yeah, the the,
because there's a couple things
as well. I mean, San Francisco,
Seattle as well. The San
Francisco especially is known
for some very steep streets.
Right. And so there's some areas
that we were five degrees and
Audrow Nash: someplace. Yeah,
exactly. Yeah. This kind of, so
Jason Richards: we wouldn't, we
wouldn't put a robot in that
area just for that reason. So we
had to make a couple of design
decisions, right, like all
engineers do. And one of those
limitations is we said, Okay,
where can we deploy this thing?
And we said anywhere that is ADA
compliant with current, you
know, if
Audrow Nash: visibility American
Disabilities associated to a
wheelchair should be able to get
Jason Richards: around there.
Correct. So any ramp, and I
don't remember what the exact
slope is, for that, but we said
that that that is going to be
kind of the max grade that we're
going to we're going to be on
which is still pretty steep. I
think it's 18%, if I'm not
mistaken. So it's still
significant. I mean, somebody is
a real metric. Give me
Audrow Nash: degrees. So yeah,
100% is straight up and so 18%
is 20% of 90 degrees. So
Jason Richards: yeah, I think
yeah, exactly like that. So,
it's not nothing though, right?
It's, it's, it's sticking really
soon. So, so but you know, same
thing, you know, at some point,
you know, you don't want this
thing flipping over on its back,
you know, and, and that kind of
thing. So stairs is something
that we know that we'll have to
deal with eventually, you know,
same with elevators, especially
for
Audrow Nash: delivery to Yeah,
elevators, like I mean, my
apartment building. There's
stairs on the way in and then
elevator. So it would have to
meet me outside.
Jason Richards: Correct? Yeah.
And I know that, you know, a lot
of UberEATS drivers and things
like that can you know, come to
the door and true, you know, a
lot of them have to get wrong in
you know, you hit a code. And
usually people meet you in the
lobby, something like that. So
there's, it's not completely
outside that the paradigm. But
when we're looking at places to
deploy currently, yeah,
obviously, we're looking for
places that are more flat, that
have less stairs that are
usually with up kept sidewalks.
I mean, the small town that
we're in is a nice little small
town to live, nice place to be
from. But it's a it's a great
place to test because as
terrible sidewalks. So we're
finding out a lot of things
about potholes and what we can
and can't do gravel. You know,
the elements getting through
mud, you know, that kind of
stuff, which is obviously great
for a testbed, but not an ideal
deployment.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, let's see.
And we are starting to run out
of time. So I would love to talk
about legislation for the robot,
because this is an interesting
thing that I hadn't considered
before you brought it up. So
yeah, just tell me a bit about
it. In January,
Jason Richards: yep. I didn't
know much about it either. Until
I until we started looking at
deploying into different places.
And the first place that had
legislation for delivery robots,
was in Washington, DC, and that
that came out in 2017. And had
different different factors
involved weight, maximum speed,
when it can and can't be on the
roads, you know, safety
information, etc. And so
different states have adapted
that to very similar, you know,
everything is fairly similar to
that. Pennsylvania, for example,
they said that, yeah, we're
going to give it the same rights
as a pedestrian minus a little
bit, they do have to yield to
pedestrians. And, and so, in
California, and Oregon,
interestingly enough, doesn't we
don't have state laws regarding
robots on sidewalks. So it's up
to individual cities and
municipalities to do that. San
Francisco banned them in in
2017. He said, disappointment.
Yeah, yeah. And, and then they
made it very, they made a very
small exception and a bunch of
hoops that had to go through, I
think Postmates is allowed to
have like, two in San Francisco
now. And that's it. And the
reason for that is, has to do
with pedestrian space, you know,
people, again, the reason that
dexpot is, is it's just
different, you know, it's
different than any other
delivery devices out there. So
in the legislation, they call,
they call it a PDD, or a
personal delivery device. So
which essentially can be
whatever you want it to be to
put a skateboard and put a motor
on it, and then say, you know,
drive it remotely with a camera.
That's a personal delivery
device, and it can drive
wherever it wants on sidewalks.
And that's how this legislation
refers to correct what we're
referring to as a delivery
robot. Okay, correct. Yep. And
so the PD ds, and so a PD DS, we
want it we're working very hard
with we, you know, worked with
the state of Maryland on their
legislation working with the
seat at Coronado on on rules
around it. And the thing is, is
that people don't have a concept
of what it could be like to have
DAX, if their only experience is
a remote control box that is
getting in their way at their
feet. They don't want it there,
versus DAX, which is a robot
like you would see in a movie
that is welcome in human space,
like a dog is. And so helping,
you know, change the legislation
is a big deal, because there are
a lot of places that it does not
make sense. And it's because
people don't want delivery
robots on their sidewalks, you
know, but when they if you just
look at it from that box
perspective, you know, like an
engineer, like I want this box
on wheels, it makes sense. It's
an easy design, it's easy to do.
But that is not what is being
accepted. So the human
acceptance piece and pedestrian
space is a much bigger deal than
most people realize. And that's
that's the thing, the DAX is
essentially solved for that, you
know, being able to be welcomed
on pedestrian spaces.
Audrow Nash: That's interesting.
So it's, it's as if part of your
role in being involved with that
spot, is that you have to work
with lawmakers and things to try
to show them that this robot is
okay in human spaces, and should
be allowed and this kind
Jason Richards: of 100% Yeah,
because, because if this is the
future that we want, namely want
robots to be able to do more
things in pedestrian spaces, we
have to make sure that we're not
legislating our way out of
existence. And not just us. I'm
talking about, you know,
robotics engineers in general,
if you're doing something that
is in is public facing, most
people think it's all magic,
right? People that are engineers
understand there's a lot of, you
know, mechanics and software and
connectivity. There's a lot
behind these machines. So I
guess my hope is that, you know,
other people that are out there
are not doing things that would
then jeopardize, you know, urban
robots for everybody else,
similar to how drones were, you
know, when drones were
introduced. A lot of people did
a lot of really silly things
with them, because it was cool
technology. And now there's so
many regulations around drones.
And they can be very, very
useful, but they're not as
useful as they could be, usually
because of legislation because
people did some silly things,
especially in the beginning. So
Audrow Nash: okay, so how do you
avoid doing silly things? For
this? If you're trying to like,
do something and you don't know,
it'll be silly. I assume people
don't go into an endeavor going,
this is going to go badly. And
it's going to hurt everyone,
because crazy regulations will
be passed for this, like, way
over correct. And make sure this
doesn't happen again. Oh,
absolutely. So how do we avoid
things?
Jason Richards: You have to
question? So like the San
Francisco problem, for example,
I'm sure that the engineers were
like, Hey, we're gonna take this
thing on the road, and
everybody's going to be in love
with it.
Audrow Nash: What's the problem?
What do you mean, the oh, that
they're,
Jason Richards: they're illegal
in San Francisco? Oh, yeah. We
can't make a delivery robot to
San Francisco. And whoever, you
know, was a part of doing that
test. The engineers, whomever,
I'm sure they were thinking this
is going to be amazing. And
everybody's going to love it.
And then people did. And so when
we go to new places, for
example, usually we're finding
out you know, what are the
rules, you have rules around
this? And then giving usually
the police department a heads
up, you know, hey, we're going
to be doing this, we're going to
be here. So when they, yeah,
when they get phone calls from
people, hey, this robot is or
there's this thing in my way, or
this thing? hit my car,
whatever. We haven't, hopefully
not. But yeah, yeah, there are
others that have. So when they
get calls, they're not
completely blindsided, and then
they get an angry phone call
from the mayor. Right? And then
that's how those things happen.
You know, it's a couple
decisions makers, they hear from
some angry people in their city
that can then essentially, like,
make it up make little buddy
eyes. Yeah, yeah. So just more
being aware and conscious of,
you know, where, where are you
at, you know, who's around, and
making sure that that, and not
necessarily calling City Hall
because they won't know. But if
you call usually the local
police department, and just ask,
Hey, you know, we're gonna be in
this area with this robot. Is
there any rules around that?
They'll usually be able to tell
you yes or no, you say, great.
We just wanted to let you know
we're in the area, give you the
heads up. And so that, you know,
if it's some robot rolling along
the street, and people think
Armageddon just happened, that
they can realize no, no, no,
this is this company, and I've
got their contact phone number,
you know, so.
Audrow Nash: So this is like
going to, I don't know small
towns and things like this and
or at least individual places
and talking to them and telling
them. This is what we're doing
talking to the local police
department. How How will it be
to go bigger than there? So if
it's like, statewide, or federal
or?
Jason Richards: Sure, yeah, when
I talk to local police
department like Portland, Oregon
isn't isn't a small town, right.
But I'm calling you know, the
Portland Police Department and
talking to them, whoever you
have to talk to, you know, at
that, at that level, let them
know what's going on. Going from
there, though, most of the
regulations are actually going
through the Department of
Transportation. So it's finding
who at the department of
transportation needs to be aware
of this, if you're going to make
a law. Again, the legislative
process takes a long time, you
know, for laws. So I would not
recommend usually people go that
route first. Especially if
they're a smaller VLANs
Audrow Nash: are going to keep
growing kind of unfettered, you
would need these laws in place
at a state and then maybe
federal level, correct for this
kind of thing.
Jason Richards: Yeah. And
federally, I don't know if that
will ever, it might, you know,
come come about some regulatory
agency like the FAA, the Federal
Aviation Administration for
drones, but probably not, it'll
probably stay at a state level
and a local level. And so the
more that you can build rapport
there
Audrow Nash: by completing all
of the local police departments,
yep,
Jason Richards: that you're safe
on there, and you're going to be
responsible. That's the thing
that people care about more than
anything, it's this thing is
safe, and we're being
responsible. And even the bigger
piece of that, you know,
obviously we don't have time
talking about privacy and you
know, things like that data
security, this isn't big brother
spying on you, you know, that
kind of thing. But, but as long
as people know, they know that
they
Audrow Nash: may get it written
in Yeah, yeah. Okay. Yeah,
that's cool. Let's see. So what
is the timeline for you guys
like beginning to wrap up? What
do you expect the next few years
for you guys? Or where are you
going? Yeah, yeah.
Jason Richards: So I expect the
next couple, a couple of years,
you know, 2022, the goal is
really to have about 100 robots
out in service in different
places, we want to keep it to
about, you know, 10, maybe 12
geographic locations, you know,
so by that, you know, Los
Angeles, well, there's Long
Beach, and there's different
places. So, you know, if we're
in Greater Los Angeles, how do
we grow from there from that
hub? Atlanta, Georgia, you know,
how do we grow from that hub, we
go to Washington, DC, how do we
go from that hub. And so we want
to have about 10 to 12 hubs or,
you know, bigger deployments in
a geographic region that we can
then grow and expand from,
because that will really, you
know, really set the tempo for
commercializing. So with the
crowdfunding rounds, being able
to build the robots that we need
to deploy them into these areas.
And then once we have that,
essentially, the operational
piece has been figured out,
right, there's revenue, so that
more it'll attract more
investors, maybe higher level
investors. So then we can go
from that and then manufacture
on a greater scale to, you know,
1000 o'clock, this kind of
thing? Exactly, yeah, bring the
cost down, bring the autonomy
up. Because both of those things
happen, right? It makes you
know, better, better margins, so
you can grow faster, and then be
able to be more the face of
robots in the same way that
Tesla became kind of the face of
electric cars. We think that DAX
is going to be more of the face
of, of urban robotics that does
delivery, because delivery
robots, again, isn't a unique
example, or isn't a unique idea.
But the way that we're going
about it is that it's cool.
People want that to be in their
towns and on their streets. So
it's going to be readily
accepted in in ways that other
companies probably won't be
right now.
Audrow Nash: Or hopefully, so
yeah. Yeah. Awesome. Okay. And
then, what have been some of
the, like, larger challenges for
you guys so far? And what would
you do differently? to kind of
get even where you are still?
Jason Richards: Yeah, um, larger
challenges. You know, one of the
things, you know, is, is
building an operating system
from the ground up because
Audrow Nash: of an operating
system from the ground. Yeah.
Jason Richards: Oh, yeah. Called
DAX Oh, s that are DAX, those,
say, Dax.
Audrow Nash: It's like, we're at
the end of the interview. And
that's a very interesting thing.
Okay.
Jason Richards: It is very
interesting. The founder, great,
great guy. And so his his thing
is, you know, obviously,
business savvy enough to know
that we can't just open up
access to everybody out there in
open source at this point. But
that is the ultimate, you know,
I think that's his ultimate
objective is he wants to be able
to open up DAC, so S, which is a
Ross like, software, you know,
but it's way more than
Audrow Nash: that it does
message passing and things like
this store. Yeah. Yeah. And it
helped and visualization
perhaps.
Jason Richards: Yeah, it does,
it does a lot of pieces. And one
of the pieces that we have is,
as far as the firmware piece is
called a nova node. So it, it
basically is an extensible piece
of the robot. So you can plug in
another Nova node. So for
example, we say, Okay, we need
an iteration where DAX has an
arm so we can push buttons or
whatever, we plug in another
Nova node. And then DAX knows,
oh, now I have this arm. And now
I'm able to do this, this thing.
And it's, it's a higher level
intelligence and has to do with
a lot of the patents in the
higher level architecture stuff.
But Daksa was that was that's
something that is absolutely
fascinating to me, my background
is software. So it's, it's
really fun for me to be able to
nerd out with the the software
guys a little bit and hear the
high level architecture around
it. And again, that that was one
of the things that the founder
wants, I mean, he he, this is
the vision that he has for this
could be like a future thing. So
we want to make a an operating
system that, you know, that is
able to be open source so that
other people can can develop
against it as well and build
their own stuff similar to like
how Ross is, if that makes
sense. You know, people are
familiar with the Ross, you
know, robot operating system.
But DAX DAX Oh, s would be
similar in that vein.
Audrow Nash: So like, is it? Is
it a real operating system?
Because the robot operating
system is not a real operating
system? It's like a flavor of
Linux or something, or what is
your deck? So yeah, you'd be
right about that. Yeah,
Jason Richards: it's it's it's
more of a flavor of another one.
But it's, yeah. When you talk
about Ross, people think oh,
operating. I know. Yes. The
communists know, for sure. Yeah.
But so. So yeah, we'll put it
that way. Yes. So yeah, on
Linux, a lot of Linux based.
Audrow Nash: I feel like it's a
very interesting idea. And one
of the things that I see is kind
of like I mean, one of the
things that's really nice with
Ross is the whole community and
all of the things that have kind
of become fairly battle hardened
there. If it's if it's too big
of a deviation from like Ubuntu
or some of the other larger
distributions, I feel like it
would make it so that there is
you can't reuse a lot of what
exists even like, sensor
packages and stuff. But you guys
are clearly doing things with
different sensors. So yeah, I
don't know, right? Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah. Is it similar enough that
you can use like anything on
Ubuntu? Or? Oh, okay. So it's
not that large of a deviation
for this kind of thing? Is it
real time? So is it a real time
operating system? Yes. Cool. So
it's deterministic? That's
awesome.
Jason Richards: Yeah, it's one
of the one of the patents that
Audrow Nash: could be my talking
a little bit longer. So we could
talk a bit about this shirt.
Yeah. I talked about that
something at the hour to run a
no, no, i Yeah. i
Jason Richards: I'll take off a
little bit after that. But yes,
yeah. So the the high level, one
of the patents that was out
there is being able to
essentially have a voting
system. How did the I don't
remember how was put it
basically democratizing decision
making. So with the, the Nova
nodes, for example, you know,
that the robot has several
different ways that it can
communicate, but then how does
it know which is is the most
important thing to do? So for
example, you say, hey, robot,
you need to take this package
and deliver it to this, this
destination robot thing goes
down that that road and says,
oh, there's a tree in the way.
This boat is telling me that I
need to go that way. You know,
what did the other boats say?
And being able to then analyze,
what are all the other factors
going on? What is the next thing
that we do? And so that was that
is? I'm like, What's your
Audrow Nash: tree? But like, it
sounds like, I mean, so you
could have a state machine or
something. But it sounds I mean,
then that could be represented
as behavior a lot more. You have
more logic kind of built in,
baked into it. Right?
Jason Richards: Okay, a lot
more. Exactly. And a lot more
real time type logic, like, what
is going on, right now, as the
environment is changing? Because
the environments changing all
the time, like, do I stop? And
so a better example would be
like, Okay, I'm, I'm supposed to
deliver this package, but I see
this, this six year old girl
coming towards me, do I stop and
talk to the girl? You know,
based on what based on? Oh, I've
got time? You know, okay, yeah,
that would vote. Okay, we're
gonna vote, we're gonna stop for
30 seconds and say hi to this
girl, versus just blowing past
because I've got something to
do. But sometimes it can be
known, this is a higher vote,
because you need to get to this
destination by this period. And
you know, so. So that that is a
big piece of kind of the patents
behind it is being able to have
a voting system. Yeah. I mean,
to know what to do next.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. Yeah.
I mean, the voting system, like
you could you could figure out
an, like, several ways of
scheduling, what would be
important. It could be
probabilistic. It could be like
a integer voting system count.
It could be real numbers, or
whatever it might be. Yeah. And
then it sounds like it's a
movie. So it sounds like you
have more of a behavior tree
setup, where it's like, I'll
choose this or this or this
based on different options that
are available. And that's very
baked into this, this kind of
conditional logic of what to do.
So maybe it has a nice
representation of how to encode
these kinds of behaviors, or
something is that so it has a
nice way for programmers to
define what it is to that should
be considered in making
decisions or how to prioritize?
Yes, yeah.
Jason Richards: Yes. I'm sure
that Wilkinson is our he was a,
he worked at Tesla for a while,
and I'm sure he would be shaking
sensing. Jason, you're totally
butchering it. He was one of the
main architects of it. But
anyway,
Audrow Nash: so with that, I
noticed right now, you don't
have very much on your on the
company GitHub website. Yeah. It
would be very nice if this that
you're talking about would be
open source. So that can be
poked around. And we can look at
it in this kind of thing,
because that would be very cool.
What Yeah, what is on there is
mostly JavaScript, which is
interesting to me. Could you
tell me a little bit about the
decision? I don't know. It's
like your operating system. A
lot of the code that you're
running is running in like a
Node js framework, which is like
a, but is it server side
JavaScript framework?
Jason Richards: Yeah, we get a
lot. We do do a lot in Node js.
Audrow Nash: So Gotcha. Yeah,
you Interesting. So it's gonna
be like a no JS Ross like thing
that has behavior trees. Would
that be a way to think of? What
do you call it again, called
DAX.
Jason Richards: So DAX is just
like the robot XO
Audrow Nash: s. Okay. Yeah.
Yeah. Gotcha. Cool. Yeah. Any
timeline on open sourcing that?
Because around No,
Jason Richards: I don't have a
timeline. And, unfortunately,
right, you have to wait, you
know, the business, the business
decisions versus, you know, it's
somewhat similar, similar with
patents, you know, anybody that
that has dealt with patents or,
you know, litigation around
that, patents aren't necessarily
the end all, it's not like, hey,
we invented this thing. And
nobody, it's actually more of a
defensive mechanism. So if a
company decided that they wanted
to file a lawsuit with us and
say, Hey, we have this patent on
this thing, and it's really a,
well, we have a patent to, you
know, so this is why we're
allowed to operate in this
space. So, so that that is, from
a business standpoint, that's
the same reason that patents
exist. But the other piece of it
too, obviously, is protecting
intellectual property, I get
that. But in the same way, like,
you know, writing, you know,
source code and things like
that, if you let out too much of
the secret sauce, when you're in
like infancy type stages, you
know, like this, it could, could
put you out of business, not
super likely know, that somebody
would take and be like, Oh,
we're gonna do exactly what DAX
did. But the but the founder,
that's definitely one of the
things that he absolutely loves,
is, you know, wanting to make
this open source. So I don't
know what the dollar amount is,
or the the comfort level is to
the point where he's gonna want
to open this up to the world.
But that's something that he
talks about pretty regularly,
you know, wanting Okay, well,
that'd be really cool. It
Audrow Nash: would probably be a
good way to battle hardened it
to absolute like you guys are
running it. And what I mean, so
you said you currently have
about 10 robots. By the time you
have 1000 robots or something
like this, it'll probably like,
the software is going to get a
lot more battle hardened,
because you'll just have run it
through so many things, but the
community probably could help in
that process. Oh, yeah.
Absolutely. Like, it's amazing.
To me some of the things like I
mean, there's so I guess, I
don't know what's public that I
can say. But there's a lot of
very, I would not expect open
source to be used in a lot of
really critical projects that
are done by companies that have
a lot of stake in reliability.
And I'm very impressed that a
lot of open source software is
being used there. So it does
battle hardened. And so it might
be a benefit for that reason to
and then also people would have
a better point of comparison to,
to look at it and see if it's
useful and this kind of thing.
And that would be awesome. Yeah,
absolutely. Okay, so now we are
going a little over time. What
do you I guess, wrapping up any
links or contact info or
anything you'd like to share
with our listeners?
Jason Richards: Sure. Yeah, I
think that, again, you know,
those that are listening just
via audio, you know, can't see
the robot behind me. So if you
go to DAX bot.com, that's D AX
vo t.com. That's, you know, you
can see kind will
Audrow Nash: links with the
episode so that they can just
click if they look in the
description.
Jason Richards: Yeah. And then
those of you that that are so
inclined, start engine comm
slash dexpot is where we're
doing our crowdfunding raise.
And you can take a look at kind
of the kind of the more the
business plan around it, you
know, kind of the the need and
the focus that we're, we're
filling and all the legal stuff
we filed with the Securities
Exchange Commission. So anyway,
those would be the two things
tax bot.com and and start engine
slash tax bot. And yeah,
Audrow Nash: appreciate that.
All right. Awesome. Been great
interviewing you. Yeah, you too.
Thanks so much. Audrow. Thanks
for listening to this
conversation with Jason
Richards. Thank you again to our
founding sponsor, open robotics
and I hope to see you next time