Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Matt Robinson,
who is a program manager for
ROS industrial Americas at the
Southwest Research Institute.
ROS industrial is a group that
seeks to help industrial users
for example, factories, leverage
ROS and its ecosystem. ROS
industrial has many parts,
including a GitHub organization
for code contributions, regional
consortiums, and a newly
announced working group. In this
interview, Matt and I talk about
how industry often solves
problems and how those solutions
can be improved with more modern
tooling like ROS and get Matt's
background, ROS industrials
consortium and ROS industrials
new working group. This is the
sensing X Podcast. I'm Audrow
Nash. Thank you to our founding
sponsor, Open Robotics. And here
is my conversation with Matt
Robinson. Hi, Matt, would you
introduce yourself?
Matt Robinson: Yes, absolutely.
I'm Matt Robinson. I'm the grace
industrial America's consortium
program manager based here at
Southwest Research Institute.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, would you
give me a bit of background on
ROS industrial?
Matt Robinson: Yeah. So. So ROS
industrial is an open source
project that seeks to extend
ROS, robot operating system to
industrial uses and applications
in industrial relevant hardware.
Right. So it was it was kind of
conceived around 2011. And then
around 2013, a consortium was
established to kind of help give
guidance to what we should be
working on next.
Audrow Nash: And can you define
industrial for me? Like what
does it mean to be like, what
are we targeting Exactly? With
industrial? In this?
Matt Robinson: Yeah, no, that's
a great question. Right. And we
get that a lot, right. So
there's a lot of sometimes
assumptions, when you tag
something as industrial in the
context of the ROS industrial
open source project. We are
seeking to provide open source
utilities that enable industrial
applications on industrial
relevant hardware. So that's the
mean, the main components of the
industrial tag, if you will,
right, there's a lot of specific
hardware that shows up in the
automation space, in factories,
and sometimes it's somewhat,
they could have like a bit long
in the tooth, right. I mean,
like, it's very common for
certain industrial industrial
sectors to put hardware that
they expected to be there for
1015 years. And so they're very
proven pipelines to facilitate
these automated processes that
are somewhat unique, right? So
we want to provide in your
faces, needs to interact and
take advantage of this robust
ecosystem. And so that's where
the extending of ROS into this
industrial space was kind of the
main component. Now that said,
as part of like, kind of like
our overriding themes and
mission is to think about the,
when people hear industrial,
where are they sort of these
things, I think, are they think
of reliability, durability,
quality, right? uptime, things
of that nature? Right? So what
are things we have to do is we
think about the capabilities
that we seek to deliver, and
tools we seek to provide, how do
we how do we realize those sort
of attributes?
Audrow Nash: Very interesting.
So going back a little bit
industrial relevant hardware,
how and you mentioned that it
should be around for a long
time, so people can plan to use
it. How do you select your
industrial relevant hardware?
Matt Robinson: Right? That's a
good question, too. Right. So
let's, let's talk about a couple
of examples of what industrial
relevant hardware may be right?
So it's kind of an it can be
somewhat ambiguous. So the
industrial manipulator, right,
so we think about, if you've
seen like the big snapshot of
like a place where they make
cars and have all of the arms
reaching in and there's
sometimes sparks flying if it's
a video, that's sort of the
industrial manipulator of
retargeting not like, behind me,
we have a number of these other
types of manipulators as well
that are sort of set up to these
in depending on the application
can work around people. But that
is also a class of industrial
relevant hardware in the context
of the manipulator. But we also
look at things like PLCs, the
programmable logic controller,
you know, provided by companies
like Rockwell and Bradley, and
of course, Siemens. And, of
course, looking at like
different like sort of vision
tools, both emerging
contemporary 3d cameras, all the
way back to Your traditional 2d
cameras which have been running
in factory lines for like last
30 years. That's sort of the
those are just some examples of
industrial hardware that we seek
to help people be able to bring
and merge with the capabilities
that are kind of coming forward
in the ROS ecosystem.
Audrow Nash: And what was kind
of the problem or something that
made it so you or whoever
started off industrial? Like,
why did it? Why did you begin it
what problem kind of led to you
wanting to create this
organization?
Matt Robinson: Right, so, you
know, my view like, and we can
talk a bit about, like the whole
layers and Thrall some
industrial, the ROS industrial
open source project was was
started as inspired by actually
a little bit similar to my
background as well, with the
group here at Southwest Research
Institute, and also deliver
solutions. Now, it's not like a
solution provider integrator in
the traditional sense, being a
not for profit Institute here at
Southwest Research Institute,
but the group here develops like
sort of like unique Hi, Max, one
of a kind, oftentimes, prototype
solutions that live and operate
in factory environments or field
environments that have been
doing so since the early 80s. Up
until or before they adopted
ROS, very often, they would
develop that advanced
application with the industrial
tools that were available at the
time. Right, so the industrial
manipulator and the control
platform that comes with the
Cuca, robot, or fanic, or ABB,
they would develop those
solutions, it gets something
working that does something new
and novel, but lo and behold,
they had to do something
similar. But someone specified a
different mix, if you will, of
the industrial hardware, they
had to basically rewrite the
software from scratch, right,
because of the industrial
ecosystem. The the whole stack
from the hardware all the way
back through how you develop
applications for that hardware
operates in a proprietary chain,
if you will. And we'll call it a
software stack. Exactly. But but
all those communication, the
middleware, if you will, as well
as like the programming language
and environments, they are all
proprietary to that hardware set
you're selecting. And then even
certain vendors, like would kind
of team up and have better
bridges are complementing those
companies. And so yeah, it
wasn't like swappable
Audrow Nash: for all these
different. So you'd make a
solution. And we'd be like a
mobile base, and then there'd be
a robot arm on it. And the
mobile phase and the robot arm,
we both have kind of like their
own ways of talking. So it was
like a domain specific language
often for using either of those.
And then you would have to have
software that is kind of
translating between them, so
that you can make them talk and
do some sort of application. Is
Matt Robinson: that correct? Or
you'd have to write in that
specific domain? Sure, right, in
that specific domain. Correct.
And that's usually what
happened. And that's from as
well, I got very adept at
scripting and, you know, vendor
specific programming languages.
And that's where a lot of us who
were doing, you know,
traditional industrial robot
deployments, dating back to the
early 90s, that's kind of how we
came up. Right. And so, you
know, the challenges is like,
hey, this industrial robotic
solution may offer some
advantages. But it brings with
it different software, different
scripting languages, how how you
implement applications, how you
set up communications, you have
to actually factor that if you
were going to actually look at
other other other solutions. And
so obviously, the advent of this
group here in front, Edwards is
in the picture behind me when
they went out to Willow Garage,
and kind of that first discover
motivator about somewhere around
2011, he created that first
interoperability between Boston
and Boston, but there was an
Aha. So hey, I can develop an
advanced application in a sort
of hardware agnostic fashion,
and not have to reinvent all
this stuff. Because I have to do
some other application with a
different hardware stuff like
that in the industrial robotic
space. That was, that was like a
real a huge one.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, yeah. So it
was a reuse. real opportunity.
Okay.
Matt Robinson: Okay, this is
big,
Audrow Nash: can you speak a bit
more, so it was a big
opportunity, because you could
make it so that instead of using
these domain specific languages
for each hardware component, you
could instead maybe abstract out
that component and then connect
to it with ROS or some other
like, high level thing that you
can use as middleware for this.
Okay. And then that gives you
the ability to just worry about
you so you Your interface for
this, whatever the device is,
then you use it in a stack. And
then you can swap it out with
other components. You can swap
new things in, as long as they
have interfaces, you have one
way of talking to them and
controlling them. Right?
Matt Robinson: Yes, that is
obviously the goal. Obviously,
the devils in the details,
always. But But yes, exactly
right. And that was definitely
new in industrial circles,
right. And either became very
good at working with like, you
know, a Cuca, oriental scholar
or offenen,
Audrow Nash: and maybe their own
language in a sense, and a lot
of
Matt Robinson: literally right,
in different support. And they
encourage people like when I
came from industry, I mean,
obviously, like, vendor X wanted
us to buy all of their stuff,
including their software
programming environments, they
were incentivized to not foster
interoperability at the time. So
fortunately, like, right, this
notion of abstraction, which is
obviously very common in the
software world, was sort of not
a new concept to develop
industrial applications.
Audrow Nash: Now, going back a
little bit, I would love to hear
about your background, and kind
of how you got started with all
of us.
Matt Robinson: You've Right,
right. So to catch up for the
listeners, right, I have to
confess that I'm not a software
developer, right. So I came out
of like, sort of like materials,
joining materials, research,
welding materials and metals,
domain. In caught on with
Caterpillar, the, the heavy
industry equipment producer, and
engine manufacturer, I worked in
our corporate research group,
and quickly got into developing
the applications on robots,
largely focusing in the early
phases on specifically welding.
Some of it pretty complex
welding operations, were trying
to control different things to
realize very specific outcomes.
And we had a lot of success in
developing applications, you
know, we had these this robot,
right, and it was all set up and
had all these extra bells and
whistles. And we get something
working really great. Like,
okay, take that and go around
the world and make it work. And
then very quickly, we learned,
Audrow Nash: what do you mean,
take that and go around the
world and make it work? So like,
deploy that scale? Or what do
you mean,
Matt Robinson: but it scales
relative for a caterpillar is
not a, you know, not a Ford or
GM, right. And so it'd be like,
you know, they may make, you
know, a given product, like a
wheel loader, they may make it
in five or six places. And the
robots may be like, maybe three
or four per site. Because you're
only because you're not making
as many wheel loaders as you're
like, you know, border states.
So, you know, not enough, not
enough, let's say buying power
to really put pressure on OEMs
to play nice, not enough buying
power to justify buying an exact
same piece of equipment and
shipping it around the world. So
what would happen is
Audrow Nash: like this lighter
spot, of where you're not able
to scale incredibly effectively,
because you don't have all the
factories lined up for it. So it
was fairly custom solutions. But
it's also big enough that you
want to deploy it 20 times or I
don't know, some some larger
number of times where it has to
be you like all the all the bugs
will come out. And it will be
unreliable unless you kind of
work it out. Well,
Matt Robinson: yeah, I, you
know, if we scale back to just
sort of a very manufacturing
benefit, in particular for
dealing with something that has
to do meaningful work in the
field, right. So like, we alert,
right, it's got to lift heavy
stuff. There's a tangible
benefit if I can use robots to
make it because the consistent
quality actually leads to a
better performing product that I
can sell to people, right, it
lifts more, it weighs less. So
it consumes less gas, or diesel
in the case of big equipment.
And so there's a real incentive
as a real marketing improved
product, I can go out there and
sell if I can leverage
automation to produce it. Now
the challenge was because we
weren't we're not you know, that
particular group I was working
with was not, you know, they
can't buy 1000s of robots,
right? GM has a real benefit
when they work with industrial
robot providers, because they
buy so many, they can make a lot
of, you know, dictate some
rules.
Audrow Nash: They say I want to
do custom thing that's going to
be a bunch of additional work.
And because of the scale of it,
the people making the robots are
like, Okay, we'll do that. That
sounds good to us.
Matt Robinson: Yeah. And I felt
like obviously, obviously, there
was a lot of other folks, if you
will, in the same boat that I
was, right where, hey, these
different sites that could
justify buying automation, but
when it came that they couldn't
necessarily buy exactly the same
thing due to support like they
would buy different brands
because that's what was
available and how
Audrow Nash: I could see why
this was so funny. because if
you're by different parts,
because different brands are
available in different regions,
now you have to hook up to that
domain specific thing. And
really quick.
Matt Robinson: Yeah, we had an
application running really well
on a nice orange robot with this
right sensor located on a
totally different mix of
hardware. And we literally
showed up, I showed up in, you
know, this other location and
had to start from scratch. My,
my, my one week trip turned into
like a month. So that that ended
up being one of the real resume
business cases to when I was at
Caterpillar to get involved with
the ROS industrial open source
projects. Well, I learned that
aerospace companies, other heavy
equipment, manufacturers, oil
and gas companies, you know,
ticking through a few even even
tier one automotive, right?
Because they have a slightly
different problem than say your
GM example.
Audrow Nash: We're here wanna
automotive? Is that like, the
really big car companies? Or I
don't know what their
Matt Robinson: tier one
whatever, there's automotive or,
or any letters? Is anyone who
provides the parts to the OEM or
the person?
Audrow Nash: Okay, and OEM is
original equipment
manufacturing, manufacturing.
Matt Robinson: So GM, yep.
Right? GM, you know, they make
the car, they're the OEM and a
company that's providing them
like, say, the seats or the
dashboard, assembly would be a
two.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so the parts
that go into the final product,
that's the tier one, so it keeps
going back. So tier two is the
ones that provide the parts to
tier one. Is it correct?
Matt Robinson: Okay, like,
right. Now we're getting into
supply chain, which is very
resident in the pandemic era.
Right? Yeah. So, but, uh, but
but, uh, sorry, one of my
speakers went out. But, but
yeah, so So we ended up learning
that a lot of other producers,
manufacturers, people interested
in adopting the benefits of
robotics ran on the same
challenges. And that was really
insightful. And all of a sudden,
we're starting to build this
little industrial community,
Audrow Nash: it's like, the
challenge was explicitly that
most things were not able to
talk well to each other because
of domain specific languages or
like custom hardware setup. So
it was like, they were very
reliable industrial devices, but
they didn't play nice with other
things. So developing kind of
like custom automation
solutions, were a was an
extremely difficult task,
because of this, the domain
specific languages that they
were
Matt Robinson: enrolled in. And
I was, I would say, that was
obviously very prescient, in
your face a big challenge. But
obviously, it also drove a lot
of like, limited ability for
reuse, you know, drove, so a lot
of like, you know, hey, we'd
fund some research in a
university, and we can maybe get
it to a point solution, but we
couldn't really leverage it
properly. Yeah. So, you know, we
ended up learning a lot of this
other sort of, you know, when
you go back and look at, you
know, how a lot of software
companies have evolved over the
years, the presence of open
source, how it's able to be
leveraged? What do we talk
about? What do we mean by pre
competitive IP, like all this
was sort of new in some of the
industrial circles, at least
that I ran in? Before, before I
got involved with the details
with less industrial, and
learning that a lot of other
manufacturers had these same
challenges. It was a learning
experience.
Audrow Nash: Okay, and then so
you were at Caterpillar? Where
did you go from? So you and then
you were building these kind of
custom solutions for doing some
sort of automation task that
would improve a fairly small
man, like you're making only? I
don't know the numbers, but you
had like 20 robots making them
or something, some product, but
a wheel loader, or whatever you
have mentioned? Yeah. Where do
you go from there?
Matt Robinson: So, you know,
like I said, I worked in
corporate research in we had a
little automation team. And so
we started basically
collaborating with the team here
at Southwest Research Institute
to identify some potential near
term use cases or business cases
around like, what what does ROS
really offer us? Right? Okay.
Audrow Nash: So at this time,
you had been exposed to ROS or
like, how did ROS come into the
picture?
Matt Robinson: We ran into the
ROS industrial team at a
conference. Okay? And ask them
we're like, Hey, what is this?
Tell us about it? And my
predecessor, Paul Voss, and
Shaun Edwards, again, pictured
over my shoulder for those
watching the video. Their boss,
Paul Evans, they came out to
caterpillar and explained it to
us, right, and then we found a
way to kind of get involved and
hence there was already this
consortium established. And as
Caterpillar, we join that
consortium, right, so I was kind
of the caterpillar face for the
ROS industrial consortium. And
I started like, kind of
collaborating and sharing core
stories with other members. But
then how do we move the ball
forward? leveraging open source
and is this is this something we
can really do in an industrial
setting? That was still a
question. Back in like,
20 2015 2014? Wow, I can't be
like why we actually saw can we
solve industrial problems with
with ROS?
Audrow Nash: Source? Yeah, yeah.
And what did to? And then how
did that investigating that
question go?
Matt Robinson: Great, right. So
obviously, we got involved. The
consortium has a bunch of other
similar minded folks with
similar challenges. You know,
and it's not relevant. It's not
narrow to like, say,
construction equipment or
whatever, I rattle off a couple
of other industries, the Boeing,
Boeing's and others, there was a
documentary for our BMW not long
ago. And so, you know, we got
involved with a couple different
pilot initiatives to kind of see
if we could prove like, hey,
what can we do? You know, to
that point, everything we did
was very, you know, I grabbed up
the user interface, the Teach
pendant on the robot, and I, you
know, programmed it, I could
script it on my computer and
then loaded onto the robot. But
I was still really, I'd still
have to go through and tweak all
those positions, like, right,
you try their interface
Audrow Nash: for how to do it.
Yeah. Right. So I've heard I've
heard some horror stories about
that. But I don't know that I
really. So that's crazy. You
would like it's like this big
tablet? And you would like,
would it be like a block
programming kind of thing on
some interface that the company
may? Or?
Matt Robinson: It's it's
scripting? Yeah, it's a
scripting language. And, and
this would be like, if I was
more prepared, I would have
probably wheeled over one of
these robots who could have done
it live. But but but no, it was
very laborious. And they were
introducing things like offline
programming, but it was really
just sitting at your desk or
doing it on a computer. Lab and
or on the shop floor?
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah. Cuz you
couldn't see what I was doing.
You could just write the bulk of
it from your computer.
Matt Robinson: Yeah. And you
might have like, a visualization
perfectly matches the physical
system. Right. So that's why
when we talk about the utilities
that for industrial use cases,
one of the ones is all the stuff
around calibration. And so we
ran some pilot programs during
my time at Caterpillar and was
like, Oh, wow, like, I could
really not do this traditional
industrial robot programming
with this teaching with the
Teach pendant or whatever, at an
offline. You know, hey, we can
basically do this notion of
like, you know, use perception
perceive things, leverage the
data streams to make decisions,
do motion planning, and actually
execute processes that was mind
blowing at the time, like in
this 2013 2014 timeframe. And so
we ran a couple pilot projects
in parallel, like we'd already
been doing work and perception,
like, hey, wow, 3d cameras, this
is this is really useful. And
notions of segmentation, right?
Like, oh, work on this and not
that. In so we've been doing
work with universities in that
space. But again, it was really
hard to scale. So bringing
generalize it
Audrow Nash: and yeah, you said
it was like a point solution. So
it's solving one specific
problem, but not, it doesn't
generalize to other problems
very easily.
Matt Robinson: Okay, we're x. So
we started getting into like,
what they called at the time,
this focus technical project,
which are these collaborative
projects in the ROS industrial
Consortium on blending, and
blending is this notion of
getting some sanding media. If
you think about your, your wood
furniture at home, like you're
going to refinish it, you want
to blend all those surfaces
together, right? So you can
repaint it, right. That's
basically what we're doing with
metal parts, we perceive them.
If it's a flat surface, I apply
some raster patterns. And then
you can sit there and visualize
the motion plan. And yeah, that
looks reasonable go never got
it. No teach pendant
programming. I don't necessarily
like drawing stuff on CAD files,
which you know, doesn't
necessarily save you time. Those
are very legal demonstrations of
proof of proof of concepts were
able to do it Caterpillar they
got really good by. That's
awesome. Then from from there
and continue to grow. This
notion of collaborative projects
and things like that. And so
now, a handful of years later, I
had the opportunity to kind of,
you know, streaking it up to the
open source Kool Aid and this
idea of leveraging ROS 2 solve
industrial problems. I had a
chance to come here and take
over the ROS industrial project
here from my predecessor, Paul
Voss, and I did that in 2017.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And how
does it actually so one thing is
when you're saying, like
collaborative work on these, you
mean basically using something
like I don't know, some version
control like Git or something so
that programmers can work on it
at the at different times in
different places and kind of all
collaborate towards one product.
Yes. Is this what you mean? Oh,
Matt Robinson: my God, like back
then, like in our life.
Manufacturing Research that was
all very new, like get get what?
Like right? At the time like,
right so that that idea of
collaborating on software from
different locations, we did that
collaborative project and the
ROS industrial sort of family,
if you will, the consortium we
partnered with Boeing was a
performer on that particular
project, as well as wolf
robotics was like the solution
provider out of Fort Collins,
they're now part of Lincoln
Electric, and of course, as
Caterpillar, and we offer like
little in kind contributions,
like we developed our team
developed a key driver for this
laser line scanner. But yeah,
but to your point, right, there
was the first time that we had
to script up stuff, put it
someplace where other people can
merge it in. And, and that sort
of workflow. workflow is very
new to a group that was very
used to like, I'm developing
right on the robot controller,
right? I'm not, I'm not putting
it someplace where it's really,
truly accessible by others. And
can be like, you know, you know,
it could be reviewed version of,
of that Git workflow, if you
will. And that's, that's been a
slow process, we still work with
traditional industrial
stakeholders that are still
getting up to speed on that kind
of get workflow. And that's been
that's been a fun ride. As we
talk about software and
industrial settings, obviously,
here in early 2020s. I mean,
right, between the startup
communities and the prevalence
or emergence of ROS and people
looking at industrial
applications, it's becoming more
commonplace. But like, in the
early 2010s, it was non
existent, almost. We had to
figure out what GitHub was
right? We have to get permission
to use it. Yeah, right. Because
the IRS corporate IT groups are
like, Oh, the
Audrow Nash: internet? Yeah, the
internet's bad. Yeah, you're
putting your stuff on there.
Yeah. It's kind of I mean, so I
guess I have most of my
background is in software, I
would say. And it is shocking to
me to hear that it was, it's
like 2010 10 years ago, ish.
That, like these kind of things
that I associate, as modern
workflows are not being used.
But that's very interesting. And
so the pipeline, but how it
typically worked, it was you
have several people that are
working on different things, and
you modularize the problem, so
that each person can do or we,
each entity can work on one
thing and have that one thing,
do it very well. And then you
just combine them and in theory,
it works perfectly. Is that is
that kind of like the
traditional way of doing things?
Matt Robinson: That's probably
Yeah, so you'd have the person
who's doing like the robot
programming, you'd have a person
who's doing like, let's say,
there's some sensor on the robot
that's gonna do some thinking or
processing a lot, the one person
who sets that up and programs
it. And then you have like, say,
an electrical engineer who who
slash controls person who might
do your PLC and control like
electrical panel, and then yes,
and then there's an integration
sort of period of time, where
all three of them will come
together and try to like, make
sure all their stuffs
communicating properly. That's,
that's actually, in some
regards, still a similar
workflow that we use here. And
we do advanced systems as we
bolted on also the software
development piece, right, which,
which enables us to kind of at
least addressed interfaces, we
can test a lot of the interfaces
and message passing, you know,
in simulation, we have a few
more tools at our disposal than
we had 10 years ago. And
obviously, even though here,
we're advanced, say compared to
traditional manufacturers, you
know, we still have to overcome
some of the limitations of the
industrial hardware, what it
will just support, right, like,
every every everyone, like no
one has like it, this notion of
a documented API. Not nice.
Right?
Audrow Nash: So there's no
application programmer interface
to, like use the things kind of
clearly.
Matt Robinson: Yeah, I mean,
well, because again, we're going
their scripting language, maybe
exactly, just did not stay in
our ecosystem,
Audrow Nash: right. That's kind
of in our ecosystem. And that's
kind of
Matt Robinson: a mantra, if you
will, right. So but that's, it's
making progress, right? Like,
you know, we were at a
conference one time, and this
guy stood up and raised his
hand, and he's lying. There was
this time, I downloaded
Solitaire and my computer got a
virus. And now you're telling us
to download download software
off the internet and run our
robots with it. And so that's
where we were starting. The
industrial sector is, I mean,
they've been they've been doing
what they do for an automation
for 50 6070 years and so cases
PLCs been around a long, long
time. So it's right it was a
real disruption to think about,
you know, over and over again,
some open source pieces layer on
kind of just like the stuff of
novel stuff to do this specific
thing. But then like not
reinvent the wheel. And like,
Hey, we're gonna maintain it and
make contributions back to the
stuff in the open source.
Because right rising tide lifts
all boats. And there are some
people that are just like, Wait,
you're going to download stuff
off the internet and run an
industrial robot. I mean, we, it
took a long time to just define
open source get a consensus of
understanding in the industrial
community. And it was funny, I
sat with a peer in Germany, he's
like, You know what? Like, the
whole, like, you can put open
source on an industrial piece of
equipment and have it do
something meaningful in a
factory and the whole place not
melt or break down. We want
that, like, we're doing that.
And we are and lots of people,
lots of great startups over the
years, was it there's that one
article, like 80% of new
startups, whatever the robot
they're putting out there. Like
there's, there's ROS, there's a
ROS something on Yeah, it's
Audrow Nash: crazy. I don't know
the number either, but it's
quite high, which is nuts. And
it's
Matt Robinson: great, right? And
that and that. And that was if
we didn't done nothing else, we
brought the industrial sector to
the party, right, and generated
some general acceptance for open
source and like, Hey, you can do
this, right. And this can work.
And that's, that's been fun.
It's been great to see that
change over time, compared to
where we were, we were like in
the early teens, 20 times.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, I imagine
it's pretty exciting to see kind
of it coming along in this. And
you can probably move a good bit
faster when you adopt some of
these kind of these different
development paradigms like
version control, and you can
collaborate and then you can tie
it with simulation, and you have
all the parts integrated. So you
can test them all together. Even
if it is limited in like, say a
simulation or something, but you
still don't it's not like this
one part. We're only going to
test that. And then we're going
to connect it to something
that's also only tested by
itself. Whereas you can like say
all of these things are in the
the gazebo simulator, and we're
just going to run this control
code on it and see if it does
what we intended to do.
Matt Robinson: That's quite
nice. Okay, so going back.
Audrow Nash: So you were at
Caterpillar? Now, did you go?
How did you end up at?
Matt Robinson: Southwest
Research Institute? Yeah, so you
know, I've been doing my job at
Caterpillar, like 10% Was this
open source? You know, motion
planning, you know, no more
teach better programming robot
stuff. Like that was like, Okay.
And that was the funnest part of
my job, right? And I had all
this other stuff. And I was
like, I was kind of like, yeah,
looking at different
opportunities, right. So I mix
it up. And the guys here heard,
and they're like, Hey, why don't
you come down here? And like,
you know, I'm like, oh, like,
run the ROS Industrial Program.
Like, you got to be kidding me.
I don't know anything about this
stuff, right? I'm just some guy,
like running some projects. Now.
Like, no, no, you have that
perspective of the person who
hates programming. Okay, I
definitely have plenty of that.
And so, so yeah, I, we talked,
and they found a role for me.
And I was like, alright, we'll
give it a shot. And so I came
down and middle of 2017. And
obviously, I brought a little
different perspective, right? I
mean, you know, I, I was putting
robots on the factory floor and
commissioning them and, and then
like, trying to replicate
successes on on certain hardware
or development configurations,
and trying to replicate that and
really struggling. So I brought
that in. So when other people
had that pain, I was like, oh,
yeah, we had that pain, too. And
then like, obviously, I come
from a pure group where, you
know, when someone brings up a
terminals, and they're like,
bouncing between the terminals,
I'm like, yeah, like people in
the industry community can't do
that now. Right? Because we're
not software developers. Right?
So there was this idea of like,
what can we do to to lower the
barrier to entry? And obviously,
we've seen a lot of progress on
that front, right between nice
IDE ease between, you know,
other, like just more Python,
right, lowers the barrier to
entry. You know, there wasn't a
ton of Python stuff. When we
first started poking around, but
all of that helps, right? And so
that the whole lower the barrier
to entry is obviously, part of
our mission is
Audrow Nash: just, I'm sure
people know, mostly but so IDE
is integrated development
environment. And so that's like
where you code. Often it makes
things a lot easier. If you have
a good IDE And then Python,
maybe I don't need to define it,
but just a programming language,
which, for ROS, we are a lot of
C++, which is low level. And we
have some Python, which is like
a nice scripting language. And
so that's higher level easier,
you can say like print,
quotations Hi, and then close
it, and it will print that out.
And so it's like it's easier. So
it makes it nicer for working,
because people can just kind of
see the logic right there. And
it's almost like a human
readable, like, paragraph kind
of thing.
Although it's death,
almost. Okay,
Audrow Nash: so one of the big
parts of ROS industrial, you're
saying is lowering that barrier
of entry? How are you doing
that? Or like, what are some
strategies you guys are working
towards to try to lower the
barrier of entry?
Matt Robinson: That's a great
question. Right. So obviously,
one of the things we do in our
little consortium family is we
provide training, right? And the
training is constantly evolving,
based on the feedback from the
membership, right? So they want
to they want more examples, and
helps them there's like, sort of
templates to do certain classes
of things. Obviously, we've
tried to give an example. Yeah,
maybe, right. But setting up
what a good example is like, we
have a training on setting up a
perception pipeline. Okay,
right. And then we have a
training class, where we
leverage the perception pipeline
to say, like, do a pick and
place down, right, so you
perceive this object, and you
identify and grasp when you go
get it? Right. So we have this
whole lab exercise that takes
place on the top, one of the
pieces of hardware that are
behind me. And then, so they get
to like kind of actually build
an application, but they have
some skeleton to start with.
Right? We went through an
example, right, which can become
sort of the template.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, that's how we
can work with some something
that kind of already works
Matt Robinson: correctly,
obviously, like, sometimes the
feedback is, well, this is a lot
of copy and paste. I don't know
what I'm copying and pasting.
But so it's a continuous
journey. And that, but that
feedback only makes it better.
But obviously, you know, the
more you know, obviously, the
issue is, you know, I mean, the
tech world is rapidly evolving
all the time. So new things are
always coming out. And of
course, what legs is the
documentation that we're in the
same boat where where we've been
doing a lot of interesting new
work and in reconstruction and
different types of motion
planners, we have an
optimization based motion
planning framework that's out
there. So
Audrow Nash: are you for all
these things? are you leveraging
things that are in Rosu? For
your navigation? Are you using
like nav two, for your motion
planning are using like move it?
Or is it kind of custom
solutions for industry things?
Matt Robinson: So where we want
to, we want to stick with, with
what's out there, emerging out
of the community, right? We
really want it's extending ROS
into industrial applications. So
creating like homegrown stuff
kind of defeats the purpose.
Now, obviously, there are cases
where something special needs to
emerge. And thereby, you will
create that, in a lot of cases,
we open sourced. Right, so one
great example that comes up in
our community is the emergence
of Tesseract, which is motion
planning environments very
similar to move it, it was born
out of a very specific use case.
And it was chosen to open source
it, because why not? Right. And
it's still it's still we we
leave, all of our training is
still built on move it we start
with movement. But then for
those interested or specific
applications, we have this
alternative called Tesseract
that, in certain situations
offers some benefits. But we
don't necessarily offer like,
say training on it. It's sort of
like, if your application sort
of would benefit from some of
the things here, you know, we
can do some use on demand,
right? But But in general, we
start with, to your point,
right, the NASDAQ move it and
the tools they're in, we want
people to because the benefit is
the whole benefit of this whole
open source idea is that once we
start using them, we make
contributions back. Right. So if
we made a bunch of replicates of
stuff, well, then we just spread
out the contributions and
they're less impactful. Right?
So we want to start in use the
most common tools as well. And
so yes, so hence we've migrated
our training over to ROS 2 as
well we're trying to as I
described earlier, right the in
the industrial crowd is slow to
move, right because they like
what works. So we've been having
to be very judicious and how we
manage rolling out in the
direction of ROS 2 but but but
we're getting right. Most
recently we also are trying to
revisit our We're gonna phases
because in the industrial side
that's really lagged. But it's a
good opportunity to revisit for
consistency purposes, you can
talk more about that. Yes, for
Audrow Nash: sure. Yeah, that's
very interesting. I want to talk
about that have you got before
have you is one approach that
you guys may do abstracting
things further. So if, say, I
want to move something from here
to here, and from one location
to another, maybe I abstract
what you need to do in that to
or subtract what you need to do
and move it or something so that
it's easier at kind of like,
like, instead of like, I'm gonna
do all like, I want to run this
specific thing, or this set of
commands in NAB to maybe like,
more at a behavioral level or
something like something that's,
that's
Matt Robinson: like, that's
actually it's interesting.
Right? So that's some of the
that sort of like, just kind of
give a higher order kind of
instruction. Yeah, exactly
assist or empower the system to
make the optimal decision. Yeah.
Because like, let's say we have
a mobile manipulator to your
right, we're now getting
involved and move it. I don't
necessarily want to have to
like, push out commands the
boat, right? It needs to be a
higher order. And then let the
system's intelligence sort of
figure out a bunch of
Audrow Nash: smart programmers
figure it out once and then
everyone gets to benefit from it
Matt Robinson: correct. And we
are we are trying to bring to
some proof of concept
capabilities in that space to
present to like, say the
manufacturing engineer knows
process, they know what they
have to do in their factory, but
is it going to, to your point,
command driven or math, right,
they're gonna have to tell it
like, hey, you need to do it
like this, just go do that.
Right? When abstract away, if
you will, that move that voice
level, but that level. Next
level down, we have some proof
of concept initiatives going in
that direction, we have put out
some material on those, and some
of the progress we're making. So
for those interested, you know,
if you when you share the
LinkedIn stuff, you'll see posts
about some of the outcomes from
some of those group meetings
that talk about some of the work
going on what we call our
development environments for
industrial applications. And
that's something we're looking
to hopefully find some people to
poke holes at and and try. And
so we're looking for some beta
testers now, we're hoping that
help some of our industrial
stakeholders lower the barrier
to and again, that whole idea of
lowering the barrier,
particularly as the systems get
more complex, of course, you'll
not just mobile, but we'll do we
do a lot with gantry based
systems. And that's where a
manipulator maybe inverted up
that upside down. And it's an a
huge gantry that has x, y, z.
And it can take that manipulator
through an entire volume.
Audrow Nash: I'm imagining a 3d
printer with an arm instead of
the printing spot.
Matt Robinson: Yeah, absolutely.
Something like that. That's,
that's a great example. And so
obviously, of all the redundant
axes, there's lots of solutions.
How do you how do you search
that space? Right. And so what
are the tools for that? How do
you prioritize using the axes?
Sorry, gantry axes versus the
manipulator axes? I mean, so,
you know, we're trying to bring
tools to kind of enable end
users to
Audrow Nash: take advantage of
that thing. That's interesting.
I don't I don't know much about
use cases for gantries with the
robotic arms on them or
anything. That seems quite cool.
I have you. I don't. I did an
interview earlier with Brett
Aldrich. From Smak. Have you
thought of there? Like, have you
looked at SMAC for kind of like
a higher level way of
controlling robots for specific
tasks? It kind of seems like
their use case.
Matt Robinson: Yeah. So it's
interesting. You mentioned Brett
and snack. I had to today's
Friday. So yesterday, I was at a
Technical Steering Committee
meeting and talking about
hardware interfaces. And and how
we'd like to do a new reference
implementation to kind of herd
the cats on hardware interfaces.
In Brett Pinkney after that
particular meeting, said like,
Hey, we should we should talk
about Smak. I was like, That's a
great idea. So other than like
reading, reading, like three
lines about it, I have immersed
myself derelict on catching up
on some of my reading. I've only
caught wind of Bratton his work
since he was getting engaged
with the Technical Steering
Committee.
Audrow Nash: One of the
community members for sure,
Matt Robinson: correct. Yeah.
And obviously, like when I read
his application, I was like,
Yeah, this guy. This guy's
awesome. For sure. So we're
excited. And I'm glad he reached
out to me and I look forward to
learning more smack Yeah, it's
probably it could be, again
much. You know, we've had folks
like Brett, come speak to our
industrial audience. And so that
those opportunities are existing
and we're just trying to I have
a hard time keeping up and I'm
like in the ROS world more than
I thought
Audrow Nash: my demo directions
in less
Matt Robinson: so right. So
where it makes sense. I tried
to, in some of our organizations
though, like stodgy or right
kind of old school, they do have
people that really are looking
for solutions. And like to hear
from these types of people,
right, so we try to we do a lot
of that matchmaking. Obviously,
if there's a chance to
collaborate with you, we'd love
to see them.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Yeah, if
you maybe some help with the
background, but if you're
speaking with him anyway,
there's a previous podcast
interview with where we went
into like, pretty deep detail on
how SMAC works and where it
might be useful. But so now
you're at Southwest at the
Southwest Research Institute,
sweary. And you're leading ROS
industrial from there, and you
have a bunch of projects and a
team, or what's the setup? And
how does it work? And how does
the organization
Matt Robinson: for great, great,
right, so we have this
manufacturing robotics
department, here at the
Institute. And they leverage all
these tools in their day to day
problem solving. Right? So
they're kind of like, the ROS
industrial developing team, if
you will, are contributors. So
the rest of us are open source
project, but their users as
well. And we try to walk the
talk, right? So we take all
these things, and we go solve
problems with that. Now, how
large
Audrow Nash: is the business
model? And is it tied to a
company and a bunch of things
like this, they don't quite
understand.
Matt Robinson: Essential,
essentially, the Institute at a
high level, right, which has
about 11 operation operating
divisions. One of the most well
known is the Space Science
Division, right? Because they
actually have a mission control
here and lead missions for NASA.
There was a couple different the
New Horizons was one where they
kind of went by and did some
shots of Pluto. Space Science,
and then here in our division,
right, so I'm in a department or
division is three of us what
unmanned ground systems are
applied sensing. And then
critical systems does a lot of
NASA software. And of course, we
collaborate with them as well to
share tips and practices and
where ROS makes sense. But
anyways, so there's, it's all
applied engineering contract
r&d. Actually, when I was at
Caterpillar, we spent a lot of
time here doing dyno testing.
Right, so about half of
caterpillars dyno testing occurs
here at Southwest Research
Institute. It's totally vital.
Sorry, yeah. So it's really
taking the engine. And they
basically try to run it, like so
they put all these they feel
they pump fuel into it and make
sure the exhaust is handled
effectively. But it just sits
there on a stand and runs, they
put it through its paces, they
may, they may make the room,
they may make the room very
cold, and they make
Audrow Nash: very hot so they
can test all the different
conditions while running. I see
Matt Robinson: my anywhere.
Correct, I was supporting on
Highway tear three emissions at
the time for modeling trucks.
Tier three was at the time they
were trying to address diesel
particulates. So I was the
materials person involved with a
lot of the creation of some of
the components for the that
particular exhaust system at the
time. And so they were running a
lot of those tests here. So but
it's but it's multi discipline,
right? So I mentioned space
science, obviously, we're
manufacturing robotics, we have
unmanned ground systems. So we
have all these different groups.
And so
Audrow Nash: an effective thing
around these. Yeah, you have
like, cuz i You say different
domains, but I assume it's like,
fairly similar competencies
between the different domains or
at least complementary in some
sense.
Matt Robinson: Yeah. So you
know, I mean, you're there's a
lot of computer science across
the Institute, a lot of material
science folks like myself,
mostly in the mechanical
engineering division. A lot of
mechanical engineers, a lot of
chemists, we have a whole
chemistry, division as well. So
so but we basically think back
to my group at Caterpillar, I
worked at corporate research.
This group had unique skills
that I didn't have software
skills in my Manufacturing
Research Group, explicitly, I
had some people could do some
Python. So we would work with
this team, we'd write a little
contract, then they worked as
like an extension, corporate r&d
team. I had worked to some
statement of work and help my
team out. And in very much like
I like to describe it, we work
with somebody, we want to lead
them, not just with something we
give them, but their staff is a
little bit better using the
tools than they were before we
show them. Right. So we don't
just deliver them something we
teach them while we work with
them as part of the delivery to
teach them as ons. Yeah, I mean,
here we are using all these open
source tools we want. We don't
want to just give you a software
that we will but ideally you
have someone in your team You
can learn it as well and be self
sufficient. So you don't
necessarily have to us. Oh,
definitely, that's that's sort
of the model here and
proliferates around the
institute. Right? The whole
there's a tagline about
benefiting science in humanity.
So we try to walk that talk,
right? We try to help our
partners teach our partners, as
well as like deliver novel
solutions. The cool thing about
unique about our department
specifically, and our division
is we don't just deliver the
novel solution, but we also try
to make contributions or offer
things in the open source. So
hence, a lot of the robot
drivers, some of the calibration
utilities, they they're born out
of this group, specifically, as
well as some of our partner
groups. ROS industrial is
stewarded by three organizations
you've mentioned Southwest
Research Institute, but I'd be
remiss not to mention Fraunhofer
IPA in Stuttgart, Germany and
the advanced remanufacturing
Technology Center in Singapore,
Stuart ROS, industrial Europe
and ROS industrial Asia
Pacific, respectively. Those
organizations also make great
contributions to open source and
of course, ROS ROS, too, and
ROS industrial.
Audrow Nash: Can you tell me a
bit about the consortium? Around
ROS industrial?
Matt Robinson: Right. So in
2013, and 2013, is when it first
got started, like, there's a lot
you can work on, right, like so
we had all these problems, just
getting the robot like getting
my application to work on all
these different robots. But
there's all this other stuff
like right, should we be doing
motion? To be What about
perception, what to focus
Audrow Nash: on, basically,
writers out there early on
things that you could possibly
focus on?
Matt Robinson: Okay. Yeah, my
apprentice, my predecessor, my
predecessor, Paul Voss, now and
plus one. He, he basically was
like, started, like, basically,
surveying industry is like, Hey,
what are some of your pain
points and work? What's really
working on it just naturally,
sort of like, like, hey, what if
we started a consortium, and you
chip in a little bit, and we
start building up this
repository and maintain it. And
for tools to enable you
Audrow Nash: to chip in a little
bit, you mean, you fund a little
bit so that, like, you have some
sort of stake, and it funds like
a few people to work on this
full time, most of their time.
Matt Robinson: That's the intent
of the consortium, right. So
there's some level of
maintenance, to keep things at
least running to a degree. And
so our membership dues are
different. Yeah. And then, and
then at enables, like some level
of technical support. So one of
the benefit benefits for people
who are involved in the
consortium, is they get some
call, like, hey, help me like
tech support. As well as like,
you know, we do a lot of
maintenance. And, of course,
obviously, pushing out some new
stuff fixes, new versions, etc,
we maintain the Qt plugin for
ROS. And different functions
like that. And put on obviously,
the training, it supports the
training events. But that's
really what the dues cover any
sort of collaborative project is
separately specked out and if
people want to contribute
income, and software or, or just
fun labor, they can do that with
veggie spun out separate. So the
consortium seeks to provide the
direction for what we do in the
open source. The first thing,
sorry,
Audrow Nash: its direction in a
sense that they inform you of
what they're working on what
their needs are. But it also
comes with these added benefits
of you, you can you support
them. And then you also provide
these training things. Drink
training, I don't know the
courses or we may refer to it
Matt Robinson: to training
events, right? Yeah, we enable
them to sort of like kind of
influence the agenda, like, oh,
it'd be nice to have more more
on navigation. Right? Oh, we
generally, like we've started
pushing out ROS 2 training and
we got a lot of feedback that
like, Hey, this is fine. But
like, how do we make it run with
our ROS one stuff? Right. So we
ended? Yeah, add in like, yeah,
added, like best practices with
the bridge, pulling exercises,
and hey, what are some things
for to help us port stuff? And
so that's, and that that's a key
role, right? I mean, Oh, for
sure. consortium, the
membership, like provides this
sort of, well, and because they
are paying membership dues, they
will definitely express their
opinions. And that's right. I
mean, we're sure
Audrow Nash: if it's the best
match desires of industry,
represented by the consortium.
Matt Robinson: Yeah. So we have
like this, like, baked in voice
of voice of the customer. Right.
So that's been really good. And
then shortly after we started
the Americas consortium,
Fraunhofer IPA stood up a ROS
industrial consortium in Europe.
They have a subset of members
and Asia Pacific. Like I said,
let a Singapore RTC Singapore.
Were there one of your
colleagues, a couple of your
colleagues in Singapore I think
just down the road from RTC.
They support the Asia Pacific
console issue and when we work
all off, like a common
agreement, so we have reciprocal
benefits. And it's really very
uniform from either outside, as
well as inside. We tried to make
it consistent, uniform
experience, like very often
often Asia Pacific member who
has someone sitting here in the
States, and they'll attend our
training events. That's okay,
that's nice. How do you?
Audrow Nash: How does it work
when companies join the
consortium? Is it? So is it like
a fixed do or can companies
though? Like, if? I don't know,
I like say it's a $5,000 for one
seat, or something? Does it is
Can someone contribute a whole
bunch and basically monopolize
how it works? Or how does all I
guess how do you balance
different companies?
Matt Robinson: That's a good
question. So so we do true there
that we have an agreement,
right, and the agreement spells
out all the details. But in
general, right, we have
different classes of membership,
which kind of make it as
accessible as possible. So like
startups and universities, can
come in at $2,500 a year, they
get a seat at every event via
networking or training. And I
still get to, like say, like,
you know, provide feedback on
the roadmap. Now we have another
level is called the consortium
Advisory Council that's reserved
for like our full members, but
they each only still get a seat.
Right? Okay. Like, even like a
big heavy hitter may come in.
Right? And be like, right, like,
hey, everyone wanted to be this.
I'm like, Well, you've only got
one vote, right? It's yeah. But
it's only one. But in the case,
like, obviously, some members
abstain. They're happy to go
right. Like if the big hitter
comes in and says X. Obviously,
in the recent years, the dynamic
is, the consortium has evolved
quite a bit. We ran it kind of a
little bit more like, like US
industry folks who used to
running right with like, email
and like, but now like we have,
we had a nice tech infusion into
the consortium. And they're
ready to develop via spreads.
And like, what a word discourse,
and I've been like having to
like my old school members. I'm
like having to this is
discourse. Yeah. Okay. Right.
You can go out there and type
something. Yeah, it's, it's been
a, it's, it's bringing those two
worlds together. It's been. That
is interesting. But yeah,
everyone has the one vote. And I
still call, like, let's have a
Zoom meeting. I send them an
invite. And it's, it's still a
lot of hand holding, but it's
fine. Right. I mean, I, I know
the context of every member
pretty personally, right? I've
had one on one conversations
with all of them. They express
their concerns, like, sometimes
they're like, Oh, this is the
fit for us. And that's okay.
Right. I want to make sure that
they're getting the value, and
that we're meeting their needs.
And if they're not, they're
back. We're not right. And
that's fine, too. Oh, totally.
I'll get like, Well, can you put
me in touch with the person who
does ROS on marketing? But
like, yes, one second. I'm the
I'm the one stop shop. Like,
right? Yeah, I managed the
website. I do all the marketing.
I do a lot of events undergoing
the podcast. Yeah. Well, that's
not entirely true. Right. Our
developer group, some of you,
your your audience may know Levi
Armstrong. Right. So he has
spoken with our his or member
team member or team members,
Michael ripperger. Just recently
spoke at ROS con, we put on a
workshop, obviously, by
Armstrong and Dr. Chris Lewis,
on the scan to wear all the
hats, but
Audrow Nash: you wear many hats.
Yeah.
Matt Robinson: Jorge, Nico was
on the ROS developers podcast
that comes out of steam. So So
you know, I really tried to
provide the forum to allow the
team to shine. But obviously, I
was invited, and I'm happy to
talk about the program level.
But obviously, I'm happy to make
somebody a little bit more
developer centric available as
well. Okay,
Audrow Nash: let's see. So then,
okay, so you have the
consortium, it's all these
companies that sit on it, how
large is it? How many companies
do you have sitting on I guess
we have the three different
branches, but like somewhere
Matt Robinson: in general,
somewhere, I'm like 65, member
company range, and government
entities. So government entities
don't have to pay a member fee.
But they have to kind of they
don't get any of the member
benefits so they have to pay if
they show up for like a meal.
But so like NIST is really great
partner here in the state side.
So we've been really benefited
that really good working
relationship with them Air Force
Research Lab, you know, in
cardiac or Army Research,
historically been the ones that
have really been great
supporters of the work we're
trying to do in industrial open
source. Yeah. I'm curious.
Audrow Nash: So like My
experience with some nonprofits,
I was with Robo hub, which is a
nonprofit news organization for
robotics. And so we would go
around and try to find sponsors
quite often. Are you? So for the
companies that you have in the
consortium? Are you doing a lot
of like reaching out to
different companies and trying
to kind of align? Or try to try
to talk to the right people? And
then have them join? Or how does
it? How does it work with this?
Are they coming to you, I
suppose it's a mix of both. But
Matt Robinson: I have to admit,
like, I could probably do more
proactive, outreach. You know,
even we were at Caterpillar,
like, they mentioned, like, hey,
we have this consortium, you can
participate. You know, a lot of
times people reach out to us,
you know, like, for instance,
if, if you have like, say, let's
say there's a more tech oriented
company that like wants to get
exposure to industry, they might
reach out. And then like, you
know, for instance, have like,
like, when I was at Caterpillar,
we needed help, but wanted to
learn ourselves. Right? So it
was a good opportunity for us to
get exposure to the training in
what's going on who are others?
What are others doing to solve
some of these challenges. And
ideally, there's other some
solution providers in that
network that that are already
industry aligned. Right, because
the issue is working with a lot
of startups, sometimes, at least
in the early 2010s. They weren't
always really ready for
industry, the too early
Audrow Nash: kind of thing. They
were still like pivoting, or
whatever it might be, or they
were over fit
Matt Robinson: to say their
initial industry, oh, my God.
And so like, obviously hanging
out and ROS industry, we can
kind of like, you know, these
other startups that were kind of
engaging, they can kind of get a
little sense for, for the flavor
of industrial member that's in
the consortium. Most of the
industrial members in the
consortium are you know, hence
there is no Ford or, well,
General Motors as a member now,
but not in the context, you
might think. But like, you know,
Ford at one time early on was a
member, but they're like, yeah,
we can just tell the robot
providers what to do. Right. So
this is less value.
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah, the big
company,
Matt Robinson: they are looking
for more capability. Right? It's
interesting, right? So even big
players like that BMW, right?
Totally. Was they're trying to
do, there's a notion of lot size
of one. And so that even though
you're making like 1000s of cars
a lot size of one, so you're
making me I'm making, I'm making
500 units a minute, right?
Normally, I might make batches.
So what's what scrap? Why not,
why not be enough, right, so I'm
going to make a 500 of the 700
series for settings, right, and
I'm gonna have them be the same.
And then I'm going to follow it
up with a bunch of my 500
series. Well, what they're
trying to get to is this notion
of, of all the product they
make, they're gonna make 500 of
them, but it's gonna be all
mixed, sprinkled in mixed by
teams, different sizes
Audrow Nash: are dynamization.
It's like, it's highly dynamic
to the needs of the company. So
it might be like, it might be
like in the in the limit, it
might be like in like Walmart or
something when someone buys a
product. And then Walmart ships
that product to the Walmart
store kind of thing. Because of
that data being taken. This car,
sends it right over,
Matt Robinson: right, just in
time manufacturing, just in time
delivery, just just in time
tagline. And like six sigma
parlons supply chain is very
common in industry. And there's
two sets here in the ROS
toolbox that can help deliver
solutions for
Audrow Nash: us, which mean a
lot of one for this, it's like I
want to make one of one thing.
And then I want to go make
something else.
Matt Robinson: Right? It's got a
you can historically you would
batch it, right? Gonna make so
many of the 700 series so many
of the 500 series, so many of
the 300 series did to optimize
my uptime. But manufacturers are
really wanting to get away from
that they
Audrow Nash: want that just in
time manufacturing. Interesting.
Okay, and so
Matt Robinson: and that's and
that's true, aerospace, heavy
industry, oiling all industries.
Audrow Nash: I mean, it's
basically saying I want
flexibility is what I hear it's
Matt Robinson: right. Or
agility, which is, you know,
different yet.
Audrow Nash: So how do you think
of them? Because I mean,
flexibility is the ability to
pivot and make different things
agility is the ability to change
quickly what you're making.
Matt Robinson: Yeah, so you
might trade off velocity in an
agile solution, right? So
flexibility, right, so Oh, boy.
It's like getting to
manufacturing lingo. So so if
I'm machining agent, right,
let's say I make lots of
different interests, different
sizes lawnmowers to dump trucks.
I can I can buy a machining
center with a huge material
handling setup with all All the
holding hardware to hold all my
different size engines. And that
way I can put all the metal
blocks I need on these like
pallets that are shuttled
around. That's a very flexible
system. But it's also very
expensive, right because like
I've got this like conveyor
system, I've got all this extra
tooling. Agile solution might
be, I have a mobile robot with a
spindle on it, that can like
brace it, and stay reverie, so
but it might be slight, it can
roll, it can roll up on the
various engine blocks and put
all the holes in it needs.
That's a magic solution. Now,
it's not going to make each one
as fast because it's a little
robot, and it's not as rigid.
But I have I have less setup. I
have like, you know, my floor
space can be very dynamic. I
don't have this huge thing that
takes up the space on my
factory. That is an agile
solution. Right? So this notion
of to your point, right, I can
respond more nimbly to changes
in condition. Flexible means
I've designed my equipment to
handle all my permutations.
Yeah, but maybe the trade offs
on consuming floorspace or
cotton,
Audrow Nash: maybe it's flexible
only in what you're already
making and not flexible and new
things to work. Maybe agile
could adapt more readily. Okay,
Matt Robinson: there's actually
an agility and robotics Working
Group in nest. And we talk
extensively about the defining
agility, right. It's a real nice
conversation. It's actually
official IEEE working group. So
if your listeners are interested
in that, I'm happy to make
introductions or, you know,
through education channels.
Audrow Nash: Again, you can drop
your contact info and
everything. But one thing kind
of so you mentioned this working
group, you had a working group
approved in the steering
committee. Yesterday.
Matt Robinson: Let's let's fresh
off the presses.
Audrow Nash: fresh off the
press. Yeah. And as so would you
talk a bit about the intention
of the working group? And then
like, maybe how people would get
involved if they are interested?
Matt Robinson: Yeah. So this is
also very new. Right. So
anyways, yeah. So So
Audrow Nash: approved yesterday,
steering committee meeting,
Matt Robinson: like this Europe,
you're very plugged in. So yes,
the Technical Steering Committee
met yesterday, we had put on
discourse, this idea of a
hardware interfaces working
group. So one of the exciting
things about our work with
industry in ROS, is the notion
of being able to abstract away
the hardware to enable like,
hey, I can run this on a yellow
robot and a blue rose. Bowl, one
thing we've seen over time, from
our experience in ROS 1, as
OEM, some OEMs, did pick up the
initiative to build their own
interfaces for us. Others did
not, but the community would
step in and offer something.
Well, I don't over time, some
OEMs would offer like this
totally different type of
interface. So
Audrow Nash: right, then you
mean software interface for
this, right? Yes, correct. So
you're meaning if some company
builds a depth sensor or
something? Maybe they would
write drivers for it. And maybe
those drivers could have a ROS
interface. So you can use it
really well with the ROS
ecosystem? Maybe it wouldn't, is
what you're saying. But there's
Okay. Well, so yeah.
Matt Robinson: But the behavior
would be mo not consistent.
Right. So you have a ROS
driver. And you would expect it
to be like, Well, when I worked
on this hardware, this sort of
this is the type this type of
message usually resulted in this
behavior. So if I
Audrow Nash: have a dense camera
by this company, a and a depth
camera by Company B, the ideally
the drivers have the same
interfaces. So I can just plug
in replace one, if I'm using
like, say I'm using a, I can
just swap to B, and my interface
is the same. So there's no
standardization in the
interfaces. Yes, similar cases,
what you're saying racks?
Matt Robinson: Yes, we're
similar to industrial
manipulators, that became in
spades. Right? So yeah, and
because, you know, and
obviously, because they are
different, but an are dry for
specification, when the author
has the time didn't think about
how those products would evolve.
And it wasn't necessarily even
associated with it just defined
in eskies. We didn't actually
say like the associated with
behavior. So it's this notion of
taking our specifications that
we worked on in the past, and
maybe extending it to behavior.
So when you're developing your
application, you know the
interface and we want to create
a reference implementation that
makes it easier for people who
are Hey, great, awesome, that
people are offering ROS
interfaces, right? And building
interfaces to enable open source
and interoperability at all. But
but if we can do something where
like provide reference
implementations that are
associated with anticipated or
expected behavior, we think that
would lead to a better developer
or end user experience,
particularly auditing the test
Audrow Nash: and also easier for
software engineers. Like
obviously easier if I have an
interface to program to and I
like if that abstraction is
already done, so I don't have to
reinvent it. If I am thinking
I'm gonna end up switching depth
cameras at some point and it's
just good practice to make it so
you abstract to But so just
baking that, and how are you
guys proposing to do that?
Matt Robinson: So I have to
admit, I didn't not write the
details of the proposal. I just
know like I've dealt with the
inconsistency in the interface.
Audrow Nash: But we're trying to
fix it for ROS 2. So the
ecosystem doesn't develop quite
as much as ROS one without
establishing a better norm.
handleless guardrails. Okay,
Matt Robinson: yeah, so the,
what we're going to do is,
obviously, we're going to
revisit a lot of the different
applicable standards. So there's
been some good standards work in
this domain, particularly in
industrial science. So we know
in Europe, there's been a few
different standards, I can't
rattle them off top, my head
bear with me. But there's gonna
be a standards review,
obviously, we'd like to take
some of the best in class, if
you will, start there. And then
maybe, like, try to benchmark
them against a couple of the
other implementations we've seen
out there. And again, targeted
around. Like how we handle
messaging for like, again, we're
going to start with industrial
manipulators, because that's
been a pain point for us and,
and how we, how we handle like,
say, like the streaming and you
know, the joint streaming, and
then you know, how we did some
of the behaviors relative
resulting to like, hey, that,
that didn't really go off, like
I expected. And then how do we
make sure we create a reference
implementation that works over a
different couple cases? And
because some OEMs are gonna also
add on functionality? Yeah, we
got to make sure the reference
implementation accounts for that
second bolt that in? Yeah,
certainly.
Audrow Nash: So it works with
existing data structures, you
basically say, Oh, well, we
expect that you might have these
additional, like fields of data
that you're going to pass
everywhere. And so it's built
into a standard interface,
rather than we keep having to
extend it for specific use
cases. There's kind of
Matt Robinson: I think your
metaphor is around depth cameras
are a little simpler to speak
around and are valid.
Absolutely. Very similar. And so
yeah, we're looking forward,
we've got some good feedback,
the discourse conversation,
obviously, TSC, we, you know,
you may not know, but CNC
meetings are very fast paced.
You can't really belabor
anyone's subject too much. But
in general, there seem to be
receptive audience, obviously,
we're asked how we're going to
sustain? I think that's a very
fair question. We as with
anything, open source projects,
we tend to get a lot of interest
upfront, and then it kind of
computer down. So I think as
long as we get sort of a core
group, I think the big thing is
having access to hardware, we're
lucky that we have plenty of
hardware around the couple of
the other partners that voiced
interest have access to
hardware. And that's a great
place to start. But obviously,
we're going to be looking for
other folks who maybe only have
a very specific piece of
hardware to test. And obviously,
we'll do our engagement with our
OEM friends to see what their
take is, because we have a
number of OEMs interested in
building out interfaces for us,
too, they don't know where to
start. So that's where also the
timing is beneficial. We'll hand
you this reference
implementation. Right, go give
feedback. And since we, yeah, we
have some industrial medullary
EMS interested in rolling out.
And they're already looking at
ROS 2 control. So that's good.
And that's that's where it
really gets into like behavior,
right? Because our a lot of our
past drivers were a little bit
more simplified. But now that
everyone's pivoting to ROS,
control based drivers, that's
the right time to do this more,
more behavior centric approach.
Do you? See?
Audrow Nash: Are you
considering? Like, will you
write ROS enhancement proposal
for this kind of thing? Or? Like
do you imagine like making a
public specification of exactly
what these may look like? Or
maybe it's like, for mobile,
manipulate or for manipulators?
Matt Robinson: Yeah, I have a
feeling it'd be more
specification based, if you
will. I said we, we would like
to go back and review existing
standards, as opposed to trading
the standard that supposedly
rules them all. In the
industrial circles, right?
Someone's always creating the
standard, that standard, I'd
like to avoid that. In the meaty
part is the reference
implementation, right? So we
obviously will have a wiki page
someplace to steer people to for
like, an of course, an
associated GitHub repository
that came to contains the
framework for whatever the
reference implementation looks
like. But ideally, right, we are
bolting in the applicable
standards, not reinventing
standards, but it'd be more
around the proper documentation
as opposed to like us, maybe
making like under the hood ROS
enhancements per se.
Audrow Nash: Right. These are,
you know what I mean by ROS
enhancement proposal.
Matt Robinson: And a rap Yes.
Yeah, right. I don't I don't
know necessarily explicitly
become a rep at this point in
time. Maybe Gotcha.
Audrow Nash: Perhaps once the
feedback is just so in, as far
as I understand, it's really
nice. If anything, It's a it's a
space that the community looks
to see if there are standards
for things. And so it seems like
a good spot for like, this is
what we think would be good for
a, say we're doing like a
robotic arm. This is what a good
message type for a vendor might
be. But I don't know. Just a
good point.
Matt Robinson: Obviously, it's
been challenging because so many
different specifications of our
robot, our robot vendors don't
necessarily, they don't know
what a rep is. Right. So so, you
know, we, we tend to try to find
places that they're more
accessible to some of the more
traditional industrial segments.
Well, I think, yeah, we'll have
to take while to take that all
under consideration, I believe,
now that you know, we talk about
it out loud. The rap does sound
like a great place, and you can
obviously be pushed in reference
other places.
Audrow Nash: Yes, totally. I
think it kind of seems like a
good way to go. If you're trying
to change how a large group of
users might use ROS. It's like
the way to have standards, as
far as I understand. And also,
reference implementations are
very important in reps. So I
think if you're making a
reference reference
implementation, it's like the
part of the rep that is the
content of your reference
implementation and the spec and
everything out the rationale,
everything I quite like the form
of it and, like, filling that
space out. Seems good to me.
Matt Robinson: But no, and you
see, this is the this the
benefit of this particular
podcast? No, yeah, no, I, like I
said, and obviously, as we begin
this journey, I think we'll
probably hash through some of
those, some of those. For sure.
In the wrap sounds like to me
like, yeah, natural and natural
step forward.
Audrow Nash: So we are coming at
the end of the time, I do have
some other questions. If you do
not have a hard stop, I'd love
to talk a little longer. I know
we started late because of
technical difficulties.
Matt Robinson: But yeah, I got
Yeah, I can I know that are
1010 12 minutes. That's good.
Audrow Nash: So the thing that
so looking at ROS industrial
the group in general, there's a
lot of things that are offered.
One other thing is the
conference, ROS industrial con,
or how do you
Matt Robinson: call it? So so we
have three different events,
because we're like a federated
organization with Europe and
Asia Pacific. So we each each
group puts on like sort of a
member gathering, if you will, a
lot of cases a events
Audrow Nash: you're speaking
about.
Matt Robinson: Okay, right. And
then we obviously do some other
smaller events as well. But
these are kind of like our big
marquee events for each region.
So ROS industrial conference is
specifically that of that name
is the one that's typically held
at the end of the year. I think
it's been considered moved away
from December. But typically
it's in December units, hosted
by ROS industrial Europe, and
then Fraunhofer IPA, and
typically in Stuttgart, Germany.
And they, they'll organize
typically their event as both
member and public over the whole
event, and obviously bring
together lots of different
speakers. Right. And so there's
tends to be conference in a very
traditional sense, where it's a
number of different speakers.
Maybe they'll have some tours
and have people set up
demonstrations as well, to make
it more interactive. So that's
once a year, Asia Pacific hosts
what they call a ROS industrial
workshop lesson destroy Asia
Pacific workshop. It is probably
somewhat similar. I believe it
is also public and member over
the whole time, you may have
some separate member breakout
time. It's been a while since
we've had one in person because
COVID COVID. But our group we've
we've been over Singapore, we
support that one actively as
well. And then of course,
Americas we typically host ours
in the spring. It is moving a
little later this year, because
in the every other year we were
co locating with the Automate
conference. And this year,
automate is in June because
they're separating from Pro
Matte, which is in the spring
and in Chicago, automate is now
splitting off separate from Pro
matte, and we'll be in Detroit.
Our event is a little different.
When we host it here in San
Antonio, we have kind of public
day and then member of the day,
like because when I get all the
members together, we tend to try
to have workshops were like hey,
what are we doing good? What's
not going so reflective
Audrow Nash: now that you have
everyone together? Yeah, what
are your
Matt Robinson: burning needs?
And so we like get out the Get
out the huge notepads and we're
like got everybody in little
small groups. And it's cool and
we try to we try to hash out
things and like just a smaller
setting. The public day is like
a big conference release. We'll
have like lab tours like members
will come and set up, set up
demos. People can play with
stuff We try to make it active.
And of course, we do that we do
the presentation gamut as well.
Last year, ours was virtual as
well. And thanks to all of our
members and and folks in the
open source community who came
and supported and spoke, folks
from Open Robotics as well. We
really appreciate the support
and the collaboration. It's been
fun, obviously, bringing all
these, it's great to get all
these folks together sharing
ideas. We look forward to kind
of getting back in person. So
our event is Detroit. Automate
runs from Monday through
Thursday. And then our event is
Friday in Detroit. We're doing a
big a big dinner Thursday, we're
going to highlight all the ROS
centric demos at automate on the
show floor. So we'll put out a
little cheat sheet like hey, if
you want to see something ROS
running under the hood, go here,
here and here. Of course, we'll
we'll get together Friday and
share kind of some of the
happenings what's going on in
our collaboration projects,
blah, blah, blah. And that'll be
in June. And we make all of that
content. Some member only
content, obviously, there's a
member portal, but most of it,
I'd say like 80% of the content
we put up on our YouTube
channel. And of course, we make
all the slide decks available.
Do write ups about like, kind of
what we learned and stuff and
trying to get that information
on there.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Have you?
Have you noticed any? Like, what
have you noticed? How long have
these conferences been going? Is
it several years? So it sounds
like consortium in 2013? Or?
Matt Robinson: Yes. So the first
can ROS industrial consortium
member meeting was in 2013. I
attended my first one in 2014.
Audrow Nash: Wow, you're so
early on it. Okay,
Matt Robinson: so yeah, as was a
caterpillar person, right? Yep.
And then I hosted my first one
as a here. I think it was 2018.
I posted? What?
Audrow Nash: What have you
noticed for the like, is it
growing? Because ISO going to
robotics conferences in the last
10 years or so? They've just
gotten huge. Are you noticing a
similar trend or any, across the
years?
Matt Robinson: Are? I think, you
know, we typically have to cap
it. Like around like, when I do
it here, I have to cap it around
like 110. It looks like a
Detroit I'm I have to cap it
around 100. So it just fills up
faster. Right. That's cool. Like
any conference, like we'll get
like in certain cases, like, you
know, over registrants, I think
in general, people want to come
and see what's going on. And
particularly, there's a lot of
demos a chance to get hands on.
Yeah, drives a lot of a lot of
interest. It's definitely not as
big as ROS brands were more
audience. But we have good
industry engagement, good engage
with the tech community. It's a
great time for those two,
sometimes still very different
communities to get together and
share ideas.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. All right. So
beginning to wrap up. Where do
you see ROS industry going? Or
ROS industrial going in the
next two, five years? Like,
where do you think it'll go?
Matt Robinson: Yeah, I think
we're at a real tipping point,
where it's not just like, say a
custom application for
industrial use. That gets
deployed or like at Site x,
we're, I think we're reaching a
point where at least certain
classes of applications can be
sort of generalized and this
notion of like creating like an
app for a class of applications,
maybe even realize that right,
where you can, like pull down
something via snap for those
snap is like sort of the app
store for Linux. You can
Audrow Nash: pull from
specifically, I don't know if
it's all windows. Sorry, isn't
going to specifically you're
correct. And one of the more
recent versions, even more
specifically, but yes,
Matt Robinson: yes. But but in
this notion of like sort of like
this app, or I can pull up
something, configure my
environment, my hardware, so
moving some things around
through some menus, and actually
do some basic sort of path
planning and setting up a bar
and visualization and maybe
hardware. I think, in the next
year or so, we might have some
sort of AP, deployable solutions
that are basically really just
ROS on industrial hardware. And
that's really exciting. I think
it can really open up different,
like a new capability to a whole
different set of users. And
obviously, on the training side,
we're really excited to see
universities offering more
training to manufacturing
engineering type people,
mechanical engineers, to get
exposed to ROS technicians. So
this notion of like, if I put a
bunch of robots out there, or
Ryan ROS, what is the
technician who has to fix the
robot do with the raw space that
that piece of the education
pipeline is still lacking?
There's a couple of programs
Wichita State, for instance, has
been looking at a program for
developing technicians for raw
space systems. We're really
excited to see see how that
evolves and been very supportive
of those educational
initiatives. So it's not like
that just makes it right Oh,
yeah.
Audrow Nash: And then do you
have any links or contact info
that you'd like to share with
our listeners and watchers? Yeah
Matt Robinson: obviously Twitter
at ROS industrial we have a
LinkedIn page both myself
personally ROS industrial and
LinkedIn pages ROS industrial
feel free to to follow us there.
We obviously have a specific
discourse category as well, ROS
industrial, we try to try to try
to have some discourse about
ROS industrial there. There
bear with the battle. So but
yeah, I am engaged on the in my
team and our colleagues in
Europe and Asia, as well. So we
were actively looking forward to
hearing what people's pain
points are, what can we be doing
better? How do we how do we how
do we increase the acceptance
and participation? So that's the
other piece, right? How do we
get this industry community to
also be actively engaging and
participating contributing to
open source? That's probably one
side of our, our queue there
Rubik that, that we're still
still working on. But I think
we're getting there. We're
getting closer.
Audrow Nash: And if people want
to join your working group, any
idea how to? Yeah,
Matt Robinson: so voice voice
your interest over in the
discourse category? I think it's
the working group proposals
under ROS discourse. Next
Generation. It's called Working
Group proposal for interfaces.
So voice or just ping me
directly via one of the
channels.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. And
actually, you guys, maybe we'll
be making a pull request to the
ROS 2 documentation and adding
your working group info there. I
assume. You let me know if you
need any pointers on that.
Matt Robinson: I'll probably
have to delegate that right.
Perfect, but um, but I'm sure
we'll figure it out once we
figure out what the next steps
are. So often, other than
hearing that it's ago, I haven't
gotten early. The next step is
the most concrete next step I've
heard so far. Okay, says that is
educational for me as it is
relative to listeners.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Well,
thank you, Matt. Bye, everyone.
Bye. Thanks for listening to
this conversation with Matt
Robinson. Thank you again to our
founding sponsor, Open Robotics.
See you next time.