Audrow Nash: Hi, everyone.
Welcome to the Sense Think Act
Podcast. I'm Audrow Nash. And in
this episode, I'm going to be
introducing the sensing gap
podcast.
So this podcast will feature
longer interviews on various
topics in robotics. So I'll
speak with people that are
starting robotics companies,
larger robotics companies,
researchers, both in academia
and in industry, people that are
involved with robotics in
government, as well as people
that are using robotics and art,
or philosophers that discuss
robotics, really anyone that I
think will make an interesting
interview for you all.
This podcast is going to be for
roboticists, as well as anyone
that is interested in robotics,
but doesn't necessarily have any
robotics knowledge. So for
roboticists, we hope that this
podcast helps them understand
different things that are
happening in robotics, outside
of their own focused area.
For everyone else, those without
robotics backgrounds. We hope
that this is an accessible way
to understand what's going on in
robotics, as well as its
limitations, and potential. And
one way that we're going to make
this podcast accessible is to
explain technical concepts as we
go. So that way, we don't leave
anyone in the dark. This is also
good for roboticist because this
is a very large field and
someone from legged mocha
locomotion may not understand
terms used by the computer
vision community say.
Now, this podcast is sponsored
by Open Robotics, which is where
I work as a software engineer.
Open Robotics makes open source
robotic software, you may be
familiar with their robot
operating system (ROS), or their
simulator, Ignition Gazebo. This
podcast isn't going to be
limited talk to talking about
topics that relate to things
that open robotics makes. So we
have free rein to talk about
everything.
For me, I have been involved in
robotics for maybe eight years,
mostly as a researcher in
academia. As I mentioned, I'm
currently working at Open
Robotics. And I was previously
involved in Robohub's robot
podcast, where I led it for
maybe five years. And I'm very
happy for this opportunity and
the support of Open Robotics to
make this podcast, very excited
to try longer interviews. And I
just enjoyed learning through
conducting interviews and
sharing that with the greater
public.
So next, where do we get the
name Sense Think Act Podcast? So
robots can be thought of as
machines that sense the world.
Think about what they see, and
then act upon the world, maybe
by moving themselves or by
moving something else, for
example. And in school, many
roboticists were probably taught
that this is a fundamental
control loop that you can think
of for roboticist. So because
this is going to be a general
robotics podcast, we thought it
was an appropriate name.
Now, you can watch this podcast
on YouTube and maybe Vimeo in
the near future. And you should
be able to listen to this
podcast on all major podcasting
platforms such as Apple
Podcasts, Spotify, Google
Podcasts, etc.
For comments, you can of course,
comment on YouTube. But we will
be using the ROS Discourse for
comments with the category since
think act. And you can you can
leave comments there, such as
thoughts on a specific episode,
or general feedback or
suggestions on things you would
like us to cover. Now you can
also access that through the
sense think act website at
SenseThinkAct.com. And well,
that's all I have for today. So
thank you to our founding
sponsor, Open Robotics, and I'll
see you every two weeks for a
new interview. Make sure to
subscribe if you want
notifications. Goodbye,
everyone.