Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Ben Raanan who is
a software engineer at the
Monterey Bay Aquarium Research
Institute, or MBARI, for short.
MBARI uses robots to
monitor and explore the oceans
to better understand climate
change, and other topics. In
general, getting ocean data is
extremely expensive. Depending
on how far the area of interest
is from the shore, it may
require a large boat with a full
crew. MBARI is working to
make this process easier and
much cheaper by having robots
stay at sea for weeks at a time
getting data on different ocean
events. This generates a lot
more data and will hopefully
greatly improve our
understanding of our oceans. I
found it exciting to talk with
Ben about how MBARI is looking
into having robots stay at sea
almost indefinitely, charging
their batteries and uploading
their data all while at sea.
This could enable fleets of
robots to continuously be at sea
giving us a much richer picture
of the health of our oceans. I'm
Audrow Nash. This is the Sense
Think Act Podcast. Thank you to
our founding sponsor Open
Robotics. And now here's my
conversation with Ben Ron on.
Hi, Ben, would you introduce
yourself?
Ben Raanan: Sure. Hi. My name is
Ben Ron on a oceanographer and
robotics software engineers here
at the Monterey Bay Aquarium
Research Institute. Or we're in
MBARI, for sure. We're in
Barcelona, California. I've been
here with the Institute for
probably coming on years now.
Working as an engineer, a
bedroom about my background,
actually, motion career about 20
years ago, I was a special
warfare operator and a combat
diver in the Israeli Navy. And
spent a good chunk of time with
the teams there. And later on,
got my undergrad in r&d tax and
biotechnology back home in
Israel. And then came here to
get my Master's in physical
oceanography. At that point, I
got involved here with the
Institute through an internship,
and then I just refused to
leave. Yeah, so now mostly what
I do is I work development and
operations with autonomous
underwater vehicles. And so I
have a few projects running, but
I think you're interested in
looking for talking about
Audrow Nash: awesome. So what
kinds of projects do you guys do
at MBARI?
Ben Raanan: Yeah, so I guess
maybe we before we dive into the
projects, can tell you a little
more about embargo in general, I
think, sure, you may be
familiar, but others may not. So
like I said, we're in Moss
Landing Fornia in the Central
California, say probably about
an hour south, from San Jose, on
the coastline, in the Monterey
Bay. And in MBARI is actually a
pretty unique Ocean Research
Institute, in the sense where
we're a private nonprofit. So
the institute is not an academic
Institute, it's kind of been
founded as an alternative to
what an academic Institute can
be for ocean research, in bars
funded almost exclusively,
through the David and Lucile
Packard Foundation. And David
Packard, which is the P and HP
and Hewlett Packard, he founded
this, yeah, he founded this
institute in 1987. So we just
celebrated our 35th birthday.
And the mission back then was
to, like I said, offer an
alternative to traditional
academic research institutes,
and take on challenges that
require development of
technology in order to, you
know, answer some of the
scientific questions that marine
scientists have. And so that's
kind of been the goal of
Institute and also remove a lot
of the, I guess, barriers,
especially when it comes to
funding. And so scientists and
engineers here get to focus more
on the doing and less than
they're proposing. And so we
have an internal proposal cycle,
in which we, you know, for our
budget, and then we get funded
through Packard Foundation,
which is phenomenal, it's
absolutely great. And so, the
type of the way the institute is
structured is we're actually
kind of like a three legged
stool. And our trifecta, never
skip on an opportunity to say
that word. And so, so, the
Institute has about 220
employees. We are divided into
science, engineering, and Marine
Operations. And we work very
closely together. So Though the
barrier or the the boundaries
between the groups is very
blurred, you know, you got a lot
of scientists that are very much
engineers and engineers that are
scientists and they work
together to find the questions
that need to be answered. And
then develop the technology that
allows us to go out and get
that. And then the Department of
Marine Operations has the
specialty in the knowledge and
how to deploy the assets and
manage, you know, so you know,
make sure everything comes back
safely, to the best of their
ability. And so that together is
what I think really makes the
institute special in its ability
to come up with very challenging
questions, develop the
technology to try and gather the
information that's required in
order to answer those questions.
And then actually go in the
field, gather the data, and and
you know, start working on the
answers. And so that's kind of
like a cycle that we exercise
here pretty regularly. And it's
it's all good fun. So I guess
that's the institute is the
that's the answer to in in in a
nutshell.
Audrow Nash: And what kind of
problems are you guys typically
like also the in Hewlett
Packard, so Packard set this
foundation, or set this up? So
he received or he sends you guys
a good number, a good amount of
money? To do the research? What
kinds of problems? Are you guys
most interested in? Solving? Or,
like, what what kind of problems
are you going after? I guess,
yeah.
Ben Raanan: So if you walk
around the hall here, you'll
find scientists pretty much any
ocean research discipline that
you can imagine. So we have
geologists, geophysicist,
chemical oceanographers,
biological oceanographers, any
kind of type of marine research
really, that you can imagine, is
happening here. And so at the
core, we're trying to describe
the ocean environment and go
after questions that also have
to do with anthropogenic impact,
that's driving change in the
ocean environment,
Audrow Nash: what does that
mean? So generic, is that
Ben Raanan: is human generated?
So, yeah, so that really relates
to some of the challenges that
are faced with climate change,
and how emissions for example,
impact our environment. And so,
the ocean is actually a really
important piece and buffering
the heat on the planet. And so,
in order to understand better
the processes that govern heat
transfer, how carbon dioxide
that gets emitted into the
atmosphere is gets absorbed and
back in the ocean and and buried
in the in the ground, that's,
you know, the carbon cycle. So,
the Institute is trying to
target research in order to
acquire data and figure out how
what governs these processes,
what are the rates, and then
through this research inform
larger models that have to do
with you know, climate change
and more of a global scale in
the global scale sense. So,
those kinds of questions they
really drive research in all the
layers of the ocean. So, from
the atmospheric to you know, the
upper water column, where the
gases kind of mix and then how
the biology interacts with the
different chemical properties of
the water, different physical
properties of the water, they
take in some of this carbon and
use it to build their bodies
right through photosynthesis,
and that later on feeds the
larger organisms and cascades
through the foodweb and
eventually, those kind of fix
organic compounds are either
pooped out or die and sink to
the bottom of the ocean right
and get buried there. And so
that okay, is the carbon cycle
in a nutshell and we focus on
research that tries to describe
each of those sections in
detail, and then
Audrow Nash: yeah, gotcha. So,
you have just to see if I
understand the carbon cycle, you
have carbon in the environment,
then you have small like algae
or something, some small things.
that will consume the carbon and
sunlight in this kind of thing
and the photosynthesis happens,
then they go through this whole
process where they're eaten by
fish or something. And somehow,
they like eaten by one fish that
small, a bigger fish eats that
whatever, eventually something
dies in there. And then it sinks
to the bottom of the ocean. And
what happens when it's at the
bottom of the ocean? It kind of
just stays there for a while.
And you get kind of like, on the
bottom of the ocean, or
Ben Raanan: Yeah, so it gets it
gets vented is sediment, and
ocean sea floor, really is, I
guess the storage of that
moment, until, you know, either
gets, then you're starting to
look at geological processes on
you know, what happens there?
How? Yeah, so how does the ocean
seafloor evolve over time? And
when does that carbon make it
back into the atmosphere? And so
I guess the point is, yeah, so
we describe a lot. And I guess
the point to really kind of take
away from this is that these are
processes that happen over many,
many, many timescales and over
very different, yeah, are very
different spatial scales as
well. And so at MBARI, we kind
of talk about it in the sense
of, you know, going from
molecules and atoms to
ecosystems and back. And so the
type of science that we do hear
goes from, but understanding the
microbial processes that you
know, what type of nutrients are
required in the ocean in order
to make these biological
plankton or bacteria flourish
and take in these gases, then,
all the way up to how does it
later cascade into the food web?
And what are the timescales that
are associated with those
things, and so that, on its own
poses many challenges, because
in order to collect relevant
information, to describe these
processes, you really have to be
at sea a lot, and have to be
there not only for the duration,
but also in the right place, and
cover and span, you know, the
area that's required in order to
to really capture those
fundamentals. So
Audrow Nash: if I understand
correctly, it sounds like you
guys are basically trying to
model so the carbon cycle and
what's occurring to accurately
model that and have a better
idea for climate change, you
need to be involved at something
through the whole spectrum,
which is a massive process that
happens everywhere in the ocean,
at all different times, with all
different creatures, there's
lots of things involved. And so
because of this, this makes it
so you guys have a very large
research mission. In a sense,
like, there's a lot of things
that you need to understand, or
there's a lot of monitoring that
needs to happen. So that you can
begin to refine your model. So
you can have a good idea of this
process, and maybe its impact,
or maybe its changes over time.
And these kinds of things.
Ben Raanan: Exactly. And the
idea is that eventually, those
type of this type of
information, can cascade into
decision makers for conservation
management, and other type of,
you know, decisions that impact
our environment, but also can
affect some of the likelihood,
for example, fishermen, and so
on.
Audrow Nash: So that sounds
incredibly lofty as in a huge,
huge challenge to basically take
on climate change. Is that
motivating everything at MBARI?
Or are there other problems that
you guys are interested in to?
Like, clearly enormous? And
that's is that everything under
that umbrella? Or are there
other umbrellas?
Ben Raanan: Well, there are
other themes as well. I mean,
you have researchers here, for
example, that are behavioral
ecologists, and they're
interested
Audrow Nash: in I don't even
know what that means at all.
Ben Raanan: Oh, they're, they're
interested in in describing, you
know, how certain species behave
under underwater and so. Right?
So you can imagine, for example,
if you're interested in studying
squids, especially if you're
interested in studying DP
squids, then, again, getting
access to to the environment
where those squids are, is an
enormous challenge. And one
that's very suited for institute
that is, you know, capable of
developing the technologies and
also executing the operations
for getting the right
information and so on. You know,
that's another type of research
that we do here. We also have a
whole mapping division, we use
vehicles to go in and do surveys
of the ocean seafloor and map
the ocean seafloor, and then
return to see how it evolves
over time. So that's a whole
kind of branch of geology that
we host here. So really, it's
it's very hard to try to capture
all the activities that go on
here and the Institute, I'd say,
climate change has definitely
been one of the main themes and
impacts of climate change on the
ocean environment has been one
of the main themes that have
governed a lot of the proposals
and the projects that have been
here. But it's not the only one,
you know, they're there. Other
projects that, you know, maybe
don't fall exactly under that
umbrella. But that is definitely
the the lead theme.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And largely
ocean related. I mean, well,
entirely ocean related, it
sounds and then it's also, I
mean, if you have better ideas
of how these creatures behave,
maybe you have a better idea of
how they are as actors in the
system, which helps you model
these things. And if you have
better maps of the environment,
perhaps that also helps you in
environmental monitoring, I
could imagine, which will go
back into climate change, in
some sense, because it's such a
large problem, that having an
accurate model has so many
pieces to
Ben Raanan: correct. And then I
guess I'll add that embargo has
been a major player, you know,
since the 80s, collecting this
information. And so at this
point, we've gathered enormous
quantities of data. And we are
working pretty hard to make this
data available for others to
use, and also process it here
and have that multi-decadal
perspective, in order to
quantify change in the
environment. So in other words,
we are establishing a baseline
starting, you know, from some
point, and looking and observing
how the environment changes over
time. And so another big mission
of embargo is to, you know,
safeguard this trove of data and
make it accessible. And so I
think that's another thing that
the Institute is unique in its
capacity to offer. So
Audrow Nash: that's really cool.
Now, so that's awesome. What are
some of the ways that you guys
have been using robots and these
different parts of kind of the
mission of MBARI?
Ben Raanan: Right, so um, you
know, we refer to oceanography
here as a contact sport, like I
mentioned, in order to gather
the data, you have to be in the
environment. And so as you know,
traditionally, oceanography for
decades and has been done using
ships. And that's great. I think
that ships and humans are always
going to be part of this type of
research. And inquiry, indeed,
operates to large ships that go
out and collect data and take
expeditions at the sea. But I
think there's also a realization
that, you know, because of these
temporal and spatial scales in
which the phenomenon that we're
interested in studying happen,
we're just not able to
Audrow Nash: get all the clients
to be everywhere all at once,
for sure. So it's much easier to
have robots go do it, for
Ben Raanan: sure. Not
impossible, but it is cost
prohibitive.
Audrow Nash: Yes. But that also
human error and all sorts of
other things, too.
Ben Raanan: Sure. I mean, robots
make mistakes, also, especially
people that operate them. So, in
fact, because, you know,
traditionally, this type of
research has been done using
chips. MBARIs also put a lot
of resources into calibrating
the measurements. Okay. So
you've done it collected data,
in a certain way, for a certain
number of years, and now you're
switching into a more automated
collection system. And so how
does that data compare? And what
are the calibration factors that
you need to apply to go from,
you know, manually collected
systems into using data that's
collected by automated systems.
And so that's, so making
Audrow Nash: sure that we have
consistency from humans taking
it too. Maybe if you can
automate it and have a robot do
it, you want them to be apples
to apples, not apples to
oranges. So you have this big
break? where the data is, like,
completely different and hard to
draw conclusions from?
Ben Raanan: Exactly. So you
don't suddenly think that
there's, you know, some kind of
climate crisis that happens to
coincide with the time you
started using certain robots. So
so we've been seeing through
this transition. Now, some of
the environments that we
researched which are very hard
to get to. So, for example, kind
of the average ocean depth here
in the Pacific is about four,
four and a half kilometers. So,
so just those are
Audrow Nash: four and a half
kilometers. That 45 football
fields deep, roughly or,
Ben Raanan: rightly so. Yeah.
And a lot of weaker but yeah,
sorry. Yeah, so so so that's
very deep. And when you think
about, for example, the type of
pressure Vironment that we live
in. We live at one atmosphere of
pressure, if you go to space,
you're almost at zero. But if
you go about 30 feet down into
water, then you've already
doubled the pressure. And every
30 feet, you add, you add a
whole nother atmosphere. So
Audrow Nash: those many
atmospheres are down there, then
Ben Raanan: we'll have to do the
math.
Audrow Nash: So 4.5 kilometers
down, correct.
Ben Raanan: It's one atmosphere
per 10 meters. So if you have
4500 meters, then you'd be at
Audrow Nash: divided by 3030
feet per or 10 meters is one
atmospheric, correct?
Ben Raanan: Yeah. So 450
atmospheres, I believe is the
number.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, that's an
easy one. Yeah, doing math
doesn't always
Ben Raanan: work. But especially
not not. Well, you're being
recorded.
Audrow Nash: Not well, sir. So
450 atmospheres?
Ben Raanan: Correct. So I guess
the pressure is immense. And so
in order to take humans into
those kinds of environments, and
support life, human life, in
those environments, you know, it
comes with a huge overhead. And
it's not risk free. And there
are systems that do that. You
know, we have deep sea sobs.
Woods Hole Oceanographic, I
believe, operates. Alvin, which
is a human submarine that's able
to go to those kinds of depths
and and collecting through
there. But it's really scalable.
And you say,
Audrow Nash: on average, just
average depth is that much,
right? What's the what's the
deepest? Like, I guess we
probably don't have a very clear
idea. But what so we do. Okay,
yeah. So how far down does it
go?
Ben Raanan: It's over 11
kilometers. taller than the
mount, the tallest mountain,
right? So and that's 1100.
atmospheres. Correct. And I
believe that's the Mariana
Trench, off the coast of Japan,
which is, so yeah, it's pretty
deep, but humans have reached
there. And vehicles have gone
down there as well. And so it's
not out of their reach. So it's
not very scalable. Right, I
guess it's the point. And, like
I mentioned, again, a lot of the
phenomenon that we're also
interested in, in studying are
very patchy and episodic in
nature, meaning, you can imagine
the wind blows a certain
direction, the currents do a
certain thing, the nutrients
emerge, and then suddenly, boom,
that creates an opportunity for
something to occur. And you're
either there, or you're not. And
sometimes you can be, I'm sorry,
Audrow Nash: give me an example.
Like what might an event that
you're trying to see occur be
like an algae bloom of some
sort, or
Ben Raanan: Yeah, that'd be a
classic example. And so
typically, the way this occurs
is winds blow, they push coastal
waters away from shore, and pull
in deeper waters that are much
richer in nutrients. And that
allows for this community to
community of microorganisms,
plankton, and phytoplankton, to
really flourish. And that mostly
happens on the, you know, upper
part of the ocean where there's
access to sunlight. And so when
those conditions come together,
and those blue dunes are, you
know, you're either there to
catch it, or you're not. And you
either have a platform that's
able to go out and collect this
information, or you don't. And
so, I guess, once that window of
opportunity closes, and
typically that's on the order
of, yeah, weeks, spanning 10s of
kilometers, at least in the
coastal environment. Yeah, that
then your window of opportunity
is is gone and you've lost your
chance to collect the relevant
data. And so having having
autonomous platforms that are
able to persistently be in the
ocean and collect information is
a huge advantage. And so we kind
of segwayed away from the deep
ocean back, you know, to the
upper water column and we
operate automated In automated
systems in both, but you either
need a very a system that's
capable of operating into depths
and in those deaths, or you need
a system that can operate up in
the water and the upper water
column that's, you know, capable
of having that persistence and
endurance to cover, you know,
those, those those areas. And so
in both cases, that those type
of problems lend themselves very
well, for automation, and for
use of autonomous platforms. And
so MBARI has developed. You
know, at the beginning, we were
very focused on getting to those
steps. And so MBARI was one of
the pioneers in developing
remotely operated vehicles,
there was a big kind of cube
like, vehicles, remotely
operated vehicles are over.
Okay. Which, yeah, and so, those
are tethered vehicles, and
they're piloted remotely from a
ship. So those still require a
ship to be in the area. And then
bears
Audrow Nash: able, correct,
yeah, going from the robot to
the ship. Yeah. Yeah, correct.
Ben Raanan: And so in borrowing
has been invested heavily in
developing those kinds of debit
technologies, and also coming up
with ways to manipulate, you
know, the environment there with
robotic arms, and so on, so
forth. And then more recently,
we focused on using autonomous
vehicles to extend the duration.
So cutting the tether, focusing
on platforms that can sustain
themselves in the environment,
with a remote operator that only
supervises periodically. And
that really gives you a ability
to design without counting on
having a ship in the area. And
B, it also opens the window for
scalability, right? So
Audrow Nash: because you don't
need that big stack, to maintain
and be running, like you don't
need a whole ship, going to the
one location because you just
have a bunch of these making
their way around the ocean,
monitoring things
Ben Raanan: correct. And you can
also have an operator that
rather than being fully engaged
in operating a machine is now
checking in periodically just to
make sure things are happening
as they should, and maybe
providing instructions for
correction. And so
Audrow Nash: the grocery store
checkout model is everywhere,
these days, for this kind of
thing, where you have like the
one person watching the 10
machines that were it's just
it's so interesting to see it
here to where you have one
person kind of supervising, but
not paying attention all the
time to all of the robots in
your groups, but just watching a
few that periodically come in
and out of contact, and they
manage maybe giving high level
directions or something like
this. It's so interesting, this
is becoming everywhere, it
seems.
Ben Raanan: Yeah. And I guess
the so there are some aspects of
doing marine robotics that I
guess they're very different
from terrestrial robots, or
aerial robots in a sense. So I
think, you know, the underwater
environment is a communication
denied. Environment, meaning,
you know, once you go on your,
the radio frequencies that we
use for localization and radio
in between our vehicles
diminishes, at that point, we're
only the only chance to our only
option to communicate with the
vehicles mystically using sound
underwater. And that presents a
whole nother set of challenges.
And that technology has come a
long way. But it's still very
limited, especially compared to
way lower bandwidth
Audrow Nash: I would imagine.
Correct. So you're, you're
talking about far less
information can be sent,
Ben Raanan: right bits per
second, and then three limited
in range with typical range, you
know, I'd say a few kilometers,
is kind of typical. Yeah, so So
the vehicles really need to be
self sustained. And they need to
know what to do and operate on
their own. And so that that's a
challenge. But at the same time,
you know, as humans, we're not
really able to be in that
environment, it's hostile for
our bodies. So any kind of
system they can put out there
and can execute a task that's
useful is going to be an
improvement of what you know, on
top of what a person can do. And
I feel here in terrestrial
robotics, we're always up to
your challenge, because, you
know, you got to do as well as
something that as well as a
human where you're already in an
environment where humans can
function fairly well. So so we
have it, you know, many
challenges of one one had but
then, you know, in some, in some
ways, it's kind of easier to
make fast progress and push the
needle further than what you
would be able to Have you used
in environments where humans are
capable?
Audrow Nash: Yeah, because it's
so cheap. So I'm a little
confused. But it. So you're
saying, because these
environments are so challenging
to get people out there, and
there's budget restrictions and
things because like, you can't
have a ship go to each location
you need, or you're interested,
but you can have a robot that
kind of manages itself much more
cheaply. And so because it's so
hostile, and because of the
scalability problem, there's a
lot of room for advancement with
these robots that are going at
the kind of the shallow depths
and monitoring things
autonomously.
Ben Raanan: Correct, or? No?
Yeah, I mean, there's, there's
just pretty much any kind of, if
you can get a system to execute
any kind of task out there at
sea, you're already pushing the
needle forward, you're improving
over what a human can do. And so
and so I guess that's one
advantage of doing marine
robotics, but it might be the
only one, because it really is
very hard. It really is.
Environment.
Audrow Nash: Oh, yeah, totally.
I imagined it's like, almost, if
not as difficult as like putting
a robot in that, like, if you
put a robot in space, it's like
tremendously difficult to get it
up there. But once it's there,
and it's in a harsh environment,
it's that's a big challenge, for
sure, like putting a rover on
the moon, or putting a rover on
Mars or putting something in
space. Like that's tremendously
challenging, given the harshness
of that environment, and that
the remoteness of it. But this
is kind of similar in that the
environments like water is
really powerful. It's very cold,
it's very rough. There's like, I
don't know, bunch of creatures
all around, I don't know, I'm
imagining like,
Ben Raanan: we did have vehicles
in the past. So vehicles have
returned with shark bites in
them and teeth embedded in
wirings. But that's actually a
really good comparison. But I
guess I would argue that, you
know, because of the pressure
and space versus pressure at
sea, we've already talked about
that. So we call that yeah, you
need to be able to sustain those
pressures, which, you know, is a
challenge, but also, even a
vehicle on Mars. Sure, you have
a 20 minutes to 20 minutes back
delay in your communication, but
you're still able to communicate
with the vehicle at all times.
Versus Right, exactly. Versus
underwater platform, where once
the vehicle is under you
typically lose contact. So yeah,
Audrow Nash: that's very
interesting for that. It's
definitely a very hard problem
space. One thing just to give it
because this is one thing that I
don't quite understand yet. What
kinds of things because these
robots are out there, and
they're monitoring something.
But what kinds of data are they
collecting? While they're out
there? Like, specifically? And
I'm sure there's a lot of things
you could look at, but like the
nature of the type of data,
you're collecting, something I
don't yet understand?
Ben Raanan: Sure, yeah. So we
have platforms, different
platforms are geared toward
collecting different types of
information. And so if you're
looking at an ROV, that's a
remotely operated vehicle that
has the option to manipulate.
And so you little hands, right,
exactly. Okay, so you can do
specimen collection, for
example, at the deep sea. We
also use those type of platforms
to do surveys of the seafloor
using video multibeam sonars.
And also for mapping and also,
now, LIDAR. And
Audrow Nash: that works under I
mean, I guess it makes sense
that it works underwater. I
imagine there's a new set of
problems and challenges with
that.
Ben Raanan: Yes, it's very
challenging. I'm actually not
working on those projects. But
we have a whole team here that's
developing that capability. And
it's pretty cool, actually. Oh,
yeah. So so they've developed
actually this really cool
device. It's, I can share a
video later. But it's an
articulating sled that connects
to the remotely operated
vehicle. And it allows the
vehicle to conduct a survey. So
you can imagine it flies over a
constant altitude. But then
regardless of how, with the
bathymetry, that's what the
bottom of the ocean. So for
example, now you're coming up
against the wall, the sled will
articulate itself. So the
sensing is always pointed
directly at the seafloor. And so
that allows you to get
continuous surveys regardless of
what the topography is doing
underwater. And with LIDAR
imagery and sonar, you get very
high resolution data. And so you
can start describing species to
the genius level using imagery.
Cool. And then by returning to
those points, you're able to
track how you know things evolve
over time. And so that's
something we do and Those,
that's one type of information
that we gather and bury those
images and videos that we
collect are one of the biggest,
I guess, databases that we have
is those videos that these
vehicles collect. And we have
also some projects going on here
now to expose some of that
information and make it bring it
to a format where you know, it's
right for automation. And so so
that's one type of data, then we
have two autonomous vehicles
that also carry those deep sea
vehicles. So also geared towards
mapping as a primary task. And
they also carry these big
sonars, and are able to do the
surveys along the sea bottom, at
depth, and retrieve, you know,
high resolution maps of certain
areas. And so that's another
type of data that we collect.
And then, in addition to that,
we also have what we refer to as
oceanographic sensors. So most
typically, there's going to be
sensors that collect
temperature, salinity,
Audrow Nash: you know, that's
how salty it is. Right? Correct.
Second one, salinity,
Ben Raanan: salinity, correct.
And the way Yeah, so that's kind
of like your, your basic, but
then you have also specialized
sensors that are able to tell
you the concentration of certain
nutrients in the ocean water,
for example, like nitrogen,
nitrates, sensors, things like
that. And then we also have even
more specialized sensors that
are able, for example, to sense
the type of bioluminescence. So
they have a chamber that past
Yeah, so so you can see how much
bioluminescence occurring in the
body of water that you're
traveling through. And so that's
another type of
Audrow Nash: does that mean like
an algae will produce light at
night? Or something? I said
analogy, or would it be like
fish in a really deep ocean? Or
both for?
Ben Raanan: Yeah, so they
bioluminescence is light
emitting organisms. And so that
actually happens in a very wide
range of species across the
entire ocean. So it's pretty
ubiquitous. And we have a lab
here that studies, you know, how
it happens. And what are the
evolution pathways that lead to
different types? That's really
cool. Yeah. So so that's another
type of, you know,
Audrow Nash: is it often in deep
sea animals? Or do you see it in
like surface algae? Or like, I
don't know if like the ocean
lights up at night? With algae?
I could imagine that. But I
wonder if it's true. No,
Ben Raanan: it is true. So
larger organisms that that have
bioluminescence are typically
found deeper. And they use
bioluminescence for various
reasons, it could be for
attracting a mate for trying to
capture prey for deterring prey.
And you see different patterns
and different colors being used
for different purposes. In the
shallower water, there are many
types of algae that have
bioluminescence, for different
reasons. And we actually have a
project going on here to try and
identify what type of allergy
you're observing just based on
the bioluminescence patterns. So
yeah, so it's actually pretty
ubiquitous in the ocean and
happens in all kinds of
Audrow Nash: just out of
curiosity, like, I don't really
know anything about this, but
why so I can understand animals
having bioluminescence? Because
they are, like, as the main
reasons you've mentioned,
hunting, or meeting or something
like this, like it's beneficial
for those reasons. But plants. I
can't like algae is a plant to
me. And I can't understand like
how that would affect like, if
there's one algae and it has a
beautiful glow, it doesn't
probably help that algae meeting
with the other one, or maybe
it's some reactive. What's the
what's the reason why algae has
bioluminescent glows?
Ben Raanan: Well, I don't have a
straight answer. There's
Audrow Nash: many. Yeah,
Ben Raanan: there are probably a
few. It could also be for
prediction avoidance. If they
all fluoresce all at once,
Audrow Nash: I guess it looks
like we are waste or something
at some stage.
Ben Raanan: If you try to
imagine trying to capture one
little particle, but suddenly, a
light show blows up in front of
you. I think it would be pretty
hard to focus just on one single
cell. But I'm not sure that's
really the reason I want to get
back into that
Audrow Nash: being some sort of
thing. It's avoiding predators.
I just intuitively I don't I
don't have a good model for why
that would be the case. And it's
fascinating that that exists.
Ben Raanan: But right, yeah,
yeah. And so Steve haddock, Dr.
Steve had a career in MBARI. He
leads research here on
bioluminescence. And so we can
go ahead and look up services
research and probably get some
answers. But he's, he's great.
Audrow Nash: So, those sensors
to your bioluminescence sensors,
and you mentioned a whole bunch
of other ones so salty and
temperature and different
nutrients correctly. So those
are the kinds of things you're
collecting data about. And I
guess, also the video one. So if
you if you see an algae bloom,
what kinds of things are you
trying to sense about that, I
suppose the nutrients is how
salty it is the temperature, but
then also maybe video of the
event, and then or
Ben Raanan: Well, yes, for a
biological shark for studying
those type of microscopic
organisms, we do have some
imagery based payloads that we
use in order to try and identify
species.
Audrow Nash: So you mean like
various cameras, camera setup,
or something that you include on
the robot. So you have your
various payloads that have
various sensors that you might
include on your robots,
Ben Raanan: okay. And in
addition to that, we also have
the ability to acquire water
samples autonomously at sea. And
so we have a whole lab here,
that's actually, that's their
focus, and they've developed a
payload on the environmental
sample processor. And this is
actually probably the most
advanced type of it's not really
a sensor, but it's more like a
payload we refer to it, it's
able to take in 60 water
samples. So you can imagine some
kind of like, a system that has
an intake and is able to filter
water, while the vehicles
deployed at sea. And then also
has some automation that's built
in to this payload, to, you
know, use the right reagents in
order to fix fixate that, that
sample. So it doesn't continue
to change after you've filtered
the water. And then that system
also how that would
Audrow Nash: be like if you had
some sort of bacteria in it, or
something that were like
continued to do, whatever. So it
like, you'll basically sterilize
everything or kill everything in
it. So you can look at its
components. And then you can
easily subtract that reagent out
when you are doing your tests on
it. So you know, kind of your
baseline, and you can see what
it was at the time. Ah,
Ben Raanan: exactly correct. And
then these payloads also have
some analytical modules that are
able to tell you things about
the sample that you just
acquired at sea. Cool. And so at
the extreme case, and this is
still hasn't been miniaturized
to the point where it runs on a
vehicle, you can run this type
of sample and actually target
specific genes. So do almost
like a genomic analysis on the
sample that you just acquired,
and radio back to shore.
Audrow Nash: What are the genes
of what is it literally genes of
something? Are you like getting
an algae sample and looking at
it streams? Or what is it the
what? Oh, it's okay. So it's an
algae that you're synchronizing
effectively. That's super cool.
Ben Raanan: Yeah. And then that
allows you over time and space
to see, you know, what was the?
What was the community, the
microbial community? What was it
looking like? And over time, how
is how has it evolved? And that,
you know, is, is really useful
for research and understanding
how things change over time and
with conditions. So as
conditions change, how does the
microbial community react, but
also, it's very useful for
monitoring. So you can example
for example, you can have, you
can imagine seeing a system like
this deployed somewhere, and
looking for a certain species of
algae that's harmful for the
environment, because it produces
some toxin. And that's kind of
like an early warning system. So
again, geared toward not only
doing research, but also
conservation and resource
management. So that's another
another piece there. And so, you
know, that generally, that
payload kind of personifies, I
guess, one of the major themes
or research that have been going
on here at the Institute, which
what we refer to as taking the
lab, to see, and being able to
do sample processing, and do as
much of the analysis that we can
at sea and inform the vehicle
autonomously, on how to proceed.
And so, taking the lab to the
ocean to the sea is has been a
major theme here. And the type
of development is also you know,
it's always geared to if you if
you could do it here at sea or
on a ship, how can we take that
same analysis and put it on a
platform and so Oh, this, this
this water sampling code that it
just described, for example, now
we're at the point where we're
adding these modules that are
able to also analyze the samples
and have the vehicle, do this
type of analysis at sea, and
radio the results back to shore.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Okay, so
they radio, the radio the
results back. So this is for
like, one of those surface
monitoring robots. So it'll kind
of like stay at some depth,
that's not very deep, collect
some information. And then it
goes in chills at the very
surface in the water, and it'll
radio back the information for
you guys to analyze, or do
something with? And probably
that's how you communicate with
it for like, send it commands or
something, as well, right?
Ben Raanan: So yeah, so the
vehicles actually, they can also
use on the sensory inputs to
inform their, you know, actions.
So our planning algorithms, for
example, that look at sensor
input, and decide how to steer
the vehicle autonomously, for
example, in order to try to stay
with some kind of maximum
concentration, where you know,
you're sensing where most of the
algae is, or where the highest
concentration of algae is. And
you can use optical sensors, to
try to see how much chlorophyll
is in the water using
fluorescence. And so then you
can use this information and
driving the vehicle to do kind
of like, you can imagine a
gradient climbing algorithm that
takes a vehicle from a, you
know, an edge and drives it into
center of the patch. And then
when it reaches the center of
patch, it will trigger a water
sample. So that's something that
we do here pretty typically. And
then, in addition to that, I
guess you mentioned
communication. So yes, the
vehicle surface periodically to
surface with shore. But those
type of applications, especially
if you want to stay with a
certain part of the water mass,
meaning, let's say, because
everything is moving in the
ocean constantly, right, you've
got currents carrying carrying
these microorganisms. And if you
lose that patch of water, and in
order to go up to the surface
and communicate well, when you
come back down, you might be
looking at our community. And so
those type of applications
really lend themselves well to
multi vehicle constellations.
And so that's been another focus
here is this multi vehicle type
of operations. And so in the
example that we just discussed,
you'll have one vehicle that is
doing this graded climbing and
looking for a maxilla. And then
once it finds the highest
concentration of chlorophyll, or
whatever it is, it's looking
for, it kind of just parks it
underwater, and stays with that
water mass and drifts. And the
issue with that is, you know,
after a while, you're not going
to know what a vehicle is, you
are not know you're not going to
know what type of information
it's looking at. And so a second
vehicle will typically track
this type of sampling vehicle,
smart. And then one is at
Audrow Nash: the surface looking
down and the other one is
drifting with this algae Max.
Ben Raanan: Well, so that's one
way to do it. And we also use
autonomous surface vessels in
order to track underwater
assets. But we typically also
have a second underwater vehicle
that's profiling around it and
tracking it, it's surfacing
periodically, and it can relay
information from the diving
vehicle. And also, it gives the
scientists more contextual data,
because usually the second
vehicle is kind of parked at one
little part of the water column.
And in order to get the full
contextual data of what's going
on, you also need a second
vehicle in order to survey and
get
Audrow Nash: the bird's eye view
are the ones in the forest. And
one is that the trees kind of
thing.
Ben Raanan: Exactly. And so
multi vehicle applications have
been, you know, a main theme
here. And I guess that kind of
leads us toward maybe talking a
little bit about the sim. Yeah,
Audrow Nash: one sec. Just
before we go into that, what are
these vehicles look like? So
specifically talking about the
surface monitoring ones where
we're looking at algae, right?
What are the what are the robots
look like?
Ben Raanan: Yeah, so typically,
they're kind of torpedo shaped
vehicles. That's the most
efficient way. And the vehicles
that we work that I work with,
specifically are kind of small
size, so they're probably two to
two and a half meters long,
depending on the type of payload
that they have. And the diameter
is about 12 inches. And there it
basically looks like torpedoes,
I can show you A picture here
maybe? Sure.
Audrow Nash: I'd love to talk a
little bit about how they work
and then get into the SIM stuff.
Because the sim stuff is very
interesting. For sure.
Ben Raanan: So this is a picture
of one of our vehicles, those
are test class long range EVs.
So, like I mentioned, these are
upper water column vehicles,
they're pressure rated for about
300 meters. And what's special
about them is really their
endurance, we decided to
Audrow Nash: fire extinguisher,
Ben Raanan: pretty much, yeah,
if you ever seen a picture of it
there, then it looks pretty much
like that with a bit with a mask
on top, and that's our
communication antenna. Yeah, so
go ahead, stop sharing it. But
so that's the long end up now. I
guess, like I mentioned, we
embark has really been on the
forefront of development of
these platforms. And so on that
vehicle that I just showed that
this class long SUV has been
developed and borrowed from
scratch. And it's also
manufactured here, and operated
here. And so everything about
that vehicle was designed here
in house, these vehicles are
special, they're special in
their capacity for their high
endurance vehicles, meaning they
can cover about 1500 kilometers.
And stay at sea for say, up to
two to three weeks, which is
unusual for vehicles at that
size. Especially for ones that
have propeller and they're able
to thrust on their own. There
are other types of vehicles that
don't have thrusters and have
longer endurance. But this
vehicle is very special and
unique. And that's capacity to
stay up there.
Audrow Nash: So it doesn't do
any, it basically you have a
battery, and that battery will
last for two to three weeks. And
that dictates how long you can
do it doesn't do any power
generation or like go up to the
surface and have solar panels
fold out or
Ben Raanan: something. But it
does. I mean, the power
management system is very
efficient, efficient. Yes, every
every aspect of that vehicle is
designed is really geared toward
efficiency from the shape to the
tail cone and how you know, the
the hydrodynamic flow, and how
water passes around it. It's
going to set to minimize drag.
And this vehicle specifically is
also special because it can
change its buoyancy. Meaning it
most people that put very
expensive pieces of equipment in
the ocean, they make them
buoyant. So if the agent stops
working, we'll come back up.
Well, this one is able to
actually change its buoyancy at
sea and fly neutral. And that
actually gives you a huge
efficiency boost, because you're
not pushing against. Yeah, this
upward force. And so then, you
know, comes the question, okay,
if something does go wrong, how
do you manage that, and so their
safety and power management are
kind of the heart of this
vehicle. And so both both have,
you know, systems that are
designed specifically in order
to optimize the routers, the
vehicle powers off systems
automatically when it doesn't
need them, even including extra
readers. So it's very smart
management on board. And, you
know, when you you know,
insurance in general, it's kind
of death by 1000 cuts, right?
Try to optimize around each
parameter, eventually, you get a
system that is able to persist
and be out there for those type
of durations. And again, the
requirements for those durations
come back to the original
processes that we've discussed
kind of in depth upon not
intended.
Audrow Nash: So many ocean ponds
are possible for sure. So with
this, when it adjusts its
buoyancy, the way it does that
is it takes on water, right,
like so it will have little
cavities or something in it, or
how does it work?
Ben Raanan: Yeah, well,
actually. So our vehicle doesn't
take in water, it uses oil. And
so it can pass oil into a
bladder that's external to the
sealed compartment. And by doing
that, so if you're taking oil
from the sealed compartment, and
pushing it out to a bladder that
can inflate, you're actually
changing the volume of the
vehicle without changing its
mass. And by definition, that
makes it more buoyant. And when
you want to become less buoyant,
you just push the oil back into
the seal compartments. And that
deflates the bladder. And the
vehicle
Audrow Nash: then becomes less
of a thing. The volume changes
in the mass stays constant and
that changes the buoyancy of the
correct Is it is it a lot of
energy to like compress the oil
Remove it inside to the oil.
What?
Ben Raanan: It's not oil, it's
not cool. It's non compressible
oil.
Audrow Nash: It's like some sort
of vacuum thing to move it from
one spot to another.
Ben Raanan: Yeah, we have a
valve that opens and then a pump
that sits inside the seal
compartment and can push oil
outside. And it's designed in a
way that, you know, it can push
against pressure, even at depth.
And then there's a lot of also
some safety built in there, you
know, what happens if suddenly
you can't push against the
pressure. And so there are some
valves that are set to close
automatically and make sure that
water never makes it back. In in
case of a failure. So like I
said, failure management is one
of the big things. Exactly. So
pretty much every aspect here.
Yeah. Go ahead. So.
Audrow Nash: So you don't want
it to fail, because you lose
your robot. How much does one of
these robots actually cost? Like
ballpark?
Ben Raanan: Yeah, sure. So I
guess these vehicles also, were
designed for what we refer to as
science users. Okay. So if
you're a researcher at a lab,
you should be able to buy one of
these and, and, and operate it
on your own with a reasonable
budget. And so that was kind of
the requirements going into
there. And so the vehicles, you
know, they're well, actually,
not sure if it's a good idea for
me to disclose the exact
Audrow Nash: like, like an order
of magnitude $50,000 robot
platform, I'd
Ben Raanan: say probably an
order of magnitude more.
Audrow Nash: Wow. So it's like
ballpark 500,000. So half a
million almost for one of these.
Yeah. And that's affordable for
large research institutions. I
take it well, if
Ben Raanan: you consider what it
costs to operate a ship. Yeah,
most of
Audrow Nash: it costs in order
to do a ship, like right, so I
guess, sorry, go ahead, because
it seems expensive. But I have
no experience in this. So no
real ability to estimate this.
Ben Raanan: Right. So a big
ship, especially one that can
operate an ROV, you're probably
looking at a few tenths of
$1,000 per day. Wow. So if it's
a bigger ship, you're around 50
to 60k. Easy per day of
operation. And so half a
million. I mean, it might sound
a lot, but when you think about
it, and ship. Exactly. And so
that's the idea, then, once you
if you can get the costs in for
the vehicle, the operational
costs are very, very cheap. You
can deploy these vehicles with,
you know, tiny, little boats,
and then you're stuck with the,
you know, whatever
communications bill for radium
satellite communication, or you
know, your, your 4g cell. So,
Audrow Nash: so they the
operational origin is, so if
they're doing, like 4g cell
service for transferring data,
does that mean that you have to
stay close to coast with these?
And that's typically how you're
using them? Because I would
imagine if you're in the middle
of the ocean, like very far from
shore, you're in the middle of
the Pacific. There's no cell
towers out there. There's no
cell service, but you did
mention satellite. So I suppose
you could use that?
Ben Raanan: Yeah. So we have, we
refer to the we have two modes
of operation. We, when you're
outside of cell range, we refer
to that as over the horizon.
When you're within cell range,
you know, why not take advantage
of cell communication and do big
data dumps when you can? I don't
know if a region is very slow,
and bandwidth limited, and so
Audrow Nash: slow is really
slow, like ballpark.
Ben Raanan: So let's see to read
the impact it is 340 bytes. And
you get about I'd say if you're
lucky, three to four per minute.
When the surface Yes, so it's
tiny. And so we play a lot of
games on board system, with
refreshing, and all sorts. Yeah,
and also not only compression,
but also selecting what
information to send what's the
most relevant piece of
information that needs to be
sent? What needs to be sent
first versus, you know, if
you're only able to get one SBD?
One ready, pack it out? You
know, what is it going to be?
And so, we work a lot with the
scientists in order to
understand the use case. You
know, get what is the crucial
information that they need for
decision making while the
vehicles deployed and then
configure the vehicle
appropriately and send it over?
And, you know, hopefully not
spend most of our time sitting
on the surface sending packets
data. Exactly. So time on the
surface is rescue vehicle
because it can get over. That's
probably the biggest risk for
these autonomous platforms
Audrow Nash: getting run over.
Not sharks. Yeah. All right.
Ben Raanan: But so it's time not
doing science. So totally.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so you have
these, what have you long range?
What was the next part?
autonomous underwater vehicles?
Or what was the thing you were
saying? Correct?
Ben Raanan: Yes, it's the long.
So these, these vehicles are
long range autonomous underwater
vehicles. So LR EVs for short.
Audrow Nash: LR UVs? LR LR UVs.
Yeah. doesn't roll off the
tongue terribly.
Ben Raanan: You know, we've had
other people try to come up with
different ways. We're kind of
stuck with that one.
Audrow Nash: Okay, I'm just
gonna say long range underwater
vehicles easier. Okay, so you
have these, Whoa, you're
mentioning that you have a bunch
of safety precautions on them?
Because so they're half a
million dollar platforms. I'm
sure that with the cost of about
you make the money back, but
it's still super expensive. So I
think institutions probably
wouldn't like to be replacing
them because they keep getting
lost at sea, literally. Right.
Can you talk about about the
safety?
Ben Raanan: So I guess I'll say
that we have eight of these
platforms here in MBARI. And
there are others coming up
online. I was holding on other
places where they're building at
the moment. And between the
fleet, we have probably nearing
35,000 hours of sea time. And
seems like that's a lot. That's
a lot.
Audrow Nash: Let's see, how many
how many days at sea is that
between the eight? So that's
1000 divided by 24. Right?
Ben Raanan: So So that's like,
four years? Four years worth of?
Yeah, it's four years of sea
time, which isn't crazy. That's
a lot. And dirt. Exactly. I was
gonna go knock on wood. But
yeah, right. We've never lost
one. Yeah. And so, again, the
reason is, because MBARI has a
lot of experience. And we've
basically taken all of our
experience and knowledge and
built it into the hardware level
of these vehicles. So this
vehicle has so many safety
features built into it. In the
hardware level, meaning the
motherboard itself, if CPU
fries. The motherboard itself
has the capacity to turn on the
radio and communicate, you know,
so you know, fire up a device
that drops a weight to make the
vehicle positively Oh stays and
we have an emergency, it's
going? Well, no, it will come
back to the surface. The drop
weight, attaches
Audrow Nash: reduces the weight.
And so it goes exactly, yeah,
it's like cutting your weights
when you're scuba diving. So
that exam you can start going
on.
Ben Raanan: And that's exactly
the idea. And then we have
transponders and all kinds of
other acoustic devices onboard
the vehicle, and then emergency
beacons, so we can, we can
always find them. So the vehicle
will try as hard as it can to
come back to the surface because
that's where it can be located.
And once it's on the surface,
even if the battery is
completely depleted, their
secondary radio, right, that
will that will communicate with
shore and send its position. And
so that's one aspect. We also
have very sophisticated ground
fault detection systems,
meaning, you know, if, if
there's a cable or something
like that that's exposed to
ocean water, that can cause
corrosion, that can cause
corrosion, just because Victor
city starts interacting with
different parks like the whole.
And so we have a very strict
monitoring system for that. We
also have, you know, in general,
you want the system to be
reliable and fault tolerant. So
you can continue to do
operations, if the vehicle has
to surface every 10 minutes,
because if you've countered an
issue that it can't resolve on
its own, well, operationally,
that doesn't scale. And so we
have also a health monitoring
system on board that's able to
power cycle different subsystems
and try to change balls. And so
yeah, a lot of thought and
effort has gone into making sure
that the system will keep doing
what it's supposed to do for as
long as it can, and only come
back to the surface and
communicate with sure when it
absolutely has to.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha Awesome.
That's so funny that it power
cycle, all the things. It's just
it's like that tried and true
wisdom of just like if it's not
working, just power cycle it. I
love that you have the ability
to do that, kind of remotely
with the robot, right?
Ben Raanan: Yeah, it'd be a step
forward or it would flip RX and
TX.
Audrow Nash: And because of
that, so just to explain, if
anyone didn't get it, it's the
transmit and receive wires. So
like a lot of times when you're
building stuff you mix up, which
is the transmitting and
receiving the flip, it all works
magically. Right. So that would
be so funny.
Ben Raanan: Yeah, that's kind of
like the classic mistake. But
yeah. So with all that, and we I
guess, I also say that we've
operated these vehicles now in
both Pacific and Atlantic
oceans, and also in the Great
Lakes. So their tried and true
vehicles. very persistent, very
reliable.
Audrow Nash: So and you
mentioned you have eight of
them. That's, I mean, that's
that's in between them, they
have tons and tons of hours, is
there a plan to like scale it
massively and get like 80 of
them, or 800 of them? Or, like,
so these are all over monitoring
everything all at once? Or?
Well? Yeah, where do you see
this going in the future?
Ben Raanan: Right. And so I
guess, you know, we're currently
I think doing multi Vehicle
Operations, has still a lot of
overhead. And so figuring out, I
guess, at first order how to
operate so many vehicles, in
conjunction, and how to automate
the processes, ongoing research
on MBARI, and I think in a lot
of other places, we've nailed
down two to three fleets of two
or three and doing
collaborative, multi vehicle
operations at sea. With you
know, that many vehicles, more
than that, you start running
into bottlenecks. For example,
if they're all using the same
acoustic channel to communicate,
well, that's kind of like a
habit, right? Only one person
can talk at any time. And so you
get where
Audrow Nash: you say, You're,
like, I'm talking to this one,
and then the message, but it's
inefficient.
Ben Raanan: Right, exactly. So
so that's another piece where we
have some ongoing research, to
figure out how we can scale
that. But then also, the
logistics of operating a fleet
like that is also you know, so
you have two weeks of battery,
and you need to if you have many
of those, they really need to be
self sustained. And XE is
Audrow Nash: some sort of power
generation method.
Ben Raanan: Correct. And so
Barbie has an ongoing project,
we have a, what we call the
energy booty to it's, it's a boy
that uses energy from waves. And
so that charges a battery, and
then in conjunction with
Audrow Nash: that, so is it kind
of like it rides along like
maybe six feet down, or
something, and then there's the
buoy moving up and down,
creating motion, and then you're
using metal icicle energy, this
Ben Raanan: is a whole separate
platform that generates power.
And then I was gonna say, and
then in addition to that
platform, it also has what we
refer to as a docking module.
And so the idea is for the
vehicles to be able to home back
to this device, dock on it, and
charge the battery. And we've
made some really good progress.
So we have a boy that, you know,
manufactures energy from waves,
and stores it. And now we've
been, we, we've actually
licensed some technology from
Northrop Grumman. And they've
developed this technology they
call Niobe, calm, which is this
metal that's based on niobium,
that is self healing. So it can
coat itself with a very thin
layer that doesn't transfer
electricity. And so it interacts
when when you power it in
interacts with seawater, and it
creates this coat round the
metal. And so that's kind of
like a self sustained piece of
equipment that you could leave
in the ocean. And then when the
vehicle comes in docks on it, it
could expose and just peel off
that tiny little thin layer, and
in connect to the power source
in charge its battery. And so
we've been working very hard to,
you know, see that through, and
we've done some sea trials, and
you know, it works, there's
still a lot of kinks to iron,
but that's for sure, no,
eventually, the the dream is to
be able to have a large number
of these vehicles out at sea
where they circulate in common,
charge their battery, do data
dumps and then go back out to
sea. And then you can even
imagine maybe that wave we is
something that's mobile, and
maybe you can direct that thing
in ordinance. And so I think
that type of constellation,
where you have an energy source
in a in a data sink, where you
know, vehicles can come in and
charge the battery and do big
data off floats and then go back
and do tasks. Is is kind of
where we're headed with this,
what we refer to as kind of like
a mobile observation platform.
Audrow Nash: And then once you
have that, then scaling is a lot
easier. It's like maybe the two
hardest challenges for this
would be the communication as
part of this, where you're
limited and how you can send to
multiple ones. And also you're
very limited by satellite radio,
I wonder if like Starlink, or
anything will help any of that.
That'd be quite cool. No, no.
Ben Raanan: Yeah, there are
still other technologies that
are coming up, that will speed
up over the horizon.
Communication. So we're excited
to see how this technology is
gonna play
Audrow Nash: out, that'd be
super cool. And then the second
one would be power generation,
because you have to retrieve it
after the battery is nearly
dead, or around the time that
the battery's nearly dead. But
if you could somehow charge with
these systems, or whatever it
might be, then you could just
stay out and continuously
revolve them. And then it's a
lot less going out and grabbing
it, which I assume is still
quite expensive to do, because
you need to take a ship. And the
ship has to have like a big
crane or something to grab it or
whatever it might be.
Ben Raanan: Sure. And I mean,
you don't assume for these
vehicles, you don't necessarily
have to have it. Yeah, but But
if they're far out, I mean, if
you're in a coastal environment,
that's great. But if, if it's
happening, if you want to do
research for that, or if it's
really just really far away.
That's an issue. Yeah. And so
we're also looking into
developing autonomous surface
vessels that are able to do
deployment and tow out, that'd
be so cool. Yeah. So that's
another kind of direction that
some researchers here are
looking at at the moment.
Audrow Nash: You mentioned
earlier that one human operator
can work with a few different of
these robots that are out how
does that look?
Ben Raanan: Yeah, so we've put a
lot of effort into developing a
user interface, that's a web
based interface that allows you
to control the fleet and
interact with it. And so we
basically have a website that
gives you all the information
you need in order to operate the
vehicles tells you where they
are to you on a map, to see what
mission they're running, and
you're able to interact and
queue up commands and send them
to the vehicles through that web
interface. Like I said, the
vehicles were, you know, really
designed with the end user in
mind. So when we have big
expeditions and experiments out
here, the scientists are the
ones that are actually running
the vehicles and not the
engineers. And so we have a
training program that we, you
know, developed in order to
train people to use them with
our web interface. And we
actually have a number of
projects here that are geared
toward, you know, improving the
user experience, and, and
rethinking a little bit how we
can do these types of multi
vehicle operations. With a
single user kind of commanding
the fleet, again, doing 234.
That's definitely manageable
with a single operator. But more
than that, I think it'd be a bit
of an overload. A lot of ends up
being, you know, what we're
identifying the bottleneck is
the ability to predict what is
going to happen next, the how
the schedule is going to work
together, how missions. So
basically, look into the future
and understand what what, what
are the next few steps that the
fleet is going to do? Currently,
it's easy to understand what's
happening at the moment, but
it's a little harder to
understand, you know, how things
are going to evolve. And so
that's another piece where we're
trying to add in, you know,
models that are maybe a way to
extrapolate out into the near
future, at least, and give the
operator an idea of what the
fleet's going to be doing, not
only what it's doing at the
moment. So,
Audrow Nash: gotcha. Awesome.
It's very interesting. It's
cool. It's cool to imagine
scaling this, I don't know, it's
really neat to me to have an
operator controlling these at a
high level and making the plans
and it's neat to consider how
that interface might be and how
it'll change over time as you
increase the efficiency for an
operator. Very cool.
Ben Raanan: Yeah. And I guess,
you know, because the timescales
we're talking about, for these
vehicles for their deployments,
I mean, that's weeks
potentially, doing development
on the system is very difficult,
because once they go to the,
there's a lot of overhead,
everything's very slow, and so
fast. And then real time
simulation really plays heavily
into what we do. And so I feel
like, you know, I think that
having those capabilities also,
especially in the fleet context,
are going to be monumental into
developing disabilities to not
only do the multi vehicle
operations at sea, but also how
to control them. So
Audrow Nash: that's tell me a
bit about the simulation. Right.
Ben Raanan: So this project is
something that we jumped up a
couple of years ago. It's The
idea was, you know, we talked a
lot about multi vehicles, and
how difficult Axi operations are
and risky. And so the idea was
to develop in a development
environment for these vehicles
that will allow us to test and
the closest way to the
conditions that we experienced
out at sea, you know, the, the
challenges and the bottlenecks
for these types of operations.
And so, we had a simulator that
was built in that we developed
the system. But we felt like it
was time for a facelift. So it
wasn't really I mean, it's a
command line tool. So it didn't
really scale well, to the motor
vehicle scenario. And so we
looked at a few options of you
know, what it would take to
upgrade it. And eventually, we
came up with this idea, maybe we
should, you know, bring in an
external platform, and we
started looking around. And
that's when we came across a
gazebo and a condition. And we
also had some folks who opened
robotics come here and visit and
started forming these
relationships. And so from here
to there, we decided to launch
this project to build a multi
vehicle underwater simulation
environment for LR UV in gazebo,
and ignition. And we got funded
through the Institute in order
to do exactly that. And we
partnered with open robotics,
and really contracted the
engineering time to do the
development for this purpose.
And so it's been a fun ride,
working with the team here at
open robotics. You know, we had
some, we weren't really sure how
it was gonna work out, we
absolutely had to have the
framework work with the flight
code of the vehicles themselves.
Typically, ignition is geared
more toward applications that
use Ross, where our vehicles run
such tiny embedded systems that
at the time, it wasn't really
possible to even get Ross loaded
on it. And so the integration
with our software was key. And
so we focus on that. And then
the second biggest requirement
was the fast in real time
capability. And so we also had
concerns with that. And that was
part of the reasons why. So we
went to ignition or gazebo
classic, is the runtime is much
quicker, and you can change
different aspects of the system
to expedite the runtimes. And so
we started with integration
built the vehicle model for L or
u v, which is now available to
download an app fuel and we can
incorporate the links maybe at
the bottom here, when we're
done. And, and so we slowly
started building the the pieces
and the different plugins that
were required. A big piece that
we recently completed was kind
of like custom sensor
environmental data. So your
ability to take detailed
information from, you know, very
sophisticated models that model
circulation and temperatures and
you know, all the different
ocean parameter, as well as the
biological activity that that
relates to those conditions, and
inject those into the system and
how the vehicles operate within
that environment that not only
has, you know, the water
properties, and waves and wind
and all those things, but it
also has kind of scientific
sensor data that the vehicle
would encounter, as if it's in
the field. And so that's a
really nice aspect of the system
that I feel we've done a little
bit different from the way
things are more traditionally
done, where you have kind of
like a lyrical model that
describes how properties change
using some function.
And another piece that we
incorporated was an acoustic
model. And so vehicles can
communicate acoustically in the
simulated environment, in order
to do these multi Vehicle
Operations, like I mentioned
before, acoustics and
coordination is a big piece. And
so we have that model with the
kind of like standardized
interface that allows the
different vehicles to send
tracking messages between each
other, and also data. And so so
that's modeled and you know, so
all the different obviously, the
vehicle model is very detailed.
So the vehicle has, you know, we
talked a little bit about the
verbal buoyancy system that we
have on board and so that pose
some some modeling challenges
because that's unusual,
especially in a simulation
environment a gazebo for
something to change its buoyancy
in that way, and so we had to
build some infrastructure into
ignition itself in so come up
with the right plugins in order
to support that type of
performance for the vehicles.
And, you know, it's it's pretty
cool and works for Very well,
we're able to achieve fast in
real time. runtimes have about
100x factor of time, which is
great. Yes. And so even with a
few vehicles in the simulation,
you're still at, you know, 60 to
80x. So, you know, 24 hours of
simulation translate into 24
minutes of runtime in the
simulator, which is great. And
it's something that, you know,
it's it's a useful simulator,
for sure. Yeah. And so that's
been really good. We're still
working on now, adding, you
know, there's a whole nother
part of the vehicle sensing
capabilities that we haven't
really touched on that has to do
with how the vehicles navigate
underwater. And so we're now
more focusing on those aspects.
And so we currently have the
ability to simulate the type of
experience that we've described
earlier, where vehicles, you
know, are searching around for
different ocean properties and
doing water samples and all that
stuff. But now, okay, what about
navigation. That's another use
case that, you know, could
benefit a lot from from this
type of simulation. And so we've
worked to add bathymetry using
levels actually. So depending on
the position of the vehicle in
the simulation, it can load a
chunk of seafloor. And so that
makes it pretty scalable. And
you can imagine titling huge
regions, and have them, you
know, loaded dynamically and
have in a memory efficient way.
Audrow Nash: So that you'll get
what you need, or only what you
need at the time. And that moves
over to the next tile, and you
load that tile and this kind of
thing, or you load a few tiles
around where it is, but it never
sees the edge of the tile. Okay,
yeah,
Ben Raanan: we ran into that. So
the tiles actually. Yeah, so So
that's working great. And now
we're working on some, some more
acoustic sensors that have to do
with sensing the bottom. So
they're what's called Doppler
velocity loggers, those are used
for navigation, it can tell you
how fast the vehicle is flying
over the bottom. And then it
becomes a question of odometry,
you know, keeping track of
integrating those velocities
into position. So you're able to
use those sensors for
navigation. And so that's kind
of the next big use case that
we're aiming the sim at, is
automated navigation, what we
refer to. And we have Yeah, we
have some cool use cases here at
MBARI. There's a lab that's
focused on doing terrain
relative navigation that I think
a lot of folks have heard of, in
the context of, you know, the
lander and Mars where they use
during real time navigation to
localize understand what they
are before they landed. And so
we do the same using the
seafloor, using maps that were
acquired with the really big,
much more expensive vehicles
later, you can load those in and
use that in order to localize
yourself based on a cemetery
where you are going to like Sam
says, and so. So that's another
aspect. I guess one more cool
piece in that is that together
with the simulation plugins, and
all the pieces that the folks
that open robotics have working
very hard and doing a tremendous
job doing, those are all going
to be open source and the RTR.
And so that's going to be
available for the community to
use and leverage. And we're
hoping that folks pick pieces
up, you know, and use them and
improve them. So pull requests
are welcome, I guess, launch
around open source community.
But in addition to that, we're
also going to be releasing a
Docker image that has a version
of the vehicles flight code. So
folks can, you know, play around
with both and operate the
vehicles with the flight code in
the loop. And in addition to
that, we also have an interface
to the vehicle that's a network
based interface. And so the idea
is, for folks that can't have
access, for example, to the
flight code, they're still able
to send commands using this
interface to the vehicle and
derive it from their
application. And so we refer to
that as the backseat driver. And
so the idea will be eventually
that you level with those Docker
images to create your own
application that's able to get
telemetry data from the main
vehicle application, feed it
into your app for processing,
whatever your use case is, and
issue commands back to the
vehicle to you know, pilot
within the the environment. And
in theory, if everything's
right, you should be able to
take that backseat application
that you've developed and put it
on a Jetson or whatever that's
mounted on board L or UV inside
the home and have it pilot
vehicle at sea. And so that's
awesome. Yeah, so the idea is
very much for this whole package
to kind of be something that's
deployable by single use. are so
they can do development again
for their back seat application
or whatever using this interface
that we've come up with. And
later take the same application,
put it on board and have it work
at sea.
Audrow Nash: That seems awesome.
I like I like that. And it
sounds like last, I haven't been
very involved in this at all at
open robotics. So just hearing
about it is very cool. But it's,
it sounds like you guys have
done a tremendous amount of work
to make it so that you have a
realistic ocean environment, for
your simulation for your robot
in simulation to drive around
and interact with. Very awesome.
Ben Raanan: Yeah. Yeah, we I
mean, there's always room for
improvement. And, you know, we
really focus on building, I
wouldn't say it's the best ocean
model, right? There are
definitely ways to do things
better. And we hope that over
time, things will improve. But I
think that goal was to kind of
close the loop to get you to an
environment that is close enough
to the real thing that allows
you to work on I'd say, kind of
guidance level parts, right. So
not so much the control, but
maybe a layer above.
Audrow Nash: And you wanted to
do. Right, exactly,
Ben Raanan: exactly. And debug
and work in a multi vehicle
setting. And so, like I said,
per use case, I'm sure that will
continue to improve the system.
But at this point, it is it's
pretty good. It's good enough to
definitely be able to test out
some of these scenarios. And
much faster and real time
capability is a godsend, really
nice. Yeah. So so that's really
cool.
Audrow Nash: What do you so
thinking forward? Where do you
imagine this whole project? And
kind of the work you're doing at
MBARI? Going? So maybe like
five years, 10 years in the
future? Where Where do you think
it will be? What do you hope it
will be?
Ben Raanan: Yeah, so I guess
we're still at a point. So the
way I think of it here is that
we've done a tremendous job,
getting a persistent platform
that's reliable. And it's taken
us the project for for LRE. V
has been running since 2008. So
even before I've just Institute,
but it's taken a while to get to
the point where the system is
now stable, and very, very
reliable. And so now, I guess,
sensing and planning are the two
big. Next, I guess challenges
that we have, okay, so
everything we do on the system
is still pretty rudimentary. So
we have really cool planning
algorithms that, you know, climb
gradients, but they use pretty
rudimentary math, there's a lot
more that we can do to
Audrow Nash: improve, like, keep
getting more algae, like if you
keep seeing more, it's good. And
if you don't, it's you've
reached the center or something.
Ben Raanan: Right. So
boundaries, the algorithms that
we're using are, I guess,
there's room for improvement.
They're great. Don't get me
wrong, we do tree work. And
yeah, but yeah, but but there's
so so that's one piece where,
you know, the autonomy piece
where the vehicles can help plan
and do and do things in
conjunction together, is, I
think, where we'll see big
advancements, I'm hoping that,
you know, the system that we
described earlier, where we have
kind of like a power system,
yeah, observatory is something
that, you know, will come into
reality. And I think the same is
also going to be paramount, and
developing those type of
systems. Because, like I
mentioned, there are lots of
challenges, communication, and
other aspects that currently, we
just aren't sure how we're going
to solve. And, and being able to
simulate everything, and much
faster real time, it kind of
lends itself to iterative
methods and other other
techniques that, you know, will
hopefully help resolve and close
some of these gaps without
having to go to see every time
and, and the overhead that goes
into that. And so I think I
think this mobile observatory,
if we can be there in 10 years,
I think that's going to be
pretty amazing. So cool. Yeah.
And then I guess another piece
where I'm really hoping to see
this project evolve into is, you
know, we've put tremendous
effort into building an
infrastructure. That's, you
know, making its way into
upstream into gazebo and
ignition at the core of it. And
so I think, you know, what I
would really like to see is
ignition being adopted widely by
the marine community, and other
folks coming in and using this,
you know, at MBARI. We're sure
100% that we can make good use
of this technology and this
application, but we're really
hoping that others also pick it
up and use it and contribute
back to it and forget or
whatever it is. But use it use
it, you know, we're also lucky
in the capacity that we have
access to the ocean. But there
could be some brilliant minds
out there that may not have that
type of budget or just straight
up, you know, don't have access
to the ocean. And so we're
hoping that that will increase
exposure, people will be able to
develop these types of
applications, and perhaps even
communicate with us and we can
get them on the vehicles to run
et Cie. So that's also very
exciting aspect of this project
they'd like to see evolve and
curious to see what kind of
collaborations and partnerships
we form, with this sim kind of
being as the is the platform
that connects, you know, because
it's out
Audrow Nash: in the community.
So yeah, you get a bunch of
people that can try it out and
start to get involved and see if
they fit well. And if they
really would want to do this,
that seems wonderful.
Ben Raanan: Yeah, yeah,
hopefully. So and I mean, there
are so you know, other
Institute's that, you know,
already are doing this type of
work. There's very little
overlap, even within MBARI,
different platforms, different
code bases. And so there's a lot
that we could do for
standardization, and then
bringing, you know, putting out
different parts of the software,
or even just interfaces to make
things, you know, a little more
interchangeable. And if I work
very hard developing a terrain
relative navigation system, you
know, I'm hoping that somebody
else can pick it up and use it
as well. Totally. So that's
another piece.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, it seems like
this is the way things go.
Typically, when it's a space,
that's more exploratory, like,
there are very few people or few
organizations doing work, like
you guys are doing. Therefore,
there's very little
standardization around it. But
think, I think creating the sim
is a wonderful thing, because
now a bunch of people can try
it, and they can run their code
on your platforms in the
simulation. And then there can
start to be more buy in from the
community around this and more
investment in ways of doing
things which leads to
standardization. So I am
optimistic for the future, and
kind of seeing where this will
go. I think that'll be awesome.
Yeah, hopefully. Do you. So what
advice do you have for people
that are say, say, like a
college student or something
that would like to be involved
in this line of work? What
advice for them Do you have?
Ben Raanan: Well, so I was very
much in that, you know,
position. When I first started
here, like I mentioned, I
started as an intern here at
MBARI. And I actually don't
have a formal engineering
background, my background is in
marine science. So you know, I
think you just have to want it
and be curious. And then seek
out, be outspoken, don't wait
for the opportunity to come to
you. So your quick story that,
you know, at the time, when I
did my internship, there was
actually wasn't budget for me to
come here and be an intern. And
I already had met with a pi. And
we had discussed a potential
project and was very excited for
the opportunity. But then
suddenly, there wasn't enough
budget to host me. And so that
was the point where I was like,
Okay, I'm gonna make this
happen. And I reached out and
wrote some blogs and ended up
raising enough money to be able
to fund my own internship.
Right, so, but I guess the the
piece is beyond the money, it's
being proactive, and, and really
wanting to take part, I think,
also, intellectually, we'd like
to see more people from
different disciplines,
especially more can engineering
based in computer science base,
and come to do ocean research.
Because there's a lot of room
for that type of knowledge to
make it into our community and
contribute. So if you're looking
to be very impactful, and help
understand what the environment
is doing, and how we're
impacting the environment, and
how it's changing, this is a
really good field for you to
come in, and apply expertise or
your research or just develop
your interests and in
contribute, and so internships
are a great way to start. But a
lot of the people that work in
this community, because they're
so they believe, you know, they
want to see progress. They're
very friendly, and they're happy
to help. So get on our website,
poke around, send an email, you
know, it's it's always great to
hear from people. And if we can
help we, we try to. So, yeah, I
guess, being proactive and not
being deterred. You know,
there's all kinds of reasons why
not to do things, but if you are
curious, just go ahead and shoot
or know or learn something new
and Push forward, eventually you
get there. I don't know. Maybe
that's a really broad piece of
advice. But that's what I got.
It sounds
Audrow Nash: wonderful. Lastly,
do you have any contact info or
links or anything you'd like to
make sure that we share with
this episode?
Ben Raanan: Sure. So I guess,
obviously, there are simulation
framework that we're developing,
which is already open and out
there. And so we'll include the
links, that's actually I know
SRF repo or C, these days. And
we'll go ahead and share that.
My information can be found on
the bar website, and I'll share
that as well. I'm also on
LinkedIn, Twitter, all those
great platforms. So feel free to
reach out if you're interested.
Especially if you want to use
the sim or if you have an idea
for a vaccine application that
you'd like to see running at C
mon are taught this class
longer. AGVs Let's talk. Yeah,
that's, that's pretty much it. I
MBARI has a wonderful website
that's full with data in
interesting stories. So feel
free to visit there. But that's
pretty much it.
Audrow Nash: Okay, awesome. It's
been wonderful talking to you.
Ben Raanan: Thank you very much
for having me.
Audrow Nash: Hi, everyone. Thank
you for listening to this
conversation with Ben Ron on.
Thank you again to our founding
sponsor, open robotics. See you
next time.