Audrow Nash: Hi, everyone.
Welcome to the Sensing Think
Act Podcast. I'm the host Audrow
Nash. And in this episode I
interview Adrian Macneil, co
founder and CEO of Foxglove,
Foxglove makes Foxglove Studio,
which is an open source
visualization debugging tool for
robotics. In this interview,
Adrian and I talk about the
origin of Foxglove, Foxglove's
business model, web technologies
and robotics, the timeline for
autonomous cars, and Adrian
gives advice for those
interested in getting more
involved in robotics. I really
enjoyed talking to Adrian, he
has an interesting perspective
on technology and seems to be
involved in interesting
technologies, right as they're
coming up. For example, He was
an early employee at Coinbase,
and Cruise. As always, a big
thank you to our founding
sponsor, Open Robotics, and I
hope you enjoy.
Hi, Adrian, would you introduce
yourself? Hi, I'm
Adrian Macneil: Adrian Macneil,
founder and CEO of Foxglove.
Audrow Nash: Now, tell me a bit
about foxglove what it does and
what problem it's solving. And
then I'd love to get into the
backstory of that after.
Adrian Macneil: Yeah,
definitely. So foxglove is a
developer tools company for
robotics. We have our main
product right now is an open
source visualization platform
for robotics. And it's browser
based cross platform. We can
allow you to really dive into
your robotics data understanding
of your sense of editing and
planning, visualize things like
point clouds, images, overlays,
markers, bounding boxes, plots,
and drill into kind of raw
messages
Audrow Nash: and you guys you
interface tightly with the robot
operating system or ROS
ecosystem, correct?
Adrian Macneil: Right? Yeah,
correct. So we we work very well
with ROS. We don't we're not
strictly limited to Russell
though. That's definitely our
best supported platform right
now. We do allow you to connect
other types of data sources like
for example, we can connect just
to a velodyne LIDAR and and talk
directly to that sensor and
visualize data coming off the
sensor. But when you're in a
ROS environment, we can
obviously make a connection to
ROS and then we have a lot of
custom visualizations that help
you understand ROS messages
like point clouds and images and
other things like
Audrow Nash: how does it compare
to existing ROS tools like ARV
is our ROS visualizer for
visualization?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, so yeah,
so we have I would say the
biggest difference is that it's
cross platform and using a web
based stack that was something
you know, we can get into the
origin a little bit that that
was something that was kind of a
key underpinning of building
this technology is that we
wanted to work with a browser
based stack which means that
they can run cross platform we
actually have desktop apps that
you can install on your computer
that run on Mac Windows and
Linux equally well and then you
can also access it in the
browser. So that you know that
makes it like very easy to just
jump into an environment and
start debugging it also kind of
unlocks that something that I
think is as important to me as
breaking robotics development
out of being stuck with like
Linux desktops and you know
Linux is great but a lot of
robotics development now is very
the software the developing is
like very tied to the platform
that you're developing on and
you know if you're using ROS
Vision X you know ROS galactic
you need to be using Ubuntu 2004
and you know that's the only
choice you have you pretty much
stuck with that for your
development handle and get
developed well
Audrow Nash: it does work so
galactic and many of the other
ROS two distributions also work
on Windows not very well I think
tier three support for Mac this
kind of thing Yeah, but
Adrian Macneil: yeah, it's
getting there I did say yeah,
you're right.
Audrow Nash: But this was this
was definitely which was kind of
the origin of like foxglove was
a rough one. Or Weber's Yeah, we
Adrian Macneil: support both
ROS one roster Yeah. But yeah,
for sure our windows support is
out there. Although you know,
most of the people I've seen
doing ROS development on
windows are using the windows
subsystem for Linux so they're
actually still running you know,
the actual Linux version. Oh,
that's fine. And then yeah, and
then Mac actually you know, Mac
came out I think ROS two
initially came out and said
we're gonna suppose a lot of
work. Yeah. Like no one kind of
stepped up to volunteer. Yeah,
so the and the actual you know,
code that you're writing big
Linux only is fine, right? Oh,
we want to break out of as the
developer tools so there's no
reason that you can't be on a
Mac developing inside a Docker
container. But But your actual
tools to like visualizing
things, it's, you know, those
graphical tools are going to be
easier if you can just connect
to them from a browser or
connect or, you know, fire up a
native emulator.
Audrow Nash: what's the what's
the big win? Or what are some of
the big wins doing it browser
based as opposed to like qT? or
something, which is what ARV is
uses?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah. Yeah,
yeah. And I think I should jump
into some of the other things to
talk to the browser based thing.
And then also some of the other
things that kind of
differentiate us with with
Office and Matthew two things.
browser based, I think, you
know, there's a few points
there. One is that it's it's
inherently cross platform, you
know, the browser is a really
great environment where, you
know, as long as you fire up
your browser and go to a
website, you can pretty much
expect the same experience,
regardless of what platform
you're on. That makes it really
good as you're scaling a
robotics team. You know, if you
start out with just one or two
people, you're working on a
project, that's, that's, you
know, it's fine if you've got a
pretty custom environment set up
on your computer. But as you
scale up that team, you want
people to just be able to, you
know, on board start working on
the code base, you know, being
able to like visit a URL and
look at things directly is
really great. And then another
point there is that it makes it
really easy for you to access
remote data as well, right? So
we can, you know, get into
talking about data storage a
little bit as well. But a lot of
the times, you know, the state
of the art and robotics today, a
lot of people are just storing,
you know, huge 100 gig bag files
on a computer, and then I've
been trying to debug it. And
that's ROS bag. You want to
share this, my friend? Yeah.
Audrow Nash: And ROS, too. It's
an SQL lite database. Right. And
I forget what it is in Roscoe,
and
Adrian Macneil: yeah, it's just
a custom format, bag. Bag file
format. That's just basically
your ROS message. But having
Audrow Nash: a big monolithic
data storage, basically.
Massive.
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah,
yeah. And so those can get
really huge if you're dealing
with multiple cameras,
especially if you start getting
into LIDAR and point clouds and
radars and sensors, bossier.
We're also recording all of the
other messages that ROS is
sending back and forth. And so,
you know, a lot of people are
working with these files
locally. But sharing that among
team members is really
challenging. It's, you know, a
case of like, either just get
someone to wait here over and
have a look at your desk. Or you
know, you can't, you can't just
like share a link in slack and
have someone else click on that
and immediately start looking at
it. So that's, that's where we
kind of see the browser's really
unlocking these workflows where
you can just click on data.
Audrow Nash: And is that talking
about having data storage
happening in the browser?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah. So
not always, I mean, the data
storage happening on a server?
Yeah. For sure, yeah. Yeah. But
yeah, once you get to having a
data stored in a centralized
location, and the browser can
just easily be streaming that,
you know, it just makes the
whole internet experience
really, really compelling.
Audrow Nash: Let's see. So I
feel like this is a good time to
get into the origin story of
foxglove. So can you tell me
where it started?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, sure. So I
spent the last five years prior
to this cruise, building self
driving cars. And I led
basically all of the developer
tools and infrastructure there.
So when I joined, it was, you
know, a very small company,
maybe 40 4050 people or so over
the over that period, we grew
into the sort of 1000 plus
range, I think it was around
1700, when I left out, and you
know, over that time, or the
engineering team grew right
from, from 20 people to well
over 1000. And so, you know,
they they started, as you know,
I'm sure a lot of our products
company, so it was a ROS stack
originally, on ROS one, and you
have a bunch of people just, you
know, contributing code,
building features, testing
things out. But as you scale
that and 100 and 1000 plus
engineers, do you really need to
start getting a lot more
disciplined around the developer
productivity? What tools are you
making available to people? What
are the workflows that you
encourage people to do? You
know, the less you standardize
things, I guess the more pain
you're in for as you start
getting into 1000 plus engineers
contributing to a project.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. And so crews
had an internal effort to make
something for visualization,
rather than using the standard
ROS one arvis. Or our Qt graph.
Yeah. Anything?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, for sure.
It started out as as visit
Accutane. As I mentioned, they
started out on a ROS one
platform, positive ROS
definitely gotten kind of
switched out over time and
replaced with in house things.
But in the early days, everyone
was just using, you know, the
standard tools like ours. And
the project that we that we
kicked off with visualization
there. I think we started back
in about 2017. It came out of a
hackathon actually it was not
instead of a top down approach
of you know, this is something
we think we need to invest in,
it was just something that some
engineers really felt needed to
exist and really felt would
would kind of streamline the
workflow. So yeah, that was kind
of the origin of width is which,
you know, some people may be
familiar with, they presented
with us at ROS con in 2019, I
think it was eventually open
sourced in 2019. But back in
2017, it really just started as,
you know, some engineers on the
team feeling that that we could,
you know, we could do better on
a couple of aspects. One is, you
know, bringing these tools to
the web where it's a lot easier
for, for, you know, people to
contribute to, like easier to
find engineers.
Audrow Nash: Easier to
contribute to it or easier to,
for people, why is web easier
for people to contribute to?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, I mean, I
guess, you know, that could be a
bit of a loaded statement,
because obviously, if you're
familiar with c++ development
and development, then it's going
to be a lot harder for you
personally, to contribute to but
you know, on a scale of, of
larger commercial engineering
teams, it's, on average, a lot
easier to find front end and
JavaScript engineers who can
build web applications. There's
just, you know, a much larger
pool of people that you can draw
Audrow Nash: from, would you
guess the order? Is there like,
there's 10 times more people
that are familiar with
JavaScript than c++ or I mean,
just ballpark for these kinds of
jobs? Yeah, I think it's 10. Or,
like this order of magnitude,
Adrian Macneil: probably in the
Bay Area. That wouldn't be far
off. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. I
haven't seen any numbers
specifically on it. But yeah,
anecdotally going out to hire a
front end engineer versus a c++
engineer who has experience
experience. Yeah, Qt experience
and things like that. Like for
sure there's a lot of really
talented c++ engineers out
there, but not so much. On the
visualization side, there's this
argument that I've, you know,
done game development and things
like that. But yeah, just just
much easier for, especially once
your company, you start building
a lot of internal tools, usually
a lot of internal tools are web
based. And I don't want to push
on, on being easy to contribute
to is like, the main thing, but
it's that combined with the fact
that anyone at the company can
just hit a URL and access that
you don't need to worry about
like deploying this app across
your team. And also, you know,
there was something that was
important to us was being able
to like unify these various
tools into one interface. So
Audrow Nash: you mean are? Like,
Adrian Macneil: yeah, yeah,
exactly. So are you able to
bring
Audrow Nash: speak to what each
does just a little bit?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah. So
avars is primarily a 3d based
visualization tool. So you can
go in and you can, you can open
up some data, and you can look
at where your model is sitting
in the world. And you can see
sensor data. And you can see,
you know, three name markers, 3d
bounding boxes, and things like
that. You can see things like
your transforms like the shape
of your robot, and you know,
where your robot is relative to
something that it's trying to
act on.
Audrow Nash: And if I understand
correctly, it's not a 3d
simulator. It's more just 3d
visualization. There's no
physics engine associated with
it.
Adrian Macneil: Right? Right.
Right, exactly. So it's purely
taking necessarily information
from a robot, and then just
showing you, you know, how your
robot is thinking, and the world
is gonna have an insight into
your robot. And then you have,
you know, acuity is sort of a
collection of tools that you can
open a standard one on Windows,
or you can kind of open them in
a sort of attached panel
configuration. And it comes with
a handful of other tools, which
can give you things like reading
diagnostics, from a robot
reading direct messages from a
robot, reading plots from a
robot or reading plots, but
displaying plots based on data
from your robot. And then you
start seeing that there's other
tools in law recently that have
come out like plot juggler and
things, you know, a separate
again. And so yeah, that was
kind of one of our insights, I
Audrow Nash: guess, cruise to
combine them.
Adrian Macneil: And one of my
early in one of my early days
there I have a vivid memory of
attending we so we had Friday
demos, basically, every weekend,
people could jump up and kind of
just show something called what
they've built. And someone from
the QA team jumped up and demoed
the script that they've written
that would basically take a bag
file and then open it, start
ROS in the background, and then
launch about like 12 different
windows on your screen and
rearrange them into position so
that you'd be ready to start
debugging. And I was like, you
know, and they got a standing
ovation for that right because
it was so much. Such a massive
time saver compared to Compared
to like, manually going through
that process and you know,
taking a backfile and wanting
ROS and then opening these
various windows, you know, I
just remember that so vividly
because it's, it's, it's, you
know, like seeing the pain of
how difficult it is just to get
to the point where you're
actually getting your work done.
It's like, this is not, this is
just like admin before you
actually get
Audrow Nash: 20 minutes of work
before you can start work.
Adrian Macneil: Right. Right.
And, you know, and that's
actually sort of another
difference that another point of
differentiation we took is that,
you know, the tools like others
are, they're very coupled with
ROS. So you have to have ROS,
you run ROS, in the background,
you stone, your ROS stack, and
then you start others, and
others will talk to ROS, and
it'll show you kind of exactly
what's happening. And if you
want to play back a bag file,
playback recording that you
have, then you need to play that
back into ROS. And then kind of
you'll see it as like a
byproduct of
Audrow Nash: going over the ROS
network, basically.
Adrian Macneil: Right, right.
Everything's kind of going over
the ROS network. And, again,
when you start thinking about
different workflows across the
company, you have QA engineers,
and they have a look at right.
Audrow Nash: So they want to
talk up to good quality, and
we're doing things well.
Adrian Macneil: Okay, right,
right, exactly. And if they're
taking let's say, there's an
incident where, you know,
something that happened on the
road, right? We pulled out this
or not, we got too close to a
cyclist, or we, you know,
whatever we did, and you've been
assigned to triage, an engineer
has been assigned to that kind
of triage this and figure out,
maybe not like, what is the root
cause just yet, but where do we
think the likely root causes?
You want to be able to just
like, open that kind of incident
directly and start looking at
it? You
Audrow Nash: know, you're saying
that the incident? Yeah, yes.
rosbank file or okay.
Adrian Macneil: Right, right.
But you want to, like, what you
actually want to do is get into
visualizing that incident as
quickly as possible. And you
don't, you know, the fact that
there steps like downloading a
bag file,
Audrow Nash: which is huge.
codebase, which is huge,
probably. So it probably takes
Adrian Macneil: a while to like
100 gigabyte
Audrow Nash: uploads are often
slow. You get it from a thumb
drive.
Adrian Macneil: Okay, yeah, tell
you all about No. So it's just a
process, right, kind of take
that back file, and you bring it
down to your computer, and then
you open up, you know, check out
the code base, and you go back
to the version of the code base
that you had last week that was
actually running on and then you
launch ROS launch hours, and
like, now you're looking at the
data. And, you know, we just
wanted to simplify the whole
process. So it's like, you click
on the link, and then you're
looking at it immediately.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, that is way
easier, where you can just open
it. And so you, and then this
gets into the cross platform and
everything because they could be
on any computer. And they don't
need to spend their money for OS
installed. And they don't need
to have ROS bag installed.
Adrian Macneil: Just run it on a
Chromebook or something and
just, you know, immediately jump
into things.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Okay, so
then I see the motivation for
this quite clearly. So you were
at cruise, and you were working
on web servers. And you had this
experience where someone
automated some of the setup that
they might go through when
trying to do some debugging. And
that was like an aha moment for
you. And then is that how web is
started?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, and, you
know, to clarify, I guess I, I
was the director of engineering,
so I didn't like contribute
much, or anything to the webfest
card itself that the team was
under me, but all the talented
engineers did the work not, not
me. But you know, I very much
agreed with the vision of of
what they were trying to achieve
there. And I think, you know,
we, the team that was working on
that there was some really
talented engineers, they kind of
made a proof of concept. Like I
said, at a hackathon. They went
around, you know, a handful of
different teams, and kind of
went team by him and said, Hey,
you know, what problems you're
having with your tools? How can
we solve them with your
visualization, and just
incorporated all of the various
workflows that were happening
across the company into this one
tool. And so, you know, over
that period of a year or so, it
just became kind of an
indispensable that everyone was
using at the company. And that
really just opened my eyes up to
you know, how much of a
productivity boost a good
quality visualization tool could
be. And, you know, that's what
ultimately led us to consulting.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And so you
open sourced web is and then now
you are with foxglove. Can you
tell me a bit about that
transition
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah, for
sure. So we open sourced my
visit cruise in around 2019. The
goal there was to, you know,
give back to the community. And,
you know, also just to put some
of that code out there as as,
you know, engineers working on
projects that companies quite
often you want to just put, you
know, anything that's not sort
of like, tied critical IP to the
company. Yeah, yeah, critical
company secrets, it's always
nice to be able to publish
things. And we published a lot
of open source code occurs
around, you know, even just
unrelated things, like how we're
managing our Kubernetes
infrastructure and things like
that. But, you know, we put
those out there, and it was
available for the community to
use. And, you know, they
presented a Roscommon 2019, I
think, and, you know, picked up
a bit of steam. Certainly people
were out there using it. But I
guess, you know, here's where I
would draw differentiation
between non open source coders
create an equal, I guess there's
a difference between kind of
code that is public versus
actual communities that are
being built. And, you know, I
don't vote Cruz for this in any
way. I think Chris is absolutely
making the right decisions for
their own prioritization and
things. But, I mean, I was like
part of these decision making
but but Chris doesn't have time
to build features and weathers
that are not useful to crews,
for example, you know, they have
the project out there, but like,
no one is building ROS 2
support and the weapons are
known as
Audrow Nash: their stack is rock
one, or
Adrian Macneil: stack now. I
mean, the stacks kind of, you
know, hitting off in a different
direction entirely. So, you
know, it's the code was out
there, and it was available for
people to use, but there was
never a kind of a pretense that
crews wanted to sort of invest
heavily in building a community
and adding features that were
like, not useful to them at all.
Like I say, this is, you know,
absolutely the right decision.
If you're, if you're, the
purpose of your company, is get
a self driving car going in San
Francisco, you know, the purpose
of the company is not build
unrelated kind of open source
communities and invest heavily
in that sometimes that happens,
you know, if you're a company
the size of Facebook, and then
you build something like react
exactly like, shot, you have
hundreds of 1000s of employees,
and you can spare a small team
of 30 to work on XYZ thing, but
Audrow Nash: it's crazy. It's
really that small. Yeah, that
makes sense. But yeah, I didn't
know. It could Yeah, or
something. Was that just guess
yeah.
Adrian Macneil: But yeah, it's
Yeah, it's, it's when you're a
sufficiently large company, you
can kind of afford to make those
bets. But for the majority of
companies out there, you're, you
know, when they're open sourcing
code, it's usually sort of isn't
code that we wrote, use it if
you like it, but we're not
supporting it. still focused on
my internal needs. Yeah. Makes
sense. Yeah. So that's, you
know, that's what ultimately led
to foxglove. We had a lot of
chances, the windows team with
courage and leadership and
several other weapons team are
working Foxcroft now. But we
wanted to make a clean break, I
guess we, you know, another bit
of context, as to the weapons,
as it exists today is pretty
tightly coupled with a lot of
internal crew systems. So the
open source version of weapons
is only you know, only about
half of the code and weapons is
actually open source, right. And
the rest of it is special custom
source that exists inside our
crews. And those two are quite
tightly intertwined. It's not
sort of super easy. For us, as
founding foxglove, it's not
super easy for us to go and kind
of contribute back to that
project without having access to
all of the closed source things.
Yep. Makes sense. So we made the
decision, when we founded Fox
five at the start of this year
that we wanted to kind of carry
on weathers in spirit. And you
know, we use the we forked the
code base originally, which
means we took that code base,
and we're basically saying, you
know, where versus here, it's,
it's the open source version of
web, this is not really
undergoing a lot of significant
changes. Right now, most of the
team that still works on that
occurs is primarily focused on
career specific additions that
are not open source yet. But you
know, we said we're gonna, we're
gonna just, you know, we want to
continue this in the spirit, but
we're going to, it's going to
become a different product over
time. And we don't want to sort
of create kind of confusion
there. We just want to say, Hey,
we're building Foxtrot. We're
using some of the stuff that was
done in the past. we're
incorporating a whole bunch of
Elon ideas, but we're not kind
of being held back by what's of
company technical. Yeah,
exactly, like company interests,
or just like, you know,
technical limitations around how
how projects are kind of tied to
internal code.
Audrow Nash: Yep. And how did
you decide to form a company
around this as opposed to any of
these Other things that you
could have done like you could
have just been a side project or
like, decide to jump on and run?
Yeah,
Adrian Macneil: I guess? Yeah,
that's a really good question. I
think, I believe very strongly
in the future of robotics. I
think, you know, there's an
enormous industry out there for
our enormous opportunity out
there for robotics to just
completely change. What our
economy looks like, what society
looks like, I think, you know, I
think people are massively under
estimating how much robotics is
going to impact the next 10 or
20 years of kind of human life.
And I also really believe that
high quality, you know, I love
engineering, productivity,
development, productivity, I
believe that high quality tools
can help people focus on doing
what they do best. And I've
seen, you know, I've seen that
kurzen and other companies I've
seen, really talented engineers
are, like deep, deep domain
experts struggle and spend 80%
of their time fighting with
something that they don't
properly understand. Because
it's not, it's not their
expertise. And, you know,
likewise, I guess that's where I
always felt that I and others
can kind of contribute, because,
you know, I'm not, I'm not kind
of, you know, controls PhD or
machine learning PhD or anything
like I don't claim to be a
super. Right, but I can tell you
how, like build systems work and
data works and and systems
brought together and
visualization and how these kind
of things work. And I really
believe that kind of, you know,
good quality tooling means that
domain experts can all focus on
kind of their, their area of
expertise.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So you're
basically making it easier for
people to work on what they are
good at.
Adrian Macneil: Right, exactly.
And yeah, and then so that, I
guess, tying it back to your
question was, you know, how did
that leave the founding box live
was that we were foxtel. If we
wanted to, you know,
visualization, that's where
we're starting. But the ultimate
goal of our slogan is to make
robotics development easier,
right? We want to be able to
help roboticists focus on their
domain problems, focus on on
shipping products, and not worry
about, you know, how they're
thinking about their tools and
their data and their development
workflow and all of these
things. So the visualization
pace was our starting point,
because I believe that there's
just, you know, such big, low
hanging fruit there. It's
something that we selfie, so
impactful at cruise, but you
know, we have kind of a roadmap
of other areas that we also
really think we can help them.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. I'm
interested to talk about that.
But first, you also had a lot of
several people go from cruise to
working at Box club with you.
Would you tell me a bit about
that?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, so we, my
co founder, and I both. So my co
founder, Roman, he's our CTO, we
have worked together for a long
time, we actually worked
together before careers, we
worked together for years before
careers, we work together at
Coinbase. And that was where we
met. So I was an early
engineering hire, and the first
head of engineering and
Coinbase, back in back in the
early days. And yeah, we met
there. We worked together for a
long time, he was actually the
one that introduced me to
careers and convince me to come
there. And then so you know, we
really wanted to do something
together around robotics,
developer tools, we got chatting
to a few folks. Many, you know,
several of our team members have
come from careers. Mostly not
directly, I guess, you know,
like I said, it was sort of five
years since I or more now since
I started at Chris or Robin,
and, you know, several of the
other folks on our team had come
from, had been at cruise for,
you know, two or three years and
then had gone to other
companies, products like this.
And then, you know, we kind of
just reconnected with a bunch of
people on our network and to see
who would be interested.
Audrow Nash: Sorry, Siri popped
up. Why would you say, for the
last?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, just just
that we, you know, all of those
people had been that had been
that curse. And then had gone on
to work at other companies. And
we just reconnected with, with
some folks in our network to see
her. You know, I was interested
in doing something around this.
Yeah.
Audrow Nash: And now, you said
you strongly believe in the
future of robotics. Would you
just tell me a bit more about
that, like, what is making you
so optimistic about the future
of robotics?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, I mean,
it's, it's, it's inevitable,
right? You see. I mean, and
partly, maybe this comes from
having worked their careers and
seeing what is possible. I
think, you know, a lot of people
haven't really had that glimpse
into what is possible, but when
you do Sit in a car that's
driving itself around a busy
intersection with, you know,
potentially hundreds of people
walking around it and cyclists
and cars and, you know, you see
a car that can, I mean, I was,
you know, six, seven years ago
very skeptical about self
driving cars. But you know,
having having gone on scene and
setting those cars and seeing
the progress that's made and
seeing things that, you know,
you hear people while you're
talking to people on the street
that have not worked in the
industry, and they say, Well, I
don't think it's after because
of course it won't because
sometimes you just need to be
able to understand you know, one
of the other humans doing and
then you see the team was just
plugging away at problems like
you know, a four way stop sign
is a very common in America, we
have we, you know, cars have to
basically take turns and giving
way to each other. And
especially in San Francisco, you
have to be quite assertive in a
four way stop sign up to a stop
sign. And you know, technically
it's your right away if you got
there first and someone else got
there half a second later. But
if you don't start pulling out
into that intersection, you
know, the other car is gonna is
gonna go very quickly, right? So
you look at these problems and
you know, you start thinking
about people signaling and
things like that, but but he
seems like chip away at these
problems and get to a point
where they've tuned the car
where you know, as as the cars
turns coming up, it has like a
very human like behavior where
it pulls forward slightly to
kind of indicate its intention
that it's going to go and that
actually causes the other cars
not to pull out because they
they can kind of see your
intention that you're planning
on going and you know, these
these things, they sound like
very human behaviors, but you
can actually just really get
down into into kind of encoding
and machine learning models or,
or even you know, hard coded
logic in some cases where the
car is like exhibiting very
human like Vega so yeah, it's,
it's really interesting, you
kind of see, see that evolve,
and then you look around the
world, and you just see how many
things done, how many sort of,
you know, tasks, or jobs are
done by humans today that are
both like a, like, very
interesting, very repetitive,
you know, couldn't be done
better, more reliably cheaper by
machines? And the kicker is that
they're way easier than driving
around San Francisco. Yeah, so
like, you know, this is great
course, you know, the future is
here, it's just not on
definitely, it's not evenly
distributed, right? It's, it's
like it's just inevitable to me
that the launch of burgers is
going to if you took all the
technology that was currently
being developed and self driving
cars and apply that to, you
know, warehouses, logistics,
manufacturing, agriculture,
shipping like this, you know,
food prep for production,
there's, there's so many areas
where all of these environments
are much more constrained than
then, you know, driving around a
city. And if you took 1000
engineers and apply that to
that, there's no doubt that
those loads will be solved. You
know, very quickly, the thing
is, right now, there's not that,
I guess, you know, economic
investment is not there to put
1000 engineers on a problem
about self driving forklift or
something. We're certainly
getting there. But it's not at
that scale yet. But you get this
kind of flywheel effect where as
more people start trying to
solve those problems, better
tools come along, better
frameworks come along, better
libraries come along, there's
more off the shelf that people
can use, you know, the flywheel
start spinning, and then teams
of 10 engineers can all of a
sudden have the output of
October 1000, you know, a decade
earlier. So yeah, just, I mean,
that's what makes me so I guess,
so interested in optimistic
about the future of robotics is
just that, you know, it's, it's,
it's going to have a massive
impact. And I think that people
are, I think it's really kind of
reached the public consciousness
yet, you know, everyone's
talking about blockchains. And
AI. You know, I think like,
robotics is kind of the defining
application of AI maybe, and
people haven't really sort of
grasp that yet, I think.
Audrow Nash: Do you? So you
mentioned several, like, I don't
know, domains, agriculture,
manufacturing, etc. Are there
any specific areas within those
are any specific problems that
you think are particularly
interesting and ripe to be
solved by robotics?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah, I've
seen some very interesting stuff
happening. You know, and
warehouses, like, Fetch robotics
are doing really interesting
stuff. They're obviously being
on your podcast earlier. And
saying, you know, I think all of
these things where you have self
driving forklifts, for example,
a lot of this stuff, I mean,
I've and you know, coming into
the agriculture industry, for
example, I grew up in New
Zealand, and kind of very in a
rural region that does a lot of
fruit growing and picking, and I
had, you know, jobs in high
school where I was packing Kiwis
and boxes, and I've got all
sorts of things that don't
pruning. And I've done a number
of these tasks that kind of
happened on the agriculture
industry. And you know, I mean,
some of the tasks that you do, I
like, sit here and watch these
fruit roll by and grab the ones
that have blemishes and put them
on, you know, grate them into
like a BSE and grab the ones
that have blemishes and put them
onto this other conveyor belt.
And it's just not a sensible
task for a human to be doing in
this day and age. Right. And I
mean, maybe it was, you know, 15
years ago or something when I
was doing it, but like, you
know, computers with computer
vision and like manipulation on
some things can just do a much
better job of this now, they're
gonna be far more reliable, they
can do it at a higher pace. And
like, guess what, that wasn't a
fun job for anyone, I certainly
didn't enjoy it. Like, there's
much like more productive things
that as humans can be kind of
putting our time and energy
towards them, watching fruit
roll by and picking out the ones
that like, look strange.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So, and one
other thing that kind of caught
my ear, was you saying, putting
1000 engineers towards the
problem? Can you just talk a bit
about that, that it's an
interesting idea to me. And it's
very different than, say, like a
startup thing, where you have
the 10 engineers that you were
mentioning, and building a
product? Or just a couple?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah, I
guess. I would look at it from a
perspective of what you know, in
1999, right. So you wanted to
start a startup in 1999. And
you're gonna build some web,
you're gonna build Amazon or
something, I guess they were a
little bit earlier. Okay, you're
gonna go to Amazon 97 or
something, okay. You're going
out and you're like, you know,
you need some people to write
code. But guess what, you also
need some people to go and buy
some servers and racks and
servers, you need, you know,
just like multiplies. You need
people doing all that,
especially as website starts
getting traction, you're
building everything from
scratch, right? You know, when
you say there's 1000 engineers
working on a problem, it's not
that they're all kind of in
they're super productive writing
the key kind of code day to day,
it's that you have to build kind
of all of the infrastructure of
the pyramid underneath you as
well, because there's nothing
Audrow Nash: because it doesn't
exist off the shelf. Whereas if
you're building PayPal or
something, or Amazon, you can
use react or some other
framework that does a lot of the
lifting for you.
Adrian Macneil: Right, if you're
doing this 20 years ago, you're
building Google or Facebook or
Amazon or Ebay or any of these
things you're building
everything from scratch, you're
not you know, you're not just
grabbing like a web framework
like react or Ruby on Rails even
know something you're kind of
you're writing all of the all of
the you know, went from scratch,
you're writing all of the
deployment from scratch, you're
buying hardware, you're racking
hardware, you're worrying about
like network connections, you're
making deals with ISP so that
you get enough bandwidth to
service like, it's crazy, man,
it sounds crazy, right? But
like, that's how one of these
companies got started. And
that's where we are in the
robotics industry today, right?
We're at this place where if you
want to build a, you know, build
a self driving car company, I
mean, 90% of the engineering
effort is not going to the core
kind of, you know, the core kind
of like algorithms and models
that are being developed on the
cards. That's all the stuff
around that everything that's
supporting and available off the
shelf today. Yeah. So you know,
if you if you talk that, you
know, one approaches kind of
brute force, which is like you
take those 1000 engineers and
say, Hey, you know, we're
pivoting to like self driving
forklifts now. Sure, like, maybe
it's an easier problem, and all
that talent could could get it
done. But I think, you know,
the, the more kind of scalable
approach over time is that
better and better quality
tooling comes out. And you know,
in the in the web industry, that
was AWS coming out, that was
Heroku coming out, that was
data, dog, and Splunk, and New
Relic and Sumo logic, and, you
know, all of these kind of
startups were founded in the
latter half of 2010, latter half
of the 2000s. where, you know,
by 2015, you want to go and set
a website up you just kind of
like slap a few things together,
and you know, two people or one
person and you have a company.
And, you know, I just I think
robotics needs to get there.
Obviously, it's, it's never
going to be as easy as building
a website and you have like
hardware and the real world to
deal with. But it could come a
long way from where it is today
in terms of like, having this
reusable components that you can
grab off the shelf glue together
and have a company
Audrow Nash: where so in all of
this building infrastructure, in
your mind, where does open
source?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, that's a
really good question. Um, open
source is has you know, it's
both like, I guess very
important. It's contributed a
lot and, you know, we deeply
believe in open source. I think
the open source industry has
matured a lot over the last kind
of five or 10 years, especially
even the last five years, and
what business models work and
what business models don't. You
know, you've had some of these
things recently, like
Elasticsearch, MongoDB, a lot of
these companies have kind of
gone through a little bit of a
crisis where they said, Hey, you
know, we give everything away
for free. And then someone like
Amazon comes along and takes
that thing that you're giving
away for free and starts
reselling it, and they've kind
of like suck the air out of the
fact that you actually storing
it to pay employees. So I think,
you know, we've, we're an
advantage that, you know,
sitting here in 2021, is a lot,
a lot of evidence of what models
work in open source and more
models don't, I think, the fact
remains that open source is a
really good way to get products
out there and make them easy and
free for people to play with,
it's a really good way to build
a community around projects.
It's also frankly, a lot easier
to work with, you know, as a
consumer of open source. Even if
you're paying for support or
services around something, if
you if you get some you know,
you're working with a tool, as a
developer, you're working with a
tool, and then it's not quite
working for you, or you find a
bug or you need a feature, it's
so much easier if you can just
like look at the code and fix
the bug and build the feature.
Yeah, rather than stuck in this
like, yeah, you know, it's not
gonna it's like crazy, where
you've got to, like, go to their
support, and, you know, like,
turn into a ticket and goes to a
pm somewhere and they farm it
out to a team and you wait, like
two months when you could have
just changed a bit of code
yourself? Yeah. So you know,
yeah, open source is really
important. I think we strive to,
and we can talk a little bit
about, you know, well, how we're
thinking and where we're drawing
our mind. But I think it's
important to, you know, try and
open source as much as you can
and make that available to the
community and build a community
around it. But also, you know,
you need to be realistic about
the fact that you need to be
able to pay your employees and
you need to kind of fund the
development and the other things
that come around. And so it's
important to have kind of clear
delineation there, I guess.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. And so now,
natural segue. What's your
business model at cruise? How
are you kind of balancing open
source and paying your employees
and yeah,
Adrian Macneil: yeah, Fox?
Audrow Nash: Or Fox? Yes.
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, exactly. So we, yeah, I
mean, in keeping with that, I
think the the model, one open
source model? And actually, you
know, I think I was just
listening to your podcast with
Nick. And I think, I mean, I
probably share some similar
views on this, I think I don't
like the open source model,
where you kind of have an open
source version, and then you
have kind of a better version
that you have to pay for, which
is just, you know, more features
around it. I think that that
frustrates people want to, you
know, it kind of feels like
you're just kind of keeping the
crown jewels for yourself, I
think, you know, much better
models that we're seeing around
open source. There's, there's
kind of two related models that
work quite well. One is just
that you have an open source
product that people can run
themselves, and then you just
sell basically hosting of that,
of that thing. So you know,
that's where you see a lot of
companies kind of doing this
today. That's, you know, what,
like Elasticsearch and MongoDB.
And some of these people do, you
also see it with, like, next js,
and wsl, they kind of offer
like, a paid hosting. So that's
a front end framework, web
development framework and a web
hosting company, and they kind
of they sponsor the thing. So
that's one option, as you know,
kind of you build a thing, which
is completely free, and then you
have the hosting of it. The
other option, and you know,
where we're going as you build a
thing that's completely free,
you get all the features button,
this kind of add on services
that you know, you need if and I
guess more specifically, in our
case, we give you Foxconn
studio, it's free, it does
everything you want, you can run
it on your computer, you can run
it on the web browser, there's
no limitations. If you want our
services for collaboration, and
for kind of like team
communication, which we're
building around that, then those
are things that you need to log
in for, and those are
automatically going to be paid
features. So we actually, I
guess, you know, sort of pre
announcing this a little bit,
we'll be coming out with more
than a couple of weeks. But we
have some features in foxglove,
where today, you can kind of
have these layouts that you have
personally that live on your
computer, you can set up
different layouts that you might
use for different tasks when
you're debugging a particular
type of event. And we are coming
out very soon with a couple of
things. One is the ability to
kind of share these layouts
among team members. So being
able to actually like login,
starting to get into this world
of where we're sharing views
among among your team and making
it easier for people to
collaborate over robots data,
robotics data. And then the
other thing that we're building
which will be kind of, you know,
hosted service that you can work
with is actually that data
storage elements or, you know,
how can we be the central
repository if we get data so
that you know, as I said earlier
on so that you can just click on
a link can immediately start
looking at it without having to
go through that whole rigmarole
of downloading 100 gig bag for
your computer and sharing it to
your friend on a hard drive.
And, you know, running any of
these things locally, you can
just have a kind of central
repository for your data, click
on a link and immediately like
jump into it.
Audrow Nash: Now I'm struck by
so you were saying you and Dave
are sharing Dave Coleman from
move it or picnic are kind of
sharing a mind for these things.
I'm struck by you guys both
calling your service with
something studio. So your Fox
Studios movie studio, their new
release? Why did you pick the
name studio? What's the What's
there?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah. And
I mean, since creating foxglove
Studio, I think maybe it's just,
I've started seeing it
everywhere. I think, you know,
we're not the only two
companies. So far five other
companies with like, you know,
XYZ company name and then XYZ
studio and
Audrow Nash: this is the paid
version of whatever.
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, I mean, I
think it's it's, it's, it's
intended to be just, you know, a
product that you can jump into,
you know, you can you can see
what's happening, I guess we
wanted to separate that product
slightly from the company name,
because, you know, as I kind of
alluded to it, we're planning to
bring on some of these other
services and things. So we
needed something to
differentiate differentiate.
Yeah, exactly. This is our, our
kind of visualization tool that
you can see and open and
probably picnic, maybe a movie
felt the same way. Yeah. But
yeah, I guess, you know, and it
starts becoming a little bit of
a mouthful, if you have another
studio releases, like an AC word
that makes sense. But if you
come up with maybe, you know,
you already have a company name,
and then you forget something
else, rather long winded on the
end of the year, your product
name, you know, you get these
things like hashey, Corp
terraform. And you're like,
Audrow Nash: what is that? Yeah,
yeah. And speaking of What's in
a name, and although it's a bit
of a digression, I'd like to get
back to more of foxglove Studio,
but how did you come up with a
name? foxglove?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah, this
is a question I get a few times.
So I have, you know, my
philosophy on naming is that I
think that if I say the name to
you, you should be able to write
it down. And if I see it written
down, or if you see it written
down, you should know how to say
it. And I get kind of
frustrated, but some of these
company names where, you know,
they're either just like,
insane, not even company just
project names. And then you have
like, Kubernetes, for example,
everyone goes around saying
Kubernetes like, it's an easy
thing to say. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: It's like some
Starcraft thing or something.
All right.
Adrian Macneil: That's a Greek
god reference design. Yes. I
Audrow Nash: mean, it just
sounds like some futuristic
device. Yeah,
Adrian Macneil: yeah. Yeah,
that's sorry. And I have this
predisposition towards names
that are easy to say, and easy
to easy to spell and easy to
read. But of course, you know,
most of us are taken. So it's
been a long time with this kind
of short list of names that I
was going through. And I was
last year, just traveling around
New Zealand. And I was doing a
bit of a road trip with my wife
and child and this kind of
foxglove flowers are all over
the side of the road. Did the
song flower I have in the
background? So it was cool.
Yeah, just just a word. And I
thought that's a cool word. And
you know, it wasn't already
taken by a startup. So they have
no robotics reference. I'm
sorry.
Audrow Nash: I didn't know. I
just had no idea where it came
from. So it's a flower in the
hills of New Zealand somewhere.
Yeah, that sounds lovely. Yeah.
Okay. So if I understand
correctly, so foxglove Studio,
the. So you have all of
foxglove, where you can
visualize the data you see, and
it's for live playing of ROS 2
data and also playing from a bag
file
Adrian Macneil: playback.
Exactly. So you can connect to a
live system, or you can just
drag it back file and
immediately stop looking at that
bag file. You don't need ROS
installed or anything. If you
have a bag fine, you can just
open up.
Audrow Nash: And then the
studio. What are the kind of
killer features that you're
adding with this? So it's layout
support. So you can save a
layout, eventually, you can
share a layout. And it's data
storage coming soon.
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, these are
the these are the paid features
that we're building around it,
basically. So anything that
involves kind of collaborating
on your robotics data, where you
have multiple team members,
again, maybe you have a team of
five, or maybe you have a team
of 20, maybe you have a team of
100. But the larger your team
grows, the more important it is
that that you can collaborate
over that data. This is I think
people naturally understand this
because, you know, normally if
you have data stored in data dog
or Splunk, or Google Analytics,
the thing is, it's kind of sad.
In nature that you can just look
around a website and then copy a
link, if you if you want to send
something to your friend, you
just copy a link and paste in
slack and they can start looking
at it. And so, you know, this
kind of collaboration around
robotics data, I think is
something that that just doesn't
exist in the industry today, if
the kind of, you know, it's very
much a single focus on just, you
know, like, hair is my personal
workflow, I have some data on my
computer, or I have a bunch of
tools locally on my computer.
And if my friend wants to look
at it, then he's gonna, you
know, they're kind of out of
luck,
Audrow Nash: or you have to
write or read me up, and then
they can try to reproduce what
you do, right? Because the Yeah,
exactly 10 steps are more
Adrian Macneil: or less file,
you know, these topics kind of
that, you know, it's just, it's
a very, sort of add surface
process.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Now, I want
to segue into talking about the
web and connecting it to
robotics, in some capacity.
Like, I'm very excited about
this, but would you speak on it?
Just playing Yeah. What do you
think the potential is there?
Why the web will be good. You
mentioned it a bit before, and
that there's a lot of people
that are knowledgeable of how to
do web programming. Yeah. But
anything else? Yeah,
Adrian Macneil: yeah, I think I
mean, this is something that a
lot of companies independently
coming to this conclusion, the
web is kind of the main platform
that anything that was built on
these days, and you know, that
can mean developer tools like
elsewhere, you're kind of diving
into specific instances. And
since of your robot, it can mean
kind of Fleet operations
tooling, we have companies like
forment.io, and freedom
robotics, and all that where you
know, you have a web based
interface where you can see you
know, your whole fleet of robots
and see what's going on with any
of them. It can also mean things
like tele operations and remote
assistance, where you need your
robot to kind of call out and
get human support and a human
eyes on things. It can even mean
you know, and web based labeling
tools, for example, where where
people are annotating data to
use for machine learning
training, those tools are again,
primarily web based. And it's
just because you have this
platform where you can build,
you know, visual interfaces, and
they're inherently plugged into
remote data stores, it's easy to
save, collaborate, it's kind of
you know, a similar transition
from having Microsoft Word
installed on your computer, to
Google Docs, right? And it's
just, you know, now you're
moving to something that is
inherently collaborative. And
so, you know, when we talk about
like the web and robots, I
think, we're not really
advocating that your robot is is
you know, written in JavaScript
or something like that, although
it's perfectly possible if you
want to go that route. But um,
but you know, the robot is the
robot, usually it's, it's, you
know, it's running ROS or
something similar. It's written
in Python or c++ or something
similar, but it needs to kind of
communicate with that outside
world. And so that means often
use web based technologies for
connecting from the robot to
services, for example, like
WebSockets are a really good way
if a robot communicating with a
server or browser communicating
with a server. You also have
technologies like web RTC, which
is a way for men, that's
probably how our video is
getting to each other right now,
it's kind of a way of streaming
videos and things like that
across the internet. So you have
a lot of these kind of web based
technologies, and they play
really well with robots, they're
really good for, you know,
communicating with fleets,
they're really good with
communicating, you know, even to
local devices. And it's really
good for building interfaces
where, you know, you don't have
to worry about which browser or
platform on things you're
running, you can just kind of,
you know, you can just open it
up, and it works.
Audrow Nash: And do you think,
can you talk a little bit more
about the benefit of making it
so that a lot of robotics
related things are made in a way
that like getting us a bigger
pool of programmers to work on
robotics problems through using
web technologies?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah, I
think, I mean, that is something
that we that always I found
interesting and Kurtis actually
was as we were hiring people,
candidates vastly underestimated
the need for robotics
experienced and work or self
driving experience to work on a
self driving car company. And
kind of, you know, am I talking
about the thing with the 1000
engineers and how, you know, 80%
of them are working on you know,
the the permit that kind of
supports the actual key
algorithm development. We needed
to hire a lot of people at
careers that were just experts
in infrastructure and data
processing and data management
and and, you know, web
development, front end
development JavaScript
engineers, and we didn't need
any of those people to have, you
know, a PhD in machine learning
or robotics or anything like
that. But there's kind of this
perception out there that like,
I'm not a robotics developer, I
can go and work at a self
driving car company. But, you
know, like I said, I think
there's this, there's, you know,
there's a large number of
candidates out, there are just,
you know, people AI engineers
out there that work for
companies doing all sorts of
stuff in the Silicon Valley
today. And around the world, and
a lot of that stuff is, you
know, much less meaningful,
there's a lot of people working
in AD tech and things like that,
that, you know, could be working
on our bonds, but maybe things
that you think that they can't,
so I would implore those people
to, you know, have a look at
some other really awesome stuff
that is happening out there. And
realize that one of the most
exciting things to me about
robotics is just how diverse of
a space it is, how many
different skill sets you need,
and you know, you can come into
it, and maybe you're experienced
in front end development, or
maybe you're experienced in
DevOps. And you'll sit down with
people who, you know, like I
said, machine learning PhDs or
something, but you sit down with
people who are physicists, and
people who are working on, you
know, hardware, and you sit down
with electrical engineers, and
all of these people need to kind
of come together and, you know,
it's, it's, it's really
important to bring all of those
skill sets together, and
robotics and I think, yeah, I
don't know, I think there's
like, a gigantic, huge
opportunity there as more of the
maybe for a look for for a long
time, robotics is kind of being
a little bit off in a corner.
You know, a lot of the industry
has been building, you know, ad
tech, and, you know, consumer
startups and even enterprise
startups and a lot of stuff for
processing enterprise data and a
lot of things for for, you know,
social media and social
networking and things. But
robotics is kind of spent a long
time and a slightly academic
corner of the world, I guess,
you know, people have been
working on robots, for, you
know, decades to this point. And
certainly the last 15 years,
there's been a lot of really
interesting stuff happening. But
you know, it hasn't had as much
kind of attention, I guess, as
like the as the wider startup
industry. And I think we're kind
of reaching a tipping point now
and more and more engineers
coming over who have experienced
and maybe more traditional
software development, maybe they
don't understand the robotics
spaces, but they can, you know,
they can sit down on paper with
the people who really
understand, you know, control
theory or, or machine learning
or planning or things like this,
and you put that together, you
get some really high quality
software.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Very
interesting perspective. Do you
think that web technologies, so
we're speaking about often web
technologies kind of on the
front end, so mostly for
visualization or connecting to
other things? Yeah. Do you think
it will ever? Or are there
benefits to doing web
technology? So like, from the
back end? So using things like
node j. s, or Dino or something
like that?
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, I think I
mean, there's kind of a tourism
that like, everything that can
be written in JavaScript will be
written in JavaScript at some
point. There's people out there
writing robots in JavaScript and
and, you know, even the
JavaScript ecosystem, that's not
what it was 10 or even five
years ago, right? It's, it's
continually moving. And a lot of
these things like TypeScript
have come out, which provide a
lot more structure around.
Audrow Nash: I really like
TypeScript type projects I've
done it seems like Yeah,
exactly.
Adrian Macneil: It's Yeah, it's
really nice. These these things
are coming out. So you know, for
sure, I think people will use
languages like JavaScript and j.
s, and, and things on robots.
But, you know, equally you're
seeing people branch out into
like, using rust for robots, for
example. And, you know, that
would arguably be a benefit for
a lot of these kinds of embedded
applications where you're, you
know, you're pretty resource
constrained, you have to deal
with, you know, even I mean,
even when you have like, a very
large computer available to you,
you're always worrying about you
know, energy consumption,
battery life and, you know,
competing things that are trying
to run moment. So say, I think,
you know, rust and go Broly or
both, yeah, potentially,
potentially quite interesting.
Things that might end up, you
know, picking up a bit of steam
on robots, but I wouldn't, I
wouldn't say that they that, you
know, JavaScript or web Tech has
an inherent advantage. for
writing kind of the robot code
itself, I would say most of the
benefit, there are things around
how you're communicating with
back end services, how your
voting UI would be able to
interact with their robots.
Things like ROS bridge, for
example, is a that's a WebSocket
protocol, where you can connect
from a ROS system to a web
browser or from a raw system to
a server to a web browser. We
you know, our team has been
contributing a bunch to ROS
bridge project lately and
getting that up and running with
ROS two, which has been You
know, really great for the
community. And you know, these
are these are really where the
web stack plugs in, and the
protocols that we're using to
communicate with robots, and
that kind of interfaces where we
can interact with robots.
Audrow Nash: Now I'd like to
talk about you for a little bit.
So you were at Coinbase, as one
of the early employees, then you
were an early employee at
cruise. And now you're starting
foxglove. The earliest? The
earliest? Yeah. So to me, it's
kind of I see it as you're
jumping into things when they're
very interesting. So you jumped
into cryptocurrency, you were
you seem like you were very
early into that, being at
Coinbase, when they were pretty
young, then self driving cars.
And it basically took off, there
was so much interest around it.
And crews went from 20 to, I
don't know, 2000 employees, or
whatever you said, Can you just
tell me a bit about your
thinking around these things?
Your experience? I don't know.
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, yeah, for
sure. I, I do really enjoy, I
guess, futuristic technologies.
And, you know, thinking about
the future. Some people maybe,
you know, take this a little too
far and think about things that
are, you know, really far out.
And if it's going to take 50
years, then, you know, maybe
it's not the best thing to
invest your time in today. Or
maybe it's something to do, but
I really like thinking about
those kind of, you know, 10 or
20 year horizon, and you know,
what direction is the world
going. And you know, that I
actually in my early in my
career, I did a lot of things
with payments and e commerce,
actually wrote an entire like e
commerce framework and a bunch
of payment gateway integrations.
And that led me to sort of
interest in Bitcoin, I guess,
pretty early on, I saw, you
know, I just started looking at
Bitcoin, I initially thought it
was a scam. But then I started
getting interested in this idea
of kind of, you know, cross
border payments and
permissionless money. And I
thought, there's a real
opportunity for this to become
something that is a lot bigger
than it is today. And it's
something that people use in
their day to day lives. I would
say with the Bitcoin space, in
particular, though, there's a
lot of, there's a lot of people
and you know, even in the early
days, there were a lot of people
who were in it for the
technology, I guess, who were
kind of, you know, excited about
in the future could bring in,
you know, even the kind of
technical developments that
happened there. But because it
was kind of also a financial
instrument, there were a lot of
people who were just in it for
the money. And that led to quite
a sort of hostile community. And
I actually think maybe kryptos,
as turned a bit of a corner, now
you get a lot of these kind of
things coming out, like NF T's
where people are clearly just
having fun with it, and not, you
know, not stressing so much
about whether they're going to
be millionaires or anything.
Maybe they still are, but but
the crypto community, I mean,
there was a lot of, especially
in the early days, there's a lot
of infighting in the community
around block sizes. And it got,
you know, it got a little
frustrating to me that yeah, it
was it was
Audrow Nash: a lot because it
could be interesting, the
technology and the implications
of it, but people are like
infighting trying to get a
little more influence or a
little better for themselves or
something
Adrian Macneil: kind of
attractive, you know, if you
have any, you know, different
people for different reasons.
Some people like to technology,
some people just want to get
rich, some people were in that
because they think like, oh,
taxation is theft, and then the
government should be abolished
or something. And so you have
this, like, kind of strange
melting pot of like, and then
Coinbase was right in the middle
of that trying to sell Bitcoin
to people who thought that, you
know, all tax was theft, but yet
had to like appease banking
regulators, or, or, you know,
her, like very much thought that
they needed, you know, legally
very much did have to understand
absolutely everything that's
happening about every
transaction on the platform. So,
you know, that was an
experience. But I, I kind of,
you know, as I said, my co
founder, sort of introduced me
to currency when he was at
Coinbase. And then he went to
cruise. And I, you know, I, I
guess I went through the
experience that I was just
describing earlier of being an
engineer, not from my robotics
background, but kind of coming
into this company. I really, my
eyes were opened up to both like
opportunities that were
possible, but also that it was
very obvious that I could
actually contribute a lot,
despite not having that robotics
experience. Because, you know, I
found that a lot of the robotics
engineers didn't have the
experience I had, it's just you
know, like I say, you have all
of these people from different
backgrounds come together and
you need that in robotics, you
need that, you know, the
hardware engineers, mechanical,
electrical engineers, you need
the you know, Now, folks, you
need the planning controls,
folks. You need the back end
infrastructure, you need the
kind of UI and visualization.
And, you know, it was it was
kind of obvious that this was
about something that, you know,
was was also going to be a, you
know, big interesting trend. But
But, you know, I just felt that
there was a lot more focus on
kind of substance, I guess,
compared to the crypto space
where Yeah, yeah, a little bit,
a little bit too much hype. So
that that kind of, you know, led
to my interest there. And I
think Cruz really opened my eyes
to, you know, what was possible
in the space, like I said, I
think it's, you know, it's
really clear that the robotics
industry has been making a ton
of progress over the years, it's
clear that a lot of these
problems that people have
struggled with, you know, actual
technical problems and robotics
that people are struggling with.
Within Reach now, they're, you
know, they're solvable, given
enough time and resources. And
given better tools, the time and
resource kind of needs are going
to come down. So yeah, that,
like I said, they're kind of
just continues the trajectory of
our stuff where I think we can
not just help us, you know, not
just have one self driving car
company get off the road. But
you know, you look around, you
see, all of the self driving car
companies are building the same
tools, and you say, Hey, hey,
there's an opportunity here to
kind of like reduce duplication,
reduce kind of people,
reinventing wheels, but also, we
can look at all these other
robotics companies that don't
have anywhere near that level of
resources. And they all need it,
too. So you know, this
opportunity is here for us to
make everyone's life easier.
Audrow Nash: Mm hmm. That's
great. I'd be remiss if I didn't
ask, what do you think the
timeline is for autonomous cars?
Adrian Macneil: That is a that's
the money question.
Audrow Nash: I mean, even like,
started, I like next couple
years, next 10s of years. Yeah,
Adrian Macneil: yeah. I mean,
they're here. Right? So it's a
question of walking on Congress,
what cannot autonomous cars
achieve? Yeah, autonomous level
for autonomous cars here, when I
was, as you know, have cars
running in Arizona today, fully
autonomous, that, you know, the
general public can can, can, I
mean, maybe it's a limited
number of people, maybe it's a
limited kind of sun. But maybe I
should back up a bit for the For
those unfamiliar with those
unfamiliar with the like levels
of autonomy. Basically, you go
from kind of a scale where level
one, I'm not even sure what
level one is level two is, is
the car can kind of like, do
basic things. So this is kind of
like a Tesla autopilot where it
can, you know, the car can steer
in a lane and the car can can
brake and accelerate for you.
But ultimately, you're at level
two, you're still completely
responsible for anything that
God does. So if the car crashes,
you can't kind of blame it on
the car. Level Three is
basically that in some
situations, the car can be fully
responsible, but it may need to
wake you up. So like, you can go
to sleep, maybe it'll put you on
the freeway, and maybe it'll do
the bulk of the driving. But
you're going to get like a 32nd
warning or something saying
like, hey, by the way, you know,
it's time to wake up because I
don't know what I'm doing, I
need help. But you know, there's
some kind of like, there's some
kind of kind of warning element,
whereas level two, it's like, I
don't know, the cop might just
do something crazy. And then the
definition of level four is that
within a defined kind of
operating domain, the car can be
fully responsible. And so
that's, you know, we see that
companies doing Robo taxis. You
know, the cars are fully
responsible, and that you jump
in the taxi, it takes you from A
to B and you jump out and you're
done. There's a geo fence around
it, you can't, you know, jump on
it and expect you to drive it to
the next day, or in some cases
of counting when you drive on
the freeway, but within the
domain that was designed for the
car was completely responsible.
Audrow Nash: Not this not not
some level of highway or some
products, like a restriction on
where I
Adrian Macneil: can go domain
could be restricted to certain
roads, it could be restricted to
a certain time of day like
night.
Audrow Nash: And weather
conditions or weather
conditions.
Adrian Macneil: Yeah, if there's
heavy rain, they're going to
pull them off the road. But in
the domain, and the operating
domain that it was designed for
the car is fully responsible.
And so that that is happening
today. Right. And that, you
know, that is, I think it's
gonna be something it'll be over
the next 10 years, you know,
it's just going to increase more
and more domains where you can
see it. More and more, you know,
companies are going to be the
flying cars out there. More
domains are opening up,
certainly, I think we'll see
this happening, you know, in San
Francisco very soon, probably on
the order of like, next year or
the year after really, after
that, but I think that and
again, and certain domains,
right, maybe if it starts
raining, which doesn't really
happen very often in San
Francisco, but maybe maybe if
that does, then the cars aren't
going to be running. I don't
know. But I think you know,
they're like us. They're already
doing this in Arizona, and I
think it's only a matter of time
for you to start seeing it in
denser cities. And then it just
evolved from there at the kind
of domain expands. And
eventually the cars have better
sensors and more processing
power and can go faster and more
safely. And so that that I think
is just gonna be, you know,
very, like, smoother than
iterative. But the, you know,
level five, I think is, is kind
of, in my opinion, not even
really worth defining level five
is kind of defined as like, the
car can do everything a human
can do. And, in my mind, I'm not
clear on why you would really
want a car to do that, I guess
like, there's this, there's
expanding level four to like,
Hey, I can drive on the road and
on the wall, right? But like
everything is human, I mean, a
human can drive like a four hour
drive through a burning forest,
avoiding flames and like, like
humans, can humans are very
adaptive in the right situation,
right. And I like I don't, I
don't know that I ever see a
world where a car is going to be
able to do literally everything
a human can do. But it doesn't
matter, right, you're going to
get to a point where a car can
drive you, you know, from one
side of the country to the other
without stopping and without you
without even having a steering
wheel, then, you know, it
doesn't really matter that it
kind of drives through a burning
forest or something.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Gotcha. Well,
that's awesome. It's so
interesting that it's so close.
I look forward to, I hope in
like a year or two, I'm able to
take a ride in San Francisco.
Adrian Macneil: I mean, these
things start slowly, right? It's
like, you know, Uber existed in
2010. But no one was using it
until until later. You know,
they're coming in, they're
onboard people, and they have to
ramp up their operations, and
they have to improve, you know,
this, this. I mean, you know,
every year the cost get better,
are they able to handle more
situations, they're more
assertive, they're more human
like, and they're driving. It's,
it's, it's only a matter of time
until the areas that they can
operate effectively, kind of
increases. But you know, you
might have to get on a waiting
list or something.
Audrow Nash: Yep. Let's see. And
so starting to wrap up, what
what advice do you have for
someone that's just starting
their career or think like
really early, like a 20 year old
you? What would that advice end
for now? Yeah, what advice would
you have?
Adrian Macneil: I think, um, you
know, robotics is a big space
and figure out which pieces that
you're interested in and you
know, a couple of things one
maybe don't get too bogged down
and thinking that you need to
like specifically work on ml or
something or, you know, you can
be an electrical engineer
working on robotics or you know,
things like that. Yeah, there
you go. So don't don't roll that
out. Right, there's a lot of
this is robotics industry is
very diverse in terms of skill
sets. And it takes all of those
different skill sets to come
together. It's not just, you
know, a bunch of ml engineers
or, or, you know, robotics,
engineers writing c++. And so I
think, you know, don't
certainly, like take classes or
try and get internships at
different companies and work on
different things. But, you know,
don't get hung up on this
feeling that you need, you know,
one specific kind of skill set
and to get into robotics, I
think, you know, everyone can
get into robotics if you're, if
you're sufficiently interested.
And then the other thing is just
I think generally, people early
in their career vastly
underestimate how valuable it
can be to build probably
projects where you control end
to end and you know, this is not
like I'm not saying like, you
know, go and do work in the
spare time or something but if
you want to understand how
robots work on their own, don't
get me you can get a kit for
under $100 off Amazon to build a
self driving car with just you
know, some little some little
motors and a little camera and a
Raspberry Pi camera on things
but build the intervention thing
right i mean there's you know,
there's stuff out there even
like Ducky town which is great
but even that is coming to you
with a lot of pieces already
kind of already thought out and
if you foster this kind of like
boat a little hobby project
where you you know, even just
get like a Raspberry Pi and so
you know, Python on figuring out
how to control the little servos
from your, from your command
line. You know, you don't even
have to have any like sensing or
thinking or acting happening
just figure out how to like get
me in a command line happening
wired up 30 of Python and make
the wheel spin you know, that'll
teach you a lot about how the
internet piece works. And when
you go into a you know, a
company Sure, it's not gonna be
like directly applicable but you
understand how the kind of you
know how the pieces fit them. I
think you know, that, that
engineers that I've worked with
that, that can kind of go from
like the very big to the very
small and back again, the best
in the industry, the ones that
are not just thinking about, you
know, what is this little
component that I'm working on,
but how does it fit into the
bigger picture and obviously,
edit the account. We know one
human can understand the big
picture. So doing that on a much
smaller scale is just really
important to understand, you
know, like what all of those
components actually look like.
Audrow Nash: So now, how can
people reach out? or How can
they contribute to the foxglove?
any links or anything you'd like
to share?
Adrian Macneil: Definitely,
yeah, we love contributions, we
love people reaching out, you
know, we have, so you can go to
Fox club dot Dev, that's our
website, you can download Fox
doc studio, you can open it in
the browser, try it out and give
us feedback. We have links on
there to our community channels,
GitHub, Slack, things like that.
You know, if you find that
useful, great, tell us, we'd
love feedback, feel free to make
contributions for requests,
report issues, those are all
helpful. Also, you know, if this
is something that's interesting
to you, if there's something you
want to work on, just feel free
to contact me or us directly.
And if it's something that that
you're working on at a company
and feel like you struggling
with these kind of tools around
how you're collaborating over
robotics data, you know, also
reach out we'd love to chat
about it, even if that's kind of
getting you access to our beta
or, or, you know, just talking
about more about where we're
going. We were an early stage
company. We love getting
feedback from people and just
engaging with the community. So
Audrow Nash: all right, awesome.
Thank you. Awesome, thanks.
That's all we have for you
today. I was surprised by
Adrian's answer to what he
thinks for the timeline of
autonomous cars. What do you
think? Let us know in the
comments on sensing act.com
thank you again to our founding
sponsor Open Robotics. Goodbye,
everyone.