Audrow Nash: Hi, everyone,
welcome to the sense think act
podcast. I'm your host Audrow
Nash. Today I speak with Melonee
Wise, former CEO of Fetch
Robotics and now VP of Robotics
Automation at Zebra
Technologies. We talked about
her experience with Fetch
robotics, the differences and
similarities between mobile
route robots and a factory
setting, and autonomous cars,
and her outlook on the future of
robotics. I really enjoyed this
interview. First, it was really
nice getting to know Melonee.
And also I found it very
interesting to hear about the
different stages that FX fetch
robotics went through before
being acquired. Specifically,
they started as a hardware
company building the robots,
which only lasted five months or
so. And then they were a
software company. And now,
Melanie is describing them as a
data company is very
interesting. With that, I hope
you enjoy. Hi, Melanie, would
you introduce yourself?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, I'm Melonee
Wise. I'm the former CEO of
Fetch Robotics now the VP of
Automation, Robotics Automation
at Zebra,
Audrow Nash: So that's really
exciting. Would you tell me a
bit how Fetch and Zebra are
related?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, so I started
fetch robotics about seven years
ago. And this week, we actually
closed on an acquisition of
zebra acquiring fetch robotics.
And so Zebra Technologies
acquired fetch to create a new
robotics automation division.
and fetch makes autonomous
mobile robots for the logistics
and manufacturing industries.
Audrow Nash: So going into fetch
a bit more congrats on being
acquired. That's so exciting.
And you said it was ahead of
your timeline, your 10 year,
whatever being your highlight,
it was actually acquired in
seven years. Would you tell me a
bit more about fetch. So it's
for warehouse related robots,
but just I guess, background
information on the company.
Melonee Wise: Yeah. And to be
clear, when I said I had a 10
year vision, What I meant is
when I, when they first started
talking about it, fetch robotics
to investors, I kind of I kind
of made sure that they were in
it for the long haul, because
robotics is such a hard problem.
So I was like, Hey, you realize
that this is a 10 year problem,
it's not like you're gonna get
an acquisition, like you would
in a software company and, you
know, pump a couple dollars into
flip into an IPO or an
acquisition a couple years. And
so, so that's there wasn't
really like, I was like, Oh, I'm
gonna sell the company in 10
years, it was more like, you
know, when you go and try and
convince people that robotics is
something interesting to invest
in, you need to help temper
their expectations. Because, you
know, if you look at the car
industry, we've been saying,
since, I don't know, 20, or 27,
like 2007, that we're gonna have
autonomous cars next year. And
we've been saying that every
year for the last, you know, 14
years.
Audrow Nash: That's crazy.
Melonee Wise: So I so seven
years ago, I started Fetch and I
started the company with three
other co founders, Derek King,
Eric Dyer, and Michael Ferguson
and we all worked at Willow
Garage together. We were part of
the robot development team had
at Willow Garage. It's a team
that that basically for about a
two year period built a lot of
different robotic prototypes to
look at different industries
that that were of interest to
Willow Garage because but two
years before it ended, the
founder that started Willow kind
of said, well, what's next?
Congratulations, you did open
source, although that's kind of
a funny statement to make. But
he kind of said Congratulations,
you did some open source. Now
what you know and, and Steve
cousins at the time said, Hey,
we need to go look at you know,
the home and then industrial
applications. And it's really
funny when you look at you know,
the people that worked at Willow
Garage and, and the companies
that were then formed by the
former employees of Willow
Garage, they all kind of reflect
the different areas that we
investigated in the last two
years. And we investigated
everything from like grocery
retail to manufacturing to
hotels, for example, Steve went
and started savvy oak and did
hotels and, and the guys in AI
that started fetch robotics. We
we looked at at the
manufacturing and logistic
verticals and we saw it as a an
interesting problem to solve.
And, and when you look at that
the reason that was interesting
to us is we thought it was
attractive, tractable problem,
like most warehouses and most
manufacturing facilities are
what you might call semi
structured. But there's also a
large, like, dynamic happening
in the industry where finding
new employees is very hard. And
even before the pandemic, there
was a large labor shortage.
Audrow Nash: You mean for
factories?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, yeah.
Audrow Nash: Okay.
Melonee Wise: Yeah. For
factories and warehouses. Before
the pandemic, there was about a
600,000 person shortage. So
there were 600,000 open jobs,
Audrow Nash: How many people in
the industry overall?
Melonee Wise: I don't know that
statistic off the top my head,
but I do know, before the
pandemic there were, there were
about 6 million jobs available.
And the job openings in the
manufacturing and logistics
industry represented about 10%
of all open jobs in the United
States. Yeah, crazy. Yeah. And
for a long time, the United
States was running at a deficit
for labor, right? So we had, for
a long time, we only had about
five or 6 million people
unemployed, and we only had
about five, we had about five or
6 million jobs available. And so
it was a close thing. There were
actually we were running what
you might call a negative
employment rate, where there
just weren't enough jobs, there
weren't enough people for all
the jobs.
Audrow Nash: So that's
interesting. I mean, you hear
about robots taking jobs and
things like this. In this case,
it's the complete opposite. It's
there are not people for that.
But we need more people to fill
out the roles so that the
companies can be more efficient.
That's very interesting.
Melonee Wise: And I think that's
one of the key reasons why over
the last couple of decades,
there's been this strong push
for automation. And why you're
seeing in a lot of
industrialized nations, you're
seeing a lot of push to get more
and more automation so that they
can stay competitive so that
they can grow their GDP, etc,
etc, etc. And so that led us to
be interested in creating fetch
and how know the
Audrow Nash: so that that is the
case now, just before COVID.
Fetch is seven years old, or so.
Was that the case then, too? And
how has that changed over time?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, so that that
trend was very much true before.
before when we started fetch,
there was just a huge labor gap
in the industry. And it what's
even worse is it's coupled with
a turnover rate of about 40%. So
super
Audrow Nash: high, basically.
What kinds of jobs are these?
Like? What are the what is a
person and these jobs do further
day at work?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, so they,
they can do anything from like
packing out a box to walking
around in 110 degree warehouse
picking boxes off the shelf?
Yeah,
Audrow Nash: turnover. So yeah,
Melonee Wise: they can be
assembling small parts or
machinery they can be. I mean,
our robots are doing the
delivery task of someone's job
and that and that's the other
thing that conflate some of the
problems is if you look at it,
when they're looking at
automation to offset labor, it's
not typically like this robot is
going to play replace this
person 100% there's just there
really isn't the possibility to
do that in most cases today. And
so we're why exactly um because
if you look at it, there's
there's a lot of tasks that make
up your job. So if you look at
say, me think a pickers job, if
we look at what a picker does,
Audrow Nash: are those a person
that picks things out of bins
and then puts them into boxes,
like an Amazon person?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, that's
that's the overall they fulfill
orders from customers. And so
there's, there's a lot of parts
of their job. So there's the
part of the job where they first
prepare all the boxes, and then
they put them on a cart. And
then they push that cart to a
location in a warehouse where
there's a shelf and they pull
something out of a box, and they
put it into a box on that cart.
And they're like scanning each
of those locations to make sure
that that thing that they're
they're picking is correct, etc.
And they do that through an
entire warehouse and then they
come back and they typically
offload the boxes from that cart
on to an area where either
separate person or that same
person packs it out. So they
take it from those boxes,
confirm that all the the items
in it are correct, and then get
it ready for shipping. And that
means putting like paperwork in
it and basically shoving it down
a line. So someone can put a
label on it and tape it. But if
you look at it, the picking task
is very hard. It's not like
there's a lot of robots today,
they can just wander up to a
shelf and pull an item out of a
box, especially when they're,
let's say they're their t
shirts. And they're, I don't
know, baby onesies. And they're
packed in a box, you know, that
is probably only meant to hold
50. But there's 500 of them in
there. And so it's a pretty
complicated task from a robotic
standpoint, whether it's
manipulation or vision. And so
we today can't do all of the
task. And so there's some things
that we replaced completely,
like we don't have them walk all
that distance, they'll meet the
robot or something like that,
or, or we change the roles like
the now if you have a robot that
where the person used to
configure the cart and put all
the boxes on the cart, maybe one
person now is just responsible
for doing that for every robot,
as opposed to that person
individually beer sponsor
responsible for their cart. And
so the the jobs change what the
roles are change, and and
really, it's about taking out
the part of their job or the set
of tasks that they do that can
be done by a robot. And I, I
think that there's good
analogues in kind of the
technical world, you know, if
you if you look at, if you look
at maybe writers, or
journalists, they previously had
researchers, and they had
secretaries, and they had all
these, all these other tools or
resources available to them. And
now, many journalists, their
entire job has been reduced down
to doing all those things
themselves. But now the tool
they have instead of a person.
is Google, or, or some search
tool. Yeah. Yeah. And, and so I
think there there's plenty of
analogues for kind of this
transition from people doing
tasks or part of our jobs for us
to us now using automated tools.
Audrow Nash: Yep. So if I
understand correctly, basically,
the shipping process has a whole
bunch of different components
that must get done on the way.
And what you do is you say, oh,
a robot might be very good at
this one spot. And so by adding
robots into the system, you free
up people from doing that one
task. But it's kind of it's not
like saying a robot replaces a
person. Because the there are
other things that the people can
focus more on, when the robot
frees up that one, that one area
with this kind of thing. So
that's why it's like apples to
oranges to say one robot in is
not one human out, kind of
Melonee Wise: it? It typically
isn't. I mean, and a
Audrow Nash: gigantic shortage,
so you can just shift the people
elsewhere? Probably.
Melonee Wise: Yeah, that's the
other thing is, is when you have
such a labor shortage, you
you're not displacing anyone,
you're just trying to fill in
the gaps.
Audrow Nash: Mm hmm. Yeah. And
make the few people that are
there as efficient as possible.
So that they can you can get as
much work done as possible,
socially? How did you guys find
the So you mentioned kind of the
detailed process of finding or
of what occurs in sending out
pick and place this kind of
thing? or picking products out?
How did you find the exact part
of that where you thought a
robot would be a good fit?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, I think that
you know, if you look at it,
some of this stuff that that we
did, it will Oh, it became clear
that that when you look at
manufacturing and logistics,
whether it's picking or it's
it's assembling something,
there's always a process in
which material has to come from
some obnoxious Lee faraway part
of the facility to another part.
And it became very clear that
there was a high transportation
cost. And there's been plenty of
studies done for like labor
analysis, looking at different
different jobs, like the
fulfillment job that I just
described, or a manufacturing
job. And typically walking time
or transport represents upwards
of 50% of the person's total
time. And so that's a that's a
very compelling statistics when
statistic when you're looking at
Should I make a mobile transport
robot
Audrow Nash: It seems like to me
that seems like almost a simple
way of identifying low hanging
fruit that can be solved with
robotics things. I'm thinking of
like nurses spend a large period
of their time commuting from
patient to patient, and then
company, hello t robotics, where
did an internship previously,
they were saying how a huge they
would have physical therapy or
caretakers come to people's
homes in Norway, and they spent
like 60% of their time commuting
from home to home. And these
seems like it seemed like really
good robotics applications to me
if you can just put a robot in
there and have it do the
commuting wabbit do away with
their commuting in some way.
Okay, so you looked at this, and
you saw this number? 660? He
said, 50% of their time walking?
Yeah. Which is crazy. So you
started there? And
Melonee Wise: then we started
with building mobile robots? Uh
huh. And then and then it came
down to now you have a mobile
robot, you have a base now what
do you have to put on it to make
it productive for the
application. And if you look at
fetch today, we offer three
major platforms, and have
different payload capacity. So
100 kilograms, 500 kilograms and
1500 kilograms. And then we put
tops on it to basically attack
the, the different problems in
the warehouse. So we have, for
our small and big robots, we
have cart Connect, which allows
us to move around carts, we have
roller top accessory, which
allows us to interface with
conveyor, we have standard
shelving, it's kind of boring,
but you know, like the shelf
with the touchscreen on it.
Stuff like that. I mean, it
really comes down to the
accessories for the hardware. I
mean, if you look at that, and
like, the vision and and what we
were trying to build from, from
day one, you know, we started as
a hardware company, and as all
robotics companies go, you
quickly become software
companies. I mean, we spent like
a hot five seconds as a hardware
company. And I mean, you work in
open robotics, and like the
whole business, their software.
Yeah. And so we spent a large
part of our middle years as a
software company in over the
last couple of years, we've been
transitioning more towards being
a data company as well.
Audrow Nash: So Wow, that's the
next level. Yeah. And so
building
Melonee Wise: out our data
platforms, building out our data
capabilities, things like that.
But that's still an ongoing
process, because you know, you
have to build a pretty large
data like to do anything.
Audrow Nash: So I imagine a lot
of like interest in cloud
robotics at the moment with this
is what you mean with the data?
Yeah,
Melonee Wise: also. So if you
look at it, if you if you look
at it, the middle years, when we
were becoming a software
company, that's when we became
we built our cloud robotics
platform. So all of our robots
are actually controlled from the
cloud, they have their
autonomous units. But if you
want to tell them to like, go
from point
Audrow Nash: A to decision
making, the lower level control
is done on the robot problem
Melonee Wise: was safety,
navigation stuff is done on the
robot. But the task level
commands like yeah, go here, do
this come from the cloud. And we
did that, because it makes
getting set up on site a lot
easier. If you, if you look at
like many of these facilities,
they're kind of out in the
boonies, they don't have good IT
support, stuff like that. And if
you come along with a very
complex thing, like a robot, and
you're like it Oh, by the way,
where do we install the server?
It kind of adds a lot. So we
went off to the cloud. But one
of the advantages of that is, we
also save the robot data. And
we're building capabilities on
top of that data. So forklift
tection, we can tell when
forklifts are speeding, we can
tell when, when they get too
close to people, things like
that. And so those are some of
the capabilities that we're
starting to build on top of our
data platform. But the important
thing is, is you need a lot of
training data, you need a lot of
real world data to do anything.
And I think it's it's one of the
reasons why when people talk
about autonomous cars, I don't
think they understand the scale
and the scope of what we're
talking about when they when
they talk about like, Oh, yeah,
it'll just machine learn it.
It's like Yeah. Yeah. Or they
they'll say like, the car has
the AI if I if I hear AI one
more time, right now
Audrow Nash: I know. It's true
for so I want to go back and
talk about the hardware company
but just tying in this for the
data company and talking about
kind of this of the challenge
for for autonomous cars. So you
mentioned warehouses, semi
structured environments is
probably your data is a lot
nicer than what you get. Would
you just talk a bit about the
difference between the data
you're getting and the type of
data needed for like an
autonomous car? And how much how
difficult that will be?
Melonee Wise: Probably. So I
think I think the thing is, is
is, I wouldn't say that the
problem we're solving is any
less difficult than that of
autonomous cars. I would say
they have unique idiosyncrasies,
Audrow Nash: what is the problem
you're solving.
Melonee Wise: So we're basically
building a ton of indoor cars
for the warehouse. The
differences is we don't have
weather, they have weather, but
they typically their sensor
package costs about $200,000.
Our sensor package costs about
18 $100. So there's order of
magnitude difference in the cost
and capability of the sensors
that we use.
Audrow Nash: So that becomes a
massive difference your sensors,
is it like a LIDAR and a few
cameras? Or
Melonee Wise: what is the LIDAR
in two cameras?
Audrow Nash: Okay, is that 1800?
And it's like, okay, that's one
LIDAR and through?
Melonee Wise: Well, that's, the
bigger robot has to LIDAR and
eight cameras. But yeah, I mean,
it's still not a $70,000
velodyne, you know, and so so
there's, there's that there's
one, the the kind of sensing
tools that we have, are very
different. And so although
although they have somewhat of a
harder problem to solve from
weather and some other aspects,
they have better budgets, and
sensing tools and fidelity, to
deal with some of those
environments that we we don't.
The other thing that's very
unique about our environment,
that's not true for cars is our
environments are far more
dynamic in some ways. While
while roads can be very dynamic,
and, and things like that, it's,
yeah, they have lots of rules of
the road. And pedestrians don't
just end up in major highways on
a regular basis. Whereas if you
look at warehouses, there's like
main highways, but people walk
into them all the time. The
other the other, the other thing
that you have to understand is
that our vehicles typically go
around 1.5 to two meters per
second. So we're talking like
three to four miles an hour. But
some of the vehicles we have to
operate around like forklifts
can go up to eight or nine miles
an hour, or even faster. And so
it's very, it's a very difficult
problem when you are in a
scenario in which vehicles
around you are going much faster
than you. And then there is the
forklift problem.
Audrow Nash: So sounds ominous.
So
Melonee Wise: cars don't have to
deal with this notion of of a
piece of equipment being around
them, that has tines that are
very thin, very
Audrow Nash: hard to detect the
like probes at the top of
Melonee Wise: the fork of the
tines before, and they can be at
any height at any time. And
Audrow Nash: so they're super
hard to sense probably to Yeah,
they're
Melonee Wise: super hard to
sense. They can be at any
height. And there's a lot of
things like we don't, cars don't
have to deal with a lot of
overhanging things. Roads are
built such that nothing is going
to be hanging in the middle of
the road. It's not like that in
manufacturing. So
Audrow Nash: what are you just
taking a plane or whatever. So
that makes it super difficult to
do a lot with computer vision?
Probably. Yeah. And that's
challenging, because you have to
recognize all these different
circumstances.
Melonee Wise: Yeah. And so I'm
not saying that that the
autonomous car problem isn't
hard. I'm saying it's very hard.
But I think sometimes people
tend to look at the problem
we're looking at, it's like,
well, it's got to be easier than
autonomous cars. And it's like,
well, it's it's not it. It's
different. And, and there's
things that constrain our
problem solving, and things like
that. And then the other thing
that is is very true, is our
industry is heavily regulated
from a safety perspective. And
autonomous cars are not yet.
They're not heavily regulated
yet. I mean, there's some
regulation, but there's no,
there's no you have to do this
test to prove that your
autonomous car is safe, etc,
etc. Sorry, I actually need to
stop and take this call really
quick. Okay.
Audrow Nash: So we were talking
about the differences between
the data and that basically the
problem of autonomous cars
versus for manufacturing,
logistics. Can you tell me a bit
more about the data differences
From these perspectives,
Melonee Wise: yeah, I will say
that from a, you know, data
perspective, you know,
autonomous cars are using a lot
more data, that's what makes us
a little bit more open to, to
being able to port and move all
of our data to the cloud. And
you do like algorithms and some
of these things in the cloud,
which a car may not have some of
the luxury of doing. I mean,
that's, I think one of the big
things that's going to happen in
the next decade or two is we
realize what it's going to take
to make the practical deployment
of autonomous cars real is the
sheer amount of data, you need
to just store, the map of the
local area drive there that you
drive on a daily basis is, is
massive, and what data networks
are going to support just that
capability, you know, everyone's
going to have to have, you know,
fiber to their house,
practically, to be able to like
overnight, download the local
area updates and things like
that. And then, if you want to
go on a long trip, you know,
say, from San Jose to Tahoe, I
can only imagine what the
strategies are going to be for,
like a four hour drive. So for
four and a half hour drive, the
the data strategy is gonna have
to be to do that the nice thing
for warehousing and in our
robots is it's a million square
feet, that's about as big as the
problem gets. And so we
definitely, we we have, we're
running into the multiple source
problem. And I think right now,
in the autonomous car space,
they're still struggling with
the single source problem of how
do you get just data out of one
car, and we're dealing with,
okay, the data that we have to
move isn't ginormous, but we
have 3050 100 500 robots that
we're, we're transmitting data
from. And that's a lot of data.
And so it's a pipe problem.
Audrow Nash: Yep. So with
autonomous cars, they're just
now thinking how to locally do
it. So how can I make this one
car do drive from one place to
another autonomously, and you're
going, we have these robots
driving around this entire
environment. They're all doing
some sort of mapping of this
environment. Like what maybe
there's an obstacle that has
occurred. And so then they all
coordinate based on this, they
go, Oh, that one path is
blocked, I'm gonna have to go
around, and then it reroutes
Melonee Wise: that, yes, as part
of our coordination, we also use
peer to peer Bluetooth. But I
was just speaking more from the
sheer amount of like, loading
the data, and then post
processing. If you if you will
get today I think most companies
Google way Mo, all those guys
use, quote, unquote, sneakernet,
which is putting a hard drive in
a mailbox and sending it in the
mail.
Audrow Nash: Oh, yes. That's
crazy. The heart? What do you
mean exactly? Where are they
doing that? So like, well,
Melonee Wise: so you say,
company has 30 autonomous cars
that their field testing?
Audrow Nash: Oh, rather than
actually putting it on the cloud
and sending it and uploading it,
they actually just physically
mailed the device because of
bandwidth constraints.
Melonee Wise: They take out the
hard drives and mail them.
That's crazy. sneakernet
Audrow Nash: Yeah, we're walking
it.
Melonee Wise: Yeah, I heard I
heard some companies are
uploading more than 40 or 50
terabytes a week? Wow. Yeah. So
a lot of data.
Audrow Nash: So you, so um, what
it sounds like, to me, you have
a good bit of faith in these
machine learning approaches in
the long game. So like 1020
years from now, for? Is that
what you think? Or because I
mean, data is not terribly
important if you're going to do
classical approaches for things,
but you're finding in the
warehouse setting that it is
important to have a lot of data.
Just Can you talk a little bit
about this?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, I think that
there are are some types of
semantic behaviors that we care
about, that we need models for.
So we need to know what the
thing is. And the problem is, is
that there's a lot of variation
in the world. And so if you
tried to build a classically
trained model for every object
in your, you know, I guess
traversable space, it would be
very hard.
Audrow Nash: And by classically
trained, would you talk about
about what that means?
Melonee Wise: You have 1000
images and data examples of say
a Volkswagen bug from 1976. And
you put that all into an
algorithm and it spits out a
model and And it's really good
that one detector is really good
at processing Volkswagen bugs.
And so if you were to look at
like the most, I guess you might
call it asinine way of
approaching the problem is you
could say, I'm going to build a
specific model for every car on
the road every year because they
change year to year. And I'm
then going to spin up parallel
detectors for all of these
things. And, and maybe want to
know, the car model, maybe you
don't, but maybe there is some
material reason why you want to
know this. Right now, I think
they reduce it down to car,
truck or other. But But say you
want to do this this thing, then
the problem is, is you're
probably going to have some set
of detectors that all say that
they found the thing, right, so
if you have 1000 detectors, and
15 of them, say I found the
thing, then you need to put it
through another set of detectors
and voting system to decide
which one of the things that
says they found the thing is
right,
Audrow Nash: or some approach to
figure out exactly what is the
one you listen to? Or what's
most likely. Okay.
Melonee Wise: And so the the
challenge with that is it takes
massive amounts of data. And
that's why people are very old,
Audrow Nash: like 1000 detectors
or something like this, because
it's that one problem. But
there's a lot more and you have
to make distinctions between
that or is it the first model,
but just a bunch of times?
Because you could probably do
that too, and then just have a
confidence and wait to
confidence?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, those those
models aren't as good because so
Audrow Nash: you want it all in
one model, basically, yeah. So
it learns the discrimination
between I think
Melonee Wise: the problem is, is
if you look at it like a good a
good way to think about, like,
our way that we've been doing
learning for a long time, is,
for a very long time, we built
models, and systems where we
said, this is the thing you care
about, this is the thing you
care about, we kept showing it,
the thing they cared about from
all angles. But if you look at
the way people learn, it's a
little bit different. We we
learn, this is the thing that
you care about. But we also see
on a regular basis 1000s of
examples of this is not the
thing you care about. Hmm,
interesting. Yeah. And so but
there's a problem of trying to
prove the negative when the
space of things that you're
trying to prove the negative on
is, is infinite, right. And, and
so this is one of the problems
with, like machine learning in
general. And, and even if you
want to show, this is the thing
that you care about, say we
wanted to show a phone, right,
this is the thing you care
about, and specifically this
phone. So it's blue, it has some
yellow buttons. You know, a
person probably only has the
tolerance to take 50 pictures
100 pictures of this phone, ad
nauseum. Yeah. And one of the
reasons that convolution neural
nets are so interesting is is it
It allows us to take the 100
images and make it into like
10,000 images. Because that's
what it is, the purpose of it is
it basically allows us to take
the pieces of all these things,
split them up, put them back
together and use them to train
to train systems. And that's why
so it's a way of artificially
creating more data. And it's
found that that artificial data
that we create results in high,
high confidence confidently
trained models, typically, now,
okay, there's a lot of tuning
and a lot of mumbo jumbo. Yeah,
it's kind of a flasher, but
definitely the same time. But a
lot of those systems, again, are
only trained on positive
examples. I'm positive. And and
this is this is in general, a
bigger problem, theoretically,
with all of robotics is because
the negative examples that can
be very bad, they can have very
bad outcomes, like how do you
teach a robot not to hit someone
when hitting them could kill a
person, right? So, so not it?
Whether or not training with
only positive reinforcement is
good. Sometimes you can't
produce negative reinforcement
data, although I have seen work
coming out more and more on how
you build simulation models to
create negative reinforcement
data, for example. But
Audrow Nash: probably that got
us all the way there, because
you can overfit the simulator
pretty heavily.
Melonee Wise: Yeah, yeah. And so
that's the problem. As far as
all sorts of problems
overfitting weird edge cases,
you know, things like
Audrow Nash: and so how this
relates. So, if I understand
quite correctly, how this
relates in the autonomous car
problem or in the way Your house
problem, you are using some sort
as you get all of this data, and
you train different models on
it. And you use that effectively
for perception to help the robot
understand the world and what's
going on around it.
Melonee Wise: So I didn't know
say that a person is a person.
And so then the robot can
exhibit different behaviors
appropriate for that person. So,
for example, the one thing
that's the most mature in our
navigation stack is robot, the
robot detection. So we know when
something is another robot. And
that allows us to implement
certain behaviors within the
robot that make them more
effective. They they will, one
give priority to other robots
based on what those robots are
doing. They will, you know,
Audrow Nash: really cool. So
it's going, Oh, it's a robot.
But it's also going, Oh, I can
understand from the context of
what I can sense what this robot
is doing. And that's a higher
priority than me, kind of thing.
That's interesting.
Melonee Wise: And until then,
that extends into things like a
forklift. One of the things we
were talking about earlier, it's
forklifts are very difficult.
Well, one of the more difficult
scenarios with a forklift is the
tines can be all the way up in
the air, they can be 15 feet up
in the air well above the robot,
and the robot can't see it. Of
course, it can't, it's very high
up near. Now, if you know what's
a forklift, you can know not to
drive into that area. Even if
you can't see what's there. And
so that's one of the examples in
which, if you can know what
things are, if you submit to
glean know that this is a person
Audrow Nash: you can inform your
policies of don't drive right in
the spot where the tongs made
come down, right, this kind of
thing.
Melonee Wise: Yeah. And that,
that is that is what the
majority of applications for
machine learning autonomous cars
are also for is semantic
understanding. This is a ramp,
this is a person, this is a
crosswalk, this is a stop sign.
Audrow Nash: Now there's one
thing that I've seen, which is
interesting to me, is ontologies
and ontologies. It's like a map
that shows how all of the
different parts that you might
see in an environment relate to
each other. So if I was an
autonomous car, it could be
like, this is a road, this is a
sidewalk, the sidewalk might
have a person or a dog on it, or
something like this. So then
it'd be like road road has a
sidewalk, sidewalk has a person,
this kind of thing. It's a
relationship between all these,
do you? And this is kind of a
manual way to specify all the
different components. Yeah. Do
you guys use ontologies? Or? So
is it interesting?
Melonee Wise: If you look at
that, and topologies in our
environment, our district and
this is one of the problems I
was saying is like, there's a
shelf, there's a ioway next to
it, but people and everything
else can be in a box can be in a
trash can be in it. person can
be in it. So it's a very flat
ontology. This is a shelf. This
is a floor. Yeah, so i think i
think i agree that ontologies
can be very, very helpful for
creating kind of semantic maps
and relationships. But they they
don't always apply well in our
environments.
Audrow Nash: Unfortunately, it's
very complex. Yeah, yeah.
Gotcha. Okay, going back a
little bit. No, it's cool. This
is all very interesting. Going
back to being a hardware
company. Yeah. Can you tell me a
bit about when you guys started
when you were a hardware
company?
Melonee Wise: Oh, yeah. Yeah. I
mean, we were hard. We were a
hardware company for about five
months.
Audrow Nash: In the seven years
that have been so fun, yes.
Crazy. Because
Melonee Wise: that's, that's
when we didn't have any robots.
So we had to make the robot.
Yeah, we had to make the robots.
The good thing is, is we had a
really stellar team of co
founders who, who all knew a lot
about hardware. And it was
really funny. I think one of the
more kind of interesting
experiences for me is is and I
think for a lot of the the guys
they started competing with is,
you know, we while we were will
abroad, we probably build five
or six different types of robots
together. And, you know, we
learned a lot of lessons
sometimes they didn't power on
sometimes they have problems.
Audrow Nash: All the things.
Melonee Wise: Yeah, yeah, all
the things. But when we, when we
started fetch, we had so much
experience like when we built
the hardware, while we design
the hardware, we sent it to his
job. It came back from the shop
we put together turned on it
worked fine. And what was really
funny is there were some
employees who had been in other
robotics companies who had been
at other hardware companies. And
like, we're like, what do you
Like, this timeline is insane.
All of this assumes that the
hardware is going to turn on and
work and not catch on fire. And
we're like, Well, first, it will
never catch on fire. We're not
that bad. But second, second,
we'll be fine. And it was, it
was an interesting thing,
because I think one of the
things that I had developed is a
somewhat like, what you might
call robotics amnesia, where it
kind of started forgetting that,
that hardware could ever really
be kind of shitty. And so and so
like,
Audrow Nash: give us a nice
position to be in when you
really are like, you're like,
Oh, I'm surprised that this
didn't work. Yes, everything has
just been working.
Melonee Wise: Yeah. And so it
was, it was definitely an
interesting juxtaposition. As,
as the four co founders were
kind of like, Oh, you know, we
got this, this isn't going to be
a problem. And then some of the
new employees that we hired
early on, were kinda like, this
rodeo before. And never, it's
never this move. So it was, it
was cool. We were a hardware
company for a very short amount
of time early on me then
eventually cycled back and we
built the bigger robots, we
became a hardware company
briefly again. But the part of
the company became a hardware
company. It wasn't like,
everyone there full time was
just doing fucked.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. So then, how
did you go about, like, the
manufacturing process and
everything for like, so once you
worked out the designs, how do
you go into actually making lots
of the robots? Like I assume
that that's quite a big thing?
Melonee Wise: It's actually
relatively simple. Because it's
not like we're bending metal,
someone else does all of that
stuff. Like they build the sheet
metal. So you do the all the CAD
designs, you do all the
drawings, you send it out to a
shop, they fabricate it. And
really what you're doing at a
robotics company, if you're
doing assembly is you're doing
assembly and test. And not to
say that we're not
manufacturing, but we're not
bending metal. And so yep, the
parts are putting together Yeah,
we're putting them together, and
then upgrading them, and then
making sure that they turn on.
And so it's, it's actually
relatively easy to build or
assemble, let's call it, robot
hardware, especially in the in
the case of the smaller robots,
the larger robots get a lot more
complicated because of the
safety systems and things like
that, that are required. But for
smaller robots, almost all the
parts in in smaller remotes are
custom. And so we have a lot of
control over it and comes in, we
put together and worked.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. That's
interesting. I've heard some
companies that I've talked to
I've had a lot of difficulties,
like finding suppliers and
working with it. And I've heard
things like the CEO will fly
every rec to or some some person
in the company will fly every
three months to say, the
Schengen area of China, and work
with them on the manufacturing.
Did you guys have to do these
kinds of things? Or?
Melonee Wise: No, we
predominantly made everything in
the United States. And anything
that wasn't made in the United
States, we had us partners that
handle all
Audrow Nash: that. Interesting.
Can you speak a bit about that
the manufacturing in the US
because I'm not honestly
terribly aware of many robotics.
things being made in the US?
Yeah, sure. new info to me.
Melonee Wise: Yeah. So if you if
you look at it, if you look at
the freight 100 or 100 kilogram
platform, it has, it has about
300 total parts about 100 unique
parts. And the the things that
are made not in the United
States are things like the laser
scanner that's made in Germany
by the, the skins, those are
injection molded in in China,
but they're designed in the
United States, actually, the
molds are designed in the United
States. And then they're built
in China, but and then our wheel
motors are based off of a hub
motor that you see in like
scooters and stuff like that.
And that was clever. Yeah. And
we did the we do the engineering
design in the United States with
a company that we use their
their Sai motors, they make
custom motors, and then they own
parts of factories in China. So
in terms of the extent of the
componentry, that's like
fabricated or made not in the
United States outside of the
computer, let's call it it's all
made in the United States. So we
designed our own PCBs, though.
prefabricated at a PCB
fabrication place in actually
California. All the sheet metal
is bent in, in many, I mean, the
bay area has a lot of
manufacturing capabilities. And
all of the sheet metal is I
mean, one of the shemale vendors
is literally blocked from our
office. They they kind of
scooted down the road. And so
all of all that in the paint,
you know, the any of the other
things like powder coating,
stuff like that, it's all done
locally. So if you if you look
at it, unfortunately, the the a
US commerce defines defined in
the USA by cost of goods. So
because we have a laser scanner
that's made in Germany, it we
can't call the robot made in the
USA, we can say design in the
United States, but but if you
look at it on a per
Audrow Nash: like because the
laser scanner is such a large
component of the whole robots
cost. Yes. Yeah. Can you can you
tell how much one of the robots
costs? No. Okay.
Melonee Wise: Sorry. That's a
closely guarded secret. Okay.
Okay. Yeah. But if you look at
it from a total part count,
sense, the majority of the parts
are made in the United States.
And so most of the labor and
things like that, and the jobs
are being created in the United
States. But there's this
technical way of judging. You
know, if
Audrow Nash: you can call what
you can call it, that makes
sense. Although, it'd be nice if
it was by item
Melonee Wise: would be, it'd be
really nice.
Audrow Nash: Because honestly,
before talking to you about
this, just now, I didn't realize
robotics manufacturer was done
in the US to any real extent.
Melonee Wise: There's lots of
companies out there fabrication
and assembly in the United
States, you'd be surprised.
Audrow Nash: I am. interested.
Interesting. Okay. I want to
learn more about that. Yeah. So
now, moving on to the next
stage. So after five months, or
whatever it was, you were a
software company?
Melonee Wise: Yes, we were. Tell
me a bit about that. Yeah. So
that's, that's building all this
software for the robotic side
and the server side. And so when
we first started, we, we, you
know, we kind of heavily heavily
modified the raw stack to
support our needs. Eventually,
we ended up basically, kind of
drawing the line where we were
going to use a lot bra stack. So
we use it, basically, for
message passing, and all the
libraries and visualization. But
we no longer base any of our
navigation and slam on top of
the Ross stack.
Audrow Nash: With that, would
that change with Ross? Two out
of curiosity? No, no, no,
Melonee Wise: no, I think that,
you know, we definitely are
going to move to Ross, two in
the future. We're trying to
figure out the right time to do
it. But the the roster,
navigation stack is a research
stack that really wasn't meant
to scale for the type of
applications that we're
deploying it in today. And the
same is true for kind of the
slant algorithms. It doesn't say
anything negative about the Ross
navigation capabilities or
anything like that. It's just
not well suited for our
application.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, you said
million square foot warehouses,
like, I'm not terribly surprised
that it doesn't scale to that.
Yeah.
Melonee Wise: And then, you
know, then we also built the
server side componentry. So this
is stuff that that I think now
you're starting to see more
attention to in Ross with, like
Ross web tools. But But
previously, there wasn't as much
focused on, you know, user
interfaces, tool chains for
editing and modifying the map
and, and things like that. And
so fetch builds all that
software stack for, for
basically allowing users who
know nothing about robots to use
robot.
Audrow Nash: Yep. So they can
have a nice interface, and the
interface kind of helps them use
the application. Yeah. I think
that's an important thing to add
into Ross.
Melonee Wise: Yeah, Ross was
ecosystem. Yeah, the Ross
ecosystem being is missing like
this entire kind of dev tools.
Robot chain.
Audrow Nash: That what do you
mean the actual robot chain?
Melonee Wise: So like, there's a
lot of deployment tools for
robots that are missing like
there's no way to there's no
good open source packages for
deploying software to lots of
robots. There's no good open
source tools for monitoring lots
of robots concurrently there
Audrow Nash: you looked at? I
don't know. I haven't used it.
Have you tried Amazon
Greengrass, and they're open
sourced? No, no, you said no.
Open Source. Yeah. No
Melonee Wise: open source. Yes.
Yeah. I mean, there's plenty of
people who are willing to charge
you money for these services.
But for me, the thing that the
thing that sparked all of the
explosion in in companies for
robotics and using Ross was that
there was no cost burden to get
started. And so those are some
of the tools that are missing
from the community.
Audrow Nash: What would you say
explicitly I mean, I'm, I'm the
Ross boss for the humble to
release in a year. And so I'm
interested in to see what like
we're still building the
roadmap, basically.
Melonee Wise: I mean, if you ask
my team today what they want
they just want documentation
like
Audrow Nash: that's that's the
biggest priority so far for
humble I totally agree with you
on that Yeah. And
Melonee Wise: you're talking to
the person who used to be the
Ross Wikis are so
Audrow Nash: back in the day
Yeah.
Melonee Wise: Well, all the
tutorials I wrote are still the
details for us.
Audrow Nash: That's crazy when
so so this the Willow Garage
days, or this is the early Ross
days, yeah, milestone
Melonee Wise: three of Ross, and
will abroad was documentation.
And during that time, I wrote
about 200 Ross tutorials. So all
the big tutorials like it's
still all your work. Any
anything you see with like
turtle sim I wrote.
Audrow Nash: That's so funny.
And now in Ross two, it's the
same thing. They're just derived
from the old ones. Yeah. So you
probably like I remember writing
that. That's Yeah, Faria.
Melonee Wise: Actually, when she
was converting, like asked me
questions about him. She's like,
your names at the bottom of all
these pages? And I was like,
yeah, cuz I wrote. Uh huh.
Audrow Nash: And Marya is the
former, she's no longer at open
robotics. But she was like the
documentation lead for the Ross
two initiative, as far as I
understand.
Melonee Wise: Yeah. And she,
she, I think she ported a lot of
the Ross one tutorials to Ross
Who?
Audrow Nash: Definitely. Okay,
so that's interesting. So you
built your own nav stack. And
then on the server side, so you
can control the robots. Those
are two things that are really
not the nav stack. But the
server side, the building user
interfaces are about web tools,
these kinds of things. These
would be good to see. And Ross,
do you think, right?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, I think I
think from an open source
perspective, yes, I think the
biggest challenge
Audrow Nash: is deployment.
Melonee Wise: Yeah, deployment,
robot monitoring, but all of
that. I mean, those are huge
undertakings and letter, whether
anyone's willing to fund it or
support it. I mean, because many
companies like Amazon are
building Greengrass, close
sourced tool chains that, you
know, they want to get you
hooked on their platforms.
Audrow Nash: Woody. So did you
guys build your own? Or do you
use one of these? Oh, yeah.
Melonee Wise: I mean, it was
early two, it was really early,
I mean, in orbit, and forment.
And what are the other six other
guys that are all doing kind of
those things? All started two or
three years after fetch started
as a company.
Audrow Nash: So you had to?
Melonee Wise: Yeah, I mean, it's
it's why, you know, it's it's
the same thing that a lot of
people ask why Ross didn't base
their communication layer off of
protobuf exists. Yeah, it didn't
exist when? When Ross started,
you know? And then DBS wasn't as
mature A long time ago. So
there's just lots of questions
like, I think, why not? Yeah,
but what do you want? It didn't
exist?
Audrow Nash: It didn't exist.
And we've been building on top
of what we have this whole time.
Yeah. Okay. And then, then
you've any what were what were
some of the hardest challenges,
I would say with the software
company that you had for before
becoming a data company? Yeah, I
mean, so million foot square
foot warehouse. Sounds really
tough. Yeah, that
Melonee Wise: was hard. Um, I
would actually say that that
many of the challenges that we
ran into were with forklifts. I
hate forklifts. Getting safety
right. That's really hard. I
think in general helping to help
customers. Understand Then what
is capable and what's or what is
possible and what's not
possible?
Audrow Nash: Just like what
you're saying at the beginning
with the tempering expectations?
Yeah, kind of thing.
Melonee Wise: Yeah, I mean, I,
you know, I think so. So, you
know a fair bit about robotics
and you probably know that,
like, the robot footprint really
matters, right? Like, as the
robot travels through the world,
it needs to know how big it is,
right? One of the most common
asks from any customer is Can't
we just, that's how it always
starts. Can't we just overhang
the footprint by an inch, or
three inches or 15 inch is? And
it's like no robot doesn't know
how big is the robot doesn't
can't see those things. But
that's one of the hardest things
with with kind of people's
understanding or lack of
understanding of robotics and
also their kind of expectations
as they see it from really
killer. You know, videos like
Boston Dynamics. I mean, those
are amazing. Yeah, yeah,
they're, they're super amazing.
But you know, I would load up
the expectations to upload the
40,000 or, you know, retakes
before they got the backflip to
work that one time.
Audrow Nash: I couldn't believe
that when that occurred, like
watching that video was like, Oh
my god, what is that? That's
crazy. I was in a legged
locomotion lab at the time. And
it was like super crazy. We're
just getting nothing to walk.
Different backflips.
Melonee Wise: Yeah. But you
know, you and I both know as
roboticist like that. There's a
real, there's a blooper reel.
And it's really huge, right?
Yeah. And so one of the bigger
things about about software, as
you know, is lots of things are
possible. But the time to
implement those things can be
very long. And they can be very
weird. They're hidden, they can
also contain very weird edge
cases and things like that. If
you were doing legged
locomotion, then you definitely
know how bad edge cases are.
Audrow Nash: Oh, it's very
spiky, the optimization space,
it would like work, great work,
great fall down. Like it would
very, very tough to tune
parameters. But yeah, yeah.
Melonee Wise: And so. So those,
I think are some of the bigger
things that we ran into, over
the time of building software,
and just figuring out how to
support some level of
adaptability of the system, or
customization without basically
writing one off code for every
customer that ever wants
anything.
Audrow Nash: Yes, totally. Yeah,
that's hard. Because it's, it's
tough to make the software
flexible, in a good way. Like, I
mean, it's good software design,
but it's hard to predict. And
it'll be like, Oh, they want
this little thing that's
slightly different. That
requires a major assumption that
the whole thing was built upon
to be J. That can be painful and
difficult. Yeah, we just want
this other little thing. Like,
no,
Melonee Wise: okay. We went
through this whole exercise for
our car Connect like and we
basically got the biggest cart
we could absolutely move around
with this robot. And, and like,
in the field, everyone's loving
it and then like about six
months in, then we start getting
the request. Can't we just make
it an inch bigger? answer's no,
we made it as big as we possibly
can. You know, there's no more
Audrow Nash: Oh, funny one inch.
Can't we just What a funny
you're like, Oh, no. Oh, no,
every time
Melonee Wise: I hear it, can't
we just are would it be so hard
if? Or
Audrow Nash: these? Yeah.
Always. Yeah. So let's see.
Okay, so we talked a little bit
about the data before and I'd
love to learn a little bit
because we're running out of
time. Sorry about that. No, it's
all been very interesting. But
I'd love to hear a little bit
about the acquisition process
with you but I know you're still
going through it.
Melonee Wise: It just closed
like in 30 minutes. I mean, we
announced a complete a couple
days ago but the money came into
the bank today.
Audrow Nash: Oh, what like what
a breaking interview just so can
you talk a bit about the
experience. I've heard horror
stories with acquisitions. If I
understand correctly, they had
say 5% or something stake in
your company and then they just
bought the rest out? Or
Melonee Wise: Yeah, I mean,
acquisition process like they
had been a previous investor. We
went through an acquisition
process we engaged with other
potential acquirers but never
really seemed like the best fit
for us. And one of the things
that really got me excited about
zebra acquisition is in January,
they actually hired Jim Lawton.
He's been in the robotics
industry for a while he worked
at rethink robotics. He, he
worked at Universal robots. And
he done a variety of different
startups, things like that, and
you have a good reputation. And
it's signaled to me that they
were very serious about robotics
and robotics, automation.
Audrow Nash: They've done their
homework, they made a good pick,
they brought someone
Melonee Wise: and someone was
working. Yeah. And, and you
know, when you when you look at
it, as you said, there's always
this this fear of the
acquisition going terrible, like
someone buying your company and
then saying, you know, what, we
want to do home robots or
something like that, I think
that would have been soul
crushing to me. Like, forget all
this stuff you've been working
on for the last half decade or
so why don't we just go work on
you know, vacuums. And so, so,
you know, the, the zebra
acquisition was really for me
about finding good fit, I mean,
obviously, money is a factor,
but making sure that the visions
are aligned, the outcomes are
well aligned. And, and I felt
like, zebra was a good fit for
us, if you, if you look at some
of the things that were
happening before that, so after
they invested in us, we started
partnering on some things, and
one of the cool things that we
did, um, about a year and a half
ago is, is so they make
camscanner so you can scan a
barcode and it like tells you
what this thing is, or you you
know, it goes to a system and
does one thing, we a year and a
half ago made it easy to
integrate their hand scanners
with our robots. So like someone
could scan a barcode and a robot
would like automatically appear.
And so that was that was a super
cool integration because if you
look in manufacturing some guys
building something right? You
know, he's, he's assembling
something, and maybe he runs out
of screws, or maybe he runs out
of something, you can just scan
a barcode in a robot with a cart
shows up and says, Here's your
thing, you know, and, and so
that that was very powerful for
some of our customers, and they,
they really liked it. And we've
been slowly expanding our
platform to integrate with, with
like, all the other industrial
IoT devices out there, we
actually created a partnership
with sec as well for this kind
of application. And so that, you
know, we that was really cool,
we had experience working with
them, we knew it wasn't like the
worst thing in the world. And it
was easy to work with them get
things done, and we got things
done. Because that's the other
thing that you could you could
run into is you you get acquired
and nothing happens Do you do
the quintessential rest invest?
And however rushed invest? It's
it's a term that people throw
around in startups, after you
get acquired. You doesn't if you
don't like what the company's
doing or you you don't like you
just know you stick around and
you just rest invest.
Audrow Nash: Rest while you're
Melonee Wise: vesting the rest
of your options or shares. Yeah,
I mean, I
Audrow Nash: typically Yeah,
you're not investing?
Melonee Wise: No, but but I
didn't that was one of my goals.
I didn't want to end up at a
company where that was my main
bag, you know?
Audrow Nash: Oh, definitely.
Yeah. Okay, and then how did you
so it's just interesting to me
to find a good fit it probably
means that there were other
companies that looked into
buying you guys
Melonee Wise: yeah, I can't I
can't speak to the whole process
in that regards. But yeah, I
like
Audrow Nash: that you found a
good fit for this kind of thing.
Like we found a good fit.
Awesome. So with just a few
minutes left, I was hoping for
more time for this because you
have an interesting perspective.
But what's the so if you if
you're projecting like five or
10 years down the road, where do
you think we're going to be with
robotics? And you can speak to
warehouses or anything else?
Melonee Wise: Not much further
than we are today. Yeah, I I,
you know, a couple years ago
actually at a Ross con, the CEO
of of Ubuntu or canonical got up
and he said, you know, the the
thing about success is it it
takes 10 years to have an
overnight success. And, and
robotics is is a slow moving
train. I think that a lot of
people probably know fetch and
you know me, don't or may not
have realized or remembered that
we're seven year old company,
right and it's taken seven years
to get to this success point and
we we have done a lot In that
seven years, and we were
Audrow Nash: involved in Willow
and everything before that,
Melonee Wise: yeah. And, and so
if you if you look at it from
the time I came out here in
2007, it's been a long time,
right? And it's not saying that
incremental advancement won't
happen over these 10 years. I
just don't see us having like
this big, light switch moment in
robotics. I mean, everything
will kind of just incrementally
trickle. But if you were to ask
me about autonomous cars, I
think we're 20 to 40 years out
on autonomous. Oh, yeah. Like,
that's all we're saying that
Tesla is going to be driving on
the BS. I mean, anyone who says
that needs to go like, yeah, go
do it for a couple years and
figure out how hard the goddamn
problem is.
Unknown: For sure.
Melonee Wise: Um, and so I, I
don't know, I mean, I think the
the one thing that I could see
that could be game changing for
indoor robotics in the next 10
years, is the new wireless
standards that are coming out
for localization to kind of
solve this, where's my robot
problem? I think that could be
really game changing if that
technology takes off like ultra
wideband location, more of the
Wi Fi six standard that includes
local local location information
as part of the Wi Fi like
packet. That's something that
can be super game changing, I
think could have a wide sweeping
effect in in robotics because
now really, then the problem
comes down to how good can your
navigation be? Not Where the
hell are you all the time? I
think that we'll see good
improvement in look like a
bipedal locomotion robots? I
don't think we'll get anything
really practical out there in
the world. I mean, you worked on
it, you know, how how, how spiky
it is, let's call it true. I
think that one thing we might
see, though, from the autonomous
car space, which I'm kind of
interested in seeing is I think
that that players like neuro and
those smaller will local
distribution, autonomy vehicles
that are more like little smart
cars with, with delivery baskets
in them on the roadways, could
be game changing. But they it's
not full autonomy. And it's kind
of you know, side streets, not
highway driving, for delivery of
groceries and things like that.
I think there's promise there.
And I think that might be
something we might be able to
deliver on inside of 10 years.
Because the complexity of the
autonomy is localized. And
limited.
Audrow Nash: Do you think? Do we
get further with like human
robot hybrid models where a
human takes control? If the
robot gets into a situation, it
doesn't have high confidence
about navigating?
Melonee Wise: Absolutely, we're
already doing that today. The
question is, is how far can we
push the safety boundaries of
that? So far, it's not clear
that we have much of a good
clear idea of what that means.
But like, if you have an
autonomous view of a truck
that's being driven remotely by
a person and the Wi Fi cuts out
it's
Audrow Nash: terrifying.
Melonee Wise: Yeah, terrifying.
Keywords terrifying. Now, if you
look at fetch and plus one and
lots of other companies we all
have remote monitoring in some
way to assist the robots but we
we greatly rely on autonomy it's
like 99.5% autonomy point 5%
human I don't know where that'll
if that'll start spectrum wise
going more towards the 90%. But
it's it's hard to provide return
on investment with a lot of
human in the loop autonomy
because of just the time
expensive and time to time to
accomplish it. Like time to
recover.
Audrow Nash: Oh, I see. Gotcha.
Okay. So let's see wrapping up.
Do you have any public like
social media or company blog or
anything that you'd like to
share with our listeners if
they'd like to learn more or
Sure,
Melonee Wise: I mean, if people
want to learn more, I mean the
biggest thing you just need to
know is how to spell my name.
It's me yellow, and E. I'm very
unique and very, I've great SEO.
I have a Twitter that's just
Melanie wise I have. Everything
is just Melanie wise. So if you
Google, Melanie wise, you'll
find my Instagram, my, my
Twitter, my LinkedIn, all of
that very easily. I will say
some some of my channels are
pretty fragmented. Some of them
are only personal stuff. So if
you go to my Instagram, there's
no robots there. It really is
just beer in travel. But, you
know,
Audrow Nash: it's a human to
Yeah. Okay, is that it for
those? deaf? Okay. Well, I've
enjoyed speaking with you. Thank
you. It's been
Melonee Wise: great. Thank you
very much. I appreciate your
time.
Audrow Nash: That's all we have
for you today. If you enjoyed
this interview, consider
subscribing to comment on this
interview or to give us general
feedback, especially while we're
just getting started. Go to
sense think act calm, or you can
find us on the Ross discourse.
We'll be back in two weeks time.
Goodbye, everyone.