Audrow Nash: Hi, everyone,
welcome to the Sense Think Act
Podcast. I'm the host Audrow
Nash. And in today's episode I
interview Ryan Gariepy, Chief
Technology Officer of Clearpath
robotics. Clearpath robotics
makes several mobile robotics
platforms that are used by
researchers and corporations. We
talk about the origin of
Clearpath robotics, how they
have focused on making extremely
robust robots, how Clearpath
uses ROS 1 and ROS 2, and on the
future of robotics, I thought it
was very interesting to see how
clear path as a company has
matured with expectations and
the robotics industry. And I
really enjoyed hearing what Ryan
thinks will be the future of
robotics in the next two to five
years. As always, big thank you
to our founding sponsor, Open
Robotics, and I hope you enjoy
the episode.
So to start, I would love to
have you just introduce yourself
and tell us a bit about
ClearPath, too.
Ryan Gariepy: Of course, the My
name is Ryan Gariepy. I'm the
CTO and co founder of Clearpath
robotics. And I have been stuck
in my office for about a year
and a half and counting.
Audrow Nash: All right, and so
tell me a bit more about
Clearpath. What's the kind of
mission that you guys are going
for? And how long has the
company been around?
Clearpath has been around for
just over 12 years, probably 12
years, 12 years, one month and
21 days, I believe, as of today.
Twenty one days!
Something like that, the we
started, we started as the
company with an intent to be the
company to go to when you had a
robotics problem, and you didn't
know where to go to solve it, or
you had ideas on a problem that
you thought you could solve with
robots, but you weren't quite
sure you weren't, you didn't
know where to go. And it wasn't
necessarily a consultancy, it
was about building some of these
products, these baseline
products and hardware and
software because it didn't exist
at the time. And that's
certainly been the case, we have
seen the robotics market grow
beyond our wildest dreams. And
six years ago, we also started a
sister company called auto
motors, which is a more
vertically integrated supplier
of production grade autonomous
materials, but autonomous mobile
robots to the materials handling
industry. And that's also been
exciting. we've, we've actually
driven, you know, millions and
millions of hours unsupervised,
fully autonomous on that side of
the business, which I'm sure for
all of the roboticists listening
out there, they they appreciate
the challenges inherent in that.
Okay, so you started ClearPath
wanting it to be for solving
general robotics problems. How
do you do approach like that?
How did you approach making it
so you could solve general
robotics problems?
Well, when we were started, or
when we, when we got started,
there was no standard way to
build a robot or no standard way
to build software, anyone doing
research, whether it's
theoretical, very academic
research, or applications level
Industrial Research, or
government research, you were
always building everything from
scratch, the hardware,
obviously, but also all of the
software, right there, there was
open source robotic software,
but it wasn't really well used.
And we want it to be that
company, where you could go to
and describe your problem,
whether it's the research, the
research problems, or the
application you were trying to
investigate. And that we would
help you move forward without
having to build your own
expertise in robotics from the
ground up, before you even
started. You want, you know,
researchers want to research or
entrepreneurs want to want to
test ideas. They don't want to
be, you know, they don't want to
be caught up in a year of
learning how to build a robot
before they even get started on
what their idea is. It's
demoralizing and frustrating.
Hmm.
And so Clearpath you guys have a
bunch of general platforms
effectively that people can
build off of for their different
applications, like on different
surfaces and things.
Yeah, we started we started in
the OCR space. And that was
because we'd realized and this
this was back in 2008 2009. We
realized that outdoors was where
the really valuable use cases
were going to start appearing.
Were the new valuable use cases
we're going to start appearing
at least That's where the
research was being done. And on
top of that, on top of that, the
on top of that, there was a lot
of recent progress around things
like sensors. For example, when
I started my undergraduate
degree it cost probably $3,000
to buy a an IMU, which was,
which was half decent, which
could tell you basically which
way was up. And then through the
end of my, under the end of my
undergraduate, it was, you know,
30 bucks. Now wide, ours were
still blindingly expensive at
the time, but we were starting
to see those prices drop we, for
example, the the U r, g o four,
which was the first really
affordable navigation grade
LIDAR, you know, small one about
that big that that appeared
through the end of my, if I
recall, correctly through the,
through the end of my
undergraduate time. So we're
starting to see this significant
drop in sensors as well as a
significant increase in the
power capabilities of the
robots. So now off road was all
of a sudden possible, and it was
this brand new space and
research
just for scale. How much do you
think you could get a comparable
IMU or Inertial Measurement
Unit? For today? Like the same
quality? Would it be like, my
guess would be like 10 bucks or
something? Or what do you think
it would be?
On the volume Far, far, far
cheaper, for cheaper, the the
most expensive part these days
would be the engineering effort
to stick it on the PCB. That's
crazy, like between the IMU
between the IMU themselves and
all of the filtering software
that now exists, and the
processing software that now
exists, like, your cell phone is
probably better than those first
time use we were using.
Yeah, that's absolutely crazy.
And then so outdoor, how did you
identify that most? Or that
there was a lot of potential
interesting things for outdoor
robotics applications? Like what
were you looking at?
Yeah, if we start from the
research space, it was because
there just weren't any research
platforms out there. Or just
there weren't many there were
very very few research platforms
out there, which could handle a
reasonable outdoor terrain.
There was a lot of indoor
platforms like you know, there
was a bunch of still a bunch of
old like, our wi indoor
platforms around there was is
that is that a company? Or was
Yeah, that was real real
interface. Okay. And you had you
know, the at the time it was
mobile robots then became adept
mobile robots and is now Homer
on but you had there, the
Pioneer three, three, dx was a
very, very much a workhorse. You
had people who are hacking
roombas around and the first
create was being used, but these
were all indoor platforms. And
the researchers there were
obvious there obviously, there
was Outdoor Research happening,
right, like the CMU robotics
Institute was, you know, had
been doing outdoor robotics
research for for decades. But it
wasn't a very common thing. And
we that's where we said it,
that's where we're gonna get
started. That's we're gonna make
our mark by building these
really solid robots that could
unlock entirely brand new fields
of field robotics work. That's
really where we got started.
It's almost ironic that auto was
that when we started auto, it's
almost entirely focused on
indoors. But that's that's
another story.
Yeah, that is funny. Okay, so
you were working on these
platforms? And just Can you give
me a sense of what they look
like overall, like a lot of the
platforms that are used for
outdoor use? What do they look
like?
You know, generally most of the
platforms we have their their
black and yellow and they have
four wheels. Yeah. And it's one
of those and research is
probably one of ours.
Yeah. And they so they mostly
they it's like a big flat spot
on the top where you can attach
different things that you might
more cameras more, anything
else.
So yeah, that was generally what
we wanted to build. I mean, we
knew that the software space in
robotics wasn't quite ready for
the software platform yet, but
we knew the world was ready for
physical platforms and we took
that somewhat literally. So
building some big
software platform, what do you
mean,
the worldwide software platform
I would mean something you know,
like the iPhone where you have,
you can write software, right
you don't need to change any
hardware. We're now at the port
Now further along that curve.
But yeah, we we tried to make it
really easy for us to integrate
things we tried to make it easy
for our customers to integrate
things the sort of robots that
if you decided that you're in
the field and something needed
to work and you could take a
hammer to it, you could take a
drill to it that it would work
you can you know, pack it
together and get it out do your
research and get it back in the
field we to the point where we
would I don't know if we still
sell these but we would sell
replacement top plates only for
when someone just wanted to, you
know drill and tap the top plate
for some research gear and then
later they realize either they
made a mistake. They really like
it. And you can take the top
plate with all your sensors, you
could put it on the shelf and
you could you could share the
asset around right that's that's
that was actually a very well,
it's still a really common thing
now that you have self driving
vehicles where you would get a,
you have a dozen researchers but
only one physical robot, right?
Because you could only afford
one, one sensor setup. Now
there's research labs where you
can have things like, you'll
have things ranging from, you
know, the turtlebot, three, all
the way up to like our, our war
hog and moose platforms, for
example, which are on a larger
size. But it was it was very
much like, Well, you know, at
the time, you had the PRT robots
in the field, and there you have
an entire research lab, which
was around those PR twos. But
even for the labs, which
couldn't afford that, they were
still bought, they would buy
like our Husky platform, which
was our first and actually one
of the most iconic platforms we
make. And you'd have to share
it, right you have this this
little robot, it's got a bunch
of sensors, you need to share it
among all your students.
That is nice. It's clever to
just replace the top plate. That
seems like a good solution. So
let's see, are there any
particularly interesting Apple,
I'm sure that people are using
your platforms for tons of
things, but are there any that
were like, particularly
interesting or surprising uses?
Well, if I go outside the if I
if I ignore some of the
confidential stuff, there's the
one which I saw most recently,
which, which surprised me and I
didn't I didn't actually know
about this one until I saw it in
the news, but was a college
which was using the boxer which
is a industrial autonomous
mobile robot that Clearpath
sells, which is actually a
variant of the auto Amr. So it's
a boat, 100 kilos, 100 kilos
built, like it can survive a
factory because it can, and it
was used, it was being used for
robotics or applications
research at St. Clair college, I
believe. By recently, obviously,
people have needed to do all
sorts of, you know, working
remotely schooling remotely and
what have you. And they rigged
it up as a, they may rigged it
up as a moving clothes, horse or
clothes, or like clothing model
for lack of a better term, where
they had a fashion, they have a
fashion program at the school.
And it was very important for
them to see to see how the
clothes would move. Like how
like how they would drape when
they would move and they get the
and it's like you can't you're
you're doing all this judging
and exhibiting remotely and you
can't you're not just gonna set
them all up and mannequins and
leave it like that and have the
judges look at it so they would
actually swap out these I can't
exactly remember how they how
they held the clothes on top the
robotic It was a mannequin or
mannequin or something else. But
they would they would swap them
out and and run the fashion show
like that. I thought that was
just you know, that was really
really interesting. I mean,
everyone hears about everyone.
Here's what the disinfection
robots that people built in the
last year like I don't know how
many have been built on our
platform, but everyone hears
about those but you never hear
about these. These little like
that. Yes, the clothes modeling
robot.
That's hilarious. What a great
youth. Oh, yeah. Okay, and then
one thing that's been very
interesting to me from your
previous talks and things, your
robots they're designed to be
super reliable, like go forever.
Can you talk a bit about this
from the from the beginning, we
would, we would joke with our,
with our prospects that that the
reliability standard standard
for our robots is is outlast the
researchers. That was the that
was the idea. Even at the clear
path, even at the Clearpath
robotics side of things where
the standards are not as high as
on the on the industrial front.
But that was the goal it was you
should never have to you should
never have to cut short your
field robotics research because
of frankly, bad weather. And I
think that comes from that comes
from us all us all being
Canadian are all the early the
founders and the early employees
all being Canadian, is that when
you're out there testing your
robots like one half of the
effective school year the winter
term, it's sort of slow and when
the snow leaves it gets replaced
by mud. So we really wanted to
not get in the way and not have
to worry about not have to worry
about the snow or not have to
worry about the rain. So that
was that was our initial
standard. And then we've kept
pushing from there and this was
a very interesting time for
robotics because the this we
were able to mature along with
the market expectations. These
days if you're starting robotics
calm It's just got to work.
Like, you know, you're compared
against, you know, robots like,
like ours are fetches as they
are now, you're not compared
against the robots that we had
10 years ago. But that's that's
what the market does.
Yeah, it matures. That is
interesting. So it's really
changed as the market has grown.
And people expect a product now,
what do you guys do differently,
to make it so that your robots
are even more reliable than they
were in the past, which was
still super reliable.
The thing that's really helped
is the fact that the rest of the
world has now caught on to the
potential power of robotics. So
it means that it's easier for us
to build partnerships with other
companies who have a lot of some
of the who have some of this
fundamental fundamental
expertise, like sensors,
sensors, or actuators, or
simulation systems. I think
that's been that's been really
helpful. So even a lot of the
larger robots, for example, like
Clearpath, robotics cells are
built in partnership with
vehicle suppliers. So where the
robotics experts, but we
actually work with other vehicle
experts, or, or even more
recently, more recently, it was
very, you know, well covered in
the robotics media that we did
a, we're doing a we have rather
a partnership with, with Boston
Dynamics for the research space.
And that just makes sense,
right? Boston Dynamics is, is
one of the leading if not the
leading manufacturer of legged
robots in the world. And we're
the world's leading integrator
and solver of these problems. So
it was it just made sense that,
that our clients in the world
needed more legged robots. And
now that that's possible. And
why would we try to do that
ourselves? Right, work with
those who've already picked it
up? Yeah. Interesting. So going
back to working with the vehicle
companies, so do take advantage
of their existing supply chain
and their existing processes? Or
reps, how does that work? Ah,
yeah,
well, ya know, they go hand in
some cases, the vehicle in some
cases, the vehicle shows up,
like at our door, where it's
been a repurposed vehicle where
they've remanufactured parts of
it, and then we will take it and
turn it from, you know, a, what
might be described as a giant
remote control car into this ROS
enabled fully integrated
research platform, you know,
upgraded power systems, upgraded
power systems, onboard compute
all of the sensor options that
we might have all of the
customization options that we've
got. So just like early days,
you could call us up, you know,
10 years ago and say that my
research, hypothetically, my
research is in, you know, mobile
manipulation and unknown
environments. And we would turn
around and say, Okay, well,
maybe if your budget is x, then
you can't do the 3d LIDAR. But
you can get an arm like this,
and you can get a camera. We've
got that same, we've got that
same. That same political
experience for for everything
else we do. It's really about
providing like I said, this
conference, one of the last
conferences, I was actually able
to speak out in person that are
we do have very reliable robots.
But in the end, what we, what we
sell, is, is the ability to
speed up the robotics
development cycle.
Hmm, definitely not true. And
just out of curiosity, where are
most of the manufacturers that
actually build the robots you
guys make?
There's a lot we work with, in
Well, in Ontario, Ontario has a
lot of vehicle manufacturers,
we've been we've been broadening
that. So traditionally, we've
been very heavy on still
building our own vehicles. And
where we've really got the
broadest reach will be in the
manipulation and setting spaces
because those markets have been
more mature for a while. In
those in those you can really,
you can imagine the countries in
particular like you know,
Germany and Japan are the two
probably largest companies on
those fronts, but that's
probably not a surprise to
anyone. America, Denmark, I
mean, you are we were we had we
worked with universal robots on
a custom skew for ourselves and
our clients. I don't know how
you go, this was what sorry,
stock keeping unit. It's a sort
of custom configuration of their
arm. So you're typically when
you bought a universal robot
arm, you needed to and you want
it to do research with it. The
Universal robot arm would have
you'd have the arm and then you
would have a control box which
is a giant control box meant for
industrial relatively decent
size meant for industrial floors
and it had three boards in it.
It had an A power supply board,
which was effectively a, you
know, transformer and step down,
or interactive rectifier and
step down transformer. And so
getting the power, yeah, power
regulator, yeah, then you'd have
a Safety Safety Board and a
controller board and have that
you have this giant enclosure,
and a big power supply. But it
turns out that most of our large
vehicles, supply the power
already supply the power at the
spec needed, because they have a
big DC, they have a big DC buses
on them for power. So if you
wanted to, if you wanted to
integrate a mobile or AI, your
robot onto a mobile robot, you
would have to put in a an
inverter like you would you
would need an inverter to go up
to AC, and then you would end up
what would end up happening
inside this black box, which was
also kind of large was that then
then it would end up losing more
power, because you're just
stepping it all the way down to
DC. So we had a race
to AC and then back to DC
and then back to DC, right,
which is generally a waste. Yep.
So it's wasted amount of wasted
space. And, and just extra cost.
So we came to an agreement with
them where we would, we would go
by the arms and by the two
boards, and then we would mount
them ourselves. And you were you
used to have this this ratchet,
just huge package, that package
was no longer there because we
could mount the components
inside of inside of the the
chassis itself. And that was
great. So that was the court
sort of partnerships, which we
were always forging, which was
to open up these brand new
markets for these partners, and
serve our customers really cool
in time because like we're
already we've already got our
hands full building the basis,
we're not going to build the
arms too.
Yeah. So you said that you guys
kind of your core competence
would be like as an integrator,
if I understood correctly of
basically taking the platform
and then adding pieces to it so
that the robotics community or
anyone who wanted to do
something with the robot could
use it. Right?
Or more, more and more. So I
mean, we're, we're very good at
vehicle design. Yeah, but you
know, we have been, there's just
now that the world is picking
up. These, you know, now that
the world is really engaging
with the robotics space in the
automation space. It's, it's
just, there's just more demand
that we can almost deal with,
like, it's one thing to maintain
a vehicle demand, like a vehicle
portfolio of a half dozen to a
dozen vehicles, which is what we
have, and we're proud of every
single one of them. But there's
so many different opportunities
out there that we've had to,
we've had to really partner in
order to keep everyone keep
growing to keep focused on what
we're good at. Yeah. And then
and so in this role, it's a lot
of taking an existing platform
and you retrofit it with
components and software, or how
would you think of that? Like,
what do you do when you get a
new platform, or it's probably
quite case by case. But yeah,
it's
very case by case I mean, you we
don't want to, we don't usually
just, you know, buy some random,
some like, I don't know, buy a
car off the lot and customize
it, we, we want to make sure
that we want to make sure that
we can provide this continual
discontinuous solution for
people, which means that we'll
we'll usually have already
spoken to the manufacturer,
we've we've come to some kind of
agreement with them, the you
know, the degree of which is is
always case by case, but we're
not trying to guess at things
right, we don't want to, we
don't want to do something a
little bit Renegade, where, you
know, you you buy a, you know,
you buy an ATV off the lot, and
then you kind of hope it works.
Because the customers, the
customers expect it to be
maintainable and for, you know,
spare parts to be available.
That's, that's the other reason
why people will, will work with
us is because when all of their
grad students have left or when
their research projects have
gone on to, to production, those
robots will still be there. And
they want to, they want the next
set of researchers in the next
set of robotics developers to be
able to, to just, you know, jump
on board, for sure. Now,
you mentioned how customers come
to you with problems and then
kind of you see if you can find
something that fits the how has
that changed while you've grown
over the last 12 years?
The problems are a lot more the
problems are a lot more diverse.
And what people are looking for
mannequin the Yeah. Well, that
one was good. We need to know
about that one. They just they
just did it. But on the plus
side, I think they're is a
growing appreciation for a
growing appreciation for what
robots can and can't do. Right?
Like when we started the even
the concept of a drone that you
could just casually buy, it
wasn't a thing. One of the, the,
the company I, company I
internship I interned at was
called aireon Labs, and they've
just been purchased by FLIR and
they sold drones for first
responders. And at the time that
they had started, you couldn't
buy an autonomous drone for
autonomous quadcopter. There
there was, there was no money
that you could pay to the
market, which would get you a
reliable autonomous quadcopter,
short of funding an entire
robotics company yourself. So
that was that was where we were
right. And self driving cars.
You know, the the urban
challenge was, was just one at
the time, I can't even remember
what year the the urban
challenge was. But that was just
around that timeframe, like
autonomous cars weren't a thing.
So there was still a little bit
of a sense of robots could
either do nothing, or they could
do everything. So early on,
there was a lot more need to
reset expectations. And on top
of that, there was wood on top
of that,
or, yeah, so you're saying
people would either think they
could do everything or nothing,
kind of like useless or they
will just be the Jetsons Butler
kind of thing effectively? Yeah,
gotcha. And so bring people down
to the level that robots
actually can do. And kind of
show them how they can be useful
still, with what they have? Or
is that we that's, that's where
we are right
now. Right? Like, you can. In
when, when we had when we were
starting, you know, there there
would be there were probably a
few 1000 people in the world,
who knew who could reasonably
describe the state of the self
driving vehicle market, like
where the technology readiness
level of the self driving
vehicle market. But now, I would
charitably guess that there are
millions of people on earth who
can generally describe what a
self driving vehicle is. And
isn't, they know what it is. And
they know it's not taking you to
Starbucks anytime soon. Without
a a well paid test driver in the
front, are you still paying 10?
Yeah. But that's that's not how
it works. So you'd have, you'd
either be, you know, selling to
someone because you knew there's
an opportunity there, and they
didn't really think that it was
possible, or they would come to
you with an opportunity. Now,
this is beyond the researchers,
this is when the commercial
demand started to take an
uptake. But you'd have people
coming in and saying, Yeah,
like, Can I pay, you know,
$5,000 to automate my old,
clunky gas powered lawnmower,
and have it run completely
unsupervised, through the middle
of a park in a crowded day.
There was a lot more requests
like that, huh, there are still
there. Just to be clear, there
are still requests like that.
But they are. But there are far
more requests, where the people
who come in the door are already
conditioned, and already
educated about what robots can
and can't do. And I think
that's, that's a that's just
wonderful for everybody, right?
Like, that's saves everyone a
whole lot of time.
And so if you're getting
requests like that, where
they're coming in and asking if
this is possible, and how much
it would be, that means that you
guys have to be extremely
knowledgeable about the state of
the art in probably a lot of
different areas. Because I mean,
there's the hardware, there's
the software component, and all
the specific things that are no
sensors how to estimate things.
Like you guys kind of have to be
broadly competent in a lot of
robotics. Yes.
Yeah. It's a it's a challenge.
Um, but the thing that gives us
that's been interesting, well,
and I'll speaking for me
personally, and it's one of the
reasons I love this work so
much, is because every day
there's a new, there's some new
development out in the world, in
the robotics space that's gonna
make that's gonna make a new
application possible. It's a new
technology and like, every day,
there's something new that I've
that I can learn. Like, I just
actually right before this, I
was I was reading a paper or
reading a paper put together
that's, that's, um, I don't know
if it's been accepted or if it's
been final submissions for iros,
which is a big robotics
conference. And it's, it's
authored by people who work for
Clearpath that's, that's just
great. And I reading through the
paper and realizing that my math
has really gone down the drain.
But anyway, I digress. Um, the
The other thing, which I mean,
it sounds kind of intimidating,
which is like our job is to stay
up to date with everything in
the field, which is robotics at
all times. But it's as, as odd
as it sounds. It's not that
challenging, because we don't
have to do any catch up. Like if
you're starting a robotics
company now. You have a lot of
catching up to do. Right like
you have decades. of progress
and you have all sorts of you
know labs to track you, you need
to know where to pay attention
who to pay attention to which
conferences to go to like all of
it, you need to catch up with
the state of the art and I had
that as you're doing that the
state of the art always
changing. But you know, we got
to do that work before this the
field before the the the
robotics field really blew up.
So now it's just it's it's day
for day.
So you wrote rode the wave,
basically. And now you're still
on it,
which is fantastic. We're just
we're just holding on now. But
it's, it's a lot easier than
then, than trying to catch it
from nothing right now.
How do you? Do you structure
your team with like experts in
specific areas? Or is it the
team of generalists? Or how do
you how would you think about
it?
So my team? Yeah, we're the team
as a whole if you include the
auto motors business unit, which
is a large portion and, you
know, sharing services and
everything like that. We're
about 200 to eight 280 to 300
people were in there. That range
right now,
are you all in Waterloo, Toronto
area, or were in the bay, I
believe, you
know, we, our offices, our
physical offices, we have four
facilities in, in the Kitchener
Waterloo Region. So if you know
the area, there's one in
Waterloo, there's two in
Kitchener, and there's one on
the near side of Cambridge, and
everything else is everything
else is remote work. And
actually, a lot of that was like
all of our sales team. And a lot
of our field team were remote
before even the pandemic hit
that was had some, you know,
engineers working remote here
and there. But overall, you
know, overall, Canada is
probably you know, if I don't
know these numbers offhand, but
I would guess 90 to 95% of the
people that we have our, you
know, live live in Canada live
in, you know, southwestern
Ontario. And then though there's
the next percentage, there'll be
a rounding error of people who
are full time around the world.
So there's someone who's in
someone in Mexico right now,
there's someone in Spain, we
have a full time member of our
team in Japan, and then everyone
else, everyone else is in the
US. So there's a lot of a lot of
salespeople in the US field
service tax systems, engineers,
people like that. Because
there's really obviously a big
export market for us is PS
autonomous systems into the US.
So
gotcha. And then for like, Is it
about the specialized versus
generalist approach? Oh, yeah.
Yeah. There's so there's,
there's probably about there's
under 20 people at the company
who would have had robotics
experience before they joined
us,
that would be Wow, my guess
that's great. Okay. So whether
that's whether that's mobile
robotics experience, like, you
know, AGV deployment in
industry, or, you know, a
Master's or PhD, it's, it's
probably around that number. I
know, the the autonomy group in
the auto space, the on the, the
auto business unit has 14, I
believe, 14 people, it's all
masters and PhDs, doing various
sorts of product development and
research, for example. But
beyond that, we really try to
bring in experts and experienced
people in their fields, whether
that's, you know, operations,
manufacturing, finance, sales,
wherever, and then even in
engineering, like I have, I
think it's seven people who
report to me right now, not a
single one, not a single one
started in a robotic space, and
only one of them had any
experience in robotics before
joining this. Wow. So it really
is, and, but people learn really
quickly, right? Like we as we've
got this foundation is, you
know, foundation of technology.
The the analogy I often make is,
if you go to, you know, you look
at a company like Audi, for
example, or you know, any
established high tech company,
how many people go into that
high tech company with expertise
in that the thing that makes
that high tech company special,
like, how many people work at
SpaceX, and of those, how many
are rocket scientists? Yeah,
like how many people work at
Audi and of those, how many
people actually know how to
build an engine? Right? Like,
definitely, that seems like
something like as a result of
the robotics field maturing, I
feel like like at the beginning,
it was probably a lot more
roboticists and now it's, people
have other specializations that
can contribute, because it's
large enough that they can focus
on something that they have
skills for.
Yeah, well, and that was
actually a big thing for us when
we decided to start getting into
getting into the industrial
space in general was hiring
people who weren't roboticists,
because you know this. This has
changed over the years, but You
know, back when we were
starting, you know, maybe 10% of
roboticist could write any kind
of decent code that you would
want running in a production
application. And I'm probably
being, I'm probably being
generous there. And that's not
an insult, because I don't think
I'd count myself as one of those
10%. But when we started really
going after the industrial
market, it was important to hire
people who had written good
software. So that's, that's what
we did. And these days, I'd say
our ratio is for every person
who writes, for every three
people who write software,
there's one roboticist and one
tester, that's probably the
rough ratio that we have.
Gotcha. Very interesting. Let's
see. So moving into software,
you at Clearpath. Were some
early adopters and supporter of
the robot operating system. Ros,
would you tell me a bit about
that
work? Yeah, I can still remember
a lot of those discussions like
they were yesterday, we started,
we started the company formally
in 2009. And at that point, we
had the philosophy that there
was always going to be more
smart people outside of the
company than inside a company.
That's, that's almost like a
statement of fact, for any
company, no matter how big. And
we said, we're going to start
with, we're gonna start with
open source. And that was number
one for that, that general
observation I just outlined. And
the other one is that one of our
largest competitors at the time,
really, really charged a lot of
researchers money for this
expensive autonomy package. Like
if you wanted to buy a laser,
you also needed to buy this
really expensive autonomy
package. And we did market
surveys of the early early
researchers to those people who
were who participated in that 12
year, 12 year old market survey,
thank you. And almost every one
of them said they didn't like
paying for the software because
they were going to write it
themselves anyway. So I said,
Okay, we will start with a small
open source software package
called player stage, because
eba, which was a combination of
three player, which is you can
look at that as an equivalent to
ROS stage, which is a 2d
simulation environment meant for
multi robot simulations and
gazebo, which most people still
know, because it's still around.
simulation. And yeah, so we
started with player was a
message passing precursor to
ROS. Right, right. This kind of
thing. Okay, so you started with
those.
We started with those. And then
in in 2010, we went to our first
official trade show, which was
ekra 2010. In the in Anchorage,
Alaska. Oh, wow. The say we'll
just say that those trade shows
are a lot classier now. But we
saw and met the crew from Willow
Garage. And one of the things
which was really interesting,
and they had their PR two out,
and they were doing all sorts of
fancy stuff, and they're way,
way better funded than we have.
But the thing that really was
impressive is that if you've
ever installed player stage,
it's a bit of a challenge. And,
and the Willow Garage team had
put so much effort into making
ROS not only just a good piece
of software, but also well
documented and easy to install.
And it just seemed like the way
to go. And we knew that people
from the player stage community
had gone over to the, you know,
being supported by were part of
Willow Garage are being
supported by Willow Garage like
Brian querque, first and
foremost. And then, so we said
that, okay, this is going to be
the way it's going to go. Right?
This is the only place which is
actually funding, not just some
software, but the community
around the software. So we
basically turned at the drop of
the hat and said, you know,
probably that that would have
been April, May and 2010. and I
are going back to going back to
Mike who's our first engineer,
first engineer at the company
saying like we need to, we need
to start this supporting this
ROS thing is starting to talk to
our customers about it. So to
the best of my knowledge, we
were the first company. We're
the first company in the world
that probably made money off off
of something tied to ROS. That's
awesome. And that was the case
for a very long time for years.
A bunch of these other companies
in the space, we're just having
an HIE and I'm like we need to
support ROS and that you could
you could get these other robots
to be supported but it was
always some third party some
third party like a library
written by a grad student who
happened to have that robot in
the shop. You can like dross and
these these days and then you
know things continue to progress
from there we have been talking
no early days about the creation
of at the time was called the
ROS foundation. That was the the
name for it. But now you know it
is the open source robotics
foundation. So that got founded
I joined the board for that. The
turtle bot turtle bot was an
interesting story. So that that
was obviously created by by
Melanie wise, you know, at
fetcher, I guess they were just
acquired. So congratulations to
them. And intelli foot is still
at the store with Open Robotics.
And they created this turtle bot
thing, which is a really cool
idea. And we had a smaller, a
more extensible, but more
expensive, but more far more
expensive educational platform
available at the time, and said
no, like this is and the other
thing that happened around the
turtlebot was that the Microsoft
Kinect came out, it was just the
perfect sensor. Like that was
the first commercially available
RGB sensor. So
then there's a camera and depth.
Camera. Yes. And, and that meant
that you never needed to worry
about LIDAR, right? Like you
didn't have to worry about the
laser, at least for small scale
stuff. So that was really cool.
And it turns out that Melanie
and Talia were tired of putting
turtle bots together by hand. So
we, we had a conversation and
ended up that we we supplied
Willow Garage with a ton of
turtle quads, and then became
the first manufacturer. First
manufacturer turtle bots in the
world. I can't I can't remember
who else was there? There was
Bill Morris from the company. He
has his own business called I
heard robots, or I heard
engineering, I think it's
changed between those names. And
I think there was a third
company at the time, I think
they were they're off in Europe,
but I can't remember who it was.
And it was like that was like 10
years ago. But that was also a
really interesting thing at the
time that, you know, we decided
we kill their own product,
because we think of the
turtlebot was going to gain
momentum in it. It certainly
did. And then yeah, other stuff
around like ROSCon i was, that
was what 2012 was the first
ROSCon. So we helped, we helped
found that. And that's still
going strong. I know literally
right before the right before
the we got on this call here. I
just finished my finished mice
my share of the reviews for
ROSCon 2021.
So we Orleans in this year, New
Orleans, that'll be a blast.
But it's been exciting, right?
Like the ROS community was huge,
or it's it just completely mind
blowing, the sort of things that
we've seen here like we when,
when you started when we started
both pockets when we started
there, ROS was out there. But
even when we started supporting
ROS, no manufacturer was out
there supporting ROS and knows,
like every sensor that you
needed to get into ROS here it
was written by, you know, Willow
Garage, it was written by us, it
was written by some grad student
halfway around the world like,
but now now you get a sensor or
you get a robot from any
reputable manufacturer, and
there's probably a ROS driver
for it. I remember getting a new
prototype sensor from a, we'll
just say it's a well known
manufacturer. And the only
instructions on how to use the
sensor was was like install the
package we gave you. And it's
ROS launch this. Yeah, that was
the instruction. And Previous to
that, and previous to that, like
every sensor manufacturer had
their own their own, usually
Java implemented sensor
visualization package. Some
still do, and I don't blame
them. But it's been this, that's
the sort of thing which is
really interesting is, you know,
first they would go from what's
ROS from, you know, they just
didn't know what it was they
didn't care. And then later we
would, you know, be trying to
lean on them a little bit and
say, Well, if you want us to
sell this new sensor you have
make it easier for us to build a
ROS driver or like release your
package online or do something.
You know, at that point. It's
like you I can I can almost
guarantee you that your own
engineers have a ROS driver if
you go and ask them. So just put
that on. Yeah. Yeah. And and now
we're at the point where the
sensors just you just come out
of the box, you don't need to
ask. And that's huge, right? Mm
hmm.
Let's see. So and you use ROS
for everything connecting
everything on your system, even
early on. Is it true? Yeah.
That's awesome. And so now how
are you guys involved in the
community with ROS? So you're
obviously still a part of it?
Yeah, definitely.
Well, you know, still on the
still on the board still running
ROSCon. Our ability to stay up
to date with all the recent
versions ebbs and flows. So I
apologize to anyone in the
community who is or who, when we
get when we caught a little get
caught a little bit behind the
ball on whatever the recent
releases. All of the auto
autonomy code is all based on
ROS and uses the ROS middleware,
it's on our fleet manager as
well. Our inter fleet and robot
comms on the, on the, for auto
for our industrial Amr, or
mobile robots. That's all
process to now. So we've started
to
all the costs of their autos.
Yeah, so all the autos all the
autos talking to our fleet, our
fleet manager, that's all based
on ROS two, since that's
exciting three, four years back.
And we were the, to the best of
my knowledge, we were one of the
first people to actually use
production or ROS to in a
production environment where,
you know, if it failed, you
would have angry phone calls. It
was, you know, it wasn't through
the entire stack, right? Like
our autonomy system is still
very ROS one based. Didn't
that's just like a legacy thing.
So we're talking about migration
plans now. But, but we actually
did an independent investigation
when we needed to really scale
up the amount of robots at a
given factory. And we found that
DDS was actually pretty good,
that DDS was a good direction to
go in and we said, okay, well
for if DDS is what's coming out
of this, then let's use ROS,
too. So we did that. And it's
Yeah, it's been great.
See, I'm looking, I always
forget what DDS stands for. data
distribution service, data
distribution service, and it's a
really, it's a flexible
middleware that allows you to
kind of interpolate between TCP,
which is lossless or not, like
it doesn't lose data, and UDP
which can lose data, but useful
for like walking robots and this
kind of thing, where you don't
want to hold it up if you miss
data. Things
Yeah, so there's
there's a bunch of stuff in
there which is just which was
already implemented, right? Like
quality of service quality of
service is a big thing. Some of
the other stuff was just more of
like how it was implemented. So
for example, with with ROS one,
both the c++ language, the c++
language bindings, or the c++
library and the Python library,
they both independently
implemented the ROS 1 protocol.
So it meant the with like so it
meant that 20 was sometimes
babies well twice as much
maintain and then sometimes you
had gotchas like especially
early on where it's like oh that
function and that function and
subscribe well that only works
if you use Python great well, or
vice versa. And so that was like
another big change that went
with ROS to was you know,
implementing everything at a you
know, implement, implementing
everything at a sink or the
bindings on top of DDS at a
single layer or a single
language then and then building
on top of that and then the
other thing that's nice about
that is that now it does make it
easier to notionally migrate to
some newer libraries like I know
rust has been talked about a lot
in the rust community these days
but yeah, there's there's all
sorts of other you know, little
things like ROS one was really
only built for a single very
complicated robot like one robot
that's doing very complicated
things and specifically the PRT
but then people started using it
for fleets and robots really
quickly or the other thing is
that people want it people want
to start running ROS on
microcontrollers for obvious
reasons and it's it's far easier
to shrink bras to down and then
I think yeah well they're
they're definitely
implementations of rosu that can
run on a microcontroller I'm not
sure how public they are it's
always difficult to remember
that so I won't mention any
right now but yeah, you can you
can fit like you can do a lot of
ROS on a microcontroller which
is now really interesting with
the ROS one days you would have
a package called ROS serial for
example which if you wanted to
talk to an Arduino you needed
you put this like lightweight
serial protocol on the ROS or on
the Arduino or you know any AVR
chip and you would basically
tell it that he was allowed to
use these know a few of these
language or a few of these these
message types but it wasn't
really ROS so now we're able to
do a lot more but there's a lot
more consideration as well for
you know real time real time
nature of it which opens up the
door to which opens up the door
to you know safety critical ROS
safety critical ROS
implementation is you know, hard
real time guarantees there's all
sorts of interesting stuff
there.
Audrow Nash: I would say I mean
and I read it, would you talk a
bit about the safety critical
ROS just kind of thing I don't
know too much about it. Right
says is it using standards
around cross where you see you
can guarantee some sort of
performance and if it's real
time you can deterministically
say this is going to happen at
this time or we know that this
task will complete and this kind
of thing.
The the thing which is
so obviously there's various
levels of you know, safety of
safety guarantees and up until
now and this is actually
including including our products
for example, a lot of the safety
happens at a lower layer under
ROS right on the motor
controllers are their safety
relays or their safety PLCs or
safety controllers programmed
and you know, some some safe art
for your jobs or whatever and
That's not that's usually not in
ROS now obviously your benefits
in so many reasons there are so
many ways to not having to do
that and the nice thing is so
Russ to on its own right now you
know it's not certified it's not
certified it's not you know if
you use everything there in ROS
you're going to be able to do
things like sort of like like
under a like a you know under
the ages need some sort or yeah
MISRA C language standards or
c++ or like ISO 26262 or IEC 61
508 like basically if you love
the standard libraries then you
you probably know what I'm
talking about do dash 178 is the
aerospace one so I need ROS ROS
to on its own because it
supports by definition so many
different languages like or so
many functions in full c++ then
it's not going to be certified
on its own right because you can
do things with c++ which are
considered not safe if you
really really try to be specific
like and you're trying to write
something that's you know safety
readable very high levels like
you know can run a nuclear power
plant levels and and what have
you that you need to avoid
things like any kind of dynamic
memory allocation ever. And so
obviously, if you if you if the
ROS community built a toolset
that didn't ever let you use any
dynamic memory allocation then
that would we'll just say not be
adopted because there's a lot of
places where that doesn't
matter. We actually built safety
rated systems and we have we've
made certain choices that
optimize towards time to market
at the expense of a little bit
of extra cost on the safety
system right but that means that
we can use the full gamut of c++
or Python functions now but
there are companies and there
are initiatives out there where
they have been able to trim it
down but the benefit of ROS 2 is
that it was is that you can at
least trim it down with ROS 1
that was just it was just on
tenable like you couldn't even
consider it but now you can't
like it's it's it's much more
technically possible thing to
build you know flight capable
control software that uses ROS 2
as a as a messaging pass as a
message passion framework
Audrow Nash: for example. And
then so you guys are migrating
your Clearpath robot, you
primarily run your ClearPath
robots with ROS 2 correct
Yeah all the all the
all the custom software we do is
ROS one right now
Audrow Nash: Is ROS 1. Any so
and you mentioned the auto where
you guys are using ROS 2
Ryan Gariepy: Sorry, sorry.
autoware as in the Sofer
autoware as in the community
initiative, we don't use that
what I was referring to was the
autonomous code that are auto
Ott Oh, autonomous mobile robots
use gotcha so that's like
everything there is remains you
know ROS one for the time being
I believe we have will be will
start supporting ROS 2 will
start supporting ROS 2 on some
research platforms in the near
future. But since I don't have
the schedule up in front of me,
I'm not going to I'm not going
to actually say those dates
because I like to support my
engineering team the the I don't
have a Twitter account where I
just I just randomly named
things on the on the the side of
our of our autonomy software, we
use ROS 2 for comms and we're
started we are starting to
consider the the migration
process we just finished the
Python three migration. So next
up is the ROS 1 to ROS 2
migration. But as you can
imagine, as you can imagine,
when you have several dozen and
software engineers writing code,
and you know, in this code is
also all going out to the
factories, you we can't stop
everything and just do a
migration of, you know,
Audrow Nash: five systems
business continues
of engineering. So I've been
talking with a lot of that stuff
if we and of course if we find
any, you know, shortcuts along
the way we'll we'll definitely
be short sharing them with the
community because I'm sure
there's other people in our, in
our situation,
for sure. Are you getting
comments from customers, or
people that are coming to you?
Or they're asking for ROS to or
how's the community?
Common? Yeah, it's
becoming more and more common I
can say from I can say from
generally looking at from
generally looking at you know,
the interests at ROSCon there's
a lot of people developing in
ROS tooth right now. And they're
developing you know, very real,
very serious things in ROS two.
We're and we're definitely
getting interest with ours. You
know, for example, One of the
very things, which is ROS 2,
which is very clearly ROS 2 is
that if you are going to
interact the API to our indoor
autonomy software, for example,
which is what runs all of our
industrial self driving vehicles
or industrial mobile robots.
That's all ROS. That's, that's
the API. So if you want to go
and talk to one of our talk to
one of our autos, ROS, who is
your only option?
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Now, let's
see worse, I would love to talk
about some other things. But
seeing that we don't have that
much time left, if we're trying
to hit an hour, I would love to
ask you some kind of larger
questions and get your
perspective on a few things. So
the first, you are saying you
caught the wave of robotics,
really, and you guys have stayed
on top of it now. And also, it
seems to me from talking now,
you guys also caught the open
source wave, which is really
exciting to be on both of those,
like, just you invested in open
source and the community and the
amount of code out there. And
the quality of code is just
grown and grown. How would you?
What advice would you give to a
startup that is looking to do a
hardware robotics startup, and
they're just beginning now, and
they don't have all this
infrastructure, or expertise.
So the first, the first bit of
advice I'd give is to not is to
know what you want, know what
value you're bringing to the
world. And partner as much as
possible around that value. And
what that means is, when we
started our auto division, we
had to build the robots from
scratch, we had to build the
autonomy from scratch, the fleet
manager, the UI, all of our
continuous integration systems,
we did a bunch of like internal
upgrades to like gazebo to make
it fit in continuous integration
systems. Like control software,
a lot like all of this stuff, we
did all that from scratch. But
now you can basically partner or
buy a lot of that stuff off the
shelf. And I would really
encourage any new startup in
robotics to start with that and
not try to build everything from
scratch, have a very good idea
of what they're bringing to the
table. And if I look at a Yeah,
if I look at the way, you know,
a typical startup, you're either
bringing a new technology to an
existing market, or you're
bringing a new market, or you're
you're, you're taking an
existing technology and applying
it to a new market. And so the
Airbnb and the Uber, for
example, like they were
bringing, they were, they had a
market hypothesis, and they were
bringing some some pretty
standard technology there. Like
at the time everyone had
smartphones. And obviously, we
all still have smartphones. But
us we had we had a newer
technology, which was being
brought to an existing market,
which was materials handling,
right? And I'm using the auto
example here. And the but you
want to pick one, right? So are
you. And these days, there's
just so much technology out
there. And really, I think a lot
of the opportunity is all these
new markets where you can apply
robotics. Yeah. And that means
not inventing the wheel along
the way. And, you know, part of
this I we spent a ton of time
earlier on in this conversation
talking about the ways that that
ClearPath engages with people.
So obviously we can support
those, those sorts of customers,
we've supported startups along
the way. If and, you know, what,
if if they're working with us,
and then the startup turns
around and says, You know what,
I've got an order for 1000. And
we're going to go and outsource
that stuff to let's say, jaybo,
for example, and because they're
going to give us the best deal.
Hey, that's cool. I don't I
don't have a problem with that.
Thank you. I'm glad you're
succeeding, right. But there are
companies like us, and then
there's all sorts of off the
shelf technology out there as
well, that can help you along
the way. So that would be the
real thing. I'd say to those new
robotics startups, like don't
try to do all the hardware and
all the autonomy and all the fee
management and all the
information that shows what you
can use what you can't like I
have I have spent those budgets.
I know how much it costs. And I
know Yeah, I know the stresses
that it brings you. And it's
it's not worth it. There's other
ways to do it. Now at least.
What do you think about this
idea as like platform as a
service or something like this
for a business model? And what I
mean by that would be, if I am a
robotics company, I'm going to
buy someone else's robot but my
own code on it, and then have it
do something useful. Do you
think that will be a reasonable
business model in the future
for robotics startups? Like
basically, so which are which
side is the startup honor? And
are they on this side of writing
the app?
Yes. Basically an app. Yeah,
right, I
think. Yeah, absolutely. I think
that's going to be I think
that's going to be the case, I
think, early on. It's going to
be combination of the app and
some tooling, not perhaps not as
complex as a robot, but that
you're going to get the
combination of the app and the
tooling. But I definitely think
that's going to be the case. And
we've seen this actually,
through the through the recent,
you know, year and a half, we've
seen a lot of companies with no
robotics expertise whatsoever
been able to build disinfection
applications, right. And that's
what they've done right? Is they
built a new application. They
built some hardware, they've
stuck it on a robot, and they're
good. So yeah, it's it's huge. I
think, I think, right? I think
for now, you're going to see it
as you're not going to
necessarily see app, like just
someone who writes apps and
makes money off the app. Or was
there even the app plus tooling,
I think there's still going to
be like, app plus tooling, plus,
you know, a sales effort on its
own right? Like you're, if
you're selling, if you make a
disinfection robot, can you've
done the app, you've built the
hardware, and then you're going
and you're going to sell it?
Right? So I don't think we're
yet as disser meat
disintermediate disintermediated
as Apple, Apple is, for example,
where they also bring you the
customers. But I definitely
think that the time for getting
a robot off the shelf and just
putting like, and just talking
to its API and throwing some
tools on it. That time is now
like, I think that is now two
years ago, it wasn't then but
but in the last year or so I
think we're over that tipping
point, which is really exciting.
I mean, I wouldn't I there's,
you're still there's still going
to be lacking in that the caveat
there is not every space, right?
Like there's no autonomy out
there, which can take like, you
know, what, a one or two killer
robot and run it around children
safely. I think that's not an
off the shelf tool yet. But
around a factory around a mine.
Now you can do that right now.
That's awesome. So you're saying
like two years ago, it wasn't
the case that we could do this?
Now? It seems to be good. Where
do you think it's going kind of
projecting out? Say the next two
years, next five years, 10
years, whatever it might be?
Where do you think the community
is going?
Well, I think in general, I
mean, I think in general, it's
this is funny, because I
actually asked a very similar
question, when I interview
people, for for jobs at our
company send out the tables have
turned, I think, I think in two
years, we're definitely gonna
see areas specific markets, like
us ours, for example, factories,
where putting robots in, or
mobile robots and, or
collaborative robots in is going
to be a pure business decision.
We have already seen this now,
where people have stopped asking
us to prove that the
localization is going to work,
for example, right? Like we
either say localization works,
and it does, or we say that it's
probably not going to work, and
we won't sell them, or we won't
try to sell it, right. Like
that's, but more and more, it's
going to be the same calculation
of always, it's just like, it's
just gonna be a business
decision, right? Like, robots
are just something that I buy
off the shelf. just purely
pragmatic, which to a lesser
extent, it's kind of that way
with robot arms still. But in
both cases, the other thing that
makes that possible, is the
significant decrease in
integration time. And cost. And
robot arms will still have a
little bit of a challenge there,
although many companies are
starting to are starting to work
around that. But you're going to
see very low integration times.
And because of that, it's going
to be a lot more commodity like
to just put some robots out in
the out in the world. Five
years, I mean, five years, I
think we're really going to
start to see robots in earnest
within the general public.
Again, maybe not, you know,
maybe not in the daycare, but
you are going to see them out in
earnest in the general public
doing useful things. So I don't
mean in science fair projects, I
don't mean little things like
that. And I know that there are
various trials, there are
various trials of delivery
robots and things like this, but
I think it'll be a there'll be
much more pervasive, much, much
more pervasive. And we will be
able to say that in certain
cases, and probably not on road
self driving, sorry to say, but
concerning cases, the safety
story is effectively salt, I
think we'll be able to say that.
And when you're there, you know,
what that means is over that,
that two to five year timeframe.
That's where the real app like
that, you know, the ecosystem
becomes really powerful. Because
you know, now we're at the point
where you can write apps for our
robots in a factory right now.
But first, you need to get into
the factory, but you can write
it right now. And but now, you
know, two years, five years from
now, they're really going to be
in front of everybody. So you'll
be able to script against one of
those robots. As as much as
everything else, and maybe what
I'll say is people might look at
this and say, Well, you know,
why are we saying this now?
Right? Like, didn't people say
this 10 years ago and 20 years
ago, whatever it like,
absolutely, they did, right.
Like there was a glut of robot
App Store companies. You know,
eight years ago, nine years ago,
roughly, around the time of the
turtlebot, one launch. And then
there was, you know, Microsoft
heavily invested in robotics
with Microsoft robotic studio.
And that was, that was a 2000s.
I think that was, but one of the
things that's happening now is
that all of those apps couldn't
rely on safe, reliable autonomy.
And then, and sort of think
about his assault
kind of thing. That's the that's
the bad word, right? Like,
yeah, you couldn't you couldn't,
you need to have a target, which
is useful, like a device target,
which is useful. And now, that
didn't used to be the case,
right? Like when these app
stores started, started up,
you're just kind of assuming
that a bunch of people on their
own, we're each going to come up
with safe, reliable autonomy.
And that's, that's hard when
you're moving, you know,
hundreds of kilos around. But
now now, no, I think we're in a
much better place like that
autonomy is well, I have, you
know, many million reasons,
million hours of operation to
say that this is possible,
right?
Hmm. That is exciting. So
wrapping up, do you have any? Do
you have a Twitter or how can
people find you or any any
public links, you'd like to
share anything?
They can find me on LinkedIn? I
unfortunately, do not. I am not
part of the the Twitter,
whatever, whatever, whatever
it's being called. But yeah, I'm
not on Twitter. I'm not on
Instagram, but they can find me
on LinkedIn. And in my email,
which which will be needed to
connect is Ryan at clear
path.ai. So they can also find
me on that email. But LinkedIn
would be preferred, I believe.
Awesome. Okay, I've enjoyed
this. Thank you.
Thank you very much.
That's all we have for you
today. I enjoyed Ryan's answer
to where thinks robotics will be
in two to five years. Where do
you think robotics will be in
two to five years? Let us know
in the comments on sensing
gackt.com or discourse. Thank
you again to Open Robotics for
being our founding sponsor.
Bye, everyone.