Audrow Nash: Hi, everyone,
welcome to the sense think act
podcast. I'm Audrow Nash, your
host and a software engineer at
Open Robotics. In today's
episode, I speak with Dave
Coleman, CEO at PickNik, which
does engineering services and
motion planning. Motion planning
is the problem of moving
something from one place to
another, such as moving a robot
from one location to another, or
picking up an object and placing
it somewhere else. This can be
made more difficult if you try
to avoid collisions. For
example, if you had something
beneath a table and want to lift
it up over the table, you have
to go around the table. And as
you can imagine, this is a
fundamental problem in robotics.
And Dave has been involved in
move it a motion planning
framework that has built on top
of robot operating system or ROS
for a number of years, and has
created picnic to do engineering
services around motion planning.
We talked about his motion
planning or the motion planning
framework, move it, how PickNik
came to be there work with NASA,
and a paid service called
movement studio that hopes to
help the problem of supervised
autonomy. And we teased the idea
of move it three. I really
enjoyed talking to Dave, he is a
fun person to interview. And I
find that he has a great
perspective on robotics and open
source, probably in no small
part because of the diverse
problems that they work on at
picnic, and his time that he has
been in the robotics community.
I hope you enjoy.
So Dave, would you start off by
introducing yourself.
Dave Coleman: Yeah. I'm Dave
Coleman, CEO of PickNik robotics
and a longtime supporter of open
source robotics contributor to
ROS and MoveIt. Glad to be here
today.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. To start
off as a general overview, would
you just tell us about move it?
What problems does it solve and
how long it's been going?
Dave Coleman: Sure. Move it is a
framework developed to do motion
planning primarily for robotic
arms, but also for the full
kinematics of your robot. It's
had some success and walking in
mobile bases, even by esoteric
things like quite like flying
robots and submersible so all
over the place move it's been
applied. And it's the problem of
how to motion plan your, your
joints through space, so you
don't hit things and that you
can do useful things like
manipulation and grasping. And
your second question, it's been
around since pic. 2010 was when
development begun, I think 2011
was the beta release of move it
and this was developed at Willow
Garage. Same place that ROS was
developed, it was developed with
the PRT program. Sasha Cheetah
was the program manager at the
time of that project. And yeah,
Willow Garage eventually closed,
but it lives on.
Audrow Nash: Let's see. And I
know we said we talked about
kind of you're coming into this
a bit later in the interview,
but might as well get into it
now. How did you get involved?
So it started in 2010 ish? at
Willow Garage. When did you come
along?
Dave Coleman: I was an intern at
Willow Garage. Willow was very
clever and having a lot of
interns huge program. So I guess
I'm not that special. And that
the CEO at the time, Steve
cousins said that the intern
program was a way of spreading
ROS. I like like a virus, he
wanted us to go back to our
research groups and get everyone
to use ROS and I think it was
overall really effective
strategy. And so I was certainly
part of that I brought ROS and
particularly move it back to our
research group at CU Boulder,
Colorado. And and so I was
developing some of the initial
parts of move it together with
Johan sukan. And the team. And I
kind of decided to base the rest
of my research during my
graduate program around move it
and kind of did a lot of open
source contributions to
Audrow Nash: it. Mm hmm. How did
that look like doing a PhD but
also contributing largely to the
open source part of this head?
Like, it seems like the
incentives are slightly
different for what the PhD would
want and what an open source
really useful tool with. One How
did that go? Do
Dave Coleman: I think I think
you know the answer this
question. leading question. I
think it worked well for me,
because working at open source
robotics gives you so much hands
on experience. It's like
relevant to industry relevant to
getting jobs after the fact. So
I think it's a great way to do
That kind of sharpen your role
or experience. However, if your
main motive is to publish
papers, then it could be
distracting. Maybe just I don't
have any experience about this
possibly could distract you from
publishing enough. But on the
flip side, if done well, there's
been a lot of examples where you
do some pretty cool research and
you publish the open source code
to it. I encourage everyone
listening to do that if you're
in academia and and you can
actually increase your citations
because people within convention
market and compare it against
other methods. And so there's
there's definitely advantages to
doing both.
Audrow Nash: Yes, for sure. And
then how did you go from PhD
student contributing to this to
now leading up to kind of taking
on the initiative yourself.
Dave Coleman: I just looked it
up. By the way, movie beta was
officially released in 2013. And
that same year, that will close
to actually and there was just
kind of a leadership void in the
movement. I think the the
project was kind of floundering,
and there are a lot of pull
requests piling up and not being
merged in. There was a little
bit of support from SRI
International after Willow
close, but it didn't last for
very long. And so I was
encouraged by a number of people
that Open Robotics and others
that were had been at Willow
Garage who had been involved in
move it that I kind of like try
revitalize it. So Michael
Ferguson was a big player and
encouraging it to be
revitalized, I think he would
the time was starting, but the
precursors to Fetch, and so that
he was interested in using Uber
for that. So he and I plan will
move a day, the first one ever
and so that was a big Kickstart
to getting a community kind of
excited about moving again. And
conveying that it is a thing and
a big part of that was getting
the website updated, so that it
was just showing that the latest
things happening and with
community. And there were two
other maintainers at the time,
who were still involved, Robert
hash and Michael corner. And and
so we had our first maintainer
meeting, I think it was kind of
three or four of us. And we're
like, yeah, let's, let's see if
we can get this thing flying.
Again, I think that was a what
Michael said. And sure enough,
what we did we you know, to keep
an open source project is just
responding to pull requests fast
enough and reliably. And if you
have enough people, so myself,
Michael and Robert, responding
to pull requests, giving decent
reviews, keeping the codebase
stable, you'll eventually build
a community assuming that the
software does anything useful
for people. And that's exactly
what we did. One of the big
issues I first took was to put
our first continuous integration
in the place which nowadays
various Bordeaux belaz. A, but
like back at Willow Garage, that
was still kind of cutting edge.
And we didn't have ci yet. So
Jonathan Bourne helped me get
Travis working. And then for the
first time, we can merge things
more confidence not breaking
down,
Audrow Nash: just to be clear,
so ci is continuous integration,
and that's running your tests
that test that the code is
working correctly.
Dave Coleman: Right? Yeah. And
he only went on your test that
you have tests and and we've
over the years, gotten the test,
better remove it, but there's
still not enough and at the
time, there wasn't not much at
all. And so not only the test it
just test the builds, and that
you can recreate the build, the
dependencies are also correctly
and, and so one of the big goals
of adding ci was reducing the
burden for the volunteer
maintainers. And so you just
want to get as many as much
automation and bots helping so
we, I implemented like a clang
format style guide enforcer,
and, and those sorts of things
so that the burden of code
reviews got easier for us. And
you know, you don't have to
always download the pull request
and test it locally. Maybe for
complex ones, you still want to
do that. But you can just review
and say this looks right. The ci
says it works. So let's merge
it. And that's a way of
leveraging automation to
Audrow Nash: reduce what we have
to do. Okay, so you did a lot of
kind of this important
infrastructure that made it
easier for you guys to go and
review pull requests quickly so
that the community can kind of
build it up? Is that really the
way to look at it with the
community contributing a lot,
and you're kind of just like,
managing it so that it stays
working? Or you guys do your own
feature development?
Dave Coleman: Yeah, yeah. It is
the way I kind of look at it.
There's different models. So
some open source projects,
there's just one or two or maybe
a small lab group of people who
are doing all the actual feature
development. And then everyone
else is kind of just benefiting
and taking and maybe submitting
a bug report but not knowing how
to fix it. Personally, I've
always taken the approach of
this project has too many too or
too much code. There's too many
features like I can't do all
this myself. So we're going to
leverage the community and
there's pluses and minuses to
putting your energy towards
fixing the problems versus it
making easier for others to fix
the problems. And you know, it's
not as simple as it sounds,
adding people in because they
have to then spend the time
understanding the codebase And
like, like dissecting it and
having quality reviews. So
there's a there's a bit of both,
I definitely added a lot of
features just as I was working
on my PhD, I was like, Oh, I
need this feature, I'm going to
get this merged in. So
Audrow Nash: gotcha. Okay. So
that's, it's an interesting
approach to focus mostly, are
focused largely on making it
easier for people to contribute.
And it's a cool approach, I do
see what you mean, when the code
base grows to be so large that
you need to make sure that like,
basically, you just facilitate
it. Rather than going deep into
adding additional users, you
can't do it yourself, because
it's too large. So it seems like
a good scalable approach to make
this kind of thing, especially
when you guys have a few
reviewers
Dave Coleman: have we been able
to grow the number of reviewers,
we call them maintainers over
the years, and that that's an
important aspect is encouraging
newcomers to get more involved
and get eventually give them the
the access to have merge access,
right access, and we actually
set up a program, I'd love to
share real quick to help with
that, to bring in beginners
more, we set up a core
contributor program. And the
idea being that when we see
people who are getting really
involved, and maybe they don't
have quite the in depth skills
yet, then we don't fully trust
them. But we want to really
appreciate what they're doing
and set them up to become a
maintainer in the future, we'll
add them as a core contributor
and put them on our website. So
they get some credit for that.
And, you know, I'm not sure if
recently we've been using that
enough, but it's been a plus,
you can see it on our website on
the on the people.
Audrow Nash: How does it compare
to like an internship or
something, it's something
someone does on their own time,
and you try to guide them or
mentor them a little bit more,
or work.
Dave Coleman: It's pretty
informal. It's not as nearly as
structured as an internship, I
mean, one, there's no no pay,
and most engineering
internships, you do get paid.
But it's more like if you were a
grad student working on motion
planning for your research, and
you know how to use move it and
you're just a rising star, then
we'll start off saying, like,
you're awesome, be a core
contributor. And then after a
few months or a year, if they
continue to, like really
demonstrate that they understand
the code base, and then they're
capable of maintaining the
quality standards and so forth.
We would invite them to become,
you know, a full ride access
maintainer. So is there a
mentorship? Like, I think anyone
who gets involved in that will
get mentorship via pull request
reviews, I think this is often
undervalued, but the time that
people put, so you say I want to
change this code. And if there
are maintainers, who decide to
respond to it, they will spend
their time showing you like, why
certain code patterns or bugs or
memory leaks, like helping you
improve your code quality over
time. So that's a great way to
get mentorship. It actually was
one of the ways I learned was
just watching my recruiter get
reviewed. And also I watched
other people's code get
reviewed. And I learned a lot
that way. Because I'd be like,
Oh, I didn't see that issue.
Next time. I'll know better to
like, look out for that,
Audrow Nash: huh, yeah, that's
been a lot of my experience to
that code reviews are it because
it's, it's line by line through
the thing through the code
change that you have. And then
they can critique you on the
approach or anything. So it's a
really good way to get feedback.
And it can be done
asynchronously. So you can take
a while to like, understand the
comments, and get lots of
different approaches. So I've
personally found that very
valuable at Open Robotics, code
reviews, and even community code
reviews, which are always
amazing when someone steps in
from the community.
Dave Coleman: Yeah, totally,
there's just got to be, yeah,
sometimes have a thick skin
because there's a lot of code
reviewed. And sometimes, I'm
sure I've been guilty of this,
like you review it really
quickly, and you don't like
cherry code it so much, you're
just like, not listening to me.
And then I've encouraged people
at the movement maintainer group
to still always say thank you
for this contribution. It's kind
of a summary. Even if we've
like, totally red line and torn
apart, you know, so you gotta
gotta just be aware that we're
just trying to help you and keep
the code quality up so that
future people can improve it
Audrow Nash: as well. Yeah, at
Open Robotics, we talked about
how a lot of times in text, it
seems to be a lot more harsh,
whatever you say. So then kind
of being aware of that while
giving feedback. But you're
right, when there's a lot of
code to review. It's like, it's,
it's tough to have really, you
have to get through it. And so
you might make a comment. That's
a little rough. That's awesome,
though. Are you so you have this
program to bring on people who
are contributing and give them a
little more responsibility
within the organization. How has
it been to grow from your core
group of three to now you guys
around 30 employees if I'm
correct, or
Dave Coleman: Yeah, I do want to
differentiate the new community
project and my company picnic
are not they're not the same
set.
Audrow Nash: Okay, let's, let's
talk. So let's explain picnic, I
guess.
Dave Coleman: Yeah. But to
finish the finish that first
thought. So Michael and Robert,
for example, they are a
professor or a PhD student and
individ respectively, in
Germany, on affiliated with
picnic, and yet they are major
contributors to the project,
there's a number of other
maintainers unaffiliated with
picnic like Felix, who does
understand a lot of great stuff.
So maybe half at this point of
the maintainers are from picnic
and I, I'm proud of that. And
I'm glad that we've been able to
hire people and get them excited
enough about open source that
they're like, major contributors
to the project now. like hitting
Kaiser has been a big lead for
the movie project Tyler. And so
yeah, there's, there's a mix,
and we want to make sure that
the movie project remains
something separate from picnic,
although there are just plenty
of overlap as well.
Audrow Nash: There's a lot of
overlap. So can you tell me a
bit about the two? So move it is
the open source, motion planning
framework? And picnic? is a
consulting and research company
around this area? Or how would
you think of it?
Dave Coleman: Yeah, we'd be
called reasonable consulting. In
the early days, I've actually
tried to distance myself from
that word, because I prefer the
word engineering services, it
comes off more as like we want
to co develop or develop for you
robotic software, using movement
using ROS using other
perception navigation packages.
And so you're not just like
advising you on how to do it. I
mean, that is a small part of
what we do. But it's not our
main goal. By working with your
with other companies and other
teams, we do kind of a consult
with them, but we do it through
working side by side.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, so it's
developing a lot rather than
just advising. And that's why
you like this engineering
services term better than
consulting. We're more hands on,
hands on. And does it? So if you
use the two different terms,
does it change the types of
clients that come to you? Or
what's the or it's how you think
of yourself, or why
Dave Coleman: it changes the
mean, words are important and
changes the mindset when, when a
potential client comes to us.
It's not that we're going to get
on a meeting with you once a
week for an hour and discuss the
best way of using moving we do
offer feasibility studies. And
those have been very popular
with our customers. But we hope
that after the feasibility study
that they would then hire us to
actually implement a lot or some
of it all of it, you know, some
combination of that with their
team. And so that's kind of our
consulting offering is the
feasibility study.
Audrow Nash: I see. And then so
now, a lot of this is it. The
business model is something
like, if they allow you to open
source, whatever you're
developing for move it, or for
them for move it, then they
don't like it's incentivized
kind of you charge them less if
what you are doing can be open
source, or it's a feature you
want, or how does a How does it
work? we don't we
Dave Coleman: don't have a model
like that. We were pretty clear
and contracts. And we have a lot
of discussions with with lawyers
that when you hire a picnic,
some portion of it is going to
be open source. And the only
question is how much and we've
had some projects that
everything is open sourced, and
we're delighted. But in reality,
we don't expect that that's not
normal. It's it's typically that
like, we're helping them build
out their application specific
IP, intellectual property. And
it's building off of move it or
ROS or other components of the
whole open source device
ecosystem. And we insist that
bug fixes or small features,
hooks, just little things that
like that really shouldn't be
anything different shitting
them, those get open sourced.
And you know, we if it's like a
thing that originated in, move
it or in ROS, and we're just
like slightly improving, it will
likely open source that. But if
it's like some fancy new
algorithm for a particular type
of application, then absolutely
like, if our customer wants that
proprietary, we're not, we're
not here to like, be be like do
to zealot about it. Huh. Okay.
The key is that we don't want to
fix the same bug over and over
Audrow Nash: again. That would
be ridiculous. Yeah, for sure.
And also, it's nice for the
whole community to just benefit
from any work you do with these
things.
Dave Coleman: Yeah, it's kind of
like giving it back paying it
forward type of thing of like,
you're benefiting from all this
prior work that's saved you tons
of r&d hours and like bootstrap,
or program you have and and now
we just ask that some of that be
contributed back to the next
person or, you know, like one of
the big moments we have about
the question of like open
sourcing versus like forking
open source project, is that you
don't want to take on
maintenance and ownership. That
project in the future, but if
you stay with the mainland
project, then companies like
picnic and Open Robotics and,
and other contributors will take
care of that for you maintaining
the basics of bug fixes and new
opera operating systems and
patches. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: And just to be
clear with the terminology, so
when you're forking a project,
you're taking it and you're
saying, This is unlike I'm
taking it in its current state,
and I'm gonna go move it
somewhere else. And then I'm
going to work on it and maintain
so you can hide it, what you
actually contribute to, if
you're some company, I'm sure
that they diverged. Oh, totally
sure.
Dave Coleman: You really can't
see it typically? Nope.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. So it's nice
having it all in the open, so
they can just grab the main
movement branch or main movement
repository and then apply fixes
directly to that and benefit
everyone. That's it seems like
the big argument for open source
to me.
Dave Coleman: Yeah, and it's
like, it's not just moving
everyone, but it's benefiting
the individual companies making
these decisions, because they're
not taking on the ownership.
They say that like, once you
like writing a line of code,
that the cost of that for like
an engineer to do that is only a
fraction of the overall cost of
that code over its lifetime.
Because for every like hour
spent coding, you're gonna spend
several more hours maintaining
it bug fixing in over the
lifetime of your product, or
your robotics project, or what
have you. So it's really
reducing your maintenance cost
over the long term.
Audrow Nash: Yep. Yeah. And time
and I don't know, energy and
everything. There's just so many
things, even like running up
your continuous integration
time, because you have to test
more things which make it more
difficult, as well as just
engineering hours to fix bugs.
Dave Coleman: It's a good point.
And we're talking a lot about
like industry users of open
source software. But you know,
there's a lot of other reasons
and motivations why students
graduate students would but
choose to contribute to open
source as well. So there's,
there's both worlds, I just want
to
Audrow Nash: want to say, what
is what are some of the
motivators for people in
academia, students to contribute
to open source,
Dave Coleman: it's building up
your portfolio, your experience,
getting that mentorship, we were
talking about, kind of being a
part of something bigger,
there's, there's this just a
sense of like, seeing that you
contribute to code that's being
used all over the world, and
being able to brag about that.
And like for many people, maybe
they haven't ever contributed to
real software before. And so
this is like, kind of a good
first step in their career. So
there's those sorts of things,
but really, there's a chance to
still learn a lot.
Audrow Nash: Hmm, totally agree.
Yeah, my experience at open
robotics. Really, I get a lot of
satisfaction from contributing
to things that I know that other
people are using. So I agree
with that. So okay, going back a
little bit. picnic, when did
picnic come along? in the scheme
of things, so you were
contributing and your PhD to
this? And it was you in a small
group of other maintainers? How,
where did picnic come from?
Dave Coleman: It was 2015. And I
like yourself. But recently, I
was an intern. And I was
interning at Google. So pretty
lucky place to be at Google
robotics to be exact. And after
the internship ended, there was
a group there who wanted I'd
help them use move it for some
projects. may actually say too
much here. But they wanted more
of that they wanted more
support. And they asked for
another internship. I said, No,
I'm not going to. I've had a lot
of internships. And so they
said, Do you want to consult for
Google? And I said, Of course I
do. And so that is what bogen
picnic. And technically, like we
had been so picnic, the term
originated from a team at the
University that I was attending
for the Amazon picking
challenge. And so it can
challenge picnic. A friend just
helped me coined this term. So I
asked the team, I was the team
lead. I was like, Hey, can I use
this term for doing some
consulting? And everyone's like,
no problem. So that's kind of
the origin story.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And so it
was just you at the beginning
consulting for Google for some
project that use move it. And
you grew from there to now 30
people or so. Yep, kind of
thing. Yeah. That's exciting. So
2015 it started and we're in
2021. Yeah,
Dave Coleman: that's also I had
to finish my PhD. So I
graduated, took a little time
off to travel. And when I came
back, I just kept getting
requests from different
companies that were using move
it for support. And so I'd fly
out to different companies and
do more consulting but also a
lot of coding. And I realized I
had too much work and I made the
pivotal decision to bring on
some co founders and that
certainly changed things. Spent
a lot of work since then an
energy company. But it's been
really fun and exciting also.
Audrow Nash: Hmm. Let's see. So
what have been some of the
projects that you've worked on
with picnic? Like just the
nature of it. So the kinds of
things you can solve with move
it in less abstract form?
Dave Coleman: Sure, yeah, I will
avoid company names because
India is get tricky. And we're
on a public forum here. But one
of so like, logistics was our
second project, like warehouse
bin picking type of stuff. The
next one was robot cooking. And
then a really big one for us was
cooking. Yeah, you know, like,
during things cutting things
like home chef.
Audrow Nash: That's cool. Oh,
yeah, there's
Dave Coleman: like, there's a
couple a couple companies out
there doing this. Yeah, we've
actually worked with a lot of
them. But that was one of our
early projects. And, yeah, we
know, all of our bigger projects
has been surgical, robotics,
and, you know, move. It's been
used to do surgery. But, of
course, they had to do a lot of
rewriting of certain segments to
make it FDA certifiable. And,
like, move, it's a really great
starting point for some
applications. But sometimes you
have to, like, do a lot of
shaping it to be something
that's safe enough for human
use. So I don't recommend you
use move it out of the box to do
surgery. Don't mistake me here.
But yeah, we work with this
company for a long time. It was
a really fun project. And and
since then, like the application
we use it for, it just
astonishes me how diverse it's
been since then. I mean, we're,
it's we've worked for several
space applications, several
underwater robotics, like doing
manipulation with oil and gas.
telehealth because all over the
place we're doing one of our big
projects now is robot farming.
So harvesting of fruits and
vegetables, you name it, like
we've probably been involved.
Audrow Nash: That's so cool. And
it's because motion planning is
just such a fundamental robotics
problem. And you guys have a
bunch of really great tools
around there.
Dave Coleman: Yeah, it turns
out, like, even though you don't
see robot arms used a lot
outside of the factory, I think
you're gonna see a lot more of
that very soon, because we're
working with a lot of early
stage r&d groups, whether
corporate or startup, to use
robots for new applications. But
it turns out that robot arms are
extremely useful because the
whole world is designed for
human arms. And that's what
we're trying to mimic.
Audrow Nash: Hmm. Okay, that's
really cool. And I actually
towards the end of the
interview, I want to ask about
where you think things are
going. Because I assume from all
the consulting, that you have an
incredible idea about kind of
where things are headed, because
you're seeing these early
applications, which is so cool.
But the Okay, so you started
this now? Congratulations,
you're having larger customers,
you mentioned that you have a
collaboration with NASA. Would
you talk a little bit about
this? Sure.
Dave Coleman: Yeah, thank you
for for bringing that up. I just
think space is really cool. This
is really cool. It seems like
there's this big movement, at
least in the US. But I think
it's pretty international of
commercializing space, it's
becoming more privatized,
there's a lot of startups there
was the X PRIZE a few years ago.
And some companies came out of
that, like that Virgin Galactic
flight just recently came out of
that. And just in general, now
that SpaceX has made flights,
getting stuff to space, so much
cheaper and more regular, we're
seeing a lot of other
applications. And so a lot of
companies are working on
satellite assembly is a big one.
And using robot arms for that
doing more experiments in the
space station or in the future
gateway station being worked on.
Audrow Nash: I don't I don't
know very much about space
applications, or the different
ways that companies are trying
to make a profit out of space.
So you said satellite assembly
that's on Earth, or is that in
space? Oh, wow. So you send up
the components and then build it
out up there? Yeah. Okay.
Dave Coleman: Yeah, I think one
of the big motivations is that
things have to currently
compress into these little
rocket modules. But sometimes
you want to build things bigger
than that. And so you need to
assemble in space.
Audrow Nash: Hmm. Okay. And that
would be used for a bunch of
applications. Like taking photos
of the earth or maybe sending
internet places like starlink or
whatever it might be this kind
of thing.
Dave Coleman: Yeah. It I guess I
don't know. a ton about like,
What? What I mean, yeah,
assembling satellites for all
the normal cases what you just
said,
Audrow Nash: Yep. Okay, and then
what other applications were you
saying? first base.
Dave Coleman: So the doing more
things without astronauts in
space like on the space station
so NASA has had this long
standing program to have robots
augment the astronauts time
astronauts are wildly expensive
to send up like every hour of
their work day their their
billable rate is very very high
now because because of just all
the training all the fuel Yeah,
Audrow Nash: infrastructure
would you I mean, I bet it's
like comically large how
expensive they are per hour what
would you do about what it was
but it's like $10,000 an hour or
is it way more than that?
Dave Coleman: I wish I had that
on my head
Audrow Nash: okay so what are
what is it that you guys are
doing? Are you looking for a
number
Dave Coleman: Yeah, I am looking
for a number but i don't i don't
see it so they're using move it
right now on the this program
called the Robonaut which is in
the space station. And to like
help do some more than
maintenance tasks of the
station. Like cleaning surfaces
or like just flipping switches
just like things that like maybe
aren't worth the astronauts time
Audrow Nash: would you describe
Bravo not because it's a pretty
wild looking thing.
Dave Coleman: Yeah, it's it's
very anthropomorphic, it like to
look like a human, for the most
part. So it's got fully
dexterous fingers. It's got a
head that can rotate. Look
around, it's got like a chest
just like a human. The legs
however, are a bit creepier.
They're think more like yes,
spider legs, there's less. But
because you're in zero G, you
don't need legs that can walk
like on Earth, you just need
something to grab on to
handrails. And so that part's a
little creepier. And I am not
the definitive source of the
status of this program. But
it's, I think it's a little bit
winding down. And they're like,
revisiting what kind of robots
best for space. And, and so for
the gateway, which is a new
station being launched soon, to
orbit the moon, one of the big
needs, there is a inner vehicle
robot that can take care of the
station when it's unmanned,
because they aren't planning on
having a human there. All times
of the year, I think closer to
like four months of the year,
it'll be manned. Eight months a
year, the robots got to take
care of the place. And so we're
currently on a grant involved
with that.
Audrow Nash: Hmm, so it'll be
the robo Robo robot on this down
the gateway, which is orbiting
the moon. And it will be taking
care of a lot of operations by
doing what a human might do if
they were on it. Is it going to
be tele operated? Or is it going
to be largely autonomous or?
Dave Coleman: Yeah, I love this
topic. I think teleoperated to
me, the definition of that is
really drive by wire, you've got
a joystick, or a mouse, or these
days, a VR headset with two hand
controllers. And you're telling
the robot what to do like
basically one to one. And you
know, it's not exactly one to
one because oftentimes, the
robot arm may have a different
kinematic morphology than a
human. And so the way it maps
out your command might be
slightly different. But for the
most part, you know, I'm talking
about like Cartesian control,
which is like effector control.
But for the most part, you're
just you tell what to do. That's
totally up to me. Yeah, so
Audrow Nash: you move like it
would be like moving joysticks
around, like the VR things. And
the robot would do pretty much
the same motion, but it might do
slightly different things.
Because its joints might be
different than humans. Exactly.
Okay.
Dave Coleman: Yeah. And so that
breaks down when you're on the
moon. And particularly if you're
going to Mars, which is the next
stepping stone for the space
program, as Ilan, lets us all
know. Because latency and
bandwidth issues, delays in
time. So I think to the moon
it's like three or four seconds,
and to the Mars to Mars, it's
like several minutes. Don't
quote me on this, I don't
memorize numbers, as you can
tell. So that becomes really
annoying and frustrating to
control something with that
amount of lag because you send a
command and then you have to
wait round trip for it to come
back. So we're very interested
technic, we're developing some
technology that is a mix of
fully autonomous and tele
operated. So what's between
those two extremes? And that's,
yeah,
Audrow Nash: that's what you're
trying to figure out, or that's
what we're proposing is what
we're working on right now. So
is it like a higher level thing
where you can delegate tasks
like at a task level, you say,
Go select this, go do your thing
here and it will kind of get
over so if it's flip a switch
will, the robot will go over
there and position itself and
perhaps flick it, but you've
directed that it should do that?
So it's like a higher level
command and I think we're, Ah,
Dave Coleman: that's, this goes
under a number of names. But
supervisor autonomy is maybe the
most common one where you You
are in such
Audrow Nash: an oxymoron. But I
get it. Yeah,
Dave Coleman: it does. So you
tell the robot, hey, here's a
high level task. And then you're
kind of observing the robot as
it goes about doing it with the
understanding that maybe the
robots not quite smart enough to
fully do the task. Because these
are just hard problems. They're
kind of unsolved so far,
especially when you're in
unstructured environments. I've
had arguments about whether a
space station like the ISS is
unstructured or not, it's kind
of an academic argument. Because
I know my mind, these things are
highly engineered things where
they have exact computer models
before they get launched. You
look at videos on like YouTube
of astronauts, giving you a tour
of the Space Station. It's
really striking how many bags
and wires and new experiments
are just floating in the middle
of the way. And so actually,
it's an extremely complex
environment. So for a robot to
be able to fully autonomously
navigate this ever changing
environment to do useful things.
It Yeah, it's hard for today's
algorithms. And so the AI going
back to supervise autonomy,
there's a human there to help it
along when needed, but really
minimizing how much intervention
is needed from that from the
human.
Audrow Nash: Okay, that's really
cool. Do you think that this
will be a larger thing in
robotics? Like the supervise
autonomy? Do you think before, I
mean, we see it with like, like,
you can think of like Tesla and
its self driving as being
somewhat supervised autonomy,
you sit there in the seat, and
it drives for you until it
cannot handle whatever's going
on. And then it gives you back
control. Do you think that this
is going to be a larger trend
before robots are like actually
capable of exactly those things
entirely?
Dave Coleman: It's exactly what
I think. So to Tesla versus
whammo versus the other crews,
self driving car companies, they
all have slightly different
approaches to how they're doing
autonomous vehicles. But I think
it's really interesting that
Weibo and a number of the other
ones, they've all kind of
realized that in order to get to
L five, autonomy, actually, you
need a remote operator that
occasionally can help this, like
the robo taxi, get unstuck. So
you know, a lot of the prototype
or concept vehicles that I think
are going to be out soon, they
may or may not have a student
steering wheel. And so if you
think about a taxi, and maybe
the seats are facing inward,
there's no one there to take
over. If the robot just the car
really gets stuck. A Tesla has a
steering wheel still, and
they're not. They're a different
player. So I would, they're a
different category of autonomy
in my opinion. But the idea with
like way, Mo is that there's
someone in a call center who
maybe isn't watching every turn
every step of the way. But when
it's needed, they can be, you
know, called in to give the
robot a little more
understanding, like, Hey, this
is a construction site. We
haven't quite seen this problem
before. But this is what I want
you to do. And the robot can
then go, Okay, I'm going to
maneuver around this. So that's
proving out to be a necessary
need in self driving cars. And I
think it's also going to be more
and more in need as we get robot
arms outside of factories,
Audrow Nash: huh? Yeah, I bet
you're right. It's a very
interesting thing. Because you
can kind of augment where, like
robots can do maybe 80% of it,
or 70% of it. But then there's
some part of it that people just
need to be there for their
judgment. And so we can buffer.
Dave Coleman: I think you kind
of hinted at it a second ago,
like, eventually, we won't need
this again, like we're gonna get
the machine learning algorithms
and the software and all of it
so intelligent that the human
will be then removed completely.
But there's been some
interesting research about like,
how AI is harder than we think.
And we've hit some critical
limits of current machine
learning techniques. And this is
why the self driving car
industry has been so delayed.
And so I think it's going to be
longer than we think like, you
kind of have to get general
intelligence, General AI in
order to completely eliminate
the human from it. And I'm not
super stoked personally about
even achieving that, because
then you have the whole super
intelligence thing. And what if
it gets smarter than us? And
Audrow Nash: Terminator? Yeah,
yeah. All that stuff. Yeah, I
don't know. It is all very
interesting. And I do from my
own, like, foray into machine
learning and things I have
trouble understanding how the
metaphors can get to a more
general intelligence at the
moment,
Dave Coleman: which is probably
good for humanity. Maybe Yeah.
Audrow Nash: But Alright, so
then your, how long have you
guys been on this NASA project?
Dave Coleman: It's actually just
the past year so not not even a
year, just under a year. We've
been involved in this. But we
recently got our next phase of
grant money with them and
Exactly. So So that's we're
doing this for NASA. But we're
also starting to do this more
and more with our other
customers, using open source,
move it, but also developing
some higher level task planning
proprietary aspects of it that
we, because we've had some
compasses customers asked us to
build this kind of one off. And
now we're making kind of a
general solution for this
overall supervisor autonomy
problem. So I think that's going
to really unlock a lot of
applications in the next decade
Audrow Nash: or two. Yeah, I've
been I don't know, I've been
thinking that this is one of the
big problems on the front of
robotics like, and I think
you're hitting on the head and
actually doing it, which is very
cool. Okay, yeah, making it so
that you can delegate at a
higher level for robots what to
do, and then have some sort of
thing come in and help babies.
It just it seems so unnecessary.
Dave Coleman: I think there's an
interesting, interesting pattern
about past robot companies and
how they've gotten around this
and why maybe there isn't a
solution out there for this
exactly, is that typically, you
choose an application, I'm going
to solve like a robot, that was
a good example here that picks
widgets from a bin, that's just
right, this is a big one, right
now, a lot of companies going
after like, a mixed parcel box.
And you can make a bunch of
assumptions and fixture stuff,
and do just enough autonomy and
AI and like computer vision to
solve that problem really well
and reliably. And those those
solutions that keep coming to
market. So like in the 70s,
maybe the problem was, how do we
spray paint a car really
reliably? And they came up with
exactly the tools for that. And
so we keep pushing slowly, the
envelope of a robot doing a very
fixed thing for harder problems.
But and there's there's a lot of
benefits, like fully autonomous
has a better return on
investment in terms of like,
you're totally eliminating the
job versus like still requiring
a human to be kind of assisting
and sometimes, yep, I just think
that's not going to go all the
way to like a robot that can
navigate through your your
office, your home, like outside,
in a wreck and just like assist
or space, in particular, for any
arbitrary problem you throw at
it and have it be able to
achieve it. So that's, I think
this was me next?
Audrow Nash: Yes, yeah, even the
modern ones, it's like, they're
somewhat like the picking the
widgets out of the bin. The
approaches seem to be somewhat
flexible to variation. But it's
like you throw a different bin
or a new widget in, and then you
have to reprogram everything and
add new, like hacks or less
general solutions to get it to
work again.
Dave Coleman: And maybe yet,
maybe machine learning
techniques, the difficulty of
adding a new widget is gone way
down. Maybe I think it's
probably really easy to
arbitrary object, train it
really quickly. Yeah, but he
still if you ask him to then,
like, paint a car or do a
different, totally different
type. It's just not going to be
Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Yep. Yeah, that's a
better way to phrase it. It's
just if you choose a different
task, it is unable to cope with
the same system, you can run
another program, and have that
actually work, perhaps, but it
has to be a specialized program
in itself to do the different
tasks. Yeah, I
Dave Coleman: think the key
there is you said you have to
run another program. And so who
isn't you the US? Yep. So so
like really giving the operator
a slew of a library of programs
that are more general and not
the robot do a lot of autonomy.
But when the robot like gets
stumped, there's a human there
to like, push it along, like,
Hey, here's a little hint. And
then one really cool idea that
we are not, you know, pursuing
exactly yet. But like, you have
all this human interfering or
intervening helping the robot,
and then that actually creates
more training data to generate.
So then you have this life cycle
of labelled semantic data that
you can use for future machine
learning models. It's
Audrow Nash: a virtuous cycle,
it is totally more data more to
train on, you can get more
sophisticated and you get closer
to actually solving your
problem.
Dave Coleman: I'm not a machine
learning expert, though, so I
won't I won't claim any of them
Audrow Nash: either. Sure. Let's
see. So that's really exciting.
How do you so witness and I
don't know if you can say, how
are you doing? Like, do you have
a simulation of what it's like
to be on the on the gateway that
space? The What do they call
them? space stations? Yeah, the
space station that's going
around the moon, do you have a
simulation of that? Are you
working on like, don't like
really specific problems for
them? Are you working on general
technologies that they're going
to apply to that situation or I
assume it's a mix
Dave Coleman: more general
technologies at this point, we
hope to move towards more
specific problems in the future.
But move it in has been used a
lot with the space station. And
so in gazebo, another open
source common library and ROS,
they groups at NASA have created
not full simulation space
station, but a full simulation
of a particular module, they
included the railing that you
can grab on to, and maybe some
problems and so they're dead
there hasn't worked that the
Robonaut using the open motion
planning library would move
through this environment using
its creepy spider legs and arms
to like, pull a cargo bag and
like open the Velcro, like some
pretty cool tasks. That that's
been worked on. And so some of
the guys that are at our company
have been involved in that
program.
Audrow Nash: So cool. Is there
any heart? So I guess, does this
already? Does the gateway
already exist? Or is it already
up there? That's a thing in the
future.
Dave Coleman: I believe it's not
launched yet.
Audrow Nash: So are there? I
mean, I'm just wondering if
you're like doing the sinusoidal
flight in an airplane with Robo
not that's floating for a few
seconds and trying to do
something or
Dave Coleman: no, no, I mean,
like it we're not, we're not
that involved in this yet.
Because that would be so cool.
That would be
Audrow Nash: so you could fight
against gravity by doing that.
It's so cool.
Dave Coleman: I mean, we don't
have gravity, it just makes all
the manipulation problems, I
think easier, because if they
don't have any momentum, they
just stay.
Audrow Nash: It's true. Unless
if they would be floating, it
would probably be very
difficult. And there's no forced
precedent like they just move
away from you if you put any
force that they symmetric into
good point. But easier if
they're stationary, because you
just but Hmm. So I think one
thing that seems really exciting
about this, to me is open source
being used at NASA is amazing.
Like that. I feel like that's a
huge win for the open source
community. Can you talk a bit
about that?
Dave Coleman: Yeah, they've
they've been involved with ROS
and funding Open Robotics for a
while, I believe is my
understanding. And I think that
they see that this is a great
way of tech transfer from what's
the latest in academia. And they
see it as a way to kind of
standardize and hire people who
already know, the technology and
I ROS just kind of become a
standard. And so NASA organizes
that on various teams at NASA
recognize it.
Audrow Nash: The really
interesting thing to me is when
I think NASA I think of like
incredibly robot, like they're
really concerned about
reliability. And it's
interesting to me that they're
going to open source for things
that are important in their
application, like controlling a
robo not. Yeah, station, like
that's really interesting to me.
Dave Coleman: Yeah, good
question. May is not a question.
But I have a thought on that is
the robot, their strategy, the
group at Johnson Space Center,
was to make the low level
controls really heartened, and
like, I'm not sure if I'd call
it like flight certified but
certified quality and rigorous
such that it was guaranteed not
to extract to exert the force to
like punch into a space station,
for example, like, they can't
break the station, because
that's extremely dangerous. And
so if you aren't like if the
underlying controllers and like
the hardware interface, it like
reaches the right certification
level of safety and that it
can't go beyond a certain
velocity and sort of torque,
then you can then think about
the layer above that kind of the
application layer with a more
modern like rapid iteration
software development techniques,
that allows for more powerful
compute and more like advanced
methodologies. But sometimes it
does, maybe sacrifice the rigor
of a very simple system that is
flight ready.
Audrow Nash: I see what you
mean. So it's nice to so we, you
can have that base layer that
NASA writes that make sure that
the robots got not going to
break anything. And then after
that, you can put your more
sophisticated layer on your
layer that does higher level
control. To do this,
Dave Coleman: there's often a
trade off of like, if you want
to have these, like high
resolution meshes that in like
sensor data, where you're like,
able to plan at higher level
thinking and that task levels,
the software gets very complex.
And there's just like a lot of
possibilities where sensor noise
could cause errors, or just all
the interacting interacting
systems on different threads and
cores, just can cause a little
bit more unexpected timing. And
so you definitely need to have
like, an underlying like, super
safe layer on top of all these
advanced capabilities.
Audrow Nash: Yep. So Now I see
that we are, like run where I
see that we're running out of
time. And I know there's a few
things that we want to talk
about. So could you tell me a
bit about premium? So move it
premium? And how like, what is
that? And what's the model?
Dave Coleman: No, I just did. So
we're calling into the studio.
And that studio. Yeah. So I'm
glad you made time for this. I'm
surprised that we're running out
of time this is flown by, but
yeah, do it. So we've, we have
been doing engineering services
for the past four or five years.
And it's been a lot of fun. But
we think that the next stage of
growth at picnic is going to
evolve, and not only the next
stage of growth, but the way
that we can have a bigger impact
towards growing the move at open
source project is by also
offering a premium version that
that like larger companies would
be really excited to pay for,
because they get all these
additional features. And, and so
we tried to make sure not to
come up with a premium feature
that conflicts with the core
feature set of move it because
we don't want to be trying to
make a better version of move it
but instead, move it studio is
the operator human loop
supervisors autonomy aspect.
That's right. Oh, that's Yeah,
so. So like, we're gonna keep
improving the underlying
grasping library and planning
libraries and kinematics and
like, the handy calibration
tools, improving all that for
the overall community. But also,
like we've we've made this
dividing line. Some might say
it's controversial, but there's
been, I've studied a lot of
like, open source business
models of past successes. And
it's like, very common, either
you come up with a SAS play,
where you're selling an internet
service on top of your open
source library, think WordPress,
or you're coming up with a
premium version of the software
that says Software as a Service
software as a service. Thank
you. Yeah. Or you have this just
like this license offer on top
of it. So WordPress actually did
that. Also, they have jetpack,
like premium plugins, if you
know WordPress at all. Or
another example is like Apache
Spark is a really popular open
source library for I think, data
analysis. I don't use it. But
this company data bricks, made a
product on top of it that has
allowed Apache Spark to continue
to grow also. So that's the the
new one of our new strategies on
top of our engineering services.
Audrow Nash: Seems smart. The AI
reminds me like another example.
There's tailwind, which is a CSS
framework, if I understand
correctly. And they have
tailwind UI, which is kind of
it's the same breakdown that
you're doing. So they have the
open source one that gives you
all the functionality. But then
they have components. So if you
want to make it more useful, and
that I guess not exactly the
same, but the like the
supervised autonomy, like more
structured interactions with
what you're doing that kind of
fit a template, they have
literal templates for making
HTML and CSS components. That's
their point that they charge
for.
Dave Coleman: a pretty good
example. I mean, for us, it's
like, one way to think about it
is that there's like a front end
for moving now. But there is a
lot more under the hood besides
just a front end.
Audrow Nash: Yep. Awesome. Very
interesting. So what's the
timeline on that? Like, where
are we now in this?
Dave Coleman: Great question. We
have to reference customers
currently that are that we've
released an alpha two. And we're
in talks a number of other early
early customers. And so we plan
to have the beta operating at
ROS con, we should have it
should be running at our booth,
if I assume our viewers are
familiar with the ROS
conference in New Orleans this
year. So that'll be October
2021. So hopefully, we'll have a
pretty cool demo to show.
Audrow Nash: I can't wait to see
Will you guys be we have move at
con or anything nearby at around
the same time, like yeah, or
whatever
Dave Coleman: it might be. This
year, we're not doing a
standalone Lubich con event. I
think our main motivation was we
weren't 100% sure about COVID.
And so we thought we would just
focus our resources on the main
ROS con event. So we are having
we are having a workshop the day
before the official ROS con
event starts, but it's part of
the ROS con workshops we're
having. And that one is actually
totally unrelated to supervise
autonomy, we have been adding to
open source move it some better
features around mobile
manipulation, which is the idea
that you can synchronize the
mobile base of your robot with
the arms so that you can expand
your workspace for for doing
tasks. So like when you think
about a human, you're trying to
reach something across the
table, you could I don't know
get up and walk around the table
or you could like reach across
it but both of those modalities
require using more than just
your arm. So that that kind of
functionality it's always kind
of been a move it but we've
greatly proved it. And so the
workshop will be about how to
use that on a Hello robot
stretch platform, which is a
startup in the Bay Area, making
some pretty cool mobile
manipulators. And by cool, I
mean low cost. It looks like a
stick figure, but it's also
Audrow Nash: really, I'm pretty
happy with it. Yeah, yeah, that
is awesome.
Dave Coleman: So they will be
there with us. picnic will be
kind of doing tutorials on how
to use, move it for that
application.
Audrow Nash: Now I know we've
said a lot about, like talking
about the studio version, and
you guys are working with NASA.
But what's, what's next for
picnic and move it outside of
those, like where you guys had?
would you think?
Dave Coleman: Yeah, so mobile
innovation is mobile
manipulation is one of our big
focus. Big like guiding winds is
like, we need arms to be able to
synchronize better with basis.
And so continuing that thread.
Another big thread for us is
hybrid planning, which is the
combination of global planners
and local planners, the best of
real time planning and global,
really smart planning. They both
have pros and cons. If you
combine them, you get the best
of both worlds. And so we've
been adding more features on
that the past year, we're
working with Fraunhofer over in
Europe on a demo of this
technology. That's that's one of
our big threads. I'm trying to
think what else is on our
roadmap, I can check real quick.
Sure. We're still like I guess
getting the last finishing
touches on move it to I mean
Move Move it to is basically a
feature complete, we have a blog
post recently just talking about
Audrow Nash: what feature
complete you mean up to move it
one in the correct abilities,
Dave Coleman: and move it to his
reminder is just move it
migrated to ROS 2. Except
it's not just that because we've
been adding, like all of our new
features are not going to move
it to so if you're on the move
at one, we encourage you to
upgrade, it has a lot of hassle,
because you have to upgrade your
ROS version as well. But I
think more and more of the
community's making the jump. And
so when I said about feature
complete parameters and launch
files are still a little bit
rough in like ROS 2 Foxy I
think a lot of ethics and
galactic. But now that it's
fixed and galactic, we're having
to finish up the moobot Setup
Assistant, which is simply a
user interface that lets you
easily set up an arbitrary robot
with movement. And we have to
just make it work with a new
style of launch files and
configuration files. So you can
do it without the Setup
Assistant, it's just more work,
we're trying to make it easier
to do it.
Audrow Nash: For sure. Yeah,
hopefully that will get even
easier with humble. The next
one, which will be released, I
don't know may of next year
2018. to hopefully, hopefully,
Dave Coleman: another big one
that I think we've momentum on
is being able to remove into
factors and different into
factors, swap them out, live in
move. And so this is a deep
structural change. But there's a
number of people at picnic
working on this right now
talking about the architecture,
we'll see if we get merged in
and the company doesn't balk at
the changes. But when you're you
already have changes it really
like it breaks a lot of
underlying data structures of
how movement thinks about your
robot. And so we're trying to
restructure that. And that's
been a common request from
customers for years. So imagine,
yeah, I'm excited about if that
actually lands in the next
version. And that actually, just
to change topics Audrow that
might end up being what we call
move three is about API change
of that magnitude we'd probably
wrap up
Audrow Nash: Oh, it's that
significant of a change it's a
huge change.
Dave Coleman: And in general
move it three is like we it's
when we stopped thinking move it
one to move it to so right now
we're actually using get able to
sync the code changes back forth
them for import, and we're gonna
draw a line in the sand and say,
we're not gonna make a lot of
huge breaking changes that
sinkings over and that's to me
kind of what movie three
represents.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Any, that's
a it's an exciting reveal. Any
idea when move it three will be
a thing when you actually do
that. Will it be like when this
when this urdf? Or that the way
of switching the robot to use a
different gripper? Well that
kind of be the catalyst to
switch it or I honestly don't
know
Dave Coleman: the date. I'm not
sure if the the main move it
team at picnic knows the date
yet. But it's just gonna be one
day that we're like, okay, we're
making huge breaking changes.
We're now drawing a line here.
Audrow Nash: Boom, move it
three. Yeah, that'll be
exciting. Do you think it'll be
in the next year?
Dave Coleman: I hope so. I
really Yeah, definitely. I think
so. Awesome.
Audrow Nash: I exciting. I'm
hesitant
Dave Coleman: to make
commitments because this is
still open source software and
funding major feature changes is
always difficult. We don't have
anyone fun. Doing this right
now. So Nick uses a small, like
a portion of our profit and like
our extra revenue, to go towards
these things. But if you know,
let's say, changing and
effectors live is something that
you really want, and you're a
company with funding, you know,
you can just hire us, we will do
it way faster and your timeline.
So that's my thought like, we're
here to do open source changes
for hire.
Audrow Nash: Now, so wrapping
up, how does someone get
involved with move it if they
want to? Like how do they become
a contributor? How should they
get started,
Dave Coleman: you use the word
involved. I like that. So the
big call to action button on the
movement website says get
involved. So you click that big
blue button at the top right.
And we recently revamped these
pages to be really pretty and
hopefully easy to follow to like
guide beginners into the
project. It used to be just a
bunch of plain text on a web
page. And so let's move on
to @ROS.org Click the Get
involved button. And I'm looking
at right now the first two
things it says is, you know, get
in touch, like saying taps by
vamos and discourse and discord,
which is unfortunately, similar
names. similar
Audrow Nash: name. Yeah, yeah,
that's me up to Yeah,
Dave Coleman: we decided not to
use slack. We thought discord
was a better open source,
Audrow Nash: like discord much
more than slack. Yeah, totally
agree with that decision? Yeah,
Dave Coleman: we use slack at
our company. But I think discord
is great for open source. And
then on the other side, it says,
you know, start contributing
day, you can click on that,
it'll tell you how to, like, get
involved with fixing issues,
improving documentation and
contributing good. Awesome,
Audrow Nash: and how can how can
people like any social media or
anything that you want to? So if
anyone wants to follow up and
learn more, how can they?
Dave Coleman: Yeah, we post
every week on LinkedIn and
Twitter under picnic robotics
handle. So a lot of good content
about the latest things and move
it and a lot of like white
papers, kind of the latest
research on how we're thinking
about doing hybrid planning or
grasping or what have you. So we
have a lot of our PhDs published
on a frequent basis there. So I
encourage you to follow us on
either those platforms. That's
been Nick robotics, and I have a
Twitter account and waffle just
panel. I don't post often
though, but I always mean to I
just don't.
Audrow Nash: All right. Awesome.
Thank you. I really enjoyed
this. And Bye, everyone. Thanks.
That's all we have for you
today. If you liked this, feel
free to subscribe, head over to
the ROS discourse if you want
to comment on the episode. Thank
you to our founding sponsor,
Open Robotics, and I'll see you
in two weeks. Bye, everyone.