Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Christian
Fritz, who is the CEO and
founder of Transitive Robotics.
Transitive Robotics makes
software for building full stack
robotics applications, meaning
that it aims to make connecting
your robot to a user interface
easier. Some reasons you might
want to do this are to remotely
monitor the health of robot
fleets. See what a robots camera
sees, or to tele operate a
robot? Transitive Robotics does
this while solving the hard
networking problem of robots
potentially coming into and out
of connectivity. I enjoyed
talking to Christian. His
perspective in forming
Transitive Robotics seems to
have been very pragmatic. And in
my opinion, Transitive Robotics
is building a tool that is very
needed by the robotics
community. It was also
interesting to hear his thoughts
on growing a robotics app
marketplace, which may be in
Transitive's future. This is the
Sense Think Act Podcast. I'm
Audrow Nash. Thank you to our
founding sponsor, Open Robotics.
And now here's my conversation
with Christian.
Christian, would you introduce
yourself?
Christian Fritz: Hi. I'm
Christian Fritz. I'm the founder
of Transitive Robotics. People
may know a little bit from my
career, where I'm coming from, I
used to be the head of software
at Savioke. And for those who
don't know, Savio, said hope
makes a really cute delivery
robot for hotels and hospitals.
And it was, it was a really fun
ride. For me. Being there, I
started when there were about
five robots in the field. When I
left there were over 100. And it
was a really an eye opening
experience. For me, my
background is in robotics, I've
done Robocop back in 2001, I've
seen all sorts of versions of
robotics, including before ROS,
which was bearish. And then at
Savioke, I learned about not
just the robotics piece, but the
full stack that went on top of
that. So that's really kind of
my background, I was leading the
application development team
there, which basically, I always
described it to new candidates
or employees as as follows. The
application development team
gets a robot that knows how to
stay localized and not bump into
anything, and turns it into
value to the company. So what
that meant was all of the HDRI
was done by our team, anything
that involves just a sense of
ambition, right, like running a
delivery, the notion of
delivery, writing elevators,
calling phones, notifying users,
all of that was done by a team.
And it was, it was a really
interesting experience. Because
I found out that while ROS is
really great, there's, there's
so much more that you need in
order to deploy a successful
robotics fleet in the real
world. And so that's, that's how
I came to start trying to
Audrow Nash: know, what exactly
are you doing at Transitive?
Like, how are you solving this
deployment problem and the
problems that you kind of saw
from your work, it's.
Christian Fritz: So it's heavy,
we spend a lot of time building,
you know, those those full stack
applications, data
synchronization between robots
and the cloud at the front end,
visualizing elements of the
robot, such as maps at laser
scans, and sending data back and
forth and doing all of that
DevOps. And it was really
interesting for me to find out
that other people at other
companies like fetch robotics
and places that we spoke with,
were basically building the
exact same thing, right. So we,
we felt that, that that's not a
good idea. And granted, there
are some solutions out there
that help try to offer you the
kind of a one stop shop for
fleet management and DevOps. And
some of them are actually done
by friends of ours. And they
approached us and said, We have
to, to see whether we would want
to use them. But the problem
that we had with them was that
they all are sinking, like
standalone platforms. So really,
they give you the choice of do I
build my own fleet management?
Or do I outsource that. And the
issue that we had with that was
that when you outsource that
your hands are tied, if the
thing is not perfect, you cannot
extend? And if there's something
that you need, you still have to
build it separately. And then
you have, well, first of all,
some type of work. But also
you're duplicating your data,
landscape, right? Some data will
live in the one side or the
other in
Audrow Nash: your domain in so
software you're using for fleet
management, and then whatever
features you build custom
yourself kind of outside of
that. For your own. Yeah,
Christian Fritz: that's exactly
right. Yeah, exactly. Right. So
you will have separate users on
different accounts. You'll have
different roles. You'll have
complex some data about the
robot. Yeah. And so what struck
us was that what people really
want is the ability to just take
individual complaints and plug
them into your existing web
application. A good example of
that is low latency video
streaming, almost everybody
wants to see what's the ability
to see what the robot is
currently seeing. And it's a
complicated application or
capability to implement. Because
there's some really great
technology like the one that
we're using here right now,
which is why Partisi, which is
running in the background, it's
very complex. And a lot of
robotics companies don't want to
get in the weeds don't want to
become experts, they don't want
to get into the weeds. So I
tried to give were basically
developing these things as
individual components. That's
the one thing that's different
about us from from the existing
offerings out there. And the
other one is that we believe in
open source. So we actually
following an open core model,
with a platform that we're
developing will be open source,
and anybody can use it, and we
hope people will, and they will
build cool things on top of
that. And this is really kind of
a philosophical thing for us. We
think that ROS has done such a
good job at uniting the robotics
community by giving us a common
platform that we can build
packages on. And so we can
share, right? So if you if you
build a really awesome
navigation functionality, and
thinking of your last you can
you can share that with the
world and the world will be a
better flex, right. And I think
ROS has done such a tremendous
job at establishing that
framework or platform on based
on which we can share it. And we
would really love to do the same
now for the for the full stack.
If it's open if it's open
source, and it's easy to
implement new capabilities that
we really think that people will
start contributing back. And we
can finally stop all reinventing
the wheel and building the same.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, for everyone
who has a fleet of robots that
needs to manage them in some
way. So now one thing I'd like
to do just kind of going more
into detail, what does it mean
to do fleet management? And what
are some of the challenges with
fleet management?
Christian Fritz: Well, so I'd
start perhaps a little bit lower
and start with why why sleep
management or anything to do
with robotics is not just
another react app, or something
else where you can use common
tools out there. And they don't
just solve the problem. The big
one is really that these robots
as much as they seem to behave
like servers are not really
servers because they run around,
they lose network connectivity,
they gather data faster than
anybody can process them. And so
you have some unique
requirements in creating a
uniform picture of your fleet in
the front end. And this is not
very unlike what some of the
cloud providers offer with their
IoT
Audrow Nash: when we say that
you mean like a web browser or
some other web browser?
Christian Fritz: Yeah, it's um,
yeah, I guess I should, I should
say that I'm asking I'm a no,
it's a it's a good point.
Because in robotics, and
especially in bras, a lot of Qt
applications are still being
fronted. We think that if you're
dealing with a broad set of
users who are distributed, have
different backgrounds and so
forth, using web technologies,
really the way to come. Because
everybody knows how to use them.
Obviously, most of the software
being developed these days, runs
in some on some form of web
technology. And it's just a very
lively and flourishing
ecosystem. So using web tools, I
think it's the best approach for
building these front ends. And
so at that point, you have to
create a link between your your
robot gathering data and user
sitting in front of a browser.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so for fleet
management, webs, web related
tools are really good. Because
they let you it's like it's
better. There's really good
tooling around there. There's a
good ecosystem, this kind of
thing, and I guess, getting into
kind of the fleet. So and then
actually, you were saying that a
server, like you can't just
treat it like a normal sir, a
robot like a normal server. And
so because of that, you have
Transitive robotics, you're
trying to make it so that you
can, in a sense, treat a robot
like a server while addressing
some of those challenges.
Christian Fritz: Yeah, that's
exactly right. I think it kind
of comes down to the core
abilities that the platform
gives you as a developer. And
one of them. I think that's
perhaps the most important one
is the data model that it gives
you. And what we're doing there
is actually not very different
from what some of the cloud
providers offer in the IoT
solutions at all on AWS, they
call them IoT shadows. In a
jury, they call them desired and
reported state of a robot, the
idea is always the same that you
have some form of data model
that tells the robot this is
what I want you to be like,
whatever that is configuration
deployment. So as a robot to get
into, basically. So it's, it's
saying I want to think of it as
you think of it as a state.
Yeah. At the state can have all
sorts of aspects to it, right?
Like which software to run, what
users to have, what
configuration values to use,
which cloud to connect to, and,
and then the problem is your
robot. Sometimes it's not just
not online, right. So you have
to make sure that you reliably
synchronize that data to the
robot, and also get the get the
data back. On the coming back
side, you have that same issue
that you may want to monitor
your robot while it is
traversing through some areas
where it has very poor
connectivity. But you don't want
the front end experience to be
chopped up, right? You want the
user to have a smooth experience
and still see the robot, even if
right now you can't get signal
from it. And that's, that's why
it is not a server, you can't
just run a web server on it and
have to reuse it connect to it
directly.
Audrow Nash: Is that is that
kind of the biggest challenge in
this? Would you say where it's,
the robot comes in and out of
connectivity? And it makes it so
that you can't make a lot of the
assumptions that people would
make about, like web servers? In
general?
Christian Fritz: I think that's
a good way of putting it. Yeah.
So
Audrow Nash: what do you what do
you do in the case? How do you
how do you make a smooth
experience when a robot is
popping in and out of
connectivity?
Christian Fritz: I think really,
the key here is an intelligent
data synchronization where the
robot essentially updates the
cloud, whenever it has
connectivity. And then the cloud
serves the serve the users front
end, right, so the user always
sees data, sometimes data will
be a little bit delayed, because
the robot hasn't gotten an
update through to the cloud. But
the cloud will be able to tell,
hey, I haven't gotten a
heartbeat from this robot in 10
seconds. So what you're seeing
maybe maybe a little bit old,
but from the user's perspective,
pages, load fine. Everything
will be there. And you will
always see the latest data that
you could possibly get
independent of when you show
data, some people think you
could just run a web server on
the robot itself, and then
connect and then the problem is
sometimes you try to build a
patient that just doesn't know
because your servers down or not
connect you.
Audrow Nash: You mean literally
host the website from the robot.
Christian Fritz: That's, that's
a lead. So let's take an
alternative. Some people are
this into the robot harvest or
like a non ROS users is a
visualization tool for ROS. And
it's it's an awesome tool. But
it's, it's not really meant to
be used remotely for for several
reasons. One, it sends a
humongous amount of data because
it actually thinks that the
connection is very good and fast
and sending duplicate data is
not a problem. And it also just
sends a ton of data. So there's
not a lot of filtering typically
going on. Which means that
remote experience with harvest
can be very choppy, and the
robot goes in and out of
connectivity sometimes. So if
you lose that you won't have a
lot of disruptions, you're
losing interest. So I think some
kind of caching of the data in
the cloud. That's one, reducing
the amount of data that you send
from the robot to the cloud is
another Oh,
Audrow Nash: yeah, that's an
important point, reducing it so
that you don't actually spend
that many resources on kind of,
I don't know, perhaps you can
get by with less. And then you
have less requirements of your
connectivity to your network.
Christian Fritz: Yep, that's
exactly right. A good example,
here is health monitoring. A lot
of your your listeners may be
familiar with how ROS solves
the diagnostics problem where
there is a nice hierarchy of
message definitions that allow
us to share diagnostic
information about your robot
such as set of values, battery
stage, and so forth. But the way
that ROS publishes status,
here's an update, here's an
update, here's an update, even
if nothing changes, right. And
that's fine with ROS, that's
not ROS is designed on the
robot. And that's, that's good.
It's actually a good approach on
the robot, but not for the
cloud, because you don't want to
repeat messages if they're
literally the same as the
previous one. So even just
duplicating sequences of
messages will already save you a
ton of data.
Audrow Nash: Yes. So how I'm
understanding what it sounds
like you're describing. So if
you want some sort of way of
monitoring your robot, your
robot has information it's
driving around, it may move in
and out of networks. What you're
doing is you're placing a cloud
component so some computer
somewhere else that's talking to
the robot. This is basically
it's keeping up the whole time.
And it's displaying whatever the
most relevant data is on there.
And then I suppose, well,
actually, and then you have the
user who looks at whatever the
cloud is doing. So the cloud has
its own host, its own website is
hosting. And the user can look
at that and get to see the state
of the robot. And then I assume
on the robot, you have something
that's saying, this is necessary
information to send up to the
cloud. So if it if it's
overheated message that's being
sent, you don't bother sending
it again, because of limited
bandwidth effectively, to try to
send data to the cloud. Like we
only want to prioritize and send
the most important updates,
probably, to the cloud. Yeah,
Christian Fritz: that's exactly
right. That's exactly right. The
way that these decisions are
made is that we believe in
vertically integrated
capabilities. So I've described
so far is this very fundamental
data synchronization layer, but
then what you build on top of
that, we think in terms of apps,
right, so let's take a remote
Tailor of capability. A lot of
people need that on the robot.
So that involves sending video
from the robot to the to the
front end, displaying the video
on the front end, and sending
back some control signals from
the from the joystick. The
Transitive is structured is that
we have this concept, very
strong concept of packages,
similar to ROS. But what's
special about Transitive is that
inside a package, you don't just
have components that run on the
robot, or the code or the front
end, you have all of them
together. And what's great about
that, is that you can you have
an end to end exchange. And if
you want to change the way that
things are visualized on the
front end, if you need, say,
some new data that you didn't
have in the previous version,
it's fine, because you're going
to publish another version of
the code that runs on the robot
and push us to the cloud as
well. So this gives you some
really nice. We think of this as
cross device dependency
management. Yeah, you don't have
to worry about oh, well, we just
upgraded our front end. So we
now also need to upgrade our
backend. It's all it's all taken
care of.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. Yeah.
Interesting. Okay. So going
back. So some of the challenges
with fleet management, we have,
basically the connectivity issue
where it's going in and out of
the network, we have, perhaps,
the, the so you have the robot,
it's sending data back and
forth. The robot may or may not
be connected, you have health
monitoring, and things like this
checking the status of the
system, and you have updating
it, which you've kind of just
mentioned, you can ship things
as components, and it's updated
universally. Are those kind of
the other additional challenges
to fleet management, and network
updates. And the second, but
yes, those are there additional
ones that are kind of critical
and fleet management, health
monitoring.
Christian Fritz: Actually, if
you don't mind, I'm going to
share a kind of famous
Greenbrier course. So this is a
list that we've put together off
things that we needed at one
point or the other, in the past.
And it's grouped by categories
of kind of apps or capabilities
that you might need to run a
fleet successfully. So there's
the category of DevOps and fleet
management software, super
modular uploads a video is Iraq,
prospect view and health
monitoring, and it goes
observability is a big one.
alerting, right. A lot of people
like to integrate with pager
duty and so forth. But then
there's also things like
application logic, right Task
Entry to a queuing of tasks,
user management, account
management, and a lot of those
things are really not that much
fun. Yeah, so that and they're
not really they're not
differentiating to a robotics
company, right? So we were we
validated this with a lot of
CEOs and CTOs of robotic
startups. And they always said
the same thing. There are
certain things that we would
like to focus on. Often, in the
ml or computer vision space, we
were talking with an apple
picking robotics company, you
can probably guess what that
was. And they said, well, our
our secret sauce is in our
ability to identify grasping
points from the computer vision,
we would never want to outsource
that. And that's where we want
to differentiate ourselves. But
there are so many things on your
list like CI CD, like anomaly
detection, that's not that's not
important to us. We would love
to outsource that. And that's
how we think about Transitive a,
a both a platform to develop
those kinds of capabilities and
then also a company that will
that will offer them
Audrow Nash: yes to you So where
are you guys currently in this
because the list of things,
there must be like 40 items or
some large number of things that
all seem really important to
shipping a robot application. Do
you have all these implemented?
Or is it like a set of them? Or
we're yet?
Christian Fritz: Yeah, no, not
at all. This is the aspirational
slide so to say. And it's also
meant to, perhaps give people
ideas of what they could develop
and contribute. This is really
the motivation to do all of
that. And the way we're going
about it is we want to develop
the platform First, open
sources, and then start building
the ecosystem to develop all of
them. Right now, if you go to
our website, there's three
capabilities that you can try
out right away. And they are
some of the ones that I've
talked about. So far. The low
latency video streaming, remote
telehealth and, and health
monitoring. Everything else?
Audrow Nash: So TBD? Yeah. So
it's, so you have this list, you
kind of gathered this list, and
I assume maybe it was somewhat
iterative in the process. But I
assume this really informed the
data model that you're using,
and the development of the
system so that you could fit all
these cases under your
framework.
Christian Fritz: So that's
exactly how we're thinking about
it. And
Audrow Nash: that's really cool.
So the, I'm kind of imagining
this is, like, I'm mapping it to
like web concepts, it's
eventually going to be like the
hosting service. For robotics
applications, probably you have
your specific logic running on
your robot. If you're using the
ROS ecosystem, you get a lot of
things for free, that might be
good enough for your
applications, like navigation or
move it for motion planning of
arms, these kinds of things, and
then you have this to make it so
you can quickly build your web
interface to monitor your
application for the people that
should make sure the robots are
running or I don't know,
whatever it is that's engaging
and engaging with your robots,
or whoever it is, yes, whatever
they're doing.
Christian Fritz: We're thinking
about this in two different
ways. One is to get people
started more quickly. So they
don't need to build these
things. And then sometimes our
investors ask, well, aren't you
going to lose those people, once
they grow to a certain scale?
And they will, they will not
care? Because they are now they
now have 200 employees, and they
will build it themselves? And my
answer to that is they still not
want to. And the reason is, like
my counter example is slack.
Yeah. Why do people use Slack?
It's not impossible to do. In
fact, it's pretty trivial.
However, are you really going to
bake it quite as well as slack?
And that's all I do. Where,
exactly, it's, it's the value of
specialization, right. And in
the end, you will use the best
solution out there, startups in
especially in robotics are
actually not as price sensitive
as you may think. And that's
because the bulk cost of robots
all of the operations is not
that cheap. So if they have to
shell out $20 a month for a
capability, there's really well,
who cares, they're spending more
on the LTD Bill per robot.
Right. So I actually think it
this is something that I've felt
with ROS, too, is that I think
ROS would actually benefit from
more entities having commercial
a business plan behind them and
commercial backing, so that the
contributions that are being
paid by those companies to ROS
have have a longer a longer
outlook, right? There's, there's
some real money behind it, we
can be certain that they will be
maintained. And there's somebody
on the hook for making sure that
they that they do that they work
well. Yeah, there was this
really, I think I wrestled last
year somebody presented this
paper, I think it was called
something like it takes a
village, I forget the details,
you remember that? I don't think
I thought it was really
interesting, because they did a
study of ROS packages, and how
many which are used, like how
many how many people use them,
and how well maintained they
are. And it was really striking
that there are some like the
core modules that are they're
all being used by almost
everybody. But then the vast
majority of packages, and of
course, there's a ton of
packages, they are not
maintained very well. So that
puts users in a difficult spot.
And in deciding of can I really
rely on this package? Or do I
have to fork it if I want to if
I want to use it. And I think
that the JavaScript community
does a very good job at that
with their with the NPM package
manager where with every package
that you can find on their site,
they will show you how about how
well does it maintained me to
how many commits Have there been
made lately? How popular is it?
How many people use it? And I
think some other metric and I
think I think that's very
helpful quality, some sort of
They bought the holiday
Audrow Nash: trick. I don't, I
don't know how to get that, but
it's quite cool.
Christian Fritz: I think it's
very helpful. And when I choose
libraries to use, that's
definitely something that I look
at. And Oh, for sure, knowing
that there's others who use it
is sometimes perhaps the most
important factor. Because I know
that if I run into issues, I
will not be alone, there will be
others who will be who are also
invested
Audrow Nash: in it. And you can
feel a little more secure in
that other people might pick up
some of the slack, you can pick
up some of the slack, but it's
not entirely on you to maintain
if the developer just goes
silent, and maintaining it. Yep.
Gotcha.
Christian Fritz: And I think if
we can stand something like that
up here, we're obviously taking
the perspective of the full
stack. But I think some of those
ideas translate into into other
ROS packages as well. And one
thing that we haven't touched on
yet is you could have a rust
package be part of one of these
apps, right? You can, the way
that we actually designed our
deployment mechanism. These
packages can contain whatever
you want. Some people cringe
when they hear whatever you
want, because that sounds
dangerous. And we can talk about
that in a second. Yeah. Yeah, so
we we've designed this from the
bottom up as a framework that
Audrow Nash: what are the
components? So in any one of
these packages? Or in any of
these components? It has the
robot arm? Or what are the parts
of it that are involved? And how
do they talk? And then
sandboxing sounds very
interesting to talk about, too.
Christian Fritz: Okay, so let's,
let's dive a little deeper up.
Before we before we get into
that, I think I should mention
that we're using TGT as the
underlying communication
mechanism for just about
everything. I think that will
help our conversation here.
Audrow Nash: I don't know much
about that. I don't know
anything about that.
Christian Fritz: Okay, so MQ TT
is a Pub Sub mechanism, where
you have topics that are
hierarchical, separated by
slashes, just like a path in
Unix,
Audrow Nash: very similar to
ROS topics, it seems like from
the description so far, in a
sense that it's good topics, and
then it's hierarchical, like
namespacing, and this kind of
thing.
Christian Fritz: That's right, I
think the main difference rough
topics is that they don't have
this notion of a message
definition. Any message in the
end is just a buffer, or a
string, like a character buffer.
And then on the receiving end,
where you will interpret
Audrow Nash: offers nicely. So
yeah.
Christian Fritz: And other than
that, I mean, it's a very well
developed technology, it's
actually underneath all of the
IoT, cloud offerings like AWS,
GCP, and Azure, all built on MQ
TT. So it's sort of battle
tested. And it's meant for IoT
devices. So for low resource
usage, very high throughput,
communication. And unlike ROS,
it was really meant to be cross
device, like the typical IoT
application, you have a large
fleet of small devices that all
send data to the cloud, and from
there potentially onwards. So
this seems like a very good
technology to build this on. And
then our packages, they are
exactly like you suggested, they
actually have three components,
there's the code that will get
installed on the robot, there's
the code that will run in the
cloud in a Docker container. And
then the third piece is, are any
sort of front end components.
And there we are using this new
technology called Web
Components, it's not a very good
name, because it's not very
unique. But web components is a
thing. And it's very nice,
because it's front end framework
agnostic, you can use it in
React or Angular, or even
without any of that. So it
really just is like a custom tag
in HTML. So you have lots you've
loaded that component to that
component, you can just type,
you know, pointy brackets, the
name of your component, and it
will appear with where you want
it to be. That's what we use for
the front end. And then
underneath, they all communicate
through through MQ TT, in a in a
namespace that is not just
specific to the capability, but
actually even to the version of
the capability. And this is what
allows us to create this cross
device dependency management.
This is this was a very big pain
point that that I've faced at
one point in my career where if
you update the cloud, you may be
forced to also update all of
your robots, depending on what
you've changed on the cloud.
Now, guess what? Your robots if
you have more than 100 robots,
at no point in time, a lot of
your robots be online at the
same time. So when do you make
the switch? Right? And so
there's different ways to deal
with it. Some people
Audrow Nash: get both, and you
just have them send their
version messages. That's how we
are solving it except super
cool. And then you kind of
delete it once they're all on
board with the most recent
version.
Christian Fritz: Nobody has been
talking to me be on that version
for a month. So just got to shut
off that Docker container.
Audrow Nash: That's super cool.
Okay, so you use MQ TT, this
gives you that really nice
version messaging behavior that
makes updates really cool. And I
really like the idea of kind of
it trickles in as the robots
become available. Okay.
Christian Fritz: So that that
tells you how the three
components in the, say the three
again, just explicitly, the
robot, yep, the cloud and the
UI. Okay.
Audrow Nash: And so for these
components, one thing, so are
they all? You get them to talk?
Like, so if I'm writing one of
these components? How does it
look? Like how can I test all of
these? What do you call with the
components within the component?
Or how do you refer to the the
web robots and cloud parts of
component?
Christian Fritz: We haven't, we
should get that terminology. We
don't have a good name for them
yet.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. That
component makes me think React
components, which is kind of
it's a, and then that makes me
think just the web part of what
your thing is. But
Christian Fritz: we could call
them modules. And well,
actually, on right now we're
referring to this whole thing as
a capability capability. Okay.
And then the three underneath
are packages or modules. But
okay.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Okay. I
like the word capability better
for discussing it just so it's
not as overloaded in my head. So
how do you write a module? And
how do you write a capability
and test all these modules? How
do they work from a developer's
point of view?
Christian Fritz: Some of this is
still being developed right now,
we have not yet made the open
source release. And one thing
that we want to get done well,
is the SDK, which is kind of
what you're asking about, right?
So there will be tools that will
allow you to create new
capabilities, quickly in the
sense that they will, I'm taking
a lot of inspiration from again,
how things like reactive office
where you have like a CLI tool,
that's where you might say,
Transitive, create new
capability, whenever it will, it
will set up the directory
structure and you know, the
package json and the web, web
pack, whatever you need, in
order to compile all of those.
Yeah, we do use I guess, I might
have to say that we do use NPM
exhaustedly, and for those of
you who don't know, NPM is the
node package manager. It's a
very nice tool. A lot of people
think like, it's only for node.
But it turns out, you can put
anything you want it to that
package, it has a lot of
advantages over say Debian
packages. That was probably too
much detail to go into, but I'll
be
Audrow Nash: talking about it
just a bit later in the
interview. Yeah, good.
Christian Fritz: So once you
have these NPM packages,
there's, you know, scripts that
you can have for NPM publish to
publish those capab those those
packages have your capability
into a into a private registry
or an Artifactory store. And
from there, your robots will be
able to pull them and and run
them the connections that you
were asking about for
communication, where they will
be set up through the further
data synchronization. So from
the from the developer's point
of view, all you're manipulating
is actually one big JSON object.
And within that JSON object, you
can decide which sub paths you
want to subscribe to which ones
you want to publish. But you
will always be dealing with a
JSON object as if it was just on
your machine, you know,
Audrow Nash: the thing that's
being passed between the modules
in the capability correct. So
you're sending that JSON object
around and that JSON object. So
that's just a data structure for
viewing everything. JavaScript
Object Notation, or whatever it
stands for.
Christian Fritz: That's what it
stands for. And data data data
synchronization that I mentioned
previously, basically just takes
care of making sure that what
the robot sees from that tracing
is exactly the same as what what
the capability in the front end
sees, and you don't have to
worry about it, you just
manipulate it on the robot. And
you will can see it like that on
the on the front end. For those
of your listeners who know how,
you know, reactive web
programming works is this is a
reactive data source. So if
something changes here, your
React component will update.
dynamically, you don't have to
pull you don't have to worry
about it. I simply will take
care of the push. And in the
moment there's a change on the
robot. You will see it on the
front end without ever folding.
Audrow Nash: So what that means
is at the second row About sends
a new image from the camera is
your component updates and shows
that new image correct a web
component.
Christian Fritz: I wouldn't
necessarily use images or an
example here, okay, because that
is more complex said for our web
RTC and like with good
compression. But the example
still holds. If you if you could
do that you could send an image
over that channel. Another
example would be like, let's say
the battery charged, if your
battery charged, that's probably
a better example. It will show
up right away on the front end.
Audrow Nash: That's really cool.
So how if I if I'm developing
this, like if I if I'm writing
my own capability, how do I test
that all of the three modules
are working well, for the
capability? Is there any like, I
don't know, the thing that makes
sure that all of them are
working well together, that data
is being sent around that I can
test my components, my q&a
module for the web browser
locally, these kinds of things,
like a storyboards for the mind,
all these things. Component,
Christian Fritz: there's a lot
of tooling, yet, so some of
these automated checks that
you're alluding to don't yet
exist. But there's definitely
the developer workflow and the
documentation on how to run it
locally in a development server.
So that you can you can try this
out. And I think that's a good
way to get started, you can use
a simulator to run you know,
your, your, your robot, whenever
we use turtle sim a lot, which
honestly is enough for a lot of
work we want to do, and then you
open the local web page on your
machine, and will you will be
able to see whether or not
things are working.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. That seems
super cool. And what is the so
in the cloud component? So
there's a web, the cloud the
robot, what does the cloud
component do?
Christian Fritz: So the cloud
component is actually a very
module. The Cloud Module,
there's, there's obviously what
you what you want the
functionality to be there can be
visualizations, and so forth.
But before it can get there,
what the what the Transitive
wrapping for that, for that
module does is twofold. One, and
that's very important is
authentication and
authorization. Because if you
want to embed this, this
component in a third party web
application, you need to get the
appropriate permissions to
actually show the data of the
robot, right? I mean, not, you
don't want the camera of your
robot to be publicly available
on the internet. And obfuscation
is not enough, you want some
really strong authentication,
the way that we solve that is
through JSON web tokens, which
is a security technology, it's
it basically allows you to take
a JSON object and sign it with
an asymmetric or symmetric key
depending on what you choose.
And we use that to basically get
permission from the back end of
your service, whatever you're
embedding it in, to show certain
things to the user. So you will
basically give your user a
signed JSON web token that says
this user has permission to see
this device, this capability for
this and that long. And then it
will be embedded in the in the
webpage that your user goes to
that webpage will talk to the
transit server, whether you host
it yourself or whether you use
our transit products hosting.
And it will let us know whether
or not we are allowed to show
the users that that kind of
data. So that's our Yeah, what
are they authorized to see that
and that's that by itself. So
it's a big pain point that a lot
of people struggle with just
this. For sure. It's complex.
And we've seen some very
successful companies offering
authentication as a service like
Okta. And for good reason. It's,
it's not a lot of fun. And if
you make a mistake, a lot of at
stake, right, your company,
you're sharing too much data
than you then you wish you were.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. And I think
that's an area where it's like,
oh, you need to go be an expert
at to do well. And so it's nice
to specialize there and have
another company that just does
this really well. But so you
don't have to worry about doing
this for your application. So
the cloud component for any of
these capabilities you're making
is going to handle the
authentication and
authorization. I imagine that's
kind of like baked in to what
you're building. So they don't
probably have to handle that
when writing their application.
Does it also handle is it on the
robot that it's running? Like, I
know that sounds silly, but is
it the thing that sends the
information up to the cloud? Or
is it actually running on the
cloud? It's actually,
Christian Fritz: yeah, the human
way the authentication is going
to be processed,
Audrow Nash: or I mean, I guess.
So the authentic authentication.
That's I guess, I'm just I'm a
little confused, because so for
that, I would think that that
would be something that you
would set up very well. And
maybe all the code lives in the
cloud component. And the person
hardly who's the developer
hardly touches the cloud one it
just like, because I don't think
like, if I want to use this to
write capability, I don't
probably want to do the
authentication and authorization
side. So I'm imagining that's
probably generated or exists in
something that's already being
used, like my code is using.
Christian Fritz: Yeah, that's
part of the the essence of the
framework. And it's actually a
feature of the MQ TT brokers
that we're using, where you can
have custom authentication and
authorization, which which we
try to offer. So the way it
works is that the the web
component actually establishes a
web a MQ TT connection over web
over WebSockets. Okay. And in
order to authenticate for that,
for that connection, it will
send its Simes JSON Web Token.
The MQ TT broker will interpret
that and say, first of all, yes,
you are who you claimed you are,
because this is a valid JSON,
valid DWT. And also I've decoded
that JSON web token. And in it,
it says you have access to the
following topics. And this can
be read or write access. And
that's all you need. Right?
Because again, this is the
beauty of relying on MPT for
everything. Now, you know, that
the broker knows which messages
it is allowed to send to you,
and which ones you are allowed
to write. And then it kind of
goes into the ether and and
everybody connected to that.
That's it. Yeah, it's, yeah,
Audrow Nash: that's magic.
That's so cool. I feel like it's
taking such a painful problem
and making it a lot less
painful. So just so the cloud,
if I'm a developer, using
writing my own capability to
cloud component, I will probably
have the ability to use the
default way of doing
authentication and
authorization. Or I can write a
custom one, if I desire. And
that's kind of all the cloud
component does, or is there
anything else?
Christian Fritz: Well, I mean,
the other thing that the cloud
component does is, of course,
the data synchronization piece,
right? So that in the cloud
component, you have immediately
access to you can subscribe to a
subset of the of the topics that
you want, and they will enter
data will magically appear on
your doorstep. And then you can
visualize it in whichever way
you want. So that you can really
focus on on just that, right?
How do I, how do I present the
data. So you know, I mentioned
your little play, I like to
think in terms of black boxes,
if you're a web component, your
black box that you receive,
after all of the magic has
happened, you receive a JSON
object. And what you're
responsible for is outputting, a
nicely rendered HTML page or
whatever or react whatever you
want to use. You have visualize
that data, right? Health
Monitoring is a good example.
Again, like you get a JSON
object that represents the
health of your fleet. And you
decide to show that as a table
with red and yellow and green
and and what have you. Right?
That's that's really the that's
really what people want to use
web components for. They don't
want to spend too much time on
the on the plumbing, as I call
it. Yeah, they just want to
visualize it. And then in the
reverse the same right, so your,
your joystick opponent says the
user has been pressing the
forward button, now you need to
send that to the robot. So you
will send the appropriate data
into the onto on that topic
where you know, the robot will
be
Audrow Nash: listening. Gotcha.
That's really cool. What does it
look like on the robot? How,
like, how do you set it up and
what's actually running on your
robots when you actually are
using this.
Christian Fritz: So the the way
to get started ended depends a
little bit on whether you want
to use the hosted solution that
we offer or whether you want to
sell photos. But in the hosted
solution, you just go to our
website and create an account
and you will get a curl script
that you can run on your robot,
which will install a Transitive
robotics agent. This is just a
small little piece of software
that runs on the robot. And it's
primarily responsible for
checking whether you are running
whether which packages are
installed, which packages should
be installed, and then
installing them and starting
them. And then once it is told
to install a certain capability,
it will fetch that from the
repository and install it and
run it in a sandbox. The Sandbox
is one of the other pieces that
is really important to the way
that we're thinking about this
because we want to enable third
parties to develop for you. We
think that sandboxing is really
important.
Audrow Nash: Tell me tell me
what sandboxing is. I know what
it means, but just like describe
it.
Christian Fritz: So the issue is
always that when you're buying
software from a third party, you
you may not want to trust it
100% So you want to reduce
basically the damage it can do
you want to reduce the
permissions that it has on both
iOS And Android has a very, very
strong sandboxing model. So if
you install an app on your
phone, it won't be able to read
the password from your from your
other apps, right, which is kind
of important. Yeah. And the same
thing here, right. And in the
ROS world, people are used to
using sudo, to install ROS
packages. And that's a very
honorable thing to do, as
opposed to give that much trust.
But if you are dealing with a
much larger ecosystem, you may
want to be a little bit more
careful about the trust that you
give and not run everything as
root. So a lot of people
wouldn't even want to run it in
the normal user space, because
even the running user could have
could have secrets and so forth.
That's one thing. The other
thing is you want to separate
those the capabilities running
on your robot from one another
so that they cannot see each
other's data. Otherwise, the
authentication and authorization
is kind of goes out of the
window, because somebody could
install everything. Yeah, and a
malicious capability could just
listen in on everybody else. So
you're solving this. Through a
number of technologies that all
borrow from Docker, we do not
use Docker on the robot, because
we don't want to use require
that as a as a as a requirement.
But we use some of the same
technologies, we use the Linux
namespaces, using the unshare
tool, to to isolate things. This
allows us to do pretty cool
things, honestly, without
requiring sudo on the on the
robot, for instance, we hide a
lot of folders on the drive, we
can hide the home folders. And
then we're also using overlay
Fs, which this technology
exhaustively used by by Docker,
to minimize the number of copies
of things that you need on the
system. So if a capability has a
requirement for a ROS package,
it will it will first check is
that already installed. And if
not, it will install it in an
overlay on top of what's already
there. This way, we don't have
to install ROS in each and
every component that we have,
which would happen if we were
running in Docker containers,
right, there would be a lot of
duplication, which we can, which
we can elegantly avoid.
Audrow Nash: That is really
cool. So you see if you have it
elsewhere. And then if you have
it elsewhere, you use it from
that location. If not you
install it. That's really cool.
So what about handling things?
So that that handles? You
mentioned a lot of things? And I
don't I'm not that familiar with
all those technologies. But it
can you hide things like the
environmental variables that one
capability can see versus
another one? Or it just like all
of the different things you give
it access to only a small part
of the file system. Yeah. How
does all this work? It sounds so
cool.
Christian Fritz: Right? Now we
go with a one size fits all type
sandbox, you don't actually
customize it, we just we just
reduce it down to what we think
is all you need. If you don't
see the environmental variables
of your user, you you're either
home folders or hidden certain
sensitive folders in the in the
file system such as var lib, or
from you as much as possible,
like the data, if you're, if
you're running a database, it
would live there and he wouldn't
be able to see that. And you
explicitly
Audrow Nash: opt in to
permissions with this, or is it
implicit in that, like, oh, this
app needs this? And then we'll
give it that? I'm not sure it's
explicit. So
Christian Fritz: so right now
we, we think actually, we have
the permissions down to what
most capabilities will will need
we there could certainly be some
people have asked us about
things like user management on
the robot, right? This is
clearly something that would
need administrative rights. And
we don't currently support that.
We are currently only supporting
things. It's a what one way to
think about this, especially for
your audiences ROS and up if
you a lot of capabilities run a
ROS node, they're able to talk
to the other ROS notes. And
that's honestly all they need to
do. Yeah, it's it's none of
their business what I have on my
on my desk, right? That's that's
not what we're here to do. So,
all of that accesses is going to
be very, very limited. Other
than say, you know, what you
need for, for for ROS
operations, such as the message
definitions, right. But most of
the file system will be hidden
from
Audrow Nash: good I saw I'm
imagining if I had some node
that so I have a module on my
robot, and that's sending up
video. And maybe I want to send
some sort of thing down from the
cloud, to say, hey, we're a bit
bogged down right now. Reduce
the video quality you're sending
up or something like this. And
maybe it's netstat and an
environmental variable, like,
could you give it access to
that? Or maybe there's a better
way to go about doing that kind
of thing?
Christian Fritz: I would have to
think about it. If by setting an
environmental variable, you mean
one that would also be written,
read by all of the other
capabilities, like some sort of
shared space? Yes, not currently
possible, there is no shared
drive space. So another piece of
technology that we've taken a
good look at is snaps on on
Ubuntu. And they, they solve
this very elegantly to where
they have, of course, you know,
containerized, or sandbox
capabilities, but they also have
some, some shared folders,
right, in which you can
collaborate if necessary. So
that that certainly, that
certainly exists. In the example
of the video streaming, I would,
I would argue that that's the
capability itself, that then
reduces that.
Audrow Nash: But yeah, you
probably wouldn't need to do it
the way I described. Because
yeah, the capability would
probably just do it. And it'd be
setting a variable inside the
module, robot module. That would
be probably the best way to do
it.
Christian Fritz: And actually,
so we do have that video
capability. And we use Web RTC,
of course, and one of the
beauties of web RTC is that it
will actually do that
automatically, right? That's so
Turman, I can't get those frames
through, we're going to reduce
quality for a little while, and
and it will adjust to that,
which is very nice. And really
one of the reasons also to use
Web RTC
Audrow Nash: for industry. Do
you think that this idea of
sandboxing will catch on more
generally, in robotics? Like I
mean, if I'm using a bunch of
software from the internet, you
never know if something has been
maliciously included? So
Christian Fritz: yep. Yeah, I, I
think so. I mean, if you've been
following what Ubuntu has been
doing with their push for four
snaps, for instance, they had a
person that was also very active
in the Rust community. And he
was in charge of ROS and snaps
on the canonical side. And he
was making some very good points
as to why snaps are a good
solution for that because they
are sandbox, like you say,
right, they are snaps for, for
those of your listeners who
don't know, basically, or you
can think of them as Docker
containers that run apps on on
Ubuntu now, people will yell at
me for describing it like that.
Because of course, in reality,
it's more sophisticated, and it
actually doesn't use Docker. But
for that, for the event, who
knows a little bit of Docker,
that's roughly how it works. And
so you get all of the beauty of
isolation, and, you know,
reliable requirements, like
dependency, dependencies, and so
forth. So I think it's useful.
I'm very curious to see how this
will evolve, and whether the
sandboxing will get into the way
of development, whether people
will prefer to install their
capabilities, quote, unquote,
privileged. But I think it's the
I think it's a, it's a
requirement for more broader
cooperation, like you said, if
we want to enable third parties
to run, and it's our fleet of
robots, right. I mean, for it
from the perspective of a
business owner in robotics,
they're very conservative about
what gets to run on the robot.
Because if you screw up, like,
these are implications, there's
a lot of implications for on the
security side, but also, even
just on the operational cost, if
for some reason, your robots one
morning, don't do it anymore,
or, or you know, they dropped
from the internet, you can't
reach them, somebody is getting
on a plane flying somewhere.
Very expensive.
Audrow Nash: Gosh, uh huh. One
thing a little bit of a tangent,
but one thing that I thought was
really interesting, and I am
hoping more things start to go
this way. There's Dino, which is
a TypeScript library or
TypeScript runtime environment.
And Dino, for us. It's kind of
like Node, but better suited for
TypeScript also runs JavaScript.
But if you explicitly opt in to
every permission that you want
to use, you can say all if you
want, but so you can say this
should only be accessing these
folders, this should only have
access to this environmental
variable. And all of the
software that you use can have
these permissions set, which is
quite cool. Because I mean, if
you're running software, there's
the chance that it's like trying
to access something you don't
want it to use. And this would
be a nice way to bet that hey,
there was an error or tried to
access some sensitive location.
We denied it and the program
exited.
Christian Fritz: That's pretty
cool. I had heard about the
though I didn't know that they
have that feature. That's uh,
I'm actually gonna take a look
at that. That's that sounds
really useful.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, I'm
sponsoring site quite a few you
know, projects cuz I really like
the direction that they're going
But the whole node ecosystem is
really, really, it's just so
much there, that it's hard to
use the you know, for anything
that you really want to build,
like, I've just been doing it
for, like, command line tools
that helped make my job at open
robotics easier to try them. And
you know, but lately node is
kind of thing.
Christian Fritz: Gotcha. So it's
not a replacement for Node js at
this point.
Audrow Nash: Not yet. But there
are quite a few packages that
are like, I mean, I don't know,
there's like an express like
thing for hosting web servers,
and routing. But if you want to
do like, really nice date time
stuff, or I don't know, there's
just a bunch of missing stuff.
Or you can go look at the CDN
serialization or whatever it is,
I don't actually know what that
does. But you can go some
packages can be translated over
to it, but it has a different
import setup. So it doesn't work
flawlessly with existing node
things, which is a bit of a
bummer. But the ecosystem is
growing. And there seem to be a
lot of really smart programmers
doing stuff on it. And building
tools.
Christian Fritz: Yeah, I mean,
that's really, I think, key to a
framework platform. You name a
working ecosystem of developers,
right. And my favorite example
there that the reason why Node
js is so popular and works so
well is because it's so popular
and works so well, right? Like
people use us developing more
things. And because they develop
more thing, it's the network
effect, right? And then more
things. So you can find a
library for just about anything
if you don't need to develop it,
yourself. There's downsides, of
course, and we've seen the news
about some, you know, either
hostile takeovers of packages,
where people have have stopped
maintaining it. Whereas
sometimes even malicious changes
that people made sometimes out
of spite or break everything,
yeah, yeah. And those issues
are, of course, serious, and we
need to take care of them, and
it'd be worried about them. But
it's a very cool technology to
build on.
Audrow Nash: Oh, definitely.
Yeah, I find it. So I mean,
working at Open Robotics, we use
a lot of C++ and Python. And
type like years and years of
using Python. But I really like
TypeScript, because defining the
interfaces is really nice. And
it helps me I feel like I'm much
more productive in it. And so
now I'm getting familiar with
the node, or NPM, packaging, and
just downloading libraries and
software from it. And I'm very
impressed. And I feel like it's
a, it's a lot more capable, in
my opinion, than a lot of the
Python libraries. And there are
obviously exceptions, like,
like, pandas is a really nice
Python library that I don't
think has a good analogue in
TypeScript or JavaScript. But
just it's an interesting space.
Christian Fritz: It absolutely
is. And I like to play dog to
that. Note, J S is actually a
bit faster than Python. And
that's because JavaScript is
compiled just in time, it's not
actually interpreted, it's just
compiled on the fly, which makes
the execution a lot faster. And
then I can, you know, say a lot
of positive things about NPM. As
a package manager, it's, it has
a lot of features. And it has a
lot of capabilities that other
package package managers have
within the past leg. So for
instance, one big one is having
multiple versions of the same
package in the repository, you
would think that this is a
trivial thing. But DVM, for
instance, doesn't, doesn't
really support that apt, you're
not really supposed to have
multiple versions of the same
package in the in the
repository. But it is important
Audrow Nash: for your
application where you're trying
to wean robots off of version,
when they're when you're
updating them. This is, this
would be very useful.
Christian Fritz: Next time, it
also for the for strict
versioning. I think that strict
versioning, of strict, strict
semantic versioning is a real
benefit. Where you in npm date,
there's this concept of a lock
file, where you will save I'm
going to lock down my versions.
And when I commit to get is
exactly this, if you execute
this, you will get the exact
same result, no matter what any
of the dependencies have done in
the meantime, in terms of
updating, you will get the exact
same. And and this is really
helpful when you're dealing with
an ecosystem like NPM, where you
have hierarchies of dependencies
that can be very, very deep,
right? You can super nest 2000
packages being installed as part
of your of your somewhat simple
application. And that's, that's
a benefit, right? You don't want
to reinvent all of those 2000.
But you do want to be certain
that if anything happens to
either of them, maybe they
introduce a bug in the new
version, your system doesn't go
down. So really locking down the
versions and deciding Yes, I
want to update or I don't want
to update it. Is, is very
powerful. And for that you need
to be able to have multiple
versions of the same package in
the repository. The other one
is, of course, all of the books
like pre installed post install,
pre uninstalled post, uninstall,
pre publish all of those kinds
of scripts that you may want to
run as different types of the
software lifecycle, they are
very powerful they can really
allow you to do I mean, us? They
are, they are very powerful in
Debian packages as well. But
because NPM has them you can do,
you can pretty much install
anything through NPM packages
that you have, because the
payload is just a tarball. And
then you run these scripts when
when it gets installed. And at
that point, you can, you could
install things out of the
tarball that say you Debian
packages, or play system files
if you have the permissions to
do that. So it's very, it's very
versatile tool. And I think
it's, it's a real good
technology to build on and
share.
Audrow Nash: Let's see. So now
segwaying, a little bit. Tell me
a bit about your open core model
at Transitive.
Christian Fritz: Yeah, this is
still still in flux. But I am a
big believer of open source
businesses, I think that there
are some very good examples that
we've seen in the past. And so
we, we really want to make this
open source model work. And from
everything that I've learned.
There's, there's basically two
things that work really well
from, from an open source
business model point of view,
one is testing. So in our case,
we are offering a hosted
solution where the cloud will be
taken care of by us, you can
still, like I said, have the
components and embed them in
your own web applications, if
even a web application is
running somewhere completely
different. But you don't have to
worry about it, setting up the
cloud, dealing with the
maintenance and administration
of that storage of data and
whatever your capabilities want
to do. That's the that's the one
model. Some of our customers
have asked about self hosted
solution. So we are offering
that as well. And this is still
a work in progress. So that has
not been released. And the
business model in that case, is
premium applications. So it's
it's really similar, I guess, to
Android, again, right? Where
Android is open source, you can
install it on any phone you
want. But then the capability
the apps in Android can also be
free, or they can be they can be
premium. And I think this is a
good model, right? It allows
people to first of all get
started with it. They it
provides developers with a
marketplace where they can
distribute their their their
contributions, their work, they
don't have to worry about, you
know, advertisement and and
billing and and all of that. And
on the receiving end, you know,
the the companies using those
capabilities will have an
ecosystem with writings with
commercial support behind it
that they can that they can rely
on. So I think that this is a
model that can that can really
work.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And so are
you experimenting between those
two models? Or your you'll think
you'll kind of see what
capabilities you have? And then
possibly add? Actually, it seems
like it makes sense to do the
Android model for what you're
talking about, where it's and
then you're doing both in a
sense, because you are providing
the hosting, but you're also
possibly going to have specific
capabilities that people can opt
into, by purchasing. Yeah,
that's,
Christian Fritz: yeah, that's
exactly right. And both are
evolving, we'll have to see
which one will be more popular
and how, for instance, what we
are still keen to find out as to
what extent will people prefer
the hosted solution versus self
hosting? There's definitely pros
and cons with both. Some people
really don't like the idea of
relying on a third party,
especially if it's a startup,
right? Because it multiplies to
whatever No. That's why the
ability to self host is
certainly desirable. Others
really don't want to take care
of the scaling of that
infrastructure and would much
rather outsource that. So this
is mongos applet service, which
I think is fantastic. If you if
you just want to set up a
database, you don't need to set
it up yourself and manage it.
But I Yeah, time will tell
really. And we're curious to
hear from from more people what
they think. And also, on the
premium app site, there's this
additional persona of the third
party developer, right. Are
people interested in developing
for this platform? I think so.
I've spoken with a lot of people
who have been working on
specific capabilities, a lot of
them in the ml or computer
vision space that they want to
market to robotics companies.
And they like the idea to not
having to do all of the legwork
in terms of marketing it and
figuring out deployment and so
forth,
Audrow Nash: having more of an
app store third approach. Yeah,
that would be super cool. I
would love if we had that kind
of thing in the robotics
ecosystem. Just like ROS really
solves a lot of problems, making
it easier for people to build
applications. But it's hard to
get it outside of your robot, as
you're saying, as we've kind of
motivated with the whole first
part of this conversation. And
so if it was like, you just try
to get you would just add
different capabilities on
through an app store like
setting and you can use them
elsewhere. That would be super
cool. Yeah, that's it. Gotcha.
How have you guys been funded so
far? And like, Would you talk a
bit more about the team and
everything,
Christian Fritz: the team is
very small, you're looking at
it. God's just, it's, I'm the
only one fully committed right
now and doing technical
development, I have a short, I
have a small list of advisors.
First and foremost, my previous
co founder, Bob Bauer, he was at
Willow Garage, and he's still
advising me. But he's not a
developer. So there's not too
much for him to do right now.
And funding, it's, it's
completely bootstrapped right
now, where, where we're
profitable in the sense that I'm
doing consulting work for
customers, helping them both
doing custom development, and
then helping them figure out how
to use Transitive as well, which
is a good model, it's, as you
can imagine, you don't get rich
doing that. But it's, it's, it
keeps the lights on. And one
thing that I've seen with
robotics companies, one, one way
that they have failed, was that
once they take money, they have
to spend it once you once you
because your investors want to
use that money to hire a bigger
team and scale faster, which,
which means that you are lacking
in a certain certain product, a
certain business model, and a
certain market fit. And if the
market fit is not great, then
you're trying to scale a
business that was not meant to
be, then you're making you're
you're digging yourself a hole.
And I really want to be certain
that we have absolutely nailed
market fit that we have gotten
adoption that we have validated
that this is something that
people want before we take on
money. And so yeah, I consulting
that actually solves two
problems here. Because, number
one, yes, there's some money
coming into the bank. And number
two, we are actually getting
validation from our customers.
So this, this really lends
itself to an iterative process
that will make sure that we will
build the right product for the
market. Yeah. And I think we
would get into race, no problem.
We've had conversations with
investors, they, they like the
idea that we are basically
indexing on the robotics market.
And what they mean by that is,
rather than so they have the
choice of which companies to
invest in. And they know that in
robotics, the differences are
stark, right? One company may be
doing apple picking the other
one maybe doing drywall
construction, another one may be
layout printing, and another one
is doing delivery on sidewalk,
another one on the street, if
they don't know what to invest
in, they all know that robotics
is going to go up. And there's
plenty of studies by IFR and all
of those API research that tells
us it's going to go through the
roof. It's it's it's a
phenomenal technology. And it's
only sort of at the start, but
they all want to invest and they
don't know where to invest. So
what they like about platforms
like this is that they know that
if robotics will succeed this
company,
Audrow Nash: as well, gotcha.
That's really cool. I really
like bootstrapping, too, as a
model. In general, I get it.
Because one of the other things
with if you take investment is
you kind of commit yourself to a
timeline that you will have some
sort of liquidation event within
some period of years, like
typically less than 10, maybe
closer to five years that the
investor would like to see a
return on their investment. And
that's tough, because as you
said, you have to like really
commit to the current fit, and
it lends itself to a certain
type of product. Yeah, and that
being said, like cobalt
robotics, they're doing the
investment route, and they're
doing a phenomenal job as far as
I can tell. Which is really
interesting. If you position
everything well. And it'll be
cool to see kind of if you start
accepting investment, and how
that helps you scale. But once
you found that really good
market fit, that seems like a
very good approach. So me.
Christian Fritz: Yeah, I'm keen
to get into that point. And I do
have a concrete plan on how to
use that money in the employee
to to foster third party
development. I think there's,
there's there's some really
interesting models that you can
that you can follow. Yeah, I
think that there are a lot of
capability. developers out there
and I love this idea of, of the
marketplace because it has
inherent network effect. So more
capabilities We have of high
quality, the more people would
want to use it, the more people
who come to our, to our app
store to look for capabilities
to what people want to develop
for it. And so that's, you know,
that's the classical network
effect that can that can
actually justify exponential
growth. And investors always
want to see exponential growth.
And I always ask them, Well,
based on what, right, it's not,
it doesn't just happen, right?
There needs to be some sort of
mechanism behind that. And it's
not bouncing a QR code on the
Super Bowl. In Super Bowl x,
right? That's, that's a lot of
money. No, you have to have
something where the classical
Atlas one, right if the ad plus
one user has a better experience
than all of the end before and
makes the experience all of the
end users before that better.
That's network effect. That's
why you have these these
conversions effects where
everybody will use the same
social network, right? If, if
you're the owner, if you and I
go on to a social and create a
new social network, and we're
the only users Well, you don't
have to have great
conversations, but but it's not
as useful as if they're more
friends of ours on that same
thing, right. And so for me, one
that we had, it gets better. And
I think, you know, marketing
marketplaces have that dynamic,
inherently built in, they're
also hard to pull off. That's
where money can be really
helpful. But I think first and
foremost, you have to make sure
that it that it goes about it
the right way and openness. And
I think it's really the the key
to all of that.
Audrow Nash: Hmm, tell me a bit
more about that. That seems very
interesting.
Christian Fritz: Well, I I just
think that if you if you want to
be if you want to establish
yourself as the framework that
everybody develops, on,
contributes toward contributes
to your store, and I'll use the
Android example. Right? Then
then being open is really what
you is really the best thing
that you can do, because you're
you're going to benefit in the
long term from people being on
your platform, if you will find
ways to pay your bills like
that. I like this quote from
Eric Schmidt, when he was still
the CEO of Google, they asked
him back in the day they asked
him, so Eric, how are you ever
going to make money from
Android? And he said, In five
years, there's going to be 1.8
billion users using Android.
We'll figure it out. I think was
brilliant. And of course, he
wasn't the first Microsoft
obviously, famously gave away MS
DOS for free at a time when
others were charging for the
operating systems. And we all
know what that did, right?
People started installing MS DOS
on their phones, just like
Android was free, right, and
they installed Android. And now
there's a big market for for
Android applications. And so
that can be that can be
monetized. And that's, and I
don't say monetize in the sense
of, you know, really making as
much money as possible. It's
more about making enough money
to do a good service and to keep
running and to make sure that it
is serving everybody involved in
the best flip.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, you can
invest it back into it. And it's
basically more ability to make a
larger impact in the future. And
then you just, I don't know,
event like that, that seems
Excellent. That is a good model,
it's interesting to consider the
network effect I had been
previously thinking of, kind of
like a zero replication cost as
the way to get towards
exponential growth, which is
like, I don't know, coding is a
good example. you code it once,
and then you can use it
anywhere. But network effects
seems like a very good thing to
think about, especially when
thinking about like a
marketplace, and this kind of
thing, because as you get more
products on there, it becomes
more valuable. So the n plus
one, as you're saying more
valuable than all the previous
people, venture
Christian Fritz: capitalists,
especially in the SAS world,
look at one ratio more than any
more than one software
Audrow Nash: as a service,
right? That Software as a
Service, yes.
Christian Fritz: They look at
one ratio more more than
anything else and that is the
lifetime value of the customer
over the customer acquisition
cost. And they mostly because
they know that the customer
acquisition cost at first is
tremendously high. They are
totally fine or they almost
expect you to spend three
quarters of all of the money
that they will invest in you on
customer acquisition which
sounds mind boggling at first,
right? What you spent so much
money just to get users why
don't they get that at work?
That's what Yeah, but it that's
why these these network effects
are so valuable from a growth
perspective because it becomes
cheaper and cheaper to acquire
new users Facebook when you when
you think back until not too
long ago, they'd never
advertised anything. It was all
word of mouth and and of course
it was because if I'm on
Facebook, I will actively
recruit my friends to come to
Facebook because hey, I don't
want to share my photos both in
email. And then also on Facebook
and also I want to know what's
what's going on. Your Life,
right? I would love to see that.
And so friends, you know, are
intrinsically motivated to
recruit friends or it doesn't
have to be friends, it can be
developers, colleagues and
whatnot, then there's a real
good chance that things will
grow. And so I think for that
there's this concept of giving
back in substances is important,
right? If I'm a developer on
Transitive, I will be recruiting
people to use it right? I will
advertise the fact that I've I
published something called
Transitive. Sure, the focus will
be on what I've published. But
in the process, I will still be
advertising the platform as
well. And then people may go,
oh, yeah, I've been consuming
capabilities through transit,
CIF, and we have developed this
cool, new, whatever it is map
display map editing tool for for
robotics, we could we could
publish that back as well.
Audrow Nash: What do you think
will be so kind of going from
where you are to starting a
marketplace of different
capabilities? What do you
imagine? Like, how will you get
from here to marketplace? Yeah,
what are how are you thinking to
proceed.
Christian Fritz: So marketplace
is, of course, the longer term
vision and aspiration as you
can, you can't even build a
platform from from day one, you
have to go vertical to
horizontal, you have to have
something that where your early
users will get some real value
out right away, before they even
recognize that there's a
platform and that they can do
more things. So that's why we we
will develop certain
capabilities ourselves. And on
our website, we already have
three that you can people can
use right away. And ease of
getting started, I think it's
really important there. So if
people are totally within 30
seconds, have can have a remote
video streaming capability,
which they previously thought
would take them months to build.
That's a great experience. And I
think that's something that we
can market and start growing up.
This is actually again, going
back to Facebook, not not very
different from the way that they
got started. If you if you may
remember, they were first just
an application for students at
Harvard, right. And then for a
while they were just for college
students. And then they brought
out like that. And it's it's a
nice model, because when you
think about it, first, you
basically conquer a small part.
But you try to get to something
like 90% users, like 90% of the
people are in that pond use it.
And of course, at that point,
okay, you've convinced yourself
that first of all, young people
want that second of all, the
network effect works. And these
people have friends outside of
Harvard, right? So they will
talk to them, and they will,
they will talk about Facebook,
and people are like, well, I
can't use it yet. But that so
that creates some some, some
sense of desire. And I think
that's, that's really the model
of vertical to horizontal, you
want to start with something
that is very small, where you
get a lot of value for
potentially a very small market
at first. But I have absolutely
absolutely no doubt about the
fact that
Audrow Nash: they are how great
it is. Yeah. How do you how do
you think you'll get your first
Harvard or whatever, in the
robotics community? Is it the
video streaming app that people
will be using? Or where do you?
Or is it sunset of the ROS
community? Or what do you think?
Christian Fritz: So we
definitely target the rust
community right now. And
especially specifically, we're
actually targeting the rust one
community, which may surprise
some of your listeners. It's
gonna ask you both want to rush
through? Yeah. So right now
we're focusing on rust one. And
that's for a very simple reason.
From us pyramids, everybody who
has an actual fleet of robots
out there that grows up using
ROS 1, and I wish it was
different, because I think ROS
two has some has some really
nice features. But until not too
long ago, it wasn't necessarily
perceived as really ready for
primetime if we've seen all of
those discussions on this course
and elsewhere. So the vast
majority of robots out there
still using ROS 1. And so
breaking into that would be sort
of the first step. The platform
that we built is not specific to
ROS 2 or ROS 1 that the
capabilities that you will build
are. And then in terms of which
capabilities to focus on. Yeah,
I think low latency video
streaming and remote tailor some
very good ones to get started
with, we know from from from
some of the existing offerings,
that's also some of the most
popular features. In fact, there
are now companies like Dr. Yu
and Fenton auto, that offer
specific remote control
capabilities for originally self
driving cars, but now they are
doing a lot of business with
auto delivery robots. So there
is a there's an absolute need
there. And so I think that's a
that's a good way to get
started. Mm hmm.
Audrow Nash: See, is there Well,
I guess, do you? How do you
imagine your team will grow over
time?
Christian Fritz: I mean, this
is, of course, a little bit of a
chicken and egg question. But we
have to first get some traction
so we can hire and then we can
get a team. But of course, in
order to high end, people may
also want to know about that
strategy at 70 of my entire team
was remote. Which, at first, I
thought is not possible for a
robotics company, because we're
dealing with hardware, right?
How can I do that remotely, but
I learned there that it is
absolutely possible. And it has
some real big benefits, like on
so many levels, like, for one,
you can tap into a much broader
pool of talent, right? Great
developers all around the world,
not just in Silicon Valley.
They, it also solves another
problem that we have here in
Silicon Valley, there's housing
is insanely expensive, because
everybody had water, if we can
work remotely. We don't need to
make this housing market here.
Any works? I know. And, and
yeah, so I'm a big believer in
hiring remotely. We have worked
in the past with people. I had
people on my team from Germany,
France, Spain, Argentina,
several places in the US, one of
my employees actually was
driving his RV, through through
the country almost every minute
started by asking where are you
today? And sometimes he had to
apologize, because there was not
enough sun to use the solar
panels to charge this batteries.
But that happened very rarely.
But it worked. And I thought it
was it really added to the
diversity of the kind of
perspective of the team. So I
want to follow that same model
and focus on like, build a
remote first kind of company.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, that seems
super cool. What are some of the
because you, you seem to like
you've been implementing
everything. So I imagine, like,
I'm wondering what what will the
first people? What will their
roles be? Do you think as you
start to grow, or as you start
to have more interest and
investment, and then have the
ability to hire some people?
Where do you think you'll start,
I think
Christian Fritz: we will be
hiring mostly on the engineering
side. And I will be handing off
more and more to my team and
focus more on the on the
leadership in sort of external
facing requirements. I also
before law, will hire a product
manager. Because I think it is
actually really important to to
really feel customers out and
understand what what pain points
they have and how we are
addressing them. And I'm also
just going by things that I know
myself, I'm not very good at.
That's perhaps the best advice
that ever got for hiring to try
to hire somebody is when you can
find somebody who can do that
role better than you. Not before
that. They're not after it's not
it's sometimes people think of
oh, I'm too overburdened, I
should hire somebody to do these
things. But if you then don't
find somebody who you really
trust to do it better than you,
it's too early to hire because
you will be questioning them and
to have micromanaging that that
will not make anybody happy. So
a lot of it will have to do also
with finding the right people at
the right time it filling in
until then then yourself which
again is is fine. Well, you're
bootstrapping. And then once
we've once we've raised money,
it will be there will be a
slightly different question. But
that will still to the to the
extent possible people model
Audrow Nash: chacha, I really
like that model. It's
interesting, because I mean, you
think if you hire someone, and
like it is to take weight off
your shoulders, if you're trying
to do everything. But then if
you don't trust them to do the
work well, then it's like, well,
now you're micromanaging. And
now you have that job still
through micromanaging. In a
sense,
Christian Fritz: I think it goes
back to the question of
accountability versus reliable,
being responsible. And I think
at the end, what you need us,
people who distribute on to whom
you can distribute the
accountability, people who you
can rely on being accountable
for something happening and
having that attitude to say,
like, well, maybe I wasn't
supposed to be working on this,
maybe it was somebody on my
team, but it's not there, I'm
going to fix it, right. That's
kind of the attitude that we
need. I've seen this in
engineering teams a lot like
sometimes the the, the amount of
features that you need to
implement, you just have too
many features or too much code
for the size of your team. There
needs to be I always think of
attempt with tentacles. That way
if you have two or three
temples, you can cover a lot of
ground just by you know spending
something over but some but at
certain points you have to hold
up the tent. You cannot with one
temple cover a lot, a lot of
area because they cannot look
there or the explanation There's
what the amount of code that you
are responsible for, as a
developer, it cannot be
infinitely not a one developer
can be responsible for 100,000
lines of code, a good rule of
thumb that I have is between
10,020 1000 lines of code per
developer is a good number.
Beyond that, you will just not
be very effective. Because if
every time you switch tasks, you
have to re familiarize yourself
with the code that you're
dabbling in, then you are in
trouble. Right. And so having
that getting that ratio down, is
it's quite important, I
Audrow Nash: think. Gotcha. Do
you think that's kind of the way
to proceed? Where you have
people in a sense specialize on
specific spots of the code. So
10 to 20,000 lines per person
where they kind of like, divvy
it up? Yeah, each person has
like a little silo? In a sense.
Christian Fritz: Yeah, I think
so. And I think with our
architecture, in particular, it
lends itself to that, because we
have the framework itself, which
breaks down into the components
for robot cloud front end. Yeah.
But then we also have the
capabilities which are super
important, right? I mean, they
aren't, and they are by design
standalone. So you don't, in
fact, it is a good thing, if
you're not too familiar with
what's going on in the platform,
because you're supposed to treat
it like a user, like the
documentation says, I should be
doing this. And that's what I
done, and it doesn't work. Okay.
Thanks, file a ticket, but you
don't have to fix it, I will fix
it. Right. And I think that's,
that's how we can divide it up
and also find interesting ways
of working together, right. So
you know, when you're working
with a remote team, sometimes
it's preferable to have
contractors rather than
employees, people may not want
to commit full time completely,
but only part of the time. And
so having this actually a
product, which is componentize,
like that lends itself to
offering all sorts of ways to
work to get right. If somebody
wants to work half time on this,
and really just wants to develop
a specific capability but wants
to get paid for it, rather than
selling it on the marketplace
afterwards. That's great,
Audrow Nash: we'd be we'd be
open to that. That's super cool.
It's very flexible, I haven't
thought of that kind of model,
where someone can be hired as a
contractor just for a specific
thing that they want to add. But
it's maybe too large to take on.
It's like a free project or this
kind of thing. Very cool. Yeah,
I
Christian Fritz: think since the
pandemic, we have seen more and
more models for how to work
remotely. And of course, they
have been even before the
pandemic, there have been things
like, I think Upwork, and Zephyr
and take these search kinds of
tools that are platforms that
allow you to outsource some
work. But I think there's a
spectrum of you know, from being
a full time employee thing to
being an hourly contractor for a
short time, there's there's a
lot to be explored in between.
And only because you're a
contractor, for instance,
doesn't mean that you can't be
treated like an employee. I
mean, it's just, to me, that's
just the burn Pratik aspect of
what's, what are you call it on
paper, but the relationship can
still be that of an employee and
location shouldn't matter for
that at
Audrow Nash: all? Yeah, for
sure. Especially I feel like
with, like with programming
tasks, I mean, we work on
GitHub, you do reviews and
things like this, it works
really well, asynchronously, is
what I'm struck by. So far,
being an Open Robotics,
Christian Fritz: it does when
you're set up for that. One
thing that I've seen, of course,
comparing those with a lot of my
friends at other companies. One
thing that I've seen, especially
with some larger companies in
the Bay Area that frown upon
remote work, and I'm not going
to mention their name. They,
they have this problem that like
90% of the people until the
pandemic were in the office. And
so anybody who was remote felt
left out, right, there were a
lot of decisions that were being
made in person meetings that
were not documented, and so
forth. And that was really hard
for the remote team. But if you
set up like a remote first
company, and some people just
happen to meet in the office,
that's it's a completely
different ballgame. Every
decision will be made in a
ticket, and everybody can chime
in, everybody can see what the
record was what led to it. And
that has so many benefits, not
just for inclusion of the remote
team. Also just for refreshing
your memory two years later is
gonna
Audrow Nash: say future you.
Christian Fritz: I always think
of it like that every time I've
write documentation. I'm sure
that I'm doing my future self a
favor. Yes.
Audrow Nash: For sure. Now, I
would love to get your thought
more thoughts more on web and
robotics, kind of how you see
actually starting it super
broad. How do you think web and
robotics kind of? I don't know,
like what do you see is the
relationship between the two
like web tools and robotics?
Christian Fritz: Yeah, I mean,
obviously I'm a big believer in
web tools. I actually have a
another bootstrap company that
is Based on web technology, it's
for scientists, I've been
running it since 2006. So I've
gone through this whole process
of web development and really
learn to love it. What I'm
struggling with in the robotics
community is that there's that
there's still a little bit of a
divide there sort of a, I
sometimes call it the group of
believers, and those who who
don't yet believe in web
technology, the tools I love
ROS, but some of the UIs like
Qt, it's not, it's not up to
snuff these days anymore. It's
not, it's not developing as fast
as web technologies, it's not as
accessible. The benefits of web
technology, the perhaps the
biggest benefit of web
technology is that everybody
immediately has access, because
they have a web browser on any
device that they have, like the
desktop portable, and Linux,
Windows, Mac, iOS, some people,
I think, still run always to
whatever you want, right? I
think I have it on your phone,
you will have access, you don't
need to run Linux to visualize
something, for instance. So I
think that by itself is perhaps
one of the biggest benefits. And
it kind of enables a broader
group of users to write side
adservio, we had a very
important part of the company
was field ops, because of
course, it's 70, we were running
robotics as a service. So we
were on the hook for making sure
that our robots work in the
field. And if there was a
problem, we wouldn't just, you
know, it wasn't our customers
problem was our problem, we
would fix it, and suddenly turn
into robots, triaging, and so
forth. That was a that was a big
part of what we did. But we
didn't want to have engineers to
have that because engineers were
busy writing, you know,
improving the software. So we
have this role of field ops
engineers. And they may not know
much about ROS nor nor do you
want to train them, because that
would be a real big limiting
factor for hiring. So being able
to give them tools that they
know how to use really enables
them, it lowers your cost, makes
makes everything easier. And so
there's a lot of a lot of good
reasons, I think, like that for
for web technologies. And now I
think what we need to do is
collectively build the tools to
make exactly that development
easier. You and I meet on the on
the ROS web tools are working
group every two weeks, and
there's a group of others,
especially the folks on
foxglove. We're very active on
that. And I think it's great
that there's all of these
contributions being made. And I
think that's how we fit in with
Transitive as well, like being
able to offer a piece of the
puzzle that helps with with data
synchronization across devices
and remote, remote robots,
hopefully will contribute to the
to this open source, web
technology ecosystem, that we
can all kind of build the
future.
Audrow Nash: Do you this, this
might be a crazy question. But
do you ever see web technologies
on the back end? Or robotic
navigation? So like, maybe like
a ROS client library and
TypeScript or something like
that? Do you think there's a
place for this?
Christian Fritz: Oh, absolutely.
I guess I should mention that
I'm one of the contributors of
rational js, which is, you know,
just like raw CPP, or ROS pi is
a native binding for for ROS.
So it speaks ROS, it just makes
TCP connections to all of the
other ROS nodes. But it's
written in Node J. S. It's a
it's a native implementation.
And, yeah, I mean, I personally
use it a lot, right? It's
certainly not as fast as C++, if
you have something that really
requires high performance, like
I wouldn't necessarily use it
for point cloud transformation.
But yeah, if you want to put
something together quickly, it's
similar. It really, I think
scratches is similar as where
you would use Python. Because
you can write it very quickly.
You can test it very easily
because it has an interpreter.
And yeah, so for sure. I mean,
they are and there are others,
right. There's ROS no Chase,
which was originally started by
Brendan Alexander and at Willow
Garage. He later became the CEO
of, of iron oxen. He was too
busy to maintain it. I took it
over at one point and around the
same time, the folks that
Rethink Robotics started to
rewrite it. So the current
version of ROS no chases based
on on what Christmas, everything
developed. And there's
alternatives. There's similar
libraries for ROS 2, as well.
I don't know I don't think it's
crazy at all. I think it's a
it's a fine language to develop
in. It's very quick to develop
in that and it's very, it has
this very nice ecosystem that
allows you to share very quickly
Audrow Nash: see, so, where do
you think robotics We'll be more
generally in like, where do you
see us going as a robotics
community in the next, say, two
to five years?
Christian Fritz: Now, that's an
interesting question. I don't I
don't spend too much time
thinking about that. But I guess
I can extrapolate a little bit
from my, from my view of the
robotics, the startups in the
space right now. Which I looked
at very carefully after, after,
after leaving Savio, Goodwin,
wondering what to do next. One
thing that struck me, of course
was, and this shouldn't be too
surprising, but I still think
it's worth mentioning the
successful robotic startups are
the ones that find a problem
worth solving first, and then
convince themselves that
robotics is the best way to
solve it. And that's, which is
honestly not happy. That's not
always been the case. Right? In
the past. There were a lot of
robotics companies that that
were trying to solve that hammer
nail problem of we have a robot,
but can we use for what to do
with it? And so I'm very excited
about this new model. And I
think that's actually what's
behind it. Again, not too
surprisingly, behind the success
of so many new robotics
companies in so many different
spaces. I mean, even just, what
is it like eight years ago, they
were they were all that many
applications of robotics,
outside of, you know, car
manufacturing. And then at the
time, that was roughly the time
when the Kiva acquisition
happened. So we were aware of
the warehouse robots, which
still was sort of a novelty.
Apart from the AGVs, that were
just following, you know, simple
trucks. And now you look around
and you find so many startups in
so many different spaces, act
Tech is a particularly
interesting space. If you ask
me, there are so many problems
there. That the and that's where
I live, like you're the title of
your podcast, sit in a sense,
plan, act, or sense Think Act
works better than the blanket
approach, because that's really
what a robot does, right? It
senses it decides what to do.
And then it acts and
when you look at for instance,
what Blue River does in
appetite, right, they will go
over a field and rather than
applying pesticides everywhere,
they will actually take a good
look at the crop that is
growing. And they will decide
how to act like what to where to
apply pesticides. And the amount
of pesticides that you use as a
result is of course, much lower,
which which is fantastic, from
an ecological point of view, but
also is a very good business
proposition. You're building
you're growing better crops. And
that's I, I really congratulate
you on that on the choice of
that of that name for the
podcast, because it is so it is
core for for what a robot does.
And it's also describes the
value very much right. But
there's so many areas that we
could explore with this
mentality of where are we
currently doing a blanket
approach where it would be
smarter to take you to look that
aside and then act and of
course, this is now being made
possible by better software,
better compute that allows us to
implement algorithms that do
service and that do think,
right, that that wasn't
necessarily possible before. And
I think it's it's super
exciting. There's one particular
area that I'm very curious of,
and that is this whole idea of
semi sorry, mixed initiative,
operation, or no, that means, so
any sort of tele operation where
you are not controlling the
robot entirely, but only perhaps
giving certain signals and then
having the robot do other
things, to kind of falls into
that category. And I think
that's a, it's a very
interesting space to look at.
Because another thing that
robotics companies in mind have
done wrong. And I'm saying that
now, I would have made the same
mistake until a few years ago,
but they made the mistake of
trying to automate everything
from the get go. Whereas
nowadays, you see a lot of very
successful robotics companies
start with fully manual approach
remote controlled, and basically
say, Let's own the problem.
First, let's build the business
problem. First, let's, let's
build a customer base, and then
automated more and more and more
to reduce our cost. And I think
that's a fantastic model.
Because you will be learning if
you will know what to automate
in the process. And the most of
the value may actually come from
something that is relatively
easy, right. So I'll give the
examples of sidewalk delivery
robots. I personally have to
admit that I was laughing at
starship when I first saw the
robot, because I looked at it
and go like you will never be
autonomous. And they laughed
back and said, We don't try to
be fully autonomous because they
they basically recognize that
they have evolved a lot since
then. But in the other day,
Steve recognized that if they
have a robot that can reliably
drive forward without bumping
into anything and noticing when
there is an obstacle and just
stop as opposed to doing all of
the great you know, path
planning, like the stuff that
you've discussed with Steve last
time, about you know, going on
around obstacles dilating the
obstacles and dealing with, with
all sorts of situations, if you
just focus on this one thing,
then all of a sudden you can
have one pilot control, whatever
it is 10 different robots at the
same time, because most of the
time, they are actually driving
by themselves. And then when
they get in trouble that they
will ask you questions that you
just, you know, we're pretty
quick without without which we
humans, right, we see this,
decide what to do which other
robot what to do. And so that
way, you can really kind of make
a step function, a gradient,
right. And of course, anybody in
machine learning will tell you
that that's the secret behind
all learning neural networks as
well, that if you have, yes, in
the end, you may need a step
function. But to learn it, you
need to smooth it out. And by
smoothing it out by giving a way
to move along that spectrum
between full automation and for
the remote control really
enables a lot of a lot of
innovation. So I'm really
curious to see what will come
from that. From a kind of vision
point of view, I like to
I sometimes ask myself, whether
it will be possible to make
everybody in the world able to
work remotely. And what I mean
by that is, we we've we've seen
that during the during the
pandemic, right, they were the I
would call us, the fortunate
ones who were able to just work
remotely and those whose job
required them to go in and they
had a big problem, either. They
couldn't go in because it was
shut down because we had
lockdowns and they suffered
economically. And that caused a
lot of hardship on a lot of
people, or they weren't able to
go in, but they sometimes, you
know, suffered and had to take
the risk of getting affected
more easily with COVID. And
that's exactly what happened. So
from almost from a fairness
perspective, I asked myself,
well, what would it take to
automate all of them not
automate, but make it possible
for everybody to work remotely.
And we've seen some, some very,
perhaps eyebrow raising examples
of that of humanoid robots being
remote control to stock shelves
in seven elevens in Japan,
where, you know, somebody was
remote controlling the arms to
take cans out of out of a tray
and opening the fridge and
putting them in there. And
people laughed at that, but
actually think that's, it's,
it's tremendous. It's, it's
exactly how we should be
thinking about it. And if you
start by remote controlling that
and then ask yourself, well,
which of these things can
actually automate? And which
ones are the really hard ones?
And just identifying the problem
and frame phrasing it? Well,
there will be actually no
shortage of people who will be
interested in solving that. Both
of us have been in academia for
long enough to know that, in
academia, often the problem is
finding the problem, like
finding a real product that fits
my solution, right? So there's,
there's almost a thirst for
problems. So if you if we as as
sort of a, the ecosystem of
companies in robotics can
identify problems worth solving,
and frame them really well. So
that we can sort of hand them
over to academia, academia would
love us, and we would love them
back for the for the solutions
that they give us. And I think
that's like building bridges
like that, between academia and
applied research and robotics in
particular, is something really
worth working towards. And I
think it's, it's really
exciting.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Well, I
think we'll end it there. Thank
you very much. Thank you,
everyone. Thanks for listening
to this conversation with
Christian Fritz. Thank you again
to our founding sponsor, open
robotics. See you next time.