Audrow Nash: This is a
conversation with Brett Aldrich
who is the CEO of a Robosoft AI.
Robosoft AI develops and
maintains SMAC, which is a
library that aims to make it
easier for roboticists to
control robot behavior. One of
the key ideas in SMAC is that a
finite state machines, we'll be
referring to finite state
machines a lot in this
interview, so I'll explain what
they are. Before we start.
Imagine that you have a lawn
mowing robot. Imagine that that
robot is powered off, and that
you turn it on by pushing a
button, it boots up and drives
to a field to mow. When it gets
to the field, it starts mowing.
Once it finishes mowing, it
drives home and powers off. This
robot has states like powered
off, booting up driving, and
mowing. The robot also has
transitions that occur on
events, such as when the robot
is turned on by you pressing the
power button, or the robot
arrives at the grass to mow
these transitions change the
robot from one state to another.
For example, the event of
arriving at the field to mow
could transition the robot from
the state of driving to mowing.
So summarizing, a finite state
machine is something made up of
states like driving, and mowing,
and transitions when the robot
has reached the destination, or
when it has finished mowing.
This is the sense think act
Podcast. I'm Audrow Nash. Thank
you to our founding sponsor open
robotics. And now here's my
conversation with Brett Aldrich.
Would you introduce yourself?
Brett Aldrich: My name is Brett
Aldrich, and I'm the author of
Smak. State Machine library for
robotic applications written in
C Plus Plus, I'm also the
founder of robust soft AI. Robot
soft. We're the keepers of the
smack tool chain. We're also the
creators of the smack to runtime
analyzer. A graphical
application lets you visualize
your state machines both
statically and at runtime.
Audrow Nash: Hmm. And what so
can you start at a high level
and explain what SMAC is, and
then what its motivation is?
Sure.
Brett Aldrich: SMACC is a state
machine library for robotic
applications. I'd like to
describe it as dealing with the
highest level of task planning
and management on a robotic
system. It has many unique
features. And.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so it's a,
it's a high level state machine
library that helps you figure
out so you get to control your
robotics application with it.
Brett Aldrich: It's a control,
it's an architecture for
control. And a couple of things
about it. You know, when you're
writing your state machine, what
one it it provides a tight
integration with. With Ross,
allowing you to generate events
for Ross topics, services
actions right out of the box. It
also offers a reference library
of state machines that are
guaranteed to compile and run
right out of the box.
Audrow Nash: So by reference
library, you mean a bunch of
state machines you can already
use for specific things. Okay.
Brett Aldrich: Exactly, exactly.
With, with simulation included
for many of them. Gotcha. It
also offers a client library.
And this, this is part of the
architecture of SMAC. That
allows Ross users to use Ross
packages like move it to or nav
to right out of the box. And it
also provides a pathway for
other Ross packages. And for the
interfaces of those packages to
be developed by specialists that
are then tied to your state
machine it all of these features
have the effect of dramatically
lowering the bar for new
developers to get started in
Ross, and then in programming in
general controlling their robot.
I can go on quite a bit longer
about this, but I would say so
it's a good high level overview
of what SMAC is,
Audrow Nash: is it kind of so
that if I if I'm using smack, I
can kind of compose more complex
behaviors out of almost like
blocks that will affect their
behavior and I can, I don't
know, like, if I have this
sensor, I can run use this block
to send out the data? Or is that
how it looks kind of like a
bunch of blocks that I can
compose together?
Brett Aldrich: Yes, yes, you
have, you have state you have
states, right? That you can let
us to divide your problems. You
have hierarchy, which does much
the same thing. You also have
the concepts of orthogonal,
which are like boxes that allow
you to modularize the physical
subsystems on a robot.
Audrow Nash: Okay, and by that
you mean kind of control them
independently or use them into
basically, right. Can you give
me a more an example, I suppose?
Brett Aldrich: Yeah, absolutely.
In fact, I'm gonna show a robot
that that was recently built
using smack as an example. So
this robot is from field work
robotics, it was built by them
along with ourselves in Bosch,
India. And as you can see,
there's four robot arms and a
couple of trays, and navigation
based, so looks like a fruit
picking robot or exactly. It
picks raspberries. Yeah. And it
was based on the work of Dr.
Sutton's at the University of
Plymouth and his soft robotics
lab.
Audrow Nash: So that just to
describe it for the audio
listeners, it's kind of like a
big moving cart with four
different arms. That probably it
that's on wheels and probably
drives through and picks stuff
for it. Would you say? That's,
that's a good description of it,
I think to add Exactly, exactly.
Okay, so use this.
Brett Aldrich: So each
orthogonal, contains an arm. So
there's this orthogonal one with
each arm. Another thought for
the base, there's probably two
more orthogonal is for there was
like, like a packaging. Not
exactly sure what you call it,
almost like a gantry. A small
gantry inside for for packaging,
the raspberries. You probably
also have your cameras with
perception, all of these would
would go into an orthogonal
using a model of let's say, the
human body. You might have
orthogonal for your eyes,
another two orthogonal for each
arm. Yet another orthogonal, so
is
Audrow Nash: it? Can you think
of it kind of like a degree of
freedom? Yes, in a sense, yeah,
you can. Yeah, cuz, so I mean,
I'm thinking of so orthogonal,
which means, like, it has a
technical definition, which I
think is it's the dot product is
zero, or something like this,
right? So it basically means
perpendicular, but it allows for
higher dimensions. Right? And so
it's like a new dimension, a new
dimension and state space kind
of thing.
Brett Aldrich: You know, I, the
term that is I use it comes from
comes from boost HR. And it was
always tied to physical
subsystems. But actually from
boosted, charted, inherited
originally from David Harold's
1987. Paper on state charts. So
in 1987, David Harrell came up
with state charts. And he
developed that formalism that I
guess you'd call it an extension
of the formalism of state
machines while working as a
consultant, Israeli Aircraft
industries, and in particularly,
in particular working on an
avionics system. And so in that,
in that context of a fighter
jet, each orthogonal basically
was tied to a physical
subsystem. Hmm. Yeah. As opposed
to, I think a more like a
mathematical interpretation,
which is, I think, where you are
going more
Audrow Nash: with yes, that's
where I know the word from I
haven't heard it. And this in
this this state machine sense.
Okay. So then, so you have all
these different orthogonal, I'm
thinking of them kind of like a
general degree of freedom, where
multiple so if you said a full
arm is one, it's kind of like a
subsystem. And then maybe you
want to do things with it. And
maybe that subsystem has several
degrees of freedom, like a
shoulder and an elbow and a
wrist, which is controlling it
independently of other parts of
the system. Is that kind of the
core part? It's an orthogonal is
something that is controlled
independent of other parts of
the system? Yes. Okay. Yes. So
I'm thinking generalized degree
of freedom. So multiple degrees
of freedom
Brett Aldrich: is probably
modularity. Yeah. Yep. Yep.
Audrow Nash: And can you have
can you have orthogonal in
orthogonal? Like, if I have an
orthogonal that's my arm? Can I
have that broken down into
orthogonal is that are my
shoulder, wrist and elbow? Is
that kind of this hierarchy?
Okay,
Brett Aldrich: so I think the
short answer is no. The
orthogonal is can be quite
complex, and so you deaf We can
have multi joint, real, you
know, arms in
Audrow Nash: one orthogonal,
orthogonal.
Brett Aldrich: But one of the
things that that that we did we
being Pablo and I in terms of
the robot, sorry, what? Oh,
Audrow Nash: sorry, I thought we
were still talking about the
robot for picking
Brett Aldrich: things in Yeah,
not for that robot in
particular, but in, in SMAC, as
a library and viewing smack in a
historical context. One of the
things that that we we did was,
we took the orthogonal concept
that David Harrell and Andreas
Huber Dawn, put into, into, you
know, instantiated essentially
in boost a chart, and we
simplify, and because up until
that point, so I think the world
of Andreas Huber Donny, but he
didn't, he never really used the
orthogonal and the orthogonal in
a, in a, in like a context of a
PC really don't make that much
sense. And so we took them and
began to use them, and we saw
shortcomings with them. And so
we, we simplified the orthogonal
structure and, and then what we
did was we added this, this
architecture part of clients and
client behaviors. So inside of
each orthogonal, so visualizing,
and orthogonal is a box, right,
a box inside an eight box, there
are generally two to further
boxes inside that have a client
and a client behavior. The
client is has a lifetime of the
entire state machine. So if you
if you have something that you
have some piece of code that you
want to effect that robot in
every state, then you just put
it in the client. So this would
be something like, let's say,
you've got a connection to a
robot arm. And if at any time
you lose that connection, you
want some event to be thrown,
you put that in the client, the
client behavior contrast,
Audrow Nash: oh, it's like a
global state in a sense. Yeah,
Brett Aldrich: there is there
was a blow valatie to it. It's a
different type of state, though,
in that. Typically, in smack,
we're talking about states in a
control sense. The states that
are stored inside clients are
more like, like an image state.
This gets confusing actually,
what it's like when you hear
about something like state
estimation, it's more like an
image in a sense, right? So that
part is stored, whereas the
control states are always
explicitly controlled within
smack the state machine back to
the talk. So if you've got
clients that are scoped to the
life of the state machine and
client behaviors, they're only
scoped to the life of that
state. And and you can have more
than one client behavior at any
one time. And I would say that
that's where really the
modularity comes in. That's
basically how you interact with
the orthogonal is through the
client behaviors, the client
that sets up, you know, would
say, all the communication and
all the kind of stuff that you
want throughout the lifetime of
the state machine. But the
particular behaviors are in are
in these modular client
behaviors that
Audrow Nash: so the client is
like, it's the manager of, but
so how do you call it so you
have the client and the client
is in a? What was the word
again, orthogonal? That so you
haven't or thought so you have
like a global state, and then
from the global state, you have
your orthogonal, your orthogonal
is some piece that can be
controlled independently of all
of the other orthogonal, and
then inside that orthogonal, you
have a client, and that client
is going to control that
orthogonal to run several
different behaviors given the
state. Am I understanding
correctly? Not the client
Brett Aldrich: and the client
behavior. But okay, what's the
sorry? What's the client
behavior? The client behavior is
different in that its lifetime
is scoped only to that state?
Audrow Nash: And how are we
talking about states? And this
You were saying something about
images? And what is the state in
this?
Brett Aldrich: Yeah, we're
talking about it thinking from a
control structure. So going back
from like, a global, yep, the
state machine is essentially
synonymous with the application
layer. Right? So the state
machine is your application. And
there's one state machine on any
one robot I mean, one time,
okay. Many libraries have like
where you start nesting state
machines inside of each other. I
don't, we don't do that with you
don't like it. Yeah, okay. I
think it it creates problems
with data with routing the data
and other problems. So, so you
have a state machine that It is
your application. And within
that state machine, you have a
series of states, and they can
be grouped in different levels
of or higher of hierarchy. So
let's say let's say back to
Audrow Nash: that vegetable
picking robot. Like that would
be a nice concrete example, to
talk about this. Okay.
Brett Aldrich: Okay, yeah, we'll
use that. And also, we'll blend
in an example that I heard about
it for the DARPA subterranean
challenge. So in starting out,
or in one of these teams that
I've had the pleasure of
speaking with people involved,
they started out with a four
state state machine. Okay, so
four states. So in that, in that
example, you would have one
state machine with four states
moving forward, nor hierarchy at
this point, I
Audrow Nash: see, I see one of
my points of confusion. So state
in robotics, and like a control
sense can mean like, the thing
that defines where the robot is.
So this joint has this degree,
this angle, this joint has the
next one. So I was trying to
understand this, but you're
using state as an in a state
machine. So is a specific state
that the state machine is in.
And that's what we're talking
about when we're saying stuck in
this. Okay. So then we're saying
we have a finite number of
states, those control basically
the behaviors, or we can do
different behaviors in different
states. And we move through from
one state to another as the
operation proceeds or something
like this based on Okay,
exactly, I see an ambiguity,
okay, that I was confused by.
But it is it's a confusing
thing. And especially, yeah,
we'll just have to say state for
state machines or something and
states for controls or
something. And that will help
keep me clear with it. Or I'll
try to make it explicit anyways.
Okay, so you have your state.
Brett Aldrich: So this is back
to this example, we have four
states, right? So, and we'll
just name them state, 123, and
four. So in each of these
states, going back to the
example of that field, work
robotics robot, we would have,
let's say, Okay, we got one
orthogonal for each arm, one for
a base, one for the two
gantries, that's for six, seven,
and let's say one for perception
eight. Okay, so in each of those
four states, you're going to see
eight orthogonal 's, that okay,
inside you, each one will have a
client in every state. And then,
depending on what behaviors we
want that robot to express, we
arranged the client behaviors
accordingly. And so it provides
like a modular control structure
for each subsystem of the robot.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So if you
are, yeah, and the state
Brett Aldrich: basically serves
is like, this gets more into
like the sub state architecture
of smack, but
those, the client behaviors, and
the clients throw events based
on what happens outside, you
know, so smack is a single node,
operate back to this example.
Smack is a single process
operating at runtime. And you're
also going to have, you know,
other processes on this system,
you're going to probably have
nav two, you're going to have
move it. One with perception.
And so when those other nodes
communicate via let's say, Ross
topics or services, the the SMAC
clients will turn those
messages, which you'll specify
into events. And then those
events are that's cool ordinated
by the state, like, like a
conductor would, you know, on
this event, we transition to
this state, at the end of the
day states are a lot of people,
you might you might incoming to
state machines, you might think
that states, that's the state
machines are about states, and
they're really not they're about
events. And okay, it's through
events that you begin the
subject of states almost, it's
like, it begs the question, you
know, like, when you have an
event, you have what was before
and what's after, right?
Audrow Nash: And then can you
define an event? Can you define
event,
Brett Aldrich: an event is
general explanations. It's like
some type of discrete.
Audrow Nash: So in Ross, it
would be have I received this
message or not sure. Is the
event is the message occurring,
this kind of thing.
Brett Aldrich: Exactly. Exactly.
Are they completing or
Audrow Nash: are they action
completing or something like
that? So if I'm using naff to,
and I want to move from one spot
to another spot, the action
completing of me moving to the
To location could be the event.
So it says I'm in this location
event has occurred, I then
occur.
Brett Aldrich: And then when
that event is occurred in some
in smack in a state Yeah, you
specify often where you will
like what the next state you'll
transition to is.
Audrow Nash: So are we always
transitioning on events? Or
should you always go to another
state, or you can probably stay
in the same state and have
several events. I'm just trying
to think of more complex
behavior. But so are events
always used? They're not always
used for transitions, but they
Brett Aldrich: not always but
and here, we get into the minute
you start using events, you
start using more. One of the
another one of the features we
added to I'm saying these are
things that I think are
interesting, historically
insensitive, like what's unique
about smack, you know, versus a
blue state chart. And what
happened before we we brought in
the concept of state reactors.
Audrow Nash: Let us define a few
things just because there's a
few things that I don't quite
understand before we get into
state reactors. So I don't quite
understand the difference
between clients and client
behaviors.
Brett Aldrich: Sure, it comes
down to the lifetime client, oh,
or lifetime to the state
machine. And behaviors have a
lifetime specific to that event.
Audrow Nash: Oh, okay. So so, so
client behaviors are just for
behaviors? Or how does it what
why are they named that? Let me
just see, I think my smoke alarm
is gone, or some smoke alarm?
Brett Aldrich: Sounds like a
smoke alarm.
Audrow Nash: I do hear a beep
beep. We just filter it out in
the thing. So long as I don't
smell smoke and whatever. Yeah.
Okay,
Brett Aldrich: you do get out of
there. Yeah, for sure. Just gets
into like the systematic
architecture of code layout SMAC
offers. So let's say you have
something that you want that
robot to do, like some type of
event that you want to respond
to in a particular way. But you
want that to be throughout the
like every state of the state
machine, you put that code in
the client.
Audrow Nash: I see. Okay, so and
then. So you're kind of you
generate these client behaviors,
when the event happens. And that
will take care of a specific,
it's the kind of created and
destroyed on a specific event,
whereas the other one occurs all
the time, I'm thinking of them,
like, kind of simple, but for
like web pages, or something
like you always want to load
this one thing, it's going to
happen no matter what page you
do. So it's like the header or
something, that's always going
to be the same. And then your
client behaviors would be the
very specific things that are on
a specific route, in this case,
yep. Is that a fair way to think
about it?
Brett Aldrich: It's not very
good, and the only nitpicking
thing I would have there is that
it's there not so much. The
client behaviors aren't created
with events, they're created
with new states. So one state to
another, that's when the client
behavior is created at runtime.
Audrow Nash: Okay, I see. Okay.
And then you're gonna so there
was another thing that you were
going to introduce?
Brett Aldrich: Yeah, state
reactors. So this is another
type of this is all part of the
the sub state architecture. So
like, once once we're in a state
and looking down at the pieces
inside of it, what state
reactors do is so
Audrow Nash: what so in the sub
state what composes a sub state?
Is it so other states within
states or are there so others?
Brett Aldrich: We do have we do
have? We do have hierarchy? Yep.
But when when we're talking
about the the, but to in the
hierarchy, one thing that that
is unique and smacker? Or maybe,
I don't know, what's one
feature? You we break down the
library into having container
states and leaf states and it's
the leaf state that has the
orthogonal and the full substate
architecture, V. Okay. The
container states don't by
default. You can turn them on.
It's smack we follow the
philosophy of we do things in a
certain implementation that you
know, as we see that we think is
best but we try not to turn off
like other ways of doing things
because some of the early
clients that we had really
challenged my views of how they
would interact with the system.
And I'm thinking to you, Bob
peetha, gray, Orange. They, they
did things that I, what, what
are you doing? You know, it took
me back. But, uh, but it totally
valid way of running things. So
we try to leave those those
sorts of things open anyway,
back to the hierarchy. So. So
generally, there's always a leaf
state that has orthogonal and
other things like that a state
reactor is is a just another one
of these objects. And what it
does is it receives events and
throws its own event. And so it
basically brings in second order
events, the first ace, so we
came up with it. This is in
like, mid 2018. And we just
begun the library in like, at
the end of 2017. And we were
contacted by the company
here.com. And they were working
on a self driving car at the
time that it had a very
complicated array of six, like
super high end cameras, was for
like a self driving car that
would map you know, as well, and
what, what they wanted it to do
was, you know, navigate from one
point to another, when it
started up, it wanted to make
sure all the cameras were ready
to go, and then drive, if
anything happened, stop, bring
all the other cameras back on
line and go. And that led me to
create the state reactors. And
so what we did is we have a
state reactive called all events
go, and it's a runtime object
that resides inside the state.
And it receives events from
camera one, that camera to event
and once it's received it from
all then it throws its own
event, and then the state
transitions. It's become such a
popular, I'd almost say it's a
state machine design pattern.
You know, we call it S T acquire
sensors. And I don't know what
percentage of state, you know,
we have in the reference
library, we have certain state
machines that are extremely
simple. It's just like this one
back and forth. So they don't
have it. But I think for all of
the other state machines that
we've like, if there's a
simulation video, I'm pretty
sure all of them have one of
these SD acquire sensor states
and very early on in the
execution chain.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. Okay, so
you have those that will kind of
take information and they take
in all the events, and then when
a specific condition is met,
they may event they may emit
another event, and that can be
used to trigger some sort of
transition or whatever might
occur. Correct. Okay.
Brett Aldrich: They also, one
other thing too about him,
that's I don't know, that might
be interesting for the
specialist out there. They
they've set the stage for us to
move ahead with cogeneration in
a new way, one of the things
that's always cool state machine
libraries,
Audrow Nash: when you try to
play code, or Yeah, well,
boilerplate,
Brett Aldrich: but also, like
graphical cogeneration. That one
of the problems that that has
are always complicated, that is
callback functions. But with
state reactors, you avoid that
by with, you know, through these
second order events. And so
yeah, and that's part of our
plans over the over the long
run, you know, to build out an
entire tool chain along with the
the ability to right now we have
this Mac to runtime analyzer,
but we want to create a smack to
writer where you can, you know,
graphically align your state
machine and have it auto
generate the code, or at least
generate some of the code, you
know, like, like a lattice
framework type thing. And, yeah,
the only thing about that is
that, in my opinion, you have to
do that last. Because if you do
that too early, and you've got
some problems in your, you know,
in your architecture, you
basically baked it in place. So,
yeah, so that's one of the
things I'm really hoping to
accomplish with SMAC, in this
current year is basically
getting more and more use cases,
to a point where it's like,
okay, no, no, we've seen you
know, we've got an idea about
every which way that the library
could conceivably be used. I
don't know if we'll get all the
way there, but,
Audrow Nash: but if you get a
lot of them, then you have a
fairly general solution, and
then it can be used for a lot of
things. That'll be great. Yeah.
So one thing that I don't quite
understand, well, I guess I'm
having trouble mapping The idea
is together. So I understand
this architecture with the
client behaviors and you have
your orthogonal and you have
your states and things like
this. Can you explain kind of so
like a simple application, say
say like that video of the
fetch, sorting, the fetch, in
simulation, sorting cubes by
color, okay, like, how do we go
from these states? And then the
orthogonalize in and then how,
just like an idea of how all the
systems work together to create
some reasonably complex
behavior? Or can be a simpler
one, if that's kind of complex?
Brett Aldrich: Yeah, maybe we'll
start with the dance bot
example. We'll kind of dive into
that one a little bit. All
right. Sure. In so for those
who, you know, who haven't seen
it, the best spot to see the
dance bot example I can like it.
Yeah, is in is in the the Ross
world 2021 presentation on smack
to It's the opening video how we
link that all together.
Audrow Nash: And just to
describe the video a bit, it's a
robot that it's in a sort of
maze, and it goes to a location
and then it drives until it hits
a wall, and then it goes back to
its original location. And then
it goes out again, but slightly
different angle from where it
was heading. So it makes kind of
like a star pattern. And where
it goes, and it bumps each of
the walls around it, and then it
goes back to its original
location, and then it goes to
some other location to start
doing the same pattern there.
And I believe the intention with
this is to map out an
environment.
Brett Aldrich: Not exactly it's
oh, there is there is a mapping
that, that, that that does
happen. But it's really more
about floor coverage. We were
modeling, you know, how how a
robot might, you know, cover a
floor space in in modular ways.
In that one, the robot navigates
to to global waypoints and
begin, proceed to perform
dinners of superstate this is,
so now we get into hierarchy a
little bit. So we've got our
leaf state. And then you can
have these containers. These are
like levels of hierarchy, which
we have shorthand for, which
I'll go into right now. So the
first level of hierarchy we
refer to as super states. The
next level we refer to as mode
states. There's no difference,
Audrow Nash: per se, it's just
because it's a hierarchy. So
super states is like high level
control. And that's like
fundamentally what the robot is
doing. It's mapping it's driving
to some location.
Brett Aldrich: In your
application, I think I think the
most common use for for Super
states is for loops, for loops,
or like, like sequences, you
know. So in that application, it
moves to the first global
waypoint. Okay, it's to execute
a super state, that is a radial
pattern. And you can set the
parameters of that radial
pattern in the superstate. So I
think in the video, it showed
something like 16 rays,
Audrow Nash: and the 360 divided
by 16. And then it just went out
exactly what each of those
angles,
Brett Aldrich: okay, but you
would just go in there, and
let's say, put in 32. And so
it's parameterised.
Exactly, exactly. It does three
of those super states in a row,
at which point it navigates to a
fourth way point, and we haven't
execute an F pattern, same kind
of thing, although it's like, I
think it's a series of seven
states that execute this
repetitive F pattern. Again,
though, designed for floor
coverage. Then it goes to a
final waypoint where it's more
of an S shaped pattern. So five
total super states and five
global way points, all the super
states parameterised. In this
case, we're only using two or
thought well, let me think there
might be more than one
orthogonal in there. But in
terms of like the crucial
orthogonal for that example,
there's two, there's the, the
the LiDAR, and to cool. Yeah, in
that particular example,
Audrow Nash: and nav to handling
the navigation of the robot from
one spot to another, okay, and
controlling the motors and
everything to drive it around.
Exactly, right. Okay.
Brett Aldrich: Yep. Yep. In
other in other state machines,
we might use, you know,
something like Ross to control
the same kind of a similar way
that that move it relies on Ross
to control the move the robot.
And we've had we've built
examples and navigation in Ross,
one where it uses the Ross two
or the Ross control draft
controller. But yeah, it's you
know, you start using like your
standard Ross stack to get
around. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: And then so if
we're in superstate one we're in
the radial star. Okay, one. What
does that look like from the
mode states, so not the super
states, but now we're in Super
state one. And so super state
one is composed of mode states,
as you were saying, with the
shorthand, yeah. So how does it
look? They're like, what, what's
going on down there? And how do
we get closer to
Brett Aldrich: the CLI that
example? Like, in depth, or just
ballpark? Yeah, I believe the
way it has is that we've got a
mode state called Run, and we
have another one called recover.
And where I see that
architecture evolving, in going,
you know, in terms of real world
is that one of the things that
SMAC offers is very advanced
recovery sequences, and
capabilities. So I imagined, and
I think one of the things that
SMAC one of the most important
things that SMAC offers and in
why it's disruptive, is that it
allows for a new order of
magnitude in the complexity of
robotic missions, particularly
age missions. So So for
instance, let's let's take an
example of a fixed wing
aircraft, right. So you'd have
one mode for taxing on the
runway, another mode or takeoff,
another mode for I don't know,
you know, the your initial
flight, where you're finding
your right heading, stuff like
that. And for each one of those
modes, you're probably going to
want to have a separate recovery
state, you know, separate
recovery mode state, where
dependent, so let's say you're
in takeoff, right, and something
wrong happens, then you switch
from that mode.
Audrow Nash: So the appropriate
recovery for that will take
Brett Aldrich: off recovery, and
you begin your, your, you know,
error recovery procedures there.
And as that continues to expand,
you just, you end up with like
greater, greater needs of
hierarchy. It also brings in the
question of where your data
goes, another unique feature of
SMAC is that every state is a
class and every container is a
class. So you can scope your
variables and other things to
the lifetime. And that's needed.
You know, perhaps you need a
variable across every state in
in a certain mode. Perfect, you
put it in the mode, you can also
do you we also have the
opportunity, or the option of
global variables. But
Audrow Nash: yeah, okay. So
interesting. And so, can you
tell me a bit more about the
real? So you're saying, I guess,
the origins of smack and how it
was born, from, I guess, a real
application and then how it's
evolved since? Yeah,
Brett Aldrich: it's in the
oranges of smack it's hard for
me to put a finger on it i i
would say it started the same.
So I graduated from UCLA with a
degree in biochemistry. And one
of the the, my first job outside
of outside of university was
under a NASA grant at the UCLA
UCLA Medical Center in the
department of Head and Neck
Surgery under a brilliant
researcher named Dr. Larry
Hoffman. And I, I ran one of the
research labs there. I forget
the exact title, but that one of
the labs was basically mine. And
what we were doing was it was
this insane program where we
were dissecting the inner ears
of we were, we were injecting,
like dyes, and then dissecting
the inner ears of mammals,
mainly chinchillas and mice. And
then we were studying the
organelles of the inner ear, the
you trickle and the sack you
will and stuff like this.
Audrow Nash: I don't know
anything about this. Okay. It's
just an our little parts of the
object. Yeah,
Brett Aldrich: even then. And in
dissecting these organelles, we
would then visualize them, you
know, under fluorescent
microscopes, and imagine like,
I'm holding up for the listening
audience. I'm holding up like my
hand, it's like an Organon. It's
like they would, they would have
these Nerf patterns that would
kind of follow through these
organelles. And we were studying
those in an effort to create
better rocket guidance systems,
which I have no idea if it ever,
you know, resulted in such
things, I have a feeling
gyroscopes do a pretty good job.
But it got me it brought up.
Audrow Nash: So it was this this
was like, fundamental. So like,
one thing that might be similar
is I think it's rapid random
exploring trees, R R T, or
something like this. Yeah. So
it's, it's almost like an you're
trying to identify an algorithm
that controls these nerves
spreading through them. And then
maybe that algorithm would be
useful in applications, like,
guided missiles, or whatever it
might have been.
Brett Aldrich: Yep, that's
exactly right. And that's, and
so it opened, expose me to to
concepts like this. neural nets
was talked about. I got to
program a little bit of Fortran.
Also, decision trees were part
of that. And it, it, it began an
interest that I had, like, even
in terms of office hours, where
I just started, I started
sketching out these kinds of
systems, you know, like, and
then, in looking back on it, it
was clear to me that I was
drawing out state machines,
although my early my earliest
state machines, it's like, each
state was a neuron. And so I was
imagining these chains of
neurons and how they would
process information. And you
know, what, where that was just
like, yeah. And so anyway, that
was, that was where, like, some
of my earliest interest in that
arose. Later, I went, I went
back to school to get a degree
in math and theoretical computer
science at the University of
Irvine, and which I did not
complete. But in some of the
early courses, you know, I was
exposed to set theory automata
theory. And so I had
Audrow Nash: no, any idea what
that latter one is. Oh, automata
Brett Aldrich: theory. That's
like, that's like the, that's
like the math behind things like
finite state machines. Okay.
Yeah. You get there into like,
whether or not state machines
are Turing complete stuff, like
Audrow Nash: proving things
about them. Theoretically. Yeah,
Brett Aldrich: exactly.
Particularly when you start
getting into advanced state
machines with event queues. You
know, and like, how then how
that maps so there was that that
part as well. I moving on later,
I remember I got there was a
when I started believing that
robotics was the next wave that
it was in I believe this still
that robotics is going to be the
next boo and probably the
biggest one in my lifetime. I
feel like that's going to happen
to within the next 10 years. And
so as I was looking forward to
that there was a book called UML
of real time systems and I read
that book like I I've gotten rid
of it since but I don't know I
could almost pry tell you on a
particular page what's on it and
sketching too at that time
though, I although I was so
interested in them I never would
have thought that I could have
written the state machine
library like that I just I would
have thought that well and at
this time this is really before
Ross you know so like the
systems were more closed off I
would have thought that that was
part of some giant proprietary
stack I see Yeah. Anyway my my
first project you know that
involved Ross was creating what
the company is real robotics and
we were creating level line
cable reels that we're going to
provide mobile robots with
tethered AC power for which you
know more
Audrow Nash: level line which is
level one okay?
Brett Aldrich: It's a level wind
meaning level wind level meaning
that if we've got a real here it
goes like a fishing exactly like
a fishing line fish yeah,
there's like a goes like this.
So it winds perfectly every
time. Cool. And I've got a
picture too of like what, what
we had in mind for the system
holding it up for the camera
right now and it's on top of
ClearPath robotics Ridgeback
robot so you can see the box
that it is the real there's a
yellow it's meant to be Like a
nine gallon Shopback that goes
on top in this application here,
I'll show it from another angle.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so it's, it
just looks like. So it looks
like one of those small clear
paths, or maybe not small, one
of those clear path robots that
has kind of the wheels
underneath. And then there's a
big cube on top of it, and it
kind of looks like there's so I
guess that's the Shopback
cylinder that sticks out of the
cube.
Brett Aldrich: Yeah, exactly,
exactly. Okay. And that's
Audrow Nash: to get started with
this. So the problem was to do
level cabling. So you wanted to
basically have the robot drive,
and it would leave a cable
behind it. And then you could
wind back on the same path, and
it would organize that cable as
it retracted it, basically,
Brett Aldrich: which, which
required tight coordination with
navigation. And, and then also
tight coordination with what
would be really the state
machine of whatever the plan was
to basically sell those to, to
OEMs. You know, and so we knew
Audrow Nash: that OEM is
original equipment
manufacturers. So let's say so
that's like,
Brett Aldrich: yeah, go ahead.
Well, yeah, somebody like Dyson
vacuum or something, you know,
more probably more industrial,
something like 10 internal
fills, but But yeah,
Audrow Nash: whoever was going
to meet or know them, but I see.
Yeah.
Brett Aldrich: And so we knew
that we were going to so we
built, you know, we started with
that software stack. And we
moved all the way up. And we
really did some beautiful work
there. Some notable people to
contributed on that project,
Dave Coleman wrote something Oh,
project. Yep. Yeah. He was this
was before picnic, he was a
graduate student at University
of Colorado Boulder, and he
wrote some of the original Ross
control code. Vince Magyar, also
worked on the project. He's the
maintainer of Ross to control. A
mathematician by the name of ROB
Hanna from UCLA. And I did some,
we mapped out all the
mathematics where, imagine that
level line system, you know, the
goal is to know exactly how much
cord is being produced with
every encoder tick, but it's
changing all the time, depending
on how many, you know, layers of
cord are on the real position of
the level line carriage where
the robot is the robot rotating.
And so we did all that. I
focused on the microcontroller
code mainly. And that's kind of
how I that that was more my
background is I came into smack
I was more like an embedded
programmer. And that time, I
thought that C 99.
Audrow Nash: That's where it's
at. Yeah.
Brett Aldrich: That was my
belief in anything involving
templates. I looked it like, you
know, I didn't like that at all.
Yeah, Pablo country project too.
And there was also a developer,
from the former ClearPath
developer named Devin Nash, he
did some really great work on
the project, too.
Audrow Nash: Anyway, it's cool
to see. It's funny to me that
it's such a small community, in
a sense, as in these names keep
popping up for a lot of
endeavors. Okay, so you worked
on this robot. And so this was
with real robotics. And this was
the application. Yep. And smack
was born from this.
Brett Aldrich: Correct? Yeah.
Because we knew that we were
going to have to integrate with
whatever the OEMs were using for
their top level coordination,
because you have to coordinate
you'd have to coordinate the
movements of the reel with the
navigation, you know, the
navigation of the robot, which
we accepted. You know, we knew
we were going to have to do
custom work like that. But in
order to, you know, develop our
own demos, the idea of a state
machine came in, also early on,
I'm going to say so we started
this in like 2015 2014 2015 by
2016, maybe even a little
earlier, I realized that smash
was not up to the task,
Audrow Nash: and smash what
Smash is that a filmer?
Brett Aldrich: Oh, yes. Smash
was smashed was a state machine
library developed by Jonathan
Bullrun, I believe in 2009. And
it was a state machine that that
powered the PR two examples.
Yeah. I think very highly of
that library. I think he did a
number of very, very innovative
things that that inspired SMAC
probably the most important was
Tying the events to actions, you
know, like, like, like, like in
the example you were describing
to navigation finally gets to a
goal that, you know, that then
creates an event and you
transition to the next state.
Exactly. There were things
though about smash that never
fully. So I want to give credit
to Jonathan Boren like for like,
it was a, it was a creative and
in essence a leap forward. I
think in terms of though, like,
it was never really suitable for
like more of a production level
of robotics. The concurrency
always had issues, the data
porting is another subtle
problem. Anytime you see, in my
opinion, anytime you see data
porting and state machines, run,
Audrow Nash: I don't know, I
don't know what data hoarding
is. Well,
Brett Aldrich: it's in in Smash.
When you want it to provide
hierarchy, right? It was, you
would put another smash state
machine inside of a state
machine. It was like, yeah, it
was like you have
Audrow Nash: that. And then you
would forward state down or
something or a well,
Brett Aldrich: yes, he did. This
is where it starts to get
interesting. And how you move
data around, it's a design
patterns are common amongst
state machine libraries, where
people try to do that. I think
it's fraught with, with
problems, and usually in where
you're trying to move data
around, you know, and where you
have to be explicit about where
it goes, that doesn't really
scale. Anyway, after so late
2015, or mid 2015, I'm looking
at Smash, and I know that it
won't be the library that allows
us to you we can't use that one.
And so I look, I looked at the
market, and I didn't see any
competitors. And I I saw a
chance, you know where we could
we could take a stab on writing
our own, I knew it was a
daunting prospect. But I don't
know, I take risks every now and
then. And and I I think I think
I fell in love with the idea. I
think if I try to justify it in
terms of cold, hard business
logic, it's sort of tough. But
but we set out that way. And you
know, I started on it
architecting out what that
solution would be where I would,
where I how I would piece that
thing together. And I settled on
booth state sharp. Mainly one
thing that helped me in that in
that in that stage was that I
focused solely on
Audrow Nash: the C++ library
booth.
Brett Aldrich: Exactly. And it's
template metaprogramming based,
which is
Audrow Nash: what was the what's
it called? Again, the library to
C
Brett Aldrich: sharp state
chart.
Audrow Nash: Charts. Oh, okay.
Brett Aldrich: Exactly. And that
comes from David Harrell named
his models of state machines
state charts. So,
Audrow Nash: huh. Yeah. Yes, an
arm to it. Great.
Brett Aldrich: And, and yeah,
over. So we started that in
approximate we started coding it
in approximately 2017. Right at
the end of 2017. Excuse me. But
I had been working on it for
about a year at that point, just
like laying out the
architecture. I use my
intuition, largely, but I got
pretty good intuition. And
later, you know, as I learned
more, I look back and I'm
surprised how many of the
decisions we got, right. Nice.
Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Okay, and so then
real, real robotics. closed down
or No? Was this? Yeah, so
Brett Aldrich: what 2017 We
began No, sorry, at the end of
2017. We began building the
library. And very, very early,
the market pull started to pull
us in. So that call with click
here.com that took place, I
think in May of 2018. So it was
as soon as we were developing
it, we started getting calls.
Then, we started working with
gray orange. I'm going to say
late 2018. So it's we started
just being pulled into you know,
one meeting after another and,
and then two I picked up
confidence as we proceeded. Yep.
Ran into So at that point, we
were developing both with both
real robotics and smack, which
later, we split off into Robo
soft, but at the same time, we
were pursuing them at the same
time. That went all the way up
until we announced the library
in 2020. In June of 2020, we
announced, wow. Okay. And we set
out one to finish up the reel.
And our plan was to launch them
together. And
Audrow Nash: launch the real
launch what together both real
and smack together, launch the
company real robotics. And with
and smack at the same time I
see. Right? Yep.
Brett Aldrich: And we ran into a
mechanical issue along the way.
So we announced the we announced
smack for Ross, one in June. And
we immediately set out to create
it for Ross too, because I
realized that as we announced
the library, that, that at that
point, most of the most of the
major players, were already
moving into Ross, two. And so we
immediately set out another
version, and also set out to
complete the reel, and where
it's at now, the real works, we
got a picture to have it like we
and we built this thing. It's
awesome. And there's one
mechanical issue. And but the
the market poll was just too
great. And so I'm putting it
down for a while and putting all
of my focus on smack now. So you
need to figure idea, you know,
Audrow Nash: so think, by market
poll, your meaning that there
was so much customer demand,
that it kind of sucked you away
from real robotics. Yeah, um,
suck the time and energy. Okay.
Yeah. So then, what do you
think? So? what is the what is
the appeal of smack to these
companies wire? Like, what are
they looking for that smack is
meeting? And why does it not?
Why why are there not
alternatives? And I don't know
what, what why is smack so
appealing to them? Basically,
Brett Aldrich: I think I think
the first part is that you've
got a standardization at the
application development layer,
you know, smack can be viewed as
basically an Application
Development Framework. So I
think that's, I think that's
what draws them. I think the
features of Smak then start to
come into play. And the main or
I'll try to go through a few
important ones. One of which is
that being a composite, smack.
With smack, you can build state
machines that are an order of
magnitude more complicated than
with almost any other library.
The reason for this is the
compile time validation. This
comes from boost state chart. So
have you ever heard of the N
times N problem in state
machine?
Audrow Nash: Not I don't know
what it is in state machines. So
Brett Aldrich: it's, you know,
I, it becomes intractable note,
that when you have when you have
n states, right, then you might
need
Audrow Nash: and transition the
Brett Aldrich: transitions,
yeah, to each state. And so it
just keeps getting bigger and
bigger. You know, like, if
you've only got five states,
okay, great. You got n times n
is 25. But what happens when you
have 20? States? 30 states?
Yeah, that expansion. And this,
I don't like I feel like the the
academic treatment of the N
times N problem is overly
simplistic and misguided. But,
but there
Audrow Nash: isn't, it might be
just more theoretical, and it
might miss some of the
application. considerations and
application.
Brett Aldrich: It's true. I
will. And I also think it it's
somewhat sloppy, versus it seems
like big O notation, but without
the without the rigor, I'd say.
But anyway, but it is true that
the larger your state machine
gets, the harder it is to, you
know, to manage that, or at
least it can be. And yeah, and
this also gets into one
criticism of state machines is
that they're a one way transfer
of control. Right, like so when
you go from one state to
another. It's this you don't you
don't automatically go back to
the state you were in currently.
And in that sense, they've been
compared to go to statements.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so I'm just
jumping around
Brett Aldrich: where you jump
around. And while I think that's
a bit of a stretch, there's a
truth that if you go to the
wrong place, then you're in big
Trouble, right? If the if you if
you're transitioning to a state
and there is no state there, you
know, we got an
Audrow Nash: undefined. Yep.
Right.
Brett Aldrich: But what happened
there is? So template
metaprogramming arose, so
Audrow Nash: does that. What
does that mean? Yeah.
Brett Aldrich: So um,
Audrow Nash: so I'm familiar
with templating and C++, Is it
anything similar?
Brett Aldrich: It's very
similar. It's the same. It's the
same type of
Audrow Nash: and Meta
Programming. Is it like lists?
Like programming? And less is?
That's what, but okay, what is
that's a beautiful thing that
happens
Brett Aldrich: it, it happens at
compile time. That's the key
thing is that, like, so?
Template metaprogramming by
occurring at compile time. It's
what sets it apart. And
Audrow Nash: because you can
have all sorts of compiler
checks, rather than runtime
checks or this kind of thing.
No, that's okay. So because of
that, you just run into a
compile and build and whatever.
And it's gonna go, and it's
gonna suss out a bunch of
problems for you, rather than
you having to like test them.
And see, so it's much faster and
easier for the developer.
Brett Aldrich: And that's right.
That's right. Much safer. That's
right.
Audrow Nash: So can I take a
stab at what template
metaprogramming would mean,
because I. So I'm imagining it's
similar to what they do in Lisp.
And I'm imagining it somewhat
similar to what they do in C++.
So it would be that you're
writing code, and your code at
compile time is going to like
expand things, run them through
functions, and then it will
change what that function does
based on arguments or this kind
of thing.
Brett Aldrich: Okay, that's more
like function templates. Yeah.
But it's okay. Same thing,
right? How do I say that? In
let's say, if you were if you
were starting to look into, like
the template metaprogramming
that works in boost HRT, that
would be like, the opening
chapter. You would, you'd start
there. Yeah. But then it moves
into class templates. And okay,
Audrow Nash: well, yeah. So you
can do all sorts of objects this
way. I mean, you could do
functions, you could do classes,
but it's fundamentally the same
kind of approach, where things
are parameterised. And it's
generating stuff based on those
parameters by following Yeah, by
following a code path that you
define, which is the meta
template programming part of it,
right? Yep, that's right.
Something like that. Yep. Okay.
Brett Aldrich: And in the, like,
1995, there was a famous paper
by James Copeland, where this
pattern called CRTP, and it
stands for the curiously
recurring template pattern was
discovered. And it was
discovered by independently by a
few, but one of them was a
female programmer by the name of
Lorraine jewel. And it's that
method was then taken by the
developers of the boost
libraries. And a lot of people
don't know this about the boost
libraries. But the boost
libraries are all based on
template metaprogramming. David
Abrams was the founder of the
boost libraries. And he wrote a
library called MPL, so meta
programming metaprogramming
library. And then, two important
state machine libraries emerged
from that early periods of boost
was founded in 2002. Libraries
boost MSM, which was written by
Christoph Henry, and then boost
HR, which is written by Andreas
Huber, Donnie, and both of them
use CRTP to validate the state
machines at compile time. And in
in Andreas Huber, Donnie, is
implementation specifically,
it's a game changer, because it
makes sure that you know, every
transition has a source and
destination, make sure that
every state has a parent and
state machine that it accounts
for
Audrow Nash: and a lot of
compile time safety, basically,
because of these validations.
Okay, yes.
Brett Aldrich: And I think too,
you get yet, one thing I've got
is that it's very easy to run a
state machine library. The trick
is making all the works. And,
and the fact that it's compiled
every time you're compiling, you
know, you're getting checked. It
just has a different different
type of reliability, a different
type of, you know, reusability
and that's tied to that. Okay.
Yeah. And hence, why I think
we're, you're able to, and that
in combination with state local
storage is what allows blue
state chart and through
inheritance SMAC to to have
state machines that are orders
of now magnitude larger than
what you would think if you
believed in the n times n
program. For instance, in the
spec to repo today, there is a
state machine known as SM
multistage one. I wrote the
state machine, it has over 165
states and over 100 transitions.
Wow. You know, that big deal?
Yeah. Like it wasn't that hard
to write it didn't take that
long. And if you mess up
anything, you know about it at
compile
Audrow Nash: time? Yeah, that's
really nice. Yeah. Okay, what?
So you mentioned all this
industry interest in why you
mentioned all this interest in
SMAC? Can you tell me some of
the types of projects that
you've been working on with it,
or some of the types of
companies or the problem domains
that the companies are
interested in solving with?
Smack?
Brett Aldrich: Hmm, trying to
think of like patterns across
them? I think the main one that
has, has brought them at this
stage, you know, to, to smack is
the problem of concurrency. You
know, basically, how do you
control? And, you know, I think
we would start with navigation,
and at least one arm and maybe
two, and then a perception
system, and maybe a gripper, you
know, just a some type of
minimal implementation like
that, although, as we saw in the
field work robotics example, you
know, quickly went to four.
Other Other ones, let's see,
what
Audrow Nash: kind of what kind
of domains or tasks are they
trying to solve? Like, what is
the task that you can
accomplish? Look like with this?
I suppose. Yeah.
Brett Aldrich: One. So you know,
one was a, like a self driving
car. Another it's it's broad.
It's broad. And yeah.
Another one was with with gray,
orange, there's was a, it was a,
it was a two armed robot with
two arms on a gantry that was in
like a warehouse type context.
And I believe it was used for
folding shirts.
Yeah. So. But again, we have
multiple orthogonal, right, like
multiple, you know, arms in one
application. And then for field
work, robotics, you know, again,
like then the the, we have the
expansion to multiple multiple
arms. I would say that that's
probably at this stage, the most
important element is the the
modularity that comes with
orthogonality. Areas that I
don't think have been touched
yet, with Smak is the complexity
that it can go to with the multi
stage missions. I'm not where
Audrow Nash: you so where would
that go? What would be some
problems that you could solve
that are kind of like, pushing
it to its limits? And
complexity?
Brett Aldrich: Hmm. Well, let's
see. See if I can think of
Audrow Nash: would it be like
space related things? Okay.
Brett Aldrich: Yeah, let me I'll
try to freestyle a space related
mission. Um, you know, one thing
I've heard being talked about
DARPA is where you can really
bring down the cost of launches,
right? Well, let's say you've
got like some type of lat like
some say, it's like a truck type
device, but it navigates out to
somewhere on its own sets up a
launch pad and then launches
into space, right? Transformer
in that sense, you know, so you
could have one, one mode state,
that's for your driving portion.
And you're going to need
different recovery procedures,
you know, depending on
Audrow Nash: driving everything,
yeah.
Brett Aldrich: Then you go to
you transition to the launch
area, setup, state, state. And,
you know, you're gonna have
multiple sequences involved,
there are different recovery
procedures, etc, etc. Finally,
the launch. And then, you know,
again, it changes. And in fact,
you're probably your orthogonal
is would change, right? Probably
like the physical subsystems
that you care about. And each
one of those contexts would
would be modified.
Audrow Nash: That's a cool
concept. It doesn't make sense.
Brett Aldrich: Yeah. And then to
you know, if that trucks got to
get out of there afterwards,
what if it has to, you know,
wants to launch and move on?
Yep, that would be another.
Another way. You just keep
changing on and on. And I do for
see. One, one bit of feedback
that we've gotten that I think
is important is that as people
We'll start to use events in
their programming, you start
having an explosion of events,
which is good, you know, but you
just want to handle them more.
And once you start using states
to chop up your problems, you
want more of them. I think
that's, that's another
interesting thing that smack
does it. If we look at it almost
from economic terms, it
dramatically lowers the costs of
creating states. Like, for
instance, one of the the
examples that I think it's sort
of striking is, you know, the
early 2000, for DARPA
challenges, right, where you're,
you're navigating across the
desert. And I feel that that's
still influences navigation,
like even to today. He's a star
planners and stuff like that,
that make these very
complicated, you know, plans,
it's almost, and
Audrow Nash: so just a little
background. So a star has kind
of an optimal planning algorithm
that'll go, and it has a
heuristic for how it proceeds.
But it goes, the goal is that
way, I'm gonna explore
everything towards that
direction. And when it arrives
at a solution, it computes the
optimal solution in the
environment. So it's a, that's
why it has the star. But okay,
so when you're doing path
planning, and you're using
something that can get an
optimal solution, this is as
compared to like, RRT, the rapid
random exploring trees, or
whatever it is, which finds an
approximate solution by kind of
branching, it's not optimal.
Brett Aldrich: Yeah. samples off
of it. Yep. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: I mean, you can use
that and then optimize from the
RT one. But okay, so you're
saying we a star for
exploration?
Brett Aldrich: Well, it sort of
as in my mind, the assumption
that there's only one state, you
know, that you've got to
navigate from here to Vegas, in
one state, maybe, maybe, right,
which is, um, and I think when
you start having like, readily
available state machine
libraries, where, you know,
developers are familiar with
them, you can all of a sudden
start using very different tools
to start, you know, chopping
that problem up.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so the basic
if you didn't have to, so if
it's complex, and you get your
trajectory from some planner,
the previous way of doing things
was you put everything in one
big state, and it's all very
complex to manage, because you
have to manage a lot of like
internal variables to figure out
how control should be handled.
And so if you can chop up the
state into small, clearly
defined problems, and you can
handle them very well. Because
you can only consider what you
need and have the like, you
basically only have the problem
parts that are required to solve
the problem. For that one
problem rather than everything
kind of mushed. Together.
Brett Aldrich: Yep. Yep. Okay,
that also has interesting
effects, you know, back to the
client libraries and stuff like
this. I, I think that one of the
ways, or one of the ways that I
hope it SMAC will influence Ross
in general, is that it will
bring down the size of the
servers and and make them more
manageable. So to give a little
context, what do you mean
servers? Sure. So let's look at
move it and enough to. So I'm
gonna throw out some statistics.
I don't know exactly how
accurate they are. I'm sure
there's people with more
accurate numbers. But I remember
speaking to Mike Loughton at a
picnic, and I'm sharing with me
that the move at code base was
something like over 100,000
lines of code. I get huge, huge.
And I also I have a tool that
attempts to tell me how many
lines of code are in something
and I ran it on nap two, and it
came back at 111,000. Okay, so
that's sort of shows like a
level of complexity in here. And
some of these like extremely
common.
Audrow Nash: Right, I see what
you're saying. Yeah. Because
because you can divide things
up. They don't have to get so
large. Yes, one. Yes. Okay.
Brett Aldrich: Much simpler
planners. Exactly. And that's
also important too, in that,
from our own experience of
developing examples, the place
that we really like you just
start burning developer hours,
is fiddling with the the
settings on these black box
planners and, and checking them
out during runtime and
simulation. Just, there's just a
slowness to it. And the way that
that everybody is generally
interacting with these is, okay,
so you write your own note,
write your own, which is
essentially like a client that's
going to interact with with nap
to let's say, and I don't know,
what would you say that they
started 60 lines of code, maybe
200. And then they, you know, we
start building out your
application, maybe it's like
1000 You know, at some point
Audrow Nash: So you're saying
1000 lines of code and relative
to all the way out to?
Brett Aldrich: Yeah, exactly.
That's a small thing interacting
with this massive, you know, we
it's like we put all the
complexity over in, in these
giant servers. Right now and
just
Audrow Nash: by by server, you
mean code base effectively?
Yeah, like we're referencing it
as a dependency in our code. And
a lot of logic is being done
over there in their code, right
here.
Brett Aldrich: Okay. Yeah,
that's exactly right. I'm
currently, so we did we, we
finished up some of the work on
our nav two Zed client today. So
this is the the client and smack
two that we use to interact with
navigation. And it's coming in
at about 7500 lines of code. And
this is all written by this.
This is written by Pablo, but
Pablo is an expert in
navigation, you know. And so I'm
imagining a world where if SMAC
becomes a standard, right, and
these clients become a standard,
you end up interacting, like
that balance between, let's say,
1000 lines of code in the
application in 110,000, in
something like NAB two
rebalances to something like 10
to 12,000 lines of code and a
client. And then my hope would
be that, let's say nav two could
come down to 70,000 lines of
code 65,000, something will you
get
Audrow Nash: by using less lines
of code? I'm sure storage and
compile time and things. But
what are the benefits?
Brett Aldrich: Well, there's
those and those add up, you
know, if you figure it out time,
Audrow Nash: yeah, yeah, right.
Test time.
Brett Aldrich: Yeah. I do agree
that, you know, measuring this
in lines of code is a crude, you
know, it's a crude metric. But I
think what you what you can get
is, I think it would be easier
for the developer teams at
places like naff to and move it
to, if they knew that the users
were going to interact with
their system in like a defined
way defined by like these
clients. Right? If if half of
the Ross community interacted
with move it to through a smack
client, right, it would sort of
like narrow the interfaces.
Yeah. Yeah. And you basically
get more like focus, less code
easier to maintain. And then
also the simplicity, you'd have
more more planners, simpler
planners? That would be easier
in
Audrow Nash: that sense. Yeah.
And one, one advantage to that,
that I see is, say you want
something to be like space
certified, or some high level of
security or you basically, the
code is really hard. And for
safety critical situations, you
can certify only a small chunk
of a larger library, rather than
the rest of the library. So
like, I'm sure certifying 10,000
lines is a lot easier than
100,000 lines. Yeah. Yeah,
that's right. This kind of
thing. Yeah. Let's see. And so
one of the things we were saying
before we started this interview
was you see the application of
SMAC really being for industry
users? And, as opposed to, like,
hobbyists, or this kind of
thing. Can you speak on this a
little bit? Maybe I've gotten
that wrong, but
Brett Aldrich: no, I think Well,
I think it's true. It's, I mean,
I hope it's Mac is used by
beginning developers, and I
think it has a lot to offer, you
know, beginning developers, but
but I don't want to, like shy
away from the question that when
it comes to design decisions,
you know, that are going to be
made. And let's say the design
decision comes down to a choice
between making them more
friendly for, you know, new
developers, or, you know, being
able to meet one day a safety
certification or something like
this. I always side with the
more high end side, it's more
important to me, that smack runs
on the most important robotic
systems of our era than it is,
you know, I'm not counting every
developer that uses it. Where,
though, that goes, you know, it
back to the bifurcation, though,
that I'm seeing in Ross, you
know, especially as I look down
the road, is, seems to me that
we've, we have on one hand, like
a research community, and this
is like students, graduate
students, people who are more
focused on usability and getting
up very quickly. I think they
tend to be more focused on their
algorithms. And so this would be
somebody who's using like a
Python node or something, they
want to get their system up and
running quickly. On the other
side, you've got those like
smack that are that are trying
They're more focused on actually
running in production. I think
also the work with self driving
cars has really led the way
here. And I love to like for
inspiration and where I want to
go next with smack, I look at
auto where I look at the work
coming out of APEX a I mean,
it's beautiful.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, absolutely.
Brett Aldrich: But it has some
interesting features to it. Um,
so, and we've done this with our
own library, we've, you know, we
brought in a more complex
continuous integration system.
And, you know, with that, I
think we have something like
seven, seven checks that we go
through on every pull request.
Every check, we add makes, it's
just one more step that a new
developer would have to go
through to submit a pull
request.
Audrow Nash: These might be
like, run the tests might be
like, do a linter, check to make
sure the code is formatted.
Right. So you're saying,
Brett Aldrich: you know, yeah,
exactly. Like, you know, and
hopefully, automation can help
lower that burden. But But I
think, too, is the libraries
like this get, you know, grow
more complex. It's tough
environment for beginners, you
know, favor, the more seasoned,
focused, I don't wanna say
professional, but I want to say
focused, you know, where you're
focused on a certain problem set
and not kind of coming in
quickly wanting to get something
fast. I recently, as a, as a
library, I won't mention it
specifically. But there's a
library out there that I admire
very, very much. And in
researching it, I, I was going
through the documentation, and I
found a couple of like, very
minor errors, the guys English
is probably their second
language, and so that, you know,
a few minor grammatical changes.
So I opened a pull request to
change it. And there's a 20 step
process. You know, this, this
board request, and I quit after
like, step six, I had other
things to do, and I pulled out
of it, I'll continue it. But I
think it just sort of highlights
something that we're going to
have to deal with as a
community. And I, again, I see
this sort of bifurcation between
these two different camps.
Audrow Nash: So one thing that I
find interesting is, like in the
web developing community, you
have really high quality,
difficult, give you everything
to play with libraries, like I
think it's d3, JS, d3, it's
amazing library. It's data
driven. It's really nice,
beautiful, beautiful, beautiful.
Yeah, amazing. But so that one
is incredibly difficult to get
into as a beginner, like I
played around with it a little
bit. It's very, it's awesome.
You can do great things, but
they're very time consuming to
do, but you can control
everything. Whereas then there
are I don't know, maybe like
chart j s or something that use
d3. But they make it a bit
easier for users that are more
casual or just want to get
something working quicker to
play around with it, or to do
something, but they don't have
access to all the knobs and all
the customization without going
into d3. JS. Yeah. Do you
imagine? Similar? Yeah. Okay.
Well, I wanted to make sure I'm
saying the right name of
something. But yeah, so I mean,
it's wonderful. But just it's
lower in difficulty than d3. Do
you imagine SMAC? Following some
sort of model similar to this to
make it more beginner friendly?
Brett Aldrich: Yeah. You know,
my So yeah, this is the
dynamics, I see it play there.
Um, I think that the, that what
smack, the advantage that smack
has is that smack as your
application grows, smack can
handle it. And so what that
allows for is the creation of
these client libraries that are
developed by experts, but
basically encapsulate much of
the higher level function, and
no, you couldn't, or you would
be foolish. So let's just say
we're taking navigation as an
example, right? I think it would
be foolish to write a client,
like nav to Zed for a state
machine library that couldn't
handle if it got to a certain
level of complexity, and then
that state machine library
couldn't handle it anymore.
You'd be foolish to write a
client for it. But because SMAC
can handle almost anything that
you would throw at it in terms
of state machine complexity. It
opens the door now for
specialist developers to write
client libraries. That's my
number one goal as we move into,
into 2022 is to expand the Every
horizontally with new clients
and new client developers. And
in that sense, I think that's
one way that we can kind of
escape this trap. You know what
I mean? This, this, this, this
d3, you know, where it's like
always, you know, if you go for
high icon, if you get with
capability, you can't use it,
you know, that, like avoiding
that, that? Yeah. And then the
second part of that is
cogeneration. I think, I think
when when we start getting
cogeneration capabilities that
are graphical, it, you know,
yeah, to bypass all that,
Audrow Nash: you can just like
visual block program, a complex
robotics application, that
actually does something, which
is not, yep, that will be super
cool.
Brett Aldrich: Yeah. And in
there, you know, then the
complexity, it wouldn't hurt you
there, either. Or you'd bypass
it, you'd be able to kind of
abstracted away
Audrow Nash: in the blocks you
use. Yeah, yeah. Um,
Brett Aldrich: and, and then
also has another, like, it
brings in another type of
efficiency where it's important.
So the SM reference library, you
know, the minute a developer
comes, they can they can get
started with a state machine
there that's guaranteed to
compile and run. Simulation is
set up. But I think the other
way to capture greater
efficiency is on the back end
where you don't, you don't have
to upgrade. You know, for
instance, back to that, that
DARPA team we were discussing
earlier, that started off with
four states, their state machine
eventually grew to 15. Now,
let's just say that it kept
going, you know, and now they're
45. And it's not working
anymore. You know, like, the
things that they were dealing
with? Probably they don't, who
knows how they're visualizing
it, you know? Yeah. But if
you're in a library, like smack
that, you know, can handle that
growth, well, then you never
have to refactor or transfer
your code base. And that's a
big, you know, that's another
like form of deficiency that I'm
hoping that, that we can verify.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, you had that
foresight. And you can see, oh,
eventually we're going to need
it. Yeah. See, there's there's
several things in that I've seen
that are similar, where they're
like, you're going to need to
use this. So might as well use
it anyway. Kind of thing. Like
might as well use it to start.
Yeah.
Brett Aldrich: Gotcha. And into
your architecture. Yep.
Audrow Nash: Now, I know. So we
are running out of time, we were
booked for two hours. We're
coming up on the end. Are you
okay to go a little bit longer?
Yeah, let's
Unknown: do it. Okay.
Audrow Nash: So one thing that I
want to so SMAC is basically for
control, high level control of
robotics applications. How does
it compare to other control
patterns, such as, like,
behavior trees, and I don't
know, whatever other whenever I
what other things exist?
Brett Aldrich: I think I think
with behavior trees, you know,
well, okay. Well, I guess the
key question there is, what do
you mean by exist? If we're
talking about, or patterns
Audrow Nash: that developers use
now for control of robots that
are doing reasonably complex
applications, you know, control
in existing applications?
Brett Aldrich: Yeah, you know,
I'll be honest, in that there
really isn't much available.
It's hard to comment on it. You
know, because there's, there's,
and I think this is one of the
real it's a problem for us as a
community at the moment, is that
it within the answer is we need
more demos with links to the
source code, you know, because I
think a lot of it sort of
reminds me in the days, you
know, for those listening off
camera Audrow And I before that
we're talking a little bit
about, we both have an interest
in jujitsu. And it reminds me in
the moment of like, the days
before the first UFC where, you
know, what would happen when
when a kickboxer fought a sumo
wrestler like no one really
knew, you know? And? Yeah, I
feel like the demos with the
sort with links to the source
code are a crucial part of
showing like, Okay, well, you
know, if it can do it, let's
prove it. And from what I've
seen, is, you know, of what's
out there. It seems like most
people are rolling with like a
roll your own solution. You
know, they're starting off with
like, I don't know, maybe a
state pattern or something like
a gang of four kind of pattern.
And it's good, although, I think
it leads us to the sort of thing
where they develop something
that's pretty cool. Let's say
it's 1520 states, and then it's
but they can't maintain it. And
so A lot of that work is lost,
you know?
Audrow Nash: Yeah, nothing,
nothing generalizes. Like it's
hard to pull components from it,
it's hard to grow the
application any larger. And it's
also intertwined with the state
representation that they have
already, that it's very hard to
pull out the parts into a
different way of organizing
them, perhaps.
Brett Aldrich: Yeah, yeah. And,
and I think that hurts us all
over the place, you know, where?
I mean, they, you know, for
instance, and I know, we're
trying to harvest what's coming
out of the DARPA subterranean
challenge. But I think we'll be
lucky if we get a couple of
planners. We'll get lucky if we,
if we get a few algorithms, but
I think the prospects of us
finding like some type of state
machine architecture that we can
pull out, I mean, very low, very
low, it would require, it would
require an advanced team. I'm
going to adjust my lighting here
a little bit. Yan is going down
one moment. Has this a better?
Very bright? Yeah, yeah. Okay,
cool.
Audrow Nash: So, yeah. And then,
so we just, um, can you speak a
little bit about the differences
between state machines and a
state or a behavior tree based
approach? Just kind of at a high
level? Because
Brett Aldrich: high level? Yeah,
the, I think the the most
fundamental differences between
this one way and two way path of
control. So in that sense, state
machines are, I guess, more like
a go to statement, although I, I
have problems with that analogy.
Whereas behavior trees are more
like a while loop. You know,
when, when you look at a
behavior tree, and it's the
ticking. That is like the key
part that makes it a while loop,
right, that you tick through all
the
Audrow Nash: skills, you keep
polling the current state or
something, too. So just just to
just give a little background to
those who don't know, for the
behavior tree, just an example
of what it might look like, is
in a video game, I think I read
on your blog, this MAC one, that
Halo two was the first video
game yeah, control before? Yep,
yep. So what they would do an
example of how a character might
be controlled in a state
machine. So in Halo two, for
example, if you had like, one of
those little grunt, aliens, it
might, if it doesn't see you, it
might just be kind of idle. Or
actually, I, let's see, actually
another example. Because I'm
going to get confused with that
one, I'm kind of going into a
state machine direction. If I
have a character and it wants to
get into a house, for a behavior
tree, that behavior tree might
go and look to see if the doors
open. And if the door is not
open, then it might go see if it
has keys. And if it has keys,
then it might use them. And if
not, it will go and see if
someone like try to knock and it
progressively goes through these
things. Eventually, it might be
like, is there a window that can
be broken to get inside? or
something? But it's a series of
like steps that are all like
conditioned on each other? Do
you agree with that or anything?
Brett Aldrich: I agree. Okay,
that conditional approach to end
the polling,
Audrow Nash: the polling part is
that at each time you go, what
have I tried before? And it kind
of brings you down each of the
leaves for this? And that would
be like, Have I tried keys? Have
I tried this? Have I tried that?
Okay, I'm here with try next,
this kind of thing.
Brett Aldrich: There's that.
And, and then there's no events?
And I think that's now that this
is true for behavior trees dot
cpp. And in a number of other
behavior tree libraries, I
think.
Audrow Nash: So there's no
events, that means it's hard to
have an event trigger something
in the behavior. That's right.
So it's kind of weird, because
it's based on like an existence
of the state. Oh, I see why that
gets confusing. Because if
you're running through your
statements, but then all of a
sudden the state changes now you
have to like recall everything.
That's right.
Brett Aldrich: That's right. And
that's if you have, that's when
you start to have So in a normal
behavior, how do I say this?
Google so so behavior trees
originally came out in 2004. And
they you got started in, in, you
know, games modeling, they call
them NPCs, non player
characters, which I have a
number of problems with in a
robotic context. I mean, these,
these creatures don't have any
kind of control system, they
don't have any kind of
orthogonality, there's no
liability. Then those, I'm gonna
call that the first generation
implementations, they did get
some success in the gaming
world. And so and I think for
that reason, people thought,
Okay, well, we can use them from
robotics, because Robotics has
always been, we've always stolen
from every other field out
there, right. But later, well,
as of today, right, there are no
behavior, I'm 99% sure that
there are no pure behavior tree
implementations left in the
gaming world, and those that
remain have all moved over to
event driven behavior tree
mouse. And event driven behavior
tree, what you need is you need
a, you need another thread, you
need like an observer thread,
you know, to check your events
coming in, amongst other
changes.
Audrow Nash: So that's it just
just from like, a high level to
see if I understand what it is
that you have the two threads,
you have the one checking for
events, what kind of so an event
occurs, something has changed.
Now your state diagram or your
behavior tree, would it just
like change all of a sudden?
Brett Aldrich: Good question.
This this, this would depend on
the implementation. I know of
two different methods. One of
them is like, yeah, you just
repol everything in the tree
every time an event occurs. And
that's like, that keeps it more
similar to the original behavior
tree design, I guess. And then
there's a second model where
you're keeping track of all it's
a more advanced method where
you're keeping track of
everything that's happening at
that point. I question. I mean,
I think you've actually got a
state machine only, you're
keeping track of state in a set
kind of way. Yeah. The thing
about event driven behavior tree
libraries, is that I think
they're highly experimental. I
mean, there's only four that I'm
aware of, you got Unreal Engine,
you've got one for unity called
MP behave. And that's like a,
like a third party plugin or
something. I don't like,
whatever. Okay. Yeah, it's like,
it's like a, like a plug in type
deal, then you've got the Cry
Engine, which I don't know that
much about. And one other one,
that doesn't count either, it's
not important, the only one of
those that matter in any sort of
way, to me is unreal engine
four. And the big difference
there is that they these, they
cannot handle concurrency. You
cannot. If we look at let's say
the implementation of Unreal
Engine four, right, the only
event driven behavior tree
library that I can think of,
they don't support multiple
orthogonal. And in fact, if
somebody cares to look into it,
in the documentation, you can
look up the simple parallel
node, where, you know, this
would have been the node where
they would have handled in their
parallel nodes, you know, you
could have multiple orthogonal,
they punted, you're only allowed
to have one a synchronous one,
and one synchronous, and that's
it. So you would never be able
to run like the kind of
orthogonality that that would be
required on that field work
robotics robot that we saw, or
let's say, let's say some type
of like military submarine, you
know, where, who knows what
they're gonna or like, hell,
like an Apache helicopter, where
there's something like 48 sensor
systems. Yeah, and complex
sensor systems, right? Not just
not just like a proximity
sensor, right? But instead, it's
like a 3d scanning array, and IR
scattering the rig. And so to
me, that's the that's the main
difficulty. Now there, there
will be a lot of debate. I've
been involved with debates with
the proponents of behavior
trees. But that's that's, that,
to me, is the most immediate,
short term shortcoming they have
I also suspect that that there
will be a way to prove
mathematically that one state
machines are more well, I know
that you could prove
mathematically that state
machines are more expressive
simply because the N times end
problem is a is a. The flip side
of that is that you have finer
grained control, you know for
instance, let's See, I've got a
200 state state machine. And at
state one nine, you
Audrow Nash: can explicitly go
from each of the states to every
other state. Yeah.
Brett Aldrich: Handling, like
certain corner cases. So in that
sense, I think the the ideal
that you get more
Audrow Nash: probably way better
for testing. I imagine it's much
easier to test all the state
transitions explicitly, with
this kind of representation.
Brett Aldrich: I would think so.
Yeah, the fact that you can do a
lot of it at compile time, I
think that's true.
Audrow Nash: Anyone, like, if I
want to simulate the robot for
like, additional testing, so
like, I know, you can do a lot
of the compile time testing,
which makes sure everything has
a connection to everything, or
to so all the connections are
set up. But having like, if I
wanted to run in simulation, I
could target each of the
transitions for a candidate for
testing, which would be nice and
explicit.
Brett Aldrich: Yep. And then to
with this gets off into, like,
where I see the future gone, but
fellow, in studying the history
of state machines in different
domains, and I've studied them
in the electronics domain, the,
the, I call it computing, I've
been able to track down the
earliest state machine and a
computer to the 1965 version of
the IBM Oh s 3/61, one that I
was able to find in
documentation where you see a
very simple state machine on the
computer. But in the in the
networking domain. You see state
machines arising from almost the
beginning, the beginnings of the
field of protocol engineering.
And TCP IP is a giant state
machine. But one of the things
that happened in the late 70s
was they started creating, like
dual state machines setups,
where one state machine would
test the protocol of another
state machine, totally
automated. And there were cases
in the development of ARPANET
where this technique exposed
something like 256 bugs with
without any human involvement.
Crazy, got me thinking about
like, Okay, wait a minute, how
do we start creating? Or how do
we start changing our automated
testing, right to start
incorporating state machines on
each side testing the other
state machine? This is one of
those areas where I, you know, I
have hopes for new fields, new
fields to arise and new types of
efficiencies to be gained. But
back to the behavior trees, I
think, I think at the
application layer, I'm yet to
see an example of behavior
trees, where we've got a demo
and the source codes, side by
side in robotics.
Audrow Nash: Does that mean
evaluate?
Brett Aldrich: Oh, yeah, that
makes it hard to comment on. And
I, I don't know, I feel that,
that we're trying to deal with
that problem of complexity, in a
sense by saying, Well, you don't
even need state machines. And I
have a hard time, I have a hard
time going down. That said, I do
want to say that I believe in
freedom. And although I may
disagree with something, hey, I
want people to know the way they
want to code. And, and let the
best man win. Let the best man
win. Let's let's you know, going
back to our discussions about
jujitsu. I was listening to an
interview with Hickson Gracie
the other day. And he was asked
to compare the cultures of Japan
where jujitsu originated in
Brazil. And what he said was
that, you know, Gracie Jiu Jitsu
could only have originated in
Brazil, because the difference
in culture cultures were in
Brazil, there was not this sense
of respect that there wasn't
like, you're very, very
respectful. Right? Okay. In
Brazil. He said No, like people
would show up at my father's
studio in the middle of the
night and want to test us out
with a fight. Wow. Yeah, it was
it was like the like you had to
be ready to, to duke it out at
any moment. And I think we need
a little bit more of that in
Ross. But you know, let's, let's
put the players on the field.
Let's let him
Audrow Nash: on. And let them
evaluate.
Brett Aldrich: Definitely. Yeah,
I think that I think the
community benefits. Yes, yeah.
Cuz
Audrow Nash: you get to evaluate
the ideas and actually compare
them fairly. And then juice from
there. What do you so going
forward? What's the future of
snack look like? Where you guys
going with your implementation?
And what do you see in the next
few years?
Brett Aldrich: I see too, you
know, a few years. I don't look
that far down the road. I'm more
like looking down on your
quarters to 2022 and that I
think there's really two things
that that we need to do, the
first thing I need to do is I
need to expand it into more of a
community project. And one of
the things I'm looking for there
is a talented pedagogue, because
I'm not the guy to, to teach
newbies about smack, I'm gonna
try, I'm gonna do my best. But I
know that there would be
somebody out there who's better
than me at doing it. And that I
think, is probably the biggest
weak point of the library at the
moment, partly because of the
way we bootstrapped it. But we
could use a lot more
documentation, we could use a
lot more tutorials, and, you
know, fostering almost into more
of a community beyond just the
robust soft team, which is where
we're at currently, I would say
we've got a handful of people
who've committed pull requests,
but it's a handful, and, and for
what I want to accomplish with
the library that needs to grow
substantially. And then the
second thing is the horizontal
growth. And that's basically new
clients. So clients, four legged
robot clients for naval, ps4 is
another one that's like really
high on my list. That's drone
community, correct drones, but
you could also use pics for
based systems for like
underwater sub stuff like that.
Audrow Nash: So cool. Yeah.
Brett Aldrich: One an autoware.
Client. I really think that
that's like, that would be very
cool. Yeah, opens up a lot of
possibilities, particularly for
multistage missions, like we
were talking about earlier.
Other ones, let's see, there's
the moose system for naval.
Would you call it but basically,
naval robotics? And let's see
what else? I would say that
that's basically it, though, the
idea of horizontal integration.
Yep.
Audrow Nash: And then wrapping
up? What advice do you have for
someone who is just getting into
robotics?
Brett Aldrich: You know, I'm
very hesitant to give advice to
anybody. I'm not sure they want
to do things away. That's
exactly the smoothest route. But
I would say this, if someone
looked at my career that they
would find, and a lot of this
hasn't been public, because it
was what the real. But over and
over, I've gone into development
projects that I really had no
business, succeeding, you know,
it would like if you if you look
before, like, what would what
would this guy's odds of success
be? You think they were low, and
over and over, I've come out of
them on top. And I there's one
secret, and that is have a spec,
not even have a good one, just
have one. I originally got a
spell book, spec, I'm talking
about a design document, minimum
three pages, but it can grow,
you know, but it's where write
it down. Particularly if other
developers are going to get
involved. You know, it's, it's,
it's just, you'd be surprised.
I've ran into people whose
credentials were so they looked
so good. And, but they didn't
write a spec. And know, the code
wasn't that good. You know, when
you have one, you'll notice you
know, that? No, like, even the
again, you may not have that
much experience, but with armed
with a spec you can do, you
should believe in yourself.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So you, you
basically you think it through
and you develop some sort of
spec sheet. And with that you're
a lot more focused and able to
kind of knock down the task to
achieve something rather than
not being focused through and
trying to, I don't know, you're
not focused on the end. If
you're, if you don't have a
spec, maybe? Yeah,
Brett Aldrich: I think too, it
allowed me to, to identify
difficulties problems. And often
there were multiple ones, you
know, like, like in something
and overcome them, you know, and
start to like, get your, they
start to get your grips on a
problem, you start to come up
with solutions. Often that don't
work. But yeah, and I've noticed
it more and more that when I
like, if I'm working with
something I say, Well, do you
have a spec, and it's rare. It's
rare, but and that originally, I
originally got that idea from
the book, Joel on software. And
that's from Joel Spolsky, who
was one of the original
Microsoft program managers at a
time when Microsoft really led
the way in terms of how to
produce code. And so that's
really the that's really the The
one piece of advice I would
give, I don't know if it'll be
enough to accomplish, you know
what someone would want to, you
know? First, you gotta have a
goal. And I don't know if a spec
alone will get you there. But
without one, you're done.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Okay. Now,
do you have any links or contact
info or anything that you would
like to share? Yeah, so
Brett Aldrich: roba soft.ai is
our website. And then the other
place that, you know, for,
especially the audience of this
podcast, is the smack to repo on
GitHub. And, as always the most
updated source of or up to date
source of information regarding
the repo. And I guess the last
thing out there is, if you're a
developer, and you've got an
idea for a client, or like a
smart client that you want to
develop something like nav two,
or we have nav two and move it
and Ross to control that if it's
something like PX four, or moose
or autoware. Get in touch with
us, we will support you and we
want to hear from you. I'm
looking for artists, globally.
Audrow Nash: Awesome. Cool. All
right. Thank you
Brett Aldrich: very much. I
really had a great time. And
it's an honor to be interviewed.
For those just tuning into this
podcast. I'm Tony The sky is the
Charlie Rose of robots.
Audrow Nash: Thank you. Hi,
everyone. Thanks for listening
to this conversation with Brett
Aldrich. Thank you again to our
founding sponsor, open robotics
and I hope to see you next time