Audrow Nash: Hi, everyone.
Welcome to the Sense Think Act
Podcast. I'm the host Audrow
Nash. And in this episode, I'm
talking to Erik Schluntz, co
founder and CTO of Cobalt
Robotics, which makes indoor
security guard robots. Erik and
I talked about having the Cobalt
robot take elevators, how Cobalt
has humans help their robots
make decisions, robot body
language, advice for
entrepreneurs and several other
things. It was great to talk to
Erik, I enjoyed learning about
how cobalt uses humans and
robots in their systems, which
each play to their strengths. It
was also a great seeing how
cobalt robotics has navigated
getting investors and funding.
As always a big thank you to our
founding sponsor, Open Robotics,
and I hope you enjoy.
All right. Hi, Eric, would you
introduce yourself?
Erik Schluntz: Hello, I'm Eric
Schluntz. I'm the co founder and
CTO of Cobalt Robotics.
Audrow Nash: Would you tell me a
bit about Cobalt?
Erik Schluntz: Absolutely. So
Cobalt builds indoor security
guard robots. So these are
robots that will patrol around
an office building, looking for
anything out of the ordinary. We
work with human operators to
help support the robots. So if
the robot comes across anything,
it doesn't know how to respond
to it switches over controls are
humans. And then our humans can
escalate exactly like a human
guard on site would, whether
that's calling the customer or
calling police, or having a
friendly video chat, instead of
asking how someone's doing just
like a security guard.
Audrow Nash: Nice. And so for
the people listening? Would you
describe what your robot looks
like? And how do we refer to it?
What do you just Is it the
cobalt robot
Erik Schluntz: or just a cobalt
robot, we actually we decided we
didn't want a separate product
name from company name. That can
be hard to to brand both of us.
So it's just a cobalt robot. And
I'll describe this actually,
while playing a video for people
that are watching. Sure, we'll
get this going here. So the
cobalt robot is about five feet
tall. And it'll control around
it has wheels, two main drive
wheels. And then for supporting
casters, it's designed to
navigate around through an
interoffice space, looking for
anything ordinary, that can
include doors or windows that
have been left open, the body is
actually coated in fabric. So
it's a little bit soft and
squishy. And this was actually a
big part of our industrial
design was that we wanted the
robot to be friendly. The job of
a security guard is to keep
people and employees feeling
safe and comfortable. And so if
the robot is scary, you know, it
really hasn't done its job,
right. There's also a
touchscreen on the front of the
robot that we use for being able
to interact with anyone around
the robot, where one of our
human operators can video call
and talk to a person on site. We
also have a lot of sensors,
cameras that are 360 degrees
around so no one can sneak up on
the robot. And then a ton of
sensors that you find in a self
driving car like LIDAR and depth
cameras, and I am Yes.
Audrow Nash: So how I'm thinking
of it. It's like a telepresence
robot that has a lot of sensors
that makes it more
sophisticated. And then you have
the whole like person in the
loop thing, which makes it a
good bit more sophisticated. But
is that a like a squishy, a
basically a telepresence robot
with a kind of cylindrical
fabric body?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, yeah. And
I'd say that's what our design
is basically that it's
telepresence five or 10% of the
time. And I'll tell you this 90%
of the time.
Audrow Nash: Okay. Now, and the
one behind you has a little arm.
Erik Schluntz: Yes, yeah. So
this is one of our add ons for
some of our customers. For our
security patrols, we want to be
able to patrol through multiple
different floors. And so to do
that, we need to ride elevators.
Now in the past, we've done
elevator integrations that are
wireless. Those take a long
time, elevator companies are
often very slow. And so actually
what we do now at a lot of
customer sites is just
physically press the button. So
we added a one degree of freedom
actuator, swing up and press
elevator buttons. And we use the
cameras and computer vision to
detect the buttons know where we
should press. And we actually
have this rolled out at a bunch
of customer sites now. And it is
a lot faster to roll out in a
wireless integration and it
works pretty well. So yeah, I'll
show a video of that for people
at all kind of narrate that. So
the robot first starts and
presses the button on the
outside of an elevator. waits
for the door to open, navigates
inside. elevators are very
technically challenging thing to
do. We find tons of things like
elevator thresholds that are
actually out of spec that would
cause a lot of problems for
people in wheelchairs.
Audrow Nash: What do you mean?
Is that like a big bump getting
into it?
Erik Schluntz: Exactly, you
know, we find elevators where
it's a two inch gap, you know,
between the elevator car and the
floor or you know, one inch
vertical, but once the robot
gets inside, it uses computer
vision to see the paddle and
know which button it should
press, flex the correct button
drives forward, depress it. And
as I mentioned earlier, this arm
that we add is only a single
degree of freedom. So we
actually use the robots drive
train to steer the robot left
and right. And to move forward
and backwards, the arm only
moves up and down. Yep. And we
use the robot for the rest of
the degrees of freedom.
Audrow Nash: You may I think you
mentioned so it has to the
cobalt robot has differential
drive or something so you can
turn it's not Omni drive, so it
doesn't move side to side.
Erik Schluntz: It's it's
differential drives, we have two
main drive wheels and four
support casters.
Audrow Nash: Okay, is that
tricky to get lined up with the
button?
Erik Schluntz: Yes, so we
definitely put a lot of work
into sort of that motion control
and planning to be able to
nicely line up and press a
button. Especially because
elevators often have very tight
space, we don't have a lot of a
lot of room just sort of back up
by 10 feet and approach it
nicely. It's, yeah, we have to
kind of operate in these very
tight spaces.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. I wonder,
do you have ever the situation
where the elevator is so tight
that you have to raise the arm
and then kind of swing into it?
Erik Schluntz: We haven't hit
that yet. And luckily, there are
rules around elevators, for
people with wheelchairs. So we
can actually just follow a lot
of those same design specs to
know what the robot hardware
needs to be capable of gotcha.
Audrow Nash: And is it difficult
when you go into a new elevator?
To find the buttons? Like I
imagine that this is fairly
custom, depending on the use
case, depending on how you're
detecting things?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, so we have
a sort of a proprietary system
that we've set up where one of
our sales engineers can go on to
new customer site with the
robot, and very quickly
calibrate the robot for that
site. So we don't need a ton of
training data or anything new
like that. We can kind of just
bring the robot through the
elevator once, and then after
that, it's able to use the
elevator by itself.
Audrow Nash: That's awesome. You
kind of... Can I guess that what
it is?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, sure.
Audrow Nash: So do you use the
depth camera at all in this for
figuring out how far away you
are. And
Erik Schluntz: Yes, we mainly
use the LIDAR for that. One of
the other interesting challenges
is that elevators are very
reflective surfaces, a lot of
times you have sort of a
polished metal. And time of
flight depth, the cameras can do
very poorly with that, because
Audrow Nash: they're shooting
out infrared and trying to see
that but then it bounces off. So
you don't get any good depth
information, maybe very noisy
information,
Erik Schluntz: you get very
noisy, but the LIDAR at the
bottom of the robot is pretty
good. And we know that in an
elevator, it's a fairly
structured environment where we
see the walls is usually in
line. Why is LIDAR
Audrow Nash: more reliable?
intuitively, that doesn't make
much sense to me. So for the
depth cameras, are they
structured lighting, where
they're projecting something
out? And then trying to observe
what that is, with the pattern
and the deformation in it? Or?
Erik Schluntz: That's a great
question. So the one we use is
not structured light, it's time
of flight. Oh, and I don't think
there's any inherent reason that
a time of flight depth camera is
is worse than a LIDAR, which
typically, what we see is that
LIDAR is are a lot more
powerful, and just put a lot
more into those be able to get a
much better signal response.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. And the
LIDAR of this robot is at the
it's like, on the base, right?
Erik Schluntz: Yes, at the very
bottom of the robot, and you can
see around 270 degrees around
the robot. So that gives us kind
of a good sort of footprint of
what the the room that said,
Yeah, and then we use the
optical camera on the front of
the robot, and can get very good
sort of optical readings, write
up the buttons and see where
they are.
Audrow Nash: Yep. And then how
do you control the press for
this, I'm imagining like, you
draw, you basically raise that
to the correct height that you
imagined the thing is, and then
you just drive forward until you
hit some sort of drive
Erik Schluntz: forward. And we
have a set Oh, very tip here to
know whether we've made contact
cool little forest, what are the
eggs? Initially, we had a force
sensor, and then for
reliability, we just switched it
to a, you know, a switch.
That's, that's calibrated. Yeah,
one of the interesting things is
sort of, you can we can tell
that we've hit something, but
you don't necessarily know
whether you engage a button or
the or that you know, the rim of
the button and maybe didn't
engage it. So there's some
interesting things we can do to
you know, to sense whether we'd
hit that one of the first things
we thought of is oh, you know,
we can tell whether the light,
the light turned on in the
button, but you'll actually find
plenty of elevators that don't
light up. And so actually what
we do now, is we have an
accelerometer of the
acceleration of the elevator.
Audrow Nash: So can you feel it
moving?
Erik Schluntz: Exactly that's
kind of you know, the sort of
that's like the the ultimate end
goal is we feel like the
elevators not moving. We know
that we've correctly told the
elevator what to do.
Audrow Nash: Now is there ever
the case where the robot is in
the elevator pushes the button,
but Miss This so that it didn't
actually click the button and
then someone calls the elevator
from a different floor, and it
sees it.
Erik Schluntz: Absolutely. And
so I think what you brought up
is that one of the really
interesting challenges of this
is that when we are in an
elevator, in the worst case,
we're inside a Faraday cage. And
so this has to be often this has
to be 100%. I'll
Audrow Nash: speak about it in a
cage for just a little bit.
Yeah,
Erik Schluntz: absolutely. So a
Faraday cage is a closed metal
structure that no radio waves or
electromagnetic waves can get in
or out of. And so that means
that for some elevators, when
we're in them, we don't have Wi
Fi or cellular. And that means
that we can't rely on our human
operators that generally we use
for ourselves.
Audrow Nash: That's hard,
because it's like one of the
more difficult situations.
Exactly, exactly. They're in a
Faraday box. That's crazy.
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, so it's
very funny but And generally,
what we say cobalt is that one
of our sort of really fun
advantages for our engineering
team over say, working at a self
driving car company, is that we
just have a lot of inherent
safety and stability that we
move slowly through indoor
spaces. If anything happens, we
can just stop and call a human
operator, you can't do that on a
freeway. And so that means that
we can basically solve for the
99% case, and we don't need to
worry about solving the last
percent bring anything in the
elevator, except in the
elevator. That's where we need
to get 100% You mean safety
Audrow Nash: instability? For
this yet safety and stability
and stability?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, you know,
we're not trying to balance on
two wheels, it is always a safe
situation for the robot to stop.
And so we can take a lot of
advantage of that, and
basically, handle covering a lot
of edge cases with that safety
behavior of I stopped the robot
and wait for a human operator,
except in the elevator, then
they realize
Audrow Nash: it. It's two
interviews that this has
occurred. So I have to figure
out how to turn that off.
Erik Schluntz: Okay, yeah, I'll
need to be careful not to save
the G word over here, but my
phone. Yeah, so And basically,
we need to make sure that
because we're in this Faraday
cage, where we can't call for
help from an operator, that this
robot is going to get itself out
of the elevator come hell or
high water. And there's all
sorts of really funny situations
you can get into. Like you
mentioned that, you know,
perfect timing, you can miss the
button, but someone else calls
the elevator at the same time.
So it thinks that it succeeded.
And we have really robust state
machines that we've built around
these behaviors. So the robot
knows what state it's in and
knows how to retry from pretty
much any state and knows that
these kinds of things happen.
That even though it's it's felt
the motion, it knows there's a
chance that maybe this is just a
coincidence. And if it doesn't
go to the right floor, hey, I
might need to retry.
Audrow Nash: Ah, okay. Yeah, cuz
what I was getting at with that
is I'm curious about the mapping
problem. So how you split up
different maps, I suppose it
like maybe Each floor has its
own map. And then you try to
once you enter a new floor, try
to figure out where exactly you
are in it. So that which Am I in
for one or three? This kind of
thing?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, so there's
a I think two interesting things
that one is sort of knowing what
floor we're on. And the other
is, is knowing where we are sort
of inside the floors. For the
know, in the foreground, we
actually use the accelerometer
to the
Audrow Nash: robot. So you need
to know the accelerations to try
to we do what did you? And I
suppose you decided not to use
like a barometer or something
like that. Was it too noisy, or
I mean, not accurate enough.
Erik Schluntz: So we explored a
bunch of different sensors,
including including barometers.
One of the things that we found
there is that indoors, pressures
terminal lot more by the H vac
system, oh, that's an actual
altitude. So you can go on one
floor and the pressure can
actually be lower, even though
it's higher, because the air
conditioning settings are
different. So it wasn't a really
good sensor for the Tirpitz.
Wild. where we are. Yeah, we did
a lot of really interesting sort
of looking at different sensory
modalities for this. Now the
accelerometer, you're absolutely
right, we're double integrating
Yep, and double integrating is a
scary thing. If you do it
forever, you're going to either
end up going to the earth's core
or going to the moon. And so one
of the things there is that we
can actually apply a lot of
structure and constraints that
we know about how elevator
systems work, in order to
basically constrain that and add
a lot of these checks that keeps
the robot from going to the
moon, or the floor. So an
interesting one there is that
you know, that basically, floors
are basically integer divisions.
So if you stop, and you're kind
of Oh, I think I'm at floor 1.1.
You can actually snap that down.
Yeah, for what, an elevator
never stops at sort of one and a
half floors. And similarly,
Audrow Nash: if it's working
still
Erik Schluntz: exactly what's
working. And similarly, there's
a lot of these other constraints
that we found out well
researching and testing on
elevator systems that they
follow very consistent
acceleration profiles and speed
profiles. And we can use a lot
of those things to basically add
these constraints. So it doesn't
become an unbounded double
integration, it becomes sort of
a much more constrained problem
that we're fitting to. Yeah. And
we didn't tell what floor we're
on pretty accurate.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So you
integrate your acceleration
results, and I guess, probably,
so integrate, get velocity
integrate, again, get position.
And then you look at the
position of the robot, how it's
changed, because it's moving.
And then you get some sort of
rough approximation of how much
you've moved. And then you use
that. So it's like weighted
information. So you say, Oh,
it's probably about this.
Erik Schluntz: Exactly. And we
can use this extra information
of, you know, when we know that
we've stopped, we can basically
clamp it to zero until we see
more than a certain amount of
acceleration. Because we know
that when the doors are open
when we stopped, you know, we
might be reading a little bit of
acceleration, but we know that
elevators don't actually jiggle
around. You know, if it's mostly
stopped, it's a terrifying
elevator. Yes. it lessens the
terrifying Okay, exactly. So
basically, we found a lot of
these hidden constraints that
let us do this very accurately,
and filter it no before.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. What
if you have to go up 20 floors
or something like this? Like
it's a skyscraper, say 50?
floors?
Erik Schluntz: There's, there's
definitely a point at which
breaks down. I assume I'm
actually not sure where that is.
But we have not yet hit a we've
not yet hit a building where it
does not work. trouble. Yeah.
It. We've been in some high
rises in the San Francisco area.
Audrow Nash: And it still works
fine. That's awesome. Yeah. So
if you want to go around that,
yeah. If you want to go to like
the 32nd floor, or what's the
how large are these high rises?
Erik Schluntz: We've done jumps
of 20 floors with good accuracy.
And I've never tested above
Audrow Nash: That's awesome,
though. Hell yeah. I mean, I'm
impressed. It works to that
level, which is awesome.
Erik Schluntz: Us as well, we
were initially much more
optimistic about the barometer,
than the accelerometer, and we
were actually very pleasantly
surprised that it works out. And
again, you can do nice things
like right before you get on the
accelerometer, right? Before you
get on the elevator, you can
pause for five seconds and zero
out your IMU calibration,
because you know, hey, I'm,
unless there's an earthquake
going on right now. I know that
I'm not accelerating. Let me
save that as gravity. And then,
you know, for for a five minute
elevator trip. You know, that
stays pretty good in that over
that short period of time.
Audrow Nash: And then how do
you? How do you store your maps?
Is it like, so I'm wondering if
it's a so say you have two
floors? Is it one map that
includes both floors? Or is it
two separate maps? One for each
floor? Or each each? Like? I
don't know, Consett? consecutive
space are contiguous. I don't
know, continuous space
contiguous space.
Erik Schluntz: So that's another
really interesting question that
we had at the beginning while
working on this. And it's also
an interesting question to ties
into our hdri of how our
operators and how our customers
interact with a robot. Because
this isn't just a robot
operating in a vacuum. This is
the operators and customers want
to see where it is on the map,
they want to see the alerts
coming from the robot. And
actually, what we found what
they liked, most was not needing
to switch between maps and only
being able to see one floor at a
time. But seeing all their
floors laid out side by side,
just like you would on a floor
plan. And so actually, what we
do is we just have them on one
giant map in different
locations. And so a robot
switching floors is implemented
as just teleporting to kind of a
new island in this map that work
and go between.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. And
the elevator is like the portal
between all of these different
floors. Exactly, yeah. Okay,
now. So getting into the robot a
little bit more.
Erik Schluntz: Yeah.
Audrow Nash: So it has a bunch
of sensors. Would you just talk
a bit more about the sensors
that are on it?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, absolutely.
So there's, I'd say two
categories here. The bottom half
of the robot is like an indoor
self driving car. And basically,
its job is mobility and safety,
to bring the robot around
through a customer space and get
the robot anywhere it needs to
be. And the top half of the
robot is all about providing the
security service that we provide
to our customers and providing
that value. And basically, it's
a mobile sensor package that can
be brought anywhere. And there's
a couple of high level goals
there. The primary thing that we
do for our customers is
detecting people. You know, if
we're trolling around the
warehouse at three in the
morning, you want to know if
there's a person, you know,
they're in the warehouse. Yeah.
And a lot of times, you know,
they are supposed to be there,
but we get an alert to our
operators, and they video call
in and say, Hey, excuse me, can
I see your badge? Why are you
here after hours, just like a
security guard on site. saying,
you know that they can
authenticate that and make sure
they're allowed to be there. The
other big category of things
that we do is facilities
inspection, going and taking
pictures of sensitive things,
whether that's an expensive
piece of equipment, either using
our optical cameras or a thermal
camera, or checking doors, sort
of sensitive things like that.
And also environmental checks.
So we have temperature sensors,
humidity sensors, carbon
dioxide, and carbon monoxide
sensors in the robot. And what's
really great is being able to
move these sensors, this sensor
package around at a tire
building, and not just get sort
of a single point measurement
like you would from an air
quality sensor. But being able
to generate a map of air
quality, and being able to say,
hey, not just what's the carbon
dioxide in my office, but get
that map and say, Wow, the
carbon dioxide is all coming
from this corner here, we must
have a broken bet. And be
basically taking that promise of
what like IoT sensors trying to
do, and bring in 1000 sensors
bring it everywhere, and to
localize that data on a map. And
so we've helped customers catch
really interesting things.
Whether that's broken h vac
systems that could possibly pose
danger, we actually found h back
issues where the with
temperature, where we show that
one half of the building was
like five or 10 degrees colder
than another. And they said, Oh,
man, we've had employees
complaining about this. For
months, we didn't believe them.
But now that we see the data
from the robot, and so really
what the robot is, is, we want
to bring sort of superhuman
sensing to what the guard could
do. And the things that a guard
could notice, while looking
around and that that can be
security or facilities.
Audrow Nash: Did you Do you guys
ever so you have this arm now.
And I feel like that's a
relatively new thing to push
elevator buttons. You ever, like
try doors to see if it's a hinge
door to see if it's locked or
interact in the environment,
interact with the environment in
any way with it.
Erik Schluntz: So we have some
interesting things coming out
for doors in the next year. I
can't talk too much about Okay,
Audrow Nash: stay tuned, stay
tuned.
Erik Schluntz: So, and I will
say with this, we can press
handicap up and Stoker doors.
Audrow Nash: Ah, that's awesome.
Let's see. So with these
sensors, now I noticed is with
all the air quality ones, I
basically how did you select the
air quality sensors? So you have
like carbon monoxide, carbon
dioxide smoke? I don't know what
else? How did you select the
sensor packages that you had
humidity and temperature? How
did you select these ones? For
as opposed to anything else?
Erik Schluntz: Yep, exactly. So
at the beginning, sort of when
we we did a lot of customer
discovery asked our existing
customers, what are the kinds of
things you're worried about in
your hair? What are the kinds of
things you you want to know
about your space that you don't
have right now, and sort of took
a lot of that input and then
looked at what was feasible, we
actually have a radiation sensor
on one of our robots from one of
our customers. So that's not a
standard option. But you know,
we could add other sensors as
needed for special cases.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. I was gonna
ask about customization next. So
you are customizing a little bit
I imagine. So with the body of
the robot being kind of a big
cylinder covered by fabric, it
seems like you can probably have
pretty large sensor payloads,
and you can swap them out fairly
easily. So you mentioned the
radiation. One, but do you do Is
there a good amount of
customization that occurs or
Erik Schluntz: only for very
large customer deals, we really
try to stay away from as much
customization as possible, the
sensor package is one thing
that's a little bit easier for
us to do. But it's sort of right
now it's tied to sort of large
new deals that we do with
customers, I would say that the
majority of what we do that's
custom, I would consider more
configuration than
customization. So we can
configure the robot with
actually different color fabrics
to match the customers. And a
lot of the robots of behaviors
actually are very different
between customer sites. And one
of the ways we think about this
is that security is basically a
big human configuration of if
this than that, if you see a
person that doesn't have the
badge, call this person, if you
see a door left open, do this.
And it's these are sort of the
instructions that are given to
human guards and sort of human
security teams, but how they
should respond to all these
different situations. And so our
robots are very highly
configurable for different
customers. So for one customer,
you know, seeing a person might
be just oh noted in the daily
security report. And for another
customer it might be immediately
called the police. And so you
know, there's these very, very
divergent actions based on what
the robots attacks. Yeah. And we
build systems that let us very
easily configure that, so that
the robot can be to basically do
exactly What your guard was
doing?
Audrow Nash: Yeah? How so how
does that work? So for you to
customize the robot's behavior?
How, like, are you using our Do
you have users use like a block
programming language? Or is it
just YouTube and a bunch of
values? How does this work? Or
use maybe select from a drop
down? If this occurs, then do
this? How do you set this up?
Yeah.
Erik Schluntz: So we'd like to
make things as easy as possible
for our customers and our
customers. They just want
security that works in they
don't want to think about the
robot or programming anything.
Yeah, so typically, one of our
account managers who's an expert
insecurity, and also now an
expert in our robot system, they
will work with a customer and
look at their existing
instructions for their guards,
and basically translate it into
our configuration for the robot.
So the customer just has to give
us their instructions as if
we're a security guard, which
they love it. And then
basically, we turn it in, on our
side, this configuration for
what the robot does.
Audrow Nash: So it's a fairly
one off thing done by an expert,
is what I am hearing for this.
And so
Erik Schluntz: Exactly, yeah.
And this is sort of pretty
standard for how the security
industry works, that every new
every sort of new building, or
company, when they get security
guards, they have an account
manager that basically helps set
what the what are the
instructions? What should they
be doing on the site?
Audrow Nash: how detailed is it?
Like, how many things to
configure? Is it? Is it like a
huge list? Or is it a few?
Simple If This Then That
statement? I guess it may vary?
Yeah,
Erik Schluntz: it varies, I'd
say there's some customers that
sort of are very new, and, you
know, young customers that are
expanding have their first few
buildings. And we actually
usually help them define sort of
what their procedure should be.
Because we've seen a lot of much
more secure much more mature
security programs, and help them
sort of know, hey, well, what
happens if this person doesn't
answer the phone, like, you
know, you don't want you don't
want something to just stop. And
so if it's a bigger company,
we'll know, here's the whole
call tree of how you escalate
things. If someone isn't
available, and for younger
companies, sort of we help them
define a lot of that same
security program with the same
rigor, so that we can help them
get
Audrow Nash: to that level.
Gotcha. That's cool. That's
interesting. You guys are
becoming security experts
through this problem.
Erik Schluntz: Exactly. And sort
of, for us, we have a big
robotics team. And we also have
a security operations team. And
they're the people that are
interacting with customers and
using the robots and using our
control interfaces, to configure
them and to respond to alerts
and help keep the customer safe.
Yeah.
Audrow Nash: So have you guys
ever had kind of a silly
question? But have you ever had
a like, where a security guard
would like, maybe try to
physically stop? If physically
stop a person from doing
something so you there's like a
thief or something? And they
would like tase the person?
Like, is there any like, would
you put a taser on the robot or
like on the little arm that
comes up?
Erik Schluntz: So there's,
there's no taser on the robot.
And I'm actually really happy.
You asked that. One of the
little known facts in security
is that a security guard will
never touch a person, it's a
huge liability issue. All they
do is call the police, you'll
actually see a lot of security
guards that either have fake
guns or unloaded guns through
that it's entirely for
deterrence. Whoa. Because
imagine sort of the the
liability if a guard misjudges.
And a person was actually an
employee, they thought they were
you know, up to no good and
tackle someone that hurts them,
you know, be this huge liability
issue. And so it's very funny
when we started off, this was
one of our big assumptions as
well. And this actually kind of
gets to how we started cobalt of
when me and my co founder,
Travis style started cobalt, we
actually didn't know what we
were going to work on. We had
both started companies in the
past, we both been through Y
Combinator. And that's where we
met each other. And we've seen a
lot of people come up with a
startup idea, and then really
get overly attached to it,
despite it not really being
needed by anyone. And so we
decided that we were going to
take the opposite approach. We
were going to find a real
customer and a real problem, and
then work backwards to the idea.
And so you know, he quit Google,
I turned down a return offer to
SpaceX with no idea what we were
going to do. Both of our
families thought we were pretty
crazy, but we're like, No, no,
no, no. startup idea is crazy.
This is better. And so we spent
the first few months
interviewing people from
different industries, anyone
that we didn't really know what
their job actually entailed. We
wanted to talk to them and just
asked, hey, what are your
problems day to day like what
what would you pay money to
solve? And luckily, one of these
people we talked to was a
director of security and he
started complaining about his
guards, sort of how unreliable
nightshift you know work can be
why his cameras weren't enough.
Yeah, and we kind of the first
thing we said is can we build
these smart security cameras.
And he actually said, No, like,
I already have smart security
cameras. But someone, someone
comes in wearing a hat, and you
can't see the face. It doesn't
matter how smart the cameras,
you either can do nothing, or
you can call the police. And
that's why people still have
guards, they still have guards
to, to follow up and investigate
as something's happening is
happening, and understand to
collect more information. And
that's when we realized, Hey,
this is the perfect job for a
mobile robot. It's kind of that
blend between a guard and a
smart camera where it's not just
about detecting a person, it's
about once you detect them being
able to follow up and gather
more information, go up to the
person and say, hey, how can I
help you? And then you can make
the call of, you know, what do I
need to ask? Or not? Exactly,
it's kind of like this, you need
this third option of following
up and getting more information
before making a final decision.
And so actually, now that's a
big direction that our product
is going is that everyone now
has tons of smart cameras and
smart sensors. And all of these
smart devices, for enterprise
security, create work, they
create alerts, they create
alarms. Yeah. And actually, a
lot of our customers that we've
talked to have had to hire more
security guards, because they
have all these things, that's
fun as they need to go
investigate them, they need to
go deal with false positives.
And our strategy is that all
this other security
infrastructure is creating
alarms. And our robots are
actually reducing work. Yeah.
And the robot automatically gets
dispatched to go investigate
these things, and say, Hey, this
door for this door force alarm
was actually a false positive,
the door looks fine. And then it
gets this batch to the next
alarm. And so basically, there's
kind of these two sides of
security, there's the detection,
and then there's the resolving.
And we actually want to be much
more on the resolving side. So
the robot is not just a moving
security camera. It's much more
than that. It's the ability to
follow up and resolve things,
which is what a guard does, not
what a camera does.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. I feel
like you've said a lot of very
interesting things just now.
Erik Schluntz: No, thanks. Yeah,
it's a, it's a really
fascinating space, I think it's
very cool seeing how more people
and enterprise security are
building sort of these, they're
trying to build these much more
autonomous systems. And he's
much more sort of systems for
handling physical security
without needing a lot of human
input. But also, you know, one
of our customers quoted general
patents us and said, fixed
infrastructure is a monument to
man's stupidity. It's a quote
from World War Two. And this is
sort of why no one builds
castles and fortresses anymore,
is that anything for
infrastructure, you have
anything that static, is at some
point, either going to be broken
and not replaced, or someone's
going to find a way around it.
And that's the difference
between cameras and sort of
fixed sensors, and robots and
guards is that we're infinitely
adaptable. A customer can call
one day and say, Hey, our left
door alarm broke, can you change
the robots patrol to stay in
that area? And we're like, yep,
we can do that. Just like a
guard, you know, you can just
call us. And we'll immediately
responds to whatever that is.
And that's why we don't want the
customer to need to go through
some interface. We don't want
us. We don't want cobalt to be a
static system. It was a flexible
and responsive system. Yeah,
that's why they have
Audrow Nash: I'm saying, so the
way that I'm thinking of cobalt
now, is you guys are almost
like, but you guys are a
security company. And your
personnel is your robots.
Exactly. Which is very
interesting. It's an interesting
model. It's almost like I don't
know you've you've taken all
it's just it's interesting,
because you're not selling the
robot, which is what I first
thought it was. You're selling
the service around the robot.
Erik Schluntz: Exactly. Yeah.
And I think that's, you know, as
we scale, we're exploring, sort
of splitting that off. So cobalt
can stay more of a technology
company and work with guard
partners with the with the
operators is
Audrow Nash: splitting exactly
what off the
Erik Schluntz: work with an
outside partner for sort of
those security to operators to
be the security part, the cobalt
can stay more of a technology. I
see. But I think in the
beginning, it's a really, really
good strategy. Very, very,
Audrow Nash: I see seems to
trigger Siri, when I say see
God's sorry, what did you say?
Erik Schluntz: That basically,
you know, there's this balance
of us being a technology company
and us being a security company.
And at the beginning, it's
really powerful that we can be
both of those things. Yes, you
can do that. So we get vertical,
we get vertical integration. And
that means that you know, our
engineers are sitting alongside
our security operators and
seeing what the deficiencies of
the robot are and seeing what
the pain points are for the
customers and They're talking to
security end users. And if we
were just selling the robots,
and someone else was
implementing security with them,
we wouldn't get any of those
learnings. And so we want to be
a place where we are a
technology company. But that's
very, very integrated with the
security and very product
focused, and really sort of end
user focused
Audrow Nash: gadget that is very
interesting. Yeah, initially,
all the questions about
configuration and things, I was
assuming that you just sell your
robot, they buy it, the customer
buys it, and then they figure
out how to use it in their
space. When really you're
saying, okay, our robot is going
to be like an employee. And
every time you want to update
it, you call us we make the
changes. And then you present
them do so you present their
security manager or something
like this with the data, or
whoever's relevant with the data
that the robot captures this
kind of thing. Yeah,
Erik Schluntz: exactly. And
that's sort of the way that we
provide the end service, you
know, the service isn't the
robot, it's the data that we
collect and provide to them. And
there's a couple things a couple
of ways we do that. One is, you
know, if there's ever any urgent
incident, we just call them Yep.
And then the customers have a
interface on a web dashboard, or
they can live see what the robot
is saying. And they can dispatch
the robot to go see something.
So we might call them and say,
hey, there's a break in, in
progress at this office, you
know, pull up the dashboard, and
you can watch while we resolve
it. And we've actually, we've
stopped a few break ins, oh,
congratulations. Thank you,
it's, it's actually much more
boring than you would think, you
know, modern Moto, you're just
going
Audrow Nash: up to them. And
you're like, stop, and they're
like, Oh, no, and then they run
out.
Erik Schluntz: Modern criminals
are not in ski masks, you know,
breaking into Windows, they are
social engineering delays, and
office buildings. And so
Audrow Nash: what do you mean
social engineering there? What
is that
Erik Schluntz: they're there
pretending to be an employee
that forgot their badge, but
they're actually not, they're
well dressed. They're, they're
trying to blend in, they're
trying to blend in, around other
people, and sort of. So we had a
customer where one of their door
locks, stopped working at a door
swung open to the streets of San
Francisco. And fairly soon after
that, our robot detected a
person in the site. We
approached them because our
operators didn't recognize the
person. And we video chat and
said, Hey, excuse me, can I see
your badge? And the person was
the video like, Oh, I'm lost?
Like, I didn't know I wasn't
supposed to be here. It's funny.
I was like, I have to in the
office building? Sure, yeah,
you're just so you know, here.
You know, we call it the
customer and call the police,
and then escorted the person out
the door. And then the robot was
able to stay century at that
door that was open for the rest
of the night. And so that's the
kind of flexibility and
responsiveness that we want is
that as an emergency happens, we
don't want to just be on a fixed
rail, like a camera, yeah, we're
going to be doing what a garden
would be doing. And that's, you
know, making value calls as we
go and deciding what is the best
way we can provide value to this
customer?
Audrow Nash: So how do you code
in all that behavior and the
flexibility I'm imagining like,
something like behavior, trees,
or whatever they do in video
games, where it's like, you can
have fairly complex layered
behavior where I go, I try this,
and that doesn't work. So I'm
going to try this other thing.
And you can keep moving from
limb to limb of the tree. Is
that how do you encode your
behavior? Basically?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, so that's a
really good question. We use a
hierarchical state machines for
most of our behaviors. But
actually, I'd say a layer above
that. And I think that it would
be misleading to say that our
state machines resolve that
case, we keep our high level
decision making done by our
human operators. And so they are
able to on the fly, say, Hey,
don't patrol tonight, stay
century here. And basically
giving them thinking that for
operators, it's more like them
playing Starcraft, they can tell
the robot what to do. And we
provide a really good interface
for them to be able to tell the
robot to do different things.
And that might be go patrol this
floor that might be stay here
that might be go recharge, okay,
and that high level decision
making, we will have to be made
by our human operators who are
very highly trained, and know
our customers. And then our
state machines that we build are
basically these primitives for
the robot to be able to do these
block size to actions. But it's
the human that's deciding sort
of which of these should be
done.
Audrow Nash: Interesting. So the
human at a very high level, it's
almost like picking the mode of
whatever the robot will do. You
do. It's like a delegation
effectively, exactly. And then
the robot will go and it will
execute this fairly. This this
decided behavior and you have
all those primitives, those
smaller action, control loop
things go around this desk, go
look in that unexplored
territory. These kinds of
things. Yeah, Yeah,
Erik Schluntz: yeah. And so we
want to build the system that I
think it's, it's, we really
consider our system. It's the
combination of human and the
robot human operators. Yeah. And
that's really it's those put
together that allow us, allow us
to provide a great service for
our customers, I think, you
know, we've seen self driving
cars being worked on for 10
years now. And they're just
barely starting to actually
give, you know, get out into the
market, and give taxi rides to
people. And for us, what really
attracted me and my co founder
to this idea was that we could
use this combination of humans
and robots to immediately get
into the market and start
providing value, like right
away. Yeah, right away, even
though pieces of the robotic
technology weren't there yet.
And now, as all this technology
gets better, what it does is it
increases our ratio of how many
robots each one of our operators
can manage.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. So tell me
a bit more about the human in
the loop kind of thing. So how
does that work? They're on a
computer somewhere logged into
some web application that you
have,
Erik Schluntz: like, how does it
work? Yeah, great question. So
we have a lot of operators, and
they work from our offices or
satellite offices. And they have
a sort of this big three
monitors set up. Each of them
for AI, basically, they can zoom
in to one robot, and they have a
fleet management view, and they
have sort of a communications
view. And so they are
Audrow Nash: management, a
little bit slower for that. So
fleet management, if they're
using many robots in the same
environment, or
Erik Schluntz: Exactly, so
they're looking at sort of the
health of all of their robot,
okay, sort of how we have it
work is there's, you know, five
to 10 of them on shift at a
time. And they split up the
fleet of robots of who's
responsible for which robots,
you know, plus some overlap. And
so dynamic changes. And they're
saying, Hey, I'm watching my
robots, and the robots are
telling them, Hey, I think I saw
something or Hey, I need help, I
got stuck. And they are zooming
into these robots kind of one at
a time, as events are popping up
that they need to go resolve. So
then they switch to that robot
specific view and can go take
action, whether that's video
chatting with a person to, you
know, talk to them, or ask, ask
to see their security badge. Or
maybe it's changing a patrol
route to go around, you know, a
new obstacle or something that's
causing issues for the robot.
And then if anything is needed,
they can go communicate with the
customer, they can escalate
something to the robot sees into
the customers dashboard, so that
they can
Audrow Nash: see Ah, so they
have, they have their setup
where they see many robots, they
have a view into one robot, and
then maybe they have a good way
of accessing commands or
something with it for escalating
the situation. Is this one robot
specific, I guess? Or is it? I
guess you don't have multiple
robots coordinating? Or maybe
you do? I don't know.
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, so for most
of our customer sites, there's
one or just a few robots. But
individual customers have many
robots across their different
buildings. And that's one of the
other things we really see is
that a customer that has this
one place really likes to expand
to all of their different
offices and satellite offices.
Yeah. So that they can get this
consistent data and reporting
evenly across sort of their
their whole site, or their whole
collection of sites. And so they
you know, there might be a call
tree that applies for these 10
robots that are all from the
same customer.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha.
Interesting. Okay. Yeah. Yeah.
And then so when the robot is
stuck, or anything they the
person takes over gives them
high level guidance, do you have
to do anything where the person
will do? So you mentioned, like,
pick another route? Or something
like this? They won't do like
map editing, or something? Like,
will they correct any sensor
errors, or say, This region is
actually a spot you shouldn't
go?
Erik Schluntz: They have some
annotations that they can add
like that on the fly. But if
there's anything bigger, like
if, if they come in one night,
and realize that the customer
has totally rearranged the
furniture, you know, they'll
basically they can create a
ticket for us to go with remap.
And we can do all that remotely.
And it's kind of like the next
day, you know, we would go look
in and see what,
Audrow Nash: so you're working
with an existing map, it makes
sense for this kind of thing. So
you can localize
Erik Schluntz: and that's
exactly and that's something
where when we first go to a new
customer, that sales engineer
goes on site for a day with the
robot shows that the building
shows that the elevators shows
that any sort of you know, doors
are handicap delicate, it needs
to know about and then we have
that map that we can navigate
against, is it some and we're
using, you know, right now some
pretty we're using Ross and
we're using, you know, a heavily
modified version of move base,
and then a half stack NaCl. So a
lot of that kind of standard
standard, but improved. Ross
systems. Yep.
Audrow Nash: So you forked
specific things, and I've
improved them internally.
Exactly. Which, which Ross are
using are using Ross one are
using Ross two.
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, so we're
using Ross one. We haven't yet
seen a lot of other people
switch to Ross two for, you
know, live deploy the customer
sites, applications yet we're
seeing a lot of interesting
traction there and sort of new
things getting started with Ross
two, but we haven't yet seen all
the level of limit that we'd
like to see before switching
would make a move.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. How? How
has it been working with Ross
stack for you? Like, what are
your? I don't know, just how,
what are your impressions of
yeltsin?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, I mean, I I
really like Ross, I think the
just the general messaging
architecture is a really, really
good way to design systems that
it sort of forces that
microservices architecture, in
the robot, and really good
separation of concerns,
definitely, to be able to work
on a lot of different pieces,
and just know what the
interfaces are. So I really love
Ross conceptually, there's, you
know, a couple downsides. And
there's a couple of rough edges,
especially of Ross pi, the
Python implementation, but you
know, the things that we work
around, and I think, I mean,
what I love most is just the
community and the ecosystem that
any sensor we find, it's like,
oh, there's a Ross node already
made for it. Like, we can just,
you know, install it, and we're
ready to go. And, you know, I
really love that. And, you know,
I want to find more things in
the future where cobalt can
contribute back into open
source. And I think that's
something that I want to do as
we get more libraries and things
built that might be a little
more general, outside of just
us,
Audrow Nash: because so for the,
like your fork of NAB two, or
any of these other raw libraries
that are built on top of Ross,
what was the decision? Are they
public? Or what was the decision
to fork for this kind of thing?
Yeah, they're not public
Erik Schluntz: yet. But it's
something we've thought about.
One of the, I'd say two of the
major areas there that we've
that we've added is one kind of
just overhauling a lot of the
innards of move base to make
things more reliable.
Audrow Nash: Base very well.
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, yeah. So
move base is one of the big
packages in the bra snap stack
that's responsible for getting a
robot from point A to point B.
And it's kind of the the nice
high level interface, where you
can say, hey, send a nav goal
here. And move base is a open
source Ross package that
implements how to do that
gotcha, you give it some
configurations about where to
find your map, where to find
your cost map and sensors, to
not hit obstacles, and how to
talk to your motors, and then it
can go. So that's kind of the
starting point of what we've,
you know what we've very heavily
modified. One of the interesting
things that we've had to change
it actually, is the ability to
send intermediate goals.
Audrow Nash: So we as opposed to
just the actions, abstraction,
as opposed
Erik Schluntz: to just work, we
send an action that has two
goals, sort of the final goal,
and I think, a waypoint along
and it will actually start
moving towards the waypoint,
even if we can't reach the final
goal.
Audrow Nash: Now is that the why
is that better than just sending
to actions, so an action just to
be give some background for
those who are not familiar. So
you send something, it's a high
level thing that you'd like the
robot to do. And then it will
send feedback throughout the
time that it's completing it,
which you can do something with,
you could say, I'll cancel
nevermind, or just monitor it in
some way. But why? So why is the
two actions within one action?
Why is that different than just
sending one action, and then
another action, I guess it takes
both into account.
Erik Schluntz: It's lower
latency, and what we care about
here, and the motivation for
this was actually getting into
elevators quickly. A lot of
times, when you press the button
at the outset of elevators, you
have three seconds until the
door starts closing. And if it's
across the elevator lobby, we
actually have to move pretty
fast to get in there. And one of
the things that we've seen is
that if you send just one Ross
action of go, Oh, so basically,
the one of the things here is
that if the elevator door has
not yet opened, if you send a
nap goal into the elevator, it
will sit there and wait until
the door opens and then start
because I can't plant a calf
there. And so basically what we
wanted to do is hey, we're
trying to get into that
elevator. Even though the door
hasn't opened yet. We should
start moving over this get lined
up in front of it. And basically
doing both of these sort of
within move base. Lets us
seamlessly transition into that
second goal as the door opens
really quickly, rather than
stopping and lining up with that
intermediate goal. And then send
the Second action to go inside,
it's much faster for us to
actually switch that goal.
Without even stopping the robot.
As soon as it sees that the
second goal is viable, yeah,
it's switched over. And the
local controller just keeps on
going. Also know, for any
listeners that aren't familiar,
of move based on the nav stack,
sort of as a two level system,
there's a global planner, that
is sort of like, think about as
you're a star, you're Google
Maps of, I'm here, I'm trying to
get there, plot a route around
my obstacles that I know about
and get there. And then the
local controller takes in that
path, and is simulating its
wheels trajectories to figure
out how it should follow that
path most quickly. Get to the
point.
Audrow Nash: Okay. And then the
interest in eventually open
sourcing things. I mean, so I
get, so from the company
perspective, it's not quite your
interest to maintain a, like an
open source, library or
anything. But why why do you
feel like you'd like to open
source things? I mean, I'm at an
open source company. So clearly,
I like it. But yeah,
Erik Schluntz: I think for me,
it's a sense of giving back and
like paying it forward. cobalt
was very heavily dependent on
open source at the beginning, we
actually launched our, our first
product and deployed the
customer sites, with myself and
a single other robotics
engineer, wow. And we would not
have been able to do that, then,
you know, plus some web
engineers and hardware. But we
would not have been able to do
that without really heavily
standing on the shoulders of
giants and using these open
source packages, and building
layers on top of them. And I
just found that really exciting
that, you know, two people were
able to build a, you know, a
production ready robotics
system, by using a lot of these
open source packages. And I just
really, really enjoyed that. And
I think I want to make sure
that, you know, problems that we
solve just sort of first
humanity, I don't want, you
know, engineers everywhere to
need to, you know, solve the
same problem over and over
again, I love it. Now, of
course, a lot of the things that
we built are very sort of
specific, customized to our
robot. But you know, we're
always looking for things that
could be a good thing to open
source.
Audrow Nash: Now, so, two
people, you had a production
ready robot, how large Are you
guys now?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, we're about
115 people right now.
Audrow Nash: And so that's a lot
of the people that are doing the
security related thing.
Erik Schluntz: Exactly. Yeah,
about half of that is actually
our human operators to supervise
the robots, control the robots.
Our engineering team is still
very small, it's about 23
people. And that split again,
across robotics, web and
hardware. So it's a really great
place where you know, the teams
are very small, each person can
have a really big impact, and
solve a lot of interesting
problems and have really good
ownership
Audrow Nash: over the code.
Totally. What's the so going
from two, you had a production
ready robot, now you have 20
engineers, or so what are the
additional 20 ish people, like
you said, or what are the
additional 18 people or so
doing? Yeah,
Erik Schluntz: we had two
engineers to get to the point
where we can have one or two
robots roll around. Now with a
much bigger fleet. There's all
sorts of other, you know, other
things we have going on. And
also for this first production
ready robots, that means that
each one of our we had one
operator at the time. So if he's
only looking at two or three
robots, the robots can be a lot
more needy. And so really, now
everything is about scalability,
and saying how many robots can
each one of our operators handle
and that means the robots being
able to, you know, not get stuck
as frequently, being able to
unstick themselves if they do
get stuck, you know, navigation
area, building a lot more
features out for our customers,
better data reporting better
information that we can send
them and do that more reliably
and more quickly. So I'd say
it's, it's really about adding a
lot of like meat to the bones of
what our product services and
increasing reliability and
making these robots, you know,
really rock solid so that we can
scale scale out the fleet. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: Can you tell me a
little bit about manufacturing
your robot or just in general
making them and deploying
because you have how many? How
many robots out in the world
now.
Erik Schluntz: We have over 100
robots deployed very exciting.
So we actually manufacture all
of our own robots in house at
our right now our office in San
Mateo in the Bay Area of
California. So we've really
liked having manufacturing in
house because it lets us have a
very, very fast iteration cycle
between engineering and
hardware. So we can solve issues
as they come up and roll them
back into the design and be have
engineering right there to solve
any issues that happen. So now
as we're scaling up
manufacturing, you know
everything is getting a lot more
locked down and as volumes Going
up, you know, you start to see
1%, you know, 1% errors where if
you're buying, you know, you
know, SSDs, you know, it's a 1%
chance that they come out of the
box debt or something like that.
I don't know about that
particular component, but
Audrow Nash: some arbitrary
about some widget. Yeah,
Erik Schluntz: widget, you know,
when you're building in five or
10, robots, you don't really
need to care about that. But
when you're building a lot of
robots, you're going to have
anything that can fail. Exactly.
And so that means you need to
build in a lot more, you know,
basically unit tests for each
component that goes into the
robot, everything gets tested
before it gets put in, they get
put into sub assemblies, those
sub assemblies get tested,
before they get put in, and
trying to catch any of these
errors sort of as early as
possible. And then every, every
robot that gets finished, goes
through two days of battle
tested at our office before they
go to battle testing. Yes,
exactly. And so it's a
basically, the robot goes back
and forth across like, a
simulated office environment
with very rough and bumpy floors
for two days to try to shake
itself apart. And it goes
through basically making sure
that it can do all the different
kinds of tasks that it will be
required to at the customer
sites, we can catch any errors
or manufacturing defects before
it gets shipped to a customer.
Audrow Nash: How is it? So where
so you're doing your assembly in
house, I assume you're buying a
good number of components to put
together? Exactly, yeah, how has
it been sourcing those
components? Like the process of
doing that is very interesting
to me,
Erik Schluntz: this has been a
very challenging year with a
global CIO like that. And so you
know, a lot of the components
are either off the shelf sensors
or compute pieces. And we do
design our own custom PCBs that
go into the robot. And I'd say
the most of the most of the off
the shelf pieces, it's, it's
fairly easy. You know, we do
research online, we test
different components and make
sure we go with vendors that are
sort of more industrial, or they
say, Hey, we're going to
guarantee that we're going to
keep making this part for at
least another three or four
years. Oh, interesting. There
are, you know, in the early
days, there were more consumer
components in the robot and
things like that are dangerous
that, you know, it works great.
But you know, the next year,
it's not available on Amazon.
You know, in the in the first
version of a robot, there were
definitely a couple of
components, you know, purchased
off Amazon. And it's a it's a
great supplier until they
disappeared.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, gosh,
Erik Schluntz: yeah.
Audrow Nash: That's so funny.
Yeah.
Erik Schluntz: And, and now with
the chip shortage, one of the
big challenges that has been
that, you know, so many people
are, are ramping up production,
for different things that even
very simple components, like
inductors, that go on a PCB will
go out of stock. And there's
been a couple times where if you
don't have those stock piles,
you know, you have to change a
PCB design to use a different a
different partner different
value, because you can't get,
you know, whatever component
that goes on it. And so things
like STM microcontrollers are
very hard to come by now. And
even surpasses our Yeah, it can
be difficult to find gotcha.
passives, like resistors.
Exactly. resistors, capacitors
inductors.
Audrow Nash: Wow, that's really
interesting.
Erik Schluntz: So it's been a
really crazy year for supply
chain management, inventory. But
we've done a good job. And
there's been a lot of heroic
lifts from the engineering team
here to redesign with available
five days is redesigned
components around, redesigned
boards around what's missing,
and find other options.
Audrow Nash: Let's see. Now
another thing, I'd like to talk
about the human robot
interaction of your robot, so
it's covered in fabric, just
tell me some of your human robot
interaction considerations in
designing the kobalt robot.
Erik Schluntz: Absolutely. So
this was one of our really,
really big sort of goals when we
started this, because when we,
again, going back to set up that
that customer driven approach
that we wanted to take, when we
first talked to customers, about
you know, whether they would
like this product, whether they
wouldn't, a lot of their biggest
fear wasn't that the robot
wouldn't work, it was that their
employees would be scared of the
robot, and that they would like
something like this. And so we
put a lot of effort into trying
to dispel that fear, and making
the robot as friendly as
possible. And so that's why we
we actually contracted a design
firm that's very well known,
called fuse project, and worked
with a world famous designer in
the heart. He actually helped
design the Herman Miller office
chairs. And kind of the sense
that we wanted to go for it was
not Terminator, Robocop, but we
wanted to feel like a high end
piece of furniture. That's
something that's natural to be
in the office that's helpful and
useful, but isn't sort of isn't
as much of like a intelligent
thing that you know you're going
to fight with. And so that's why
we went with sort of the fabric
basis that it was, it's nice and
sunny. And it's actually we've
seen it like crazy it's we go
when we went to early customers,
and would you an onboarding, for
them to bring the robots there
and basically tell the employees
what it was and how it was going
to work. A lot of people were
initially very scared about the
idea of a security robot. They
were picturing picturing
Terminator or Robocop with a
taser. But you know, as soon as
they came to the, you know, the
all hands or the lunch and learn
that we were host, and they saw
the robot, and they touched the
robot and realized that it was
soft. And they talked to one of
our operators, they realized,
Oh, this is just like a security
guard that just happens to be
remote. And that just getting
people to come touch the robot
and interact with the robot. And
see what it is really, really
helps with that. Yeah, but
Hollywood, sort of, Oh, yeah.
Hollywood's depiction of robots
is, you know, definitely not
good for us. And, you know,
we're trying to stay far away
from that.
Audrow Nash: Very interesting,
that's crazy to me that people
were afraid. I mean, I guess
I've been involved in robotics
for so long and not talking to
customers. So that
Erik Schluntz: exactly, this is
something that's, you know,
challenging, and that would why
we wanted to make sure that we
were very close to customers is
that for us as roboticists, it's
very easy to say, oh, who
doesn't love robots? Yeah, so a
lot of people don't. And so it's
something that we want to be
really, really careful of, and
really just take, you know, very
good consideration. And so
actually, that goes in not just
to the industrial design of the
robot, but also into a lot of
what we call the body language
of the robot, and the software
and behaviors. And so there's
some interesting things there,
if you know, we have an issue in
the past, where if they, if the
robot got stuck, and was waiting
for a human operator to you
know, help it proceed, if it was
stuck near a person, the person
would think, why did the robot
stop and just stare at me for 10
seconds, you know, and then
continue on. And actually, it
was that the robot was just
stuck, staring at that it just
happened to get stuck near that
assumed and a person that
doesn't know that assumes
there's attention. So now we do
things, like if the robot gets
stuck, it's something displays
on the screen that says, you
know, oops, I've gotten stuck,
I'll be on my way shortly. And
make sure that people understand
what the intention of the robot
is. And that's made people a lot
more comfortable around.
Audrow Nash: What other so
that's really funny about the
body language of the same
phrasing it as the body language
of the robot. And so I see so
you'll see someone who's
watching the robot or sees the
robot come up, and they assume a
sort of intention behind
whatever the robots doing. And
so then you have to so you're
making this explicit message of
Oops, I'm actually stuck. I'm
not just like staring at you, or
something like this. How do you
find those? Is it is it case by
case where someone will be like,
This made me uncomfortable of
what the robot did? Or how do
you? How do you go about
designing robot body language?
And I would love to hear other
examples of robot body language.
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, so I think
the one of the best ways that we
do it is that we have our own
offices patrolled by cobalt
robots, for our security. And so
that just means, you know, we're
dogfooding we're trying our own
products, and dogfooding, for
anyone that hasn't heard of it
as a term of basically, if
you're a company that makes dog
food, you should eat your own
dog food to make sure it
actually tastes good and is high
quality. That's, if you want to
express your own product. If you
don't use your own product, like
how can you expect customers to
use it. So that's something
that's really important to us.
And so that, as we're working in
the office, you know, to feel
what it's like to have a robot
go go past you, or someone to
come up and ask to see your
badge with a robot. And so doing
that is really, really important
just to get that sense of what
it's like. We also have
engineers that will go on site
to customers, with customers and
walk around the robot and see,
you know, see how people
interact with it. And we just
really try to get as much
exposure as possible for our
engineers to be with end
customers, and also to be with
our operators. Because a lot of
times our operators see or
they're seeing everything that
goes on around the robot, and
they're talking to people out
there, they'll hear complaints,
or they'll, they'll hear sort of
people being delighted that
they're talking to someone
through a robot. And we're just
trying to keep engineers not
just looking at code, but
involved with the end product
and seeing the pain points is
really important to us.
Audrow Nash: That's very
interesting. Have you. So
there's a growing space of
research, rather human
interaction space. Has any of
that research been useful to you
guys? Or like, have you been
leveraging it or it's all things
that you've been finding kind of
organically.
Erik Schluntz: I'd say it's a
mix and one of our advisors,
Laila Akiyama, she's an expert
in HR II, and so we brainstorm
with her. And I say that's a mix
of things that There's a lot of
things that once you hear them
feel like common sense. But
there's also really good things
that are, you know, very non
intuitive that are very cool.
One of the things that we had
heard and learned from HR AI
experts, and some of this
research is that being
completely stationary, for
humans is actually a very
aggressive and sort of assertive
behavior. It's like, I am rock
solid, and medicine. And for a
robot, though, because like, by
default, a human doesn't stay
Stockstill, they fidget. And a
robot by default stays stuck.
And it's the one of the ideas
that we've had is that if we're,
if the robot is idle, instead of
being stocked still, it should
fit. You know, when kids turn
back and forth a little bit. You
know, that's one of the things
we're thinking about
implementing now. But kind of
going back to that body language
is that being stationary is
actually like, more aggressive
than moving sometimes. And so
there's a lot of interesting
things like that, that we've
learned about
Audrow Nash: interesting. And
see. So
Erik Schluntz: yeah, I think
those are often called keep
alive movements keep alive show
that the robots Yeah, show that
the robot is still active, it's
still doing something, even if
it can't make progress towards
its goal.
Audrow Nash: Yep. Yeah, I'm
always a little disappointed as
someone working on robots that
almost all the time or robots
are off. And so it's like,
almost all of the robots are
just completely still for almost
all the time around robots,
which maybe it will change at
some point in the near future.
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, yeah. And I
think for us that that's
actually an interesting segue
that some of our future plans is
making our robots a lot more
general purpose. And our
thoughts there is that security
guards actually do a lot at, you
know, at employers, they're
making sure nothing bad happens
at night. But during the day,
they're doing visitor
management, they're checking
people in, a lot of times,
they're almost acting like a
secretary, or sort of a
receptionist. And so one of our
goals is that, while the robots
are doing security at night,
during the day, they can be a
Virtual Receptionist, and check
someone in just like envoy but
then actually lead the person to
the conference room, you know
where they're supposed to be.
And the idea is that, you know,
once you have a robot on site
somewhere, I just want to use it
any functionality that you can
do with our software updates,
it's you have the hardware
there, it's already paid for by
security, because that's sort of
a big cost, you know, the big
cost, and you can start adding
all these other applications.
And we've already started doing
that with some of that
facilities monitoring that I
talked about. But one of the
next ones we're looking at is
more daytime applications.
Robots, you know, more active,
and so people will be able to
see them moving around and
interact with them during the
day.
Audrow Nash: Let's see, maybe a
bit more of a controversial
check. Question. But so how does
this relate to jobs for security
guards and things like this?
Because it is, in a sense,
automating the job and maybe in
the end automating receptionist
so our inspection people? How do
you look at this? Yeah,
Erik Schluntz: that's a really
good question. And definitely
one that we take very seriously.
What we found is actually that
robots replace tasks, not jobs,
and really sort of change how
jobs are done. And what we've
seen is, you know, we've never
had a security guard laid off.
Because of a customer getting
robots, what we typically see is
that customers can't find enough
security guards that watch work.
Or they'll work night shift, but
as soon as they have any other
job opportunity, they're
switching to something else.
Exactly. And so we've redeployed
customers and they can take
their good nightshift guards,
and let them work day shift now.
Or have that the guards focus on
more interesting things like
interacting with people, while
the robot is doing the much more
monotonous, sort of patrolling
around go like and checking all
these alarms, and checking for
doors and windows being close to
what's really sort of changed
how people do security. And the
other thing is that his
customers are adding these in
places where they didn't
previously have guards. Because
guards are quite expensive,
especially, you know, if you
want to guard 20 473 65, it can
be very expensive, you can
actually need three or four
security guards to cover that
amount of time. Yeah. And so
what we see is that companies
had guards for receptionists at
their main office, but none of
their satellite offices. And now
because the robots are much
cheaper, they can put the robot
at all the satellite offices
where they never had security
presence before, and basically
get that additional coverage.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. That's
awesome. I really like framing
it in the robots replace tasks,
not jobs way. And I'm hearing
this pattern in the last several
interviews that I've done, where
it's like, it's the same thing
you're saying, which is that
we're having trouble finding the
workers for this kind of thing.
So like I'm thinking of the
interview I did with Melanie
wise who in factories settings
like there's a tremendous
shortage of workers. And so it's
interesting to hear the same
kind of thing here. But there's
a shortage of security guards.
Erik Schluntz: Yep, exactly.
Yeah. And I think comes from the
fact that robots and humans are
good at such different things.
You know, humans are amazing at
making good decisions, hands
like guantes interacting with
people, and they're terrible at
anything monotonous, or
something that requires Long,
long focus. And the robot has no
trouble at all for, you know,
eight hours, never blinking. And
checking, you know, checking
whether that doors open with
just as much sort of sincerity
and, you know, carefulness as
the the 100th time they did it
as the first time they did it.
So it's something where, you
know, you can create a much
better solution using both of
those. And that's, you know,
it's at several levels. That's,
that's why we have our human
operators that are handling the
interesting parts of security
while the robots are doing the
monotonous parts. And we've seen
the same thing with our
customers, is they can take the
monotonous parts of their
security program, and do them
with robots, and re designate
their security guards to be
working during the day shift,
much more round people
responding to things.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, gotcha. I'm
also I'm hearing another echo in
this interview, where it's that
we have humans in the loop in
some way, augmenting the tasks.
And yeah, I mean, you've spoken
about how the humans are doing
the things humans are good at,
and the robots are doing things
that the robots are good at. So
long attention, grueling,
mundane work. Can you just talk
about this model within
robotics? A little bit? Because
I think it's a big one? And it
seems like we're at a good time
for this?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, absolutely.
So human in the loop is
definitely a really, really big
wave in robotics, where I think
this kind of comes back to my
point that it's let us get into
the market, and ship a product
when in an area where the
robotic technology was not good
enough by itself to do the
whole, to do the whole job. But
because we're able to kind of
augment these two things
together of what the humans good
at what the robots good at, we
can provide the value from day
one. And it lets us both focus
the engineering work on the
pieces that are easy for robots,
and save, you know, you know,
it'll be very hard to automate
something like how do you
respond to a person that says
they're an employee, but doesn't
have their badge? Like, that's a
crazy hard situation to be to
handle. And, you know, it will
take engineers a lot of time to
write something is correct. And
if there is a case, there isn't
a correct, you know, it depends
probably for each customer, how
they would want to do it. And,
you know, some would say, Oh,
just don't want them in some
would say, call this number and
verify whether they're there.
And you know, that's something
that having a human do that they
can respond with a lot more
nuance. And I think there's a
couple different archetypes of
human in the loop, that sort of
different levels of shared
autonomy. And we use a couple of
these different levels, I'd say
the, on one extreme, this is
sort of complete autonomy. And
that, you know, you can see with
factory robots where a person
doesn't need to be involved at
all. On the other extreme, you
have complete Telly off, it's a
person directly controlling a
robot, you know, one for one,
and exactly specify what it
should do. And a couple of the
layers in between there is back
to the sort of the autonomy
side, there's autonomy with
supervision. So the robot is
still doing an autonomous thing,
but a person is supervising it,
and they can hit the stop
button, or they can hit the
correct button. One more step
towards human is sort of human
review, which is the robot is
explicitly saying, Hey, I'm
about to make this decision. Can
you approve it? And that's great
for something like, Hey, I am
you know, 90% sure this, this
door is open, can you approve
this. And that's great for
things that are, you know,
something where we want to
remove false positives, we don't
want to integrate our customers
with false positives of this
door was left open, or you know,
this, we saw this person. So
anything like that, we always go
through human review first. And
it's something the robot can do
by itself, but we want to make
sure a human reviews then kind
of one step more towards human,
I would say there is
I don't actually have a great
term for this maybe robot
accelerated or robot assisted
human decisions, okay. And what
that might mean is, let's say,
we don't have any software to
check, maybe a new customer
feature, go check whether all of
our fire extinguishers are
there. Maybe we don't have code
for that yet to classify whether
we see a fire extinguisher in
the correct spot. There. robot
could still go and collect all
the pictures of the 10 places
they're supposed to be, and then
show the human them all at once.
Yeah, that way the human, the
human can batch their work. And
we don't actually have to
automate the work, we just have
to automate walking between the
worker where a security guard
would take 45 minutes to go walk
around and check all these fire
extinguishers, the robot can do
that 45 minutes of walking, and
then our human operator can go
review them in 30 seconds. So
basically batching and assisting
work to let a human give just a
little bit of input that makes
the work. Basically, it's
automating 95% of a task, and
letting the human do it. And
then kind of the, we get back,
that's sort of the the far end,
and then maybe you just have
complete human control on the
other end. So we have things
that are sort of all along the
spectrum. And as we automate
more things, we try to move
things further to the right, to
make them more automated and
take less human time. And that's
a lot of the interesting things
that our engineering team is
working on now is, hey, how can
we take something that right now
we're just showing a person? And
how can we have the robot make a
decision and just have the human
review and said, Yeah, cuz
that's a lot easier, for sure.
And the really cool thing about
this model of having these
different collections of kinds
of human in the loop is that our
humans basically act as a buffer
for engineering work, where if
there's a new feature that a
customer requests, start a call,
where it's done fully manually.
And what that does is there can
be a crazy new request from a
customer. And normally, you'd
have to say, ah, like, do we do
this, it's this big product
decision, you can try it and
then see if you try it, and see
if they actually use it and see
if other if other people
actually like it. Yep. And then
if everyone does start using
this feature, great, like, let's
automate it. But if you know, no
one is using it, if it's kind of
a one off, you can either leave
it manual or quietly deprecated.
So it lets us kind of dip our
toes in the water with a lot of
features, and then automate them
as needed later. So we spend a
lot less time implementing
features that no one needs, and
a lot more time implementing a
feature. Once we have amazing
training data for an example.
Yes. Because then when we go and
do what automate it, we have,
you know, two months of humans
doing it manually with all that
data recorded. Yeah.
Audrow Nash: So for many of the
things that you're inspecting,
and where you get the data, and
then you try to do it in an
automatic way. Are you using any
machine learning on this? Or
what what kind of tasks are you
using machine learning for?
Erik Schluntz: Yep, yeah, so we
use a combination of classical
methods and machine learning for
a lot of these different things
that we're inspecting or
checking. And kind of one of the
ways that we refer to this is
auditing the physical world for
our customers. So we Yeah,
exactly. You know, you want to
be able to audit that everyone
in your organization has, you
know, two factor authentication
turned on, the robot lets you
audit the physical world in a
very reliable and trustable way.
That you know, before you
couldn't really trust the Oh,
your guard says, Yeah, all the
doors are closed. And we've had
plenty of times where someone
says that and then we sent the
robot two doors to your robot to
his
Audrow Nash: employee. That's
like really diligent. That
example. Yeah, other workers
really dislike said it was done.
Erik Schluntz: Humans are not
exactly humans aren't good at
that kind of deal. Don't worry,
but robots are. Yeah, um, but so
basically. Sorry, what was your
question? I got the
Audrow Nash: what do you do with
what is machine learning? Yeah,
yeah. On your platform? Like,
what kinds of tasks are you
learning?
Erik Schluntz: So generally, I
would say that machine learning
should be a last approach when
it's just, you know,
Audrow Nash: data. But and so I
love that I associated it with
it. I know you don't, you can
use classical methods with the
training data to just see if it
kind of lines up. But
Erik Schluntz: yeah, yeah,
exactly. So I would say, you
know, we, we usually start for
something new that we're doing,
trying to use classical methods
and trying to like, Hey, can we
write an explicit solution for
this? And then if not, if it's
something that's challenging,
We'll train a neural network,
you know, based on some of the
data. But it's actually really
interesting that we've gotten
very far using some even
classical computer vision
techniques and looking for
diffs. Really. So an example is
because our robot has very good
localization, we can go take a
picture of the same thing from
exactly the same spot each time.
And we can just look at a diff
and say, Hey, this looks
different than last time bow.
And then suddenly, you have a
way to inspect, you know,
anything new, even if it's a,
you know, whatever the arbitrary
scene is, yeah, wherever the
arbitrary scene is, we have now
a way to flag this up to an
operator of Hey, I don't know
whether there's a fire
extinguisher here. But it looks
different than the last time I
saw. Yeah. Yeah, that actually
was no
Audrow Nash: semantic
understanding. But you're still
like, I ran a diff on the old
image and the new image, I
looked at the difference. And I
saw that there was this many
pixels different, or some
measure of entropy or whatever
it might be. And yeah,
Erik Schluntz: and we found some
very interesting pre processing
techniques to do the diff in a
non pixel space. Oh, that lets
us signal much more area, much
more invariant to lighting
conditions, and things like
that.
Audrow Nash: Hmm, that's
awesome. can speak on that a
little bit? Or is, yeah,
Erik Schluntz: one, one example
is that you can do things like
edge, detect the image, and then
do gifts at the edge detected
images. And that that lets you
see that something's sort of
with heart outlines has moved in
the scene. But an overall
lighting change is very, not
very picked out. Yeah. doesn't
doesn't trigger that. And so we
have sort of things like that,
that we can do to very easily
notice changes. It's
Audrow Nash: cool to use these
like incredibly simple
operations. So if you want to
get an edge detection, you just
multiply plus like a plus one
and a minus one over the
convolve it over the whole
image, and then you get your
edges from the resulting image.
It's and it's so crazy that you
can use that and that will be
useful and fairly invariant,
which is very nice to different
lighting conditions. And
Erik Schluntz: yeah, yeah, we're
we're really big fans of keeping
things very simple in the
design. And if something feels
sort of overly complicated, it's
probably going to be fragile.
When it actually gets working in
the real. This, we see lots of
things, you know, from research,
like oh, like, did they need to
do that? Like, was that
something in a research paper
just to make it more
publishable?
Audrow Nash: Totally, how phony
now so we're running out of
time, I'd like to talk a little
bit. So your experience in
startups in this startup, and I
you said you previously were
starting companies or have
started companies. And talk to
me just a little bit about this
time, like right now for being a
robotics startup, and maybe just
the landscape as you see it?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, yeah. So
it's a really interesting time
for robotics companies. And
maybe I'll actually kind of
backup Sure, maybe kind of my
history of how I got here is, I
started my first company called
pulse metrics. In college with a
friend, we dropped out of
Harvard for a year went through
Y Combinator. And that company
eventually got acquired while I
went back to school to finish my
degree. Oh, congrats. That's
awesome. Thank you. That's
actually where I met my current
co founder, Travis style. He
also had a startup at the time
that he was working on, we
became pretty good friends
chatting about robotics, even
though neither of us at the time
were doing robotics. And we just
kind of stayed in touch. We're
always bouncing startup ideas
off of each other. And I think
the really cool thing is of
being a second time founder, was
it just felt like we knew what
we should be doing. You know,
looking back to the first
startup, it's crazy that we got
anywhere, because we didn't know
what we were doing. It's like,
oh, maybe we should try
marketing today. Maybe we should
try to build features. Yeah, we
didn't know what the goalposts
were. And I think that's the
really great time without her
The really great thing about
doing something the second time
is, we know, what are the goals
that we need to hit. And I think
that a lot of the ways that I
think about startups is
progressive de risking, and look
at what are the experiments you
can be running each week that
reduced the risk of your
business as much as possible.
And think about what is that
next milestone we need to hit?
And what are the kind of
waterfall things that we need to
do to get there. And a lot of
times for early stage startups,
that's different funding rounds,
and sort of think, Okay, well,
they get this, I need to
probably have this much revenue.
That means I need to get this
many customers, that means I
need to get this many features
as an adult. And so you can kind
of work backwards to what you
need. And that helps decide what
you actually need to be focused
on. As a founder of what games
your engineering team to be
focused on, to decide, you know,
really what's, what's going to
be a feature that works and is
important, and, you know, helps
the company versus something
that's just nice to have.
Audrow Nash: So how do you so is
this? Can you speak a bit more
about picking a problem?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, sure. So
when when Travis and I started
looking at ideas, we had a
couple of constraints. We wanted
to find something that we could
see ourselves loving and doing
for 10 years. And you know,
cobalt is an amazing fit for
that pelea. You know, secure
security just feels like this
amazing first use for robots.
And it's really good opportunity
to get robots out into the
physical world and get around
people, not just in factories
where no one's going to see
them, but in office buildings
where they're going to be around
people all day. And it was
something that could be too
could be done with today's
technology, sort of really like
the other sort of constraint
that we had her. We wanted to
find something that we could
immediately get it to market
with, you know, no research and
development. That was another
really good thing about cobalt
is we could go and we could use
human in the loop to fill in the
deficiencies. And we didn't want
to do something that would take,
you know, a lot of r&d or had
very high technical risk. Yep,
we wanted to find something that
we could use today's technology,
and that will just get better
over time. And in our last
constraint, believe it or not,
was no hardware totally failed
on and we were actually looking
at a lot of non robotics ideas
at the time, but this one,
actually we, we kind of found
that it was such, we found such
a strong demand from this first
customer we talked to, and then
he put us in touch with all of
his other friends in the
security industry. And we just
got such a positive response,
like, wow, yeah, you know, it's
gonna be a lot harder to do a
hardware startup, but like, we
do have the background for it.
And you know, we do have, you
know, it seems like it's a
really good, good problem and
space to tackle. But we were
basically looking for, for
customers, and where they said
they had a problem, and they
would pay money to solve it. And
that they would give us a
handshake deal that, once this
is ready, I will pay for it at
this price. And we got a couple
people to get to that point do
that those handshake deals. And
that was enough for us to go
raise our first funding round
of, Hey, this is our idea. Don't
believe us go talk to these
customers that have done these
handshake deals with us, and
said, Let them tell you how
excited they are for this
product, and how they would use
it.
Audrow Nash: Okay, so a few
things here. Very interesting to
me the first, can you just tell
me a bit about a bit more in
detail about how you did your
initial market research, when
you were talking to people and
seeing what they would pay for
in this kind of thing? Like, how
does someone do that kind of
thing? How do you just, I don't
know, like, how do you go about
meeting these people? And what
kind of questions and like,
what's the heuristic when doing
that kind of thing? Yeah.
Erik Schluntz: So what we were
looking for was talking to
anyone that we didn't know what
their job actually entailed. And
it's funny, but it's, it's not
that hard to do, you just kind
of have to go and start doing
it. And whether that's talking
to strangers at Starbucks, which
actually isn't that effective.
But really, what we found most
effective was going through our
network, and really going in
like asking, I asked every
single one of my friends, what
are your parents do? What are
your aunts and uncles do? And
you know what, to people that I
knew, like, just asking them
what their friends did and like,
Audrow Nash: oh, cool,
Erik Schluntz: I made this like
kind of List of everyone I knew
and went through them. And like,
tell me about like everyone that
you're, like, close enough to
that you could ask for a favor
and like, tell me like, what is
your uncle do? What is your aunt
do? And we kind of wrote out
like, Oh, actually, I don't know
what being a pharmacist is like,
like, yeah, go talk to that
person. I don't know what the
security director is like, let's
go talk to that person. I don't
know what being a lawyer is
like, let's go talk to that
person. And then once we were
talking to those, those people,
you know, in our, in the back of
our minds, we had a couple broad
theses that we cared about, and
that things that we were looking
for, they were mainly around
enterprise, and finding ways
that we could use software or AI
to make some process better or
more efficient, or cheaper. And
so that was kind of a lens that
we were looking at these
interviews through, but a lot of
it was trying to be very open
ended, like, tell me what you
actually do day to day. But if
there's one problem that you
could solve, or like pay money
to solve at work, what would it
be, and trying to really focus
on the problem, because a lot of
times people will come up with
an idea that they want you to do
what it's kind of like people
asking for the faster horse. But
you have to kind of keep going
back and really understanding
what is the pain point that they
have? Like, what would it
actually mean solving. And a lot
of times from someone saying an
idea that they have, you can
kind of work back to what is
that actual pain?
Audrow Nash: What is the pain
point? Yeah,
Erik Schluntz: come up with an
even better idea.
Audrow Nash: Gotcha. What an
interesting thing. Okay. And
then the other thing that I'm
really curious, so you can you
talk a little bit about kind of
the way that you have been
funded at cobalt?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, absolutely.
So we have great financial
backers. Bloomberg beta, did our
seed round in 2016. So they're
really good fund focus on the
future of work kind of
designing, you know, their,
their main LP is Michael
Bloomberg. So they really care
about helping invent what his
work is going to be like in the
future. Then for our series, a
we raised from Alfred Lind at
Sequoia, he was sort of, Oh,
yeah. Yeah. So Sequoia has a
really, really amazing duster.
And Alfred Lin was actually the
top of our list of who we wanted
to, to go with for our series.
Wow. You know, he is a he's a
really, really incredible
individual. He was the CEO of
Zappos, and actually was helped
bring Kiva robotics into Amazon
after Zappos got acquired by
Amazon, and so he's very
familiar with robotics. He was
most importantly to us. He is an
operator. He's been in startups
and feels the pain And you know,
knows what it's like, you know,
with the time pressure and like
everything on fire. And we
really wanted people like that
people that had been through
this themselves and could sort
of know what Travis and I were
going through, rather than
someone that was kind of just a
financial analysts that had
never been in it themselves and
was making a bet on us. And then
we raised a Series B from cotu.
Later, and we raised about,
we've raised around 16 million
total, from our series A's and
B's. cotu was another great
investor, our partner there is
Chris Fredrickson. He was very
early in luxury, and actually
did a lot of really hard work
around deliveries and logistics.
And that's something that's very
hard for us as we're moving
hardware around around the
country. And actually, across
different continents. We
actually have customers in
Australia and Japan. Oh, wow.
The UK. So Oh, yeah. You know,
logistics are very hard for
moving five foot tall robot
around on. So yeah. So we've
been very, very happy with our
investors at some of the best
companies in Silicon Valley.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. That's, yeah,
I mean, you guys are very
promising. So it's wonderful to
see Great Investors supporting
you, as well. Can you can you?
So for someone who wants advice
on how to approach investors? Or
how to look for the I just any
advice on getting funding? I
suppose that you have?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, yeah. I
would say to put your mind, put
yourself in the mind of the
investor. And what they're
looking for is, how is this
going to fail? And they're
looking for the startup idea,
that's, they're looking for a
startup where they look at it,
like, Oh, I don't see any
possible way this could fail.
And so sort of think, put
yourself in that mindset and
think, why would an investor say
no to me, and then start working
on fixing those things. And that
might be they, they think, oh, I
don't think this technology is
possible, then go build a
prototype, they might say, I
don't think, you know, people
are going to actually want this
go get customers, or, you know,
I don't think people are going
to pay for this show that people
will pay a high price for it.
It's a really, you know, think
about what the objections are
going to be. And then your work
as an early stage founder is, is
doing things and collecting
evidence to show that this is
working. Yeah, and a lot of that
evidence looks like building an
early stage business of getting
customers building a prototype.
But really sort of it, you know,
in the first year of a business
are yours to the revenue isn't
actually important, it's it's
just an indicator that you will
get more revenue in the future.
And so you need to be thinking
about it in terms of what is an
investor need to see, to show
that this is a great idea, and
that people are going to want
this and that we're the correct
team to build it.
Audrow Nash: Yeah. So one thing
that I have seen many times is
people or companies accepting
funding, and the funding comes
with terms and things that
eventually suffocate the
company. Can you talk a little
bit about avoiding things like
this, or just how do you make
sure you don't accept bad
investment or whatever it might
be? Yeah.
Erik Schluntz: So it's, that's
definitely sort of a negotiation
game. And you just need to make
sure that you're in a strong
enough point where, even if
someone is offering more money,
if there are those bad terms in
there, you should probably take
someone else's money. And being
just knowledgeable about it,
really reading through the docs
and understanding sort of what's
you know, what's happening, and
cut, some of the things to worry
about are sort of guaranteed
returns, or sort of any sort of
overhangs where someone can get
sort of more than they otherwise
would, if your valuation is
lower. But one of the best
things there is to get, you
know, a really, really good
investor on your cap table to
start. And then, you know, with
us having Sequoia and Bloomberg
and cotu, no investor is going
to try that. Yeah, they don't
want Sequoia to get mad at them.
And so having really, really
good partners, helps you
negotiate because you know, that
new investor you're talking to,
you know, your existing
investors are on your side, and
that, that when you're talking
to so getting really good
partners, and really well known
people where they care about
that reputation, a no name
investor might give you money,
but if they don't have a
reputation to lose, if something
comes up, they might try to
squeeze you for any penny of
your work. Whereas a really well
known and sort of prominent
investor like Sequoia, they care
more about their reputation with
other founders and sort of
showing that they're gonna do
right by people. They care more
about that than making a few
extra dollars got any deal.
Audrow Nash: Alright, so
wrapping up. What advice do you
have for say, like a 20 year old
version of yourself? I guess in
now or in back then. Let's just
how would you do the same thing
I Then a little better, or what
would you wish you better know?
Yeah, advice for young,
Erik Schluntz: I would say the
most important thing is just
always keep talking to customers
and sort of always stay
skeptical. You know, make sure
you're always going to figure
out what the pain point is and,
and never sort of stop and think
that you've, you've solved
something. Because definitely
for us, you know, from that
first robot, to sort of where we
are now, so many things have
changed not just about the
robot, but how we're delivering
the value to the customer. And
those iterations have led us
really grow and scale and
provide way better value. So I'd
say just really stay focused on
the customer. The technology and
the product is just a means to
an end. It's not an end in
itself, you need to stay focused
on the customer and their pain
points. Awesome.
Audrow Nash: So wrapping up, do
you have any links or social
media or anything you'd like to
share with our listeners?
Erik Schluntz: Yeah, absolutely.
I can put in a couple links to
some YouTube videos of our robot
using elevators, with its
elevator arm. some links to sort
of our hiring page, and we are
looking for robotics engineers
and web engineers. Pretty much
everything right now we have a
really strong or a lot of really
strong customer growth. And
we're trying to keep up the
engineering team with it to help
deliver that value.
Audrow Nash: Yeah, awesome. So
I'll put links in the video
description and podcast
description. That sounds good.
Thank you. It's been a pleasure.
Erik Schluntz: Thank you so
much, everyone.
Audrow Nash: That's all we have
for you today. I hope you
enjoyed the episode. I was
surprised during the interview
that the cobalt robot is going
to be trying receptionist work
during the day. What other
applications could you think of
a robot like Cobalts robot? Let
me know in the comments on
sensing act calm. Thank you
again to our founding sponsor
open robotics. Goodbye,
everyone.